<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36971180</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>HLA-DQ-conferred risk for type 1 diabetes does not alter neutralizing antibody response to a widely used enterovirus vaccine, the poliovirus vaccine.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28707</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28707</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28707</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study investigated whether children with HLA-DQ-conferred risk for type 1 diabetes (T1D) have an altered immune response to the widely-used enterovirus vaccine, namely poliovirus vaccine, and whether initiation of autoimmunity to pancreatic islets modulates this response. Neutralizing antibodies induced by the inactivated poliovirus vaccine against poliovirus type 1 (Salk) were analysed as a marker of protective immunity at the age of 18 months in a prospective birth cohort. No differences were observed in antibody titers between children with and without genetic risk for T1D (odds ratio [OR] = 0.90 [0.83, 1.06], p = 0.30). In the presence of the genetic risk, no difference was observed between children with and without islet autoimmunity (OR = 1.00 [0.78, 1.28], p = 1.00). This did not change when only children with the autoimmunity before 18 months of age were included in the analyses (OR = 1.00 [0.85, 1.18], p = 1.00). No effect was observed when groups were stratified based on autoantigen specificity of the first-appearing autoantibody (IAA or GADA). The children in each comparison group were matched for sex, calendar year and month of birth, and municipality. Accordingly, we found no indication that children who are at risk to develop islet autoimmunity would have a compromised humoral immune response which could have increased their susceptibility for enterovirus infections. In addition, the proper immune response supports the idea of testing novel enterovirus vaccines for the prevention of T1D among these individuals.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors. Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sioofy-Khojine</LastName><ForeName>Amir-Babak</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5538-5153</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lehtonen</LastName><ForeName>Jussi P</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nurminen</LastName><ForeName>Noora</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laiho</LastName><ForeName>Jutta E</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toppari</LastName><ForeName>Jorma</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, Turku University Hospital, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Institute of Biomedicine, Research Centre for Integrative Physiology and Pharmacology, University of Turku, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Veijola</LastName><ForeName>Riitta</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department for Children and Adolescents, Oulu University Hospital, Oulu, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, MRC Oulu, University of Oulu, Oulu, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lempainen</LastName><ForeName>Johanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, Turku University Hospital, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunogenetics Laboratory, Institute of Biomedicine, University of Turku, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Turku University Hospital, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ilonen</LastName><ForeName>Jorma</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunogenetics Laboratory, Institute of Biomedicine, University of Turku, Turku, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knip</LastName><ForeName>Mikael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Program for Clinical and Molecular Metabolism, Faculty of Medicine, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Research Centre, New Children's Hospital, Helsinki University Hospital, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tampere Centre for Child Health Research, Tampere University Hospital, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hyöty</LastName><ForeName>Heikki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fimlab Laboratories, Pirkanmaa Hospital District, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D057134">Antibodies, Neutralizing</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D001323">Autoantibodies</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011054">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D006683">HLA-DQ Antigens</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003922" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057134" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Neutralizing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001323" MajorTopicYN="N">Autoantibodies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011054" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006683" MajorTopicYN="N">HLA-DQ Antigens</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007515" MajorTopicYN="Y">Islets of Langerhans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GADA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IAA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">defective immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutralizing antibody</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus type 1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">type 1 diabetes</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36971180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Hyoty H. Viruses in T1D. Pediatr Diabetes. 2016;17(suppl 22):56-64. doi:10.1111/pedi.12370</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Correction to: recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(6):1515. doi:10.1007/s00705-020-04558-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vehik K, Lynch KF, Wong MC, et al. Prospective virome analyses in young children at increased genetic risk for type 1 diabetes. Nature Med. 2019;25(12):1865-1872. doi:10.1038/s41591-019-0667-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honkanen H, Oikarinen S, Nurminen N, et al. Detection of enteroviruses in stools precedes islet autoimmunity by several months: possible evidence for slowly operating mechanisms in virus-induced autoimmunity. Diabetologia. 2017;60(3):424-431. doi:10.1007/s00125-016-4177-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laitinen OH, Honkanen H, Pakkanen O, et al. Coxsackievirus B1 is associated with induction of β-cell autoimmunity that portends type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2014;63(2):446-455. doi:10.2337/db13-0619</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sioofy-Khojine AB, Lehtonen J, Nurminen N, et al. Coxsackievirus B1 infections are associated with the initiation of insulin-driven autoimmunity that progresses to type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2018;61(5):1193-1202. doi:10.1007/s00125-018-4561-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clements GB, Galbraith DN, Taylor KW. Coxsackie B virus infection and onset of childhood diabetes. The Lancet. 1995;346(8969):221-223. doi:10.1016/s0140-6736(95)91270-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen S, Tauriainen S, Hober D, et al. Virus antibody survey in different European populations indicates risk association between coxsackievirus B1 and type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2014;63(2):655-662. doi:10.2337/db13-0620</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Ye F, Chen Y, et al. Association between enterovirus infection and type 1 diabetes risk: a meta-analysis of 38 case-control studies. Front Endocrinol. 2021;12:706964. doi:10.3389/fendo.2021.706964</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenson AB, Rosenberg HS, Notkins AL. Pancreatic islet-cell damage in children with fatal viral infections. Lancet (London, England). 1980;2(8190):354-358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ifie E, Russell MA, Dhayal S, et al. Unexpected subcellular distribution of a specific isoform of the coxsackie and adenovirus receptor, CAR-SIV, in human pancreatic beta cells. Diabetologia. 2018;61(11):2344-2355. doi:10.1007/s00125-018-4704-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyöty H, Leon F, Knip M. Developing a vaccine for type 1 diabetes by targeting coxsackievirus B. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2018;17(12):1071-1083. doi:10.1080/14760584.2018.1548281</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Provention Bio, Inc. (2021) A phase 1, first-in-human, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multiple-dose-escalation study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of PRV-101, a Coxsackie virus B (CVB) vaccine, in healthy adult subjects clinicaltrials.gov</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pallansch MA. Coxsackievirus B epidemiology and public health concerns. In: Tracy S, Chapman NM, Mahy BWJ, (eds.), The Coxsackie B Viruses. Springer; 1997:pp 13-30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone VM, Hankaniemi MM, Laitinen OH, et al. A hexavalent coxsackievirus B vaccine is highly immunogenic and has a strong protective capacity in mice and nonhuman primates. Sci Adv. 2020;6(19):eaaz2433. doi:10.1126/sciadv.aaz2433</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone VM, Butrym M, Hankaniemi MM, et al. Coxsackievirus B vaccines prevent infection-accelerated diabetes in NOD mice and have no disease-inducing effect. Diabetes. 2021;70(12):2871-2878.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leonardi S, Vitaliti G, Garozzo MT, Miraglia del Giudice M, Marseglia G, La Rosa M. Hepatitis B vaccination failure in children with diabetes mellitus? The debate continues. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2012;8(4):448-452. doi:10.4161/hv.19107</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanoni G, Contreas G, Valletta E, Gabrielli O, Mengoli C, Veneri D. Normal or defective immune response to hepatitis B vaccine in patients with diabetes and celiac disease. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2014;11(1):58-62. doi:10.4161/hv.34309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Mariotti Zani E, Torelli L, et al. Childhood vaccinations and type 1 diabetes. Front Immunol. 2021;12:667889. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2021.667889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesavadev J, Misra A, Das A, et al. Suggested use of vaccines in diabetes. Indian J Endocrinol Metab. 2012;16(6):886-893. doi:10.4103/2230-8210.102982</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z-K, Nie J-J, Li J, Zhuang H. The effect of HLA on immunological response to hepatitis B vaccine in healthy people: a meta-analysis. Vaccine. 2013;31(40):4355-4361. doi:10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.06.108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posteraro B, Pastorino R, Di Giannantonio P, et al. The link between genetic variation and variability in vaccine responses: systematic review and meta-analyses. Vaccine. 2014;32(15):1661-1669. doi:10.1016/j.vaccine.2014.01.057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashton MP, Eugster A, Walther D, et al. Incomplete immune response to coxsackie B viruses associates with early autoimmunity against insulin. Sci Rep. 2016;6:32899. doi:10.1038/srep32899</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarasova AA, Kniagina ON, Kalashnikova NA, Kostinov MP, Erukhimov VL. Immunity to poliovirus after vaccination of children with T1D mellitus and rheumatic diseases. Zh Mikrobiol Epidemiol Immunobiol. 2009;(5):52-56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikk M-L, Kiviniemi M, Laine A-P, et al. The HLA-B*39 allele increases type 1 diabetes risk conferred by HLA-DRB1*04:04-DQB1*03:02 and HLA-DRB1*08-DQB1*04 class II haplotypes. Hum Immunol. 2014;75(1):65-70. doi:10.1016/j.humimm.2013.09.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Enterovirus 71. https://www.who.int/teams/health-product-policy-and-standards/standards-and-specifications/vaccine-standardization/enterovirus-71 Accessed 12 Sep 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kouiavskaia D, Chen Z, Dragunsky E, Mirochnitchenko O, Purcell R, Chumakov K. A single chimpanzee-human neutralizing monoclonal antibody provides post-exposure protection against type 1 and type 2 polioviruses. J Clin Virol. 2015;65:32-37. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2015.01.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsson PG, Lakshmikanth T, Laitinen OH, et al. A preclinical study on the efficacy and safety of a new vaccine against coxsackievirus B1 reveals no risk for accelerated diabetes development in mouse models. Diabetologia. 2015;58:346-354. doi:10.1007/s00125-014-3436-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, Protocol for notification, risk assessment, and response following detection of poliovirus type 2 following globally-coordinated cessation of serotype 2-containing oral polio vaccine (2015), https://apps.who.int/gb/ebwha/pdf_files/WHA71/A71_R16-en.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krischer JP, Lynch KF, Schatz DA, et al. The 6 year incidence of diabetes-associated autoantibodies in genetically at-risk children: the TEDDY study. Diabetologia. 2015;58(5):980-987. doi:10.1007/s00125-015-3514-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Näntö-Salonen K, Kupila A, Simell S, et al. Nasal insulin to prevent type 1 diabetes in children with HLA genotypes and autoantibodies conferring increased risk of disease: a double-blind, randomised controlled trial. The Lancet. 2008;372(9651):1746-1755. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61309-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilonen J, Kiviniemi M, Lempainen J, et al. Genetic susceptibility to type 1 diabetes in childhood - estimation of HLA class II associated disease risk and class II effect in various phases of islet autoimmunity: HLA class II effects in T1D. Pediatr Diabetes. 2016;17(suppl 22):8-16. doi:10.1111/pedi.12327</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner SG, Gale EA, Williams AJ, et al. Progression to diabetes in relatives with islet autoantibodies. Is it inevitable? Diabetes Care. 1999;22(12):2049-2054. doi:10.2337/diacare.22.12.2049</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng K, Stavropoulos H, Anand V, et al. Islet autoantibody type-specific titer thresholds improve stratification of risk of progression to type 1 diabetes in children. Diabetes Care. 2022;45(1):160-168. doi:10.2337/dc21-0878</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegler AG, Rewers M, Simell O, et al. Seroconversion to multiple islet autoantibodies and risk of progression to diabetes in children. JAMA. 2013;309(23):2473-2479. doi:10.1001/jama.2013.6285</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapola S. National immunization program in Finland. Int J Circumpolar Health. 2007;66(5):382-389. doi:10.3402/ijch.v66i5.18310</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathanson N. David Bodian's contribution to the development of poliovirus vaccine. Am J Epidemiol. 2005;161(3):207-212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Expanded Programme on Immunization. Guidelines for WHO/EPI collaborative studies on poliomyelitis: standard procedure for determining immunity to poliovirus using the microneutralization test. World Health Organization; 1993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo C-L, Duan Y, Grady J. Unconditional or conditional logistic regression model for age-matched case-control data? Front Public Health. 2018;6:57. doi:10.3389/fpubh.2018.00057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silvestri F, Tromba V, Mazzotta I, Costantino F. How diabetes type 1 affects immune response to hepatitis B virus vaccine in pediatric population? Evaluation of a booster dose in unresponsive subjects with type 1 diabetes. Minerva Pediatrics. 2019; Nov 11. doi:10.23736/S0026-4946.19.05678-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eibl N, Spatz M, Fischer GF, et al. Impaired primary immune response in type-1 diabetes: results from a controlled vaccination study. Clinical immunology (Orlando, Fla.). 2002;103(3 Pt 1):249-259. doi:10.1006/clim.2002.5220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battaglia M, Ahmed S, Anderson MS, et al. Introducing the endotype concept to address the challenge of disease heterogeneity in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2020;43(1):5-12. doi:10.2337/dc19-0880</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morse ZJ, Horwitz MS. Virus infection is an instigator of intestinal dysbiosis leading to type 1 diabetes. Front Immunol. 2021;12:751337. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2021.751337</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>