<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36977948</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-8798</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>168</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Archives of virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arch Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Roles and mechanisms of exosomal microRNAs in viral infections.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>121</StartPage><MedlinePgn>121</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">121</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00705-023-05744-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Exosomes are small extracellular vesicles with a diameter of 30-150 nm that originate from endosomes and fuse with the plasma membrane. They are secreted by almost all kinds of cells and can stably transfer different kinds of cargo from donor to recipient cells, thereby altering cellular functions for assisting cell-to-cell communication. Exosomes derived from virus-infected cells during viral infections are likely to contain different microRNAs (miRNAs) that can be transferred to recipient cells. Exosomes can either promote or suppress viral infections and therefore play a dual role in viral infection. In this review, we summarize the current knowledge about the role of exosomal miRNAs during infection by six important viruses (hepatitis C virus, enterovirus A71, Epstein-Barr virus, human immunodeficiency virus, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2, and Zika virus), each of which causes a significant global public health problem. We describe how these exosomal miRNAs, including both donor-cell-derived and virus-encoded miRNAs, modulate the functions of the recipient cell. Lastly, we briefly discuss their potential value for the diagnosis and treatment of viral infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Austria, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Mao</LastName><ForeName>Lingxiang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Affiliated Kunshan Hospital of Jiangsu University, Kunshan, China. maolingxiang@aliyun.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yiwen</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Affiliated Kunshan Hospital of Jiangsu University, Kunshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Laboratory Medicine, School of Medicine, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gu</LastName><ForeName>Jiaqi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital and Jiangsu Key Laboratory for Molecular Medicine, Nanjing University Medicine School of Medicine, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Yuxue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Affiliated Kunshan Hospital of Jiangsu University, Kunshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Laboratory Medicine, School of Medicine, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Qiaoqiao</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Affiliated Kunshan Hospital of Jiangsu University, Kunshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Laboratory Medicine, School of Medicine, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32070182</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ZD2021049</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Commission of Health</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Austria</Country><MedlineTA>Arch Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7506870</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0304-8608</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D035683">MicroRNAs</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D035683" MajorTopicYN="Y">MicroRNAs</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020031" MajorTopicYN="Y">Epstein-Barr Virus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004854" MajorTopicYN="N">Herpesvirus 4, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055354" MajorTopicYN="Y">Exosomes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071244" MajorTopicYN="Y">Zika Virus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071243" MajorTopicYN="Y">Zika Virus Infection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36977948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10047465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-023-05744-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00705-023-05744-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>van Niel G, D'Angelo G, Raposo G. Shedding light on the cell biology of extracellular vesicles. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2018;19:213–228. doi: 10.1038/nrm.2017.125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrm.2017.125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29339798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anand S, Samuel M, Kumar S, Mathivanan S. Ticket to a bubble ride: Cargo sorting into exosomes and extracellular vesicles. Biochim Biophys Acta Proteins Proteom. 2019;1867:140203. doi: 10.1016/j.bbapap.2019.02.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbapap.2019.02.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30822540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowal J, Tkach M, Thery C. Biogenesis and secretion of exosomes. Curr Opin Cell Biol. 2014;29:116–125. doi: 10.1016/j.ceb.2014.05.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2014.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24959705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colombo M, Moita C, van Niel G, Kowal J, Vigneron J, Benaroch P, Manel N, Moita LF, Théry C, Raposo G. Analysis of ESCRT functions in exosome biogenesis, composition and secretion highlights the heterogeneity of extracellular vesicles. J Cell Sci. 2013;126:5553–5565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24105262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittelbrunn M, Sanchez-Madrid F. Intercellular communication: diverse structures for exchange of genetic information. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2012;13:328–335. doi: 10.1038/nrm3335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrm3335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3738855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22510790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathieu M, Martin-Jaular L, Lavieu G, Théry C. Specificities of secretion and uptake of exosomes and other extracellular vesicles for cell-to-cell communication. Nat Cell Biol. 2019;21:9–17. doi: 10.1038/s41556-018-0250-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41556-018-0250-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30602770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Théry C, Witwer KW, Aikawa E, Alcaraz MJ, Anderson JD, Andriantsitohaina R, Antoniou A, Arab T, Archer F, Atkin-Smith GK, Ayre DC, Bach JM, Bachurski D, Baharvand H, Balaj L, Baldacchino S, Bauer NN, Baxter AA, Bebawy M, Beckham C, Bedina Zavec A, Benmoussa A, Berardi AC, Bergese P, Bielska E, Blenkiron C, Bobis-Wozowicz S, Boilard E, Boireau W, Bongiovanni A, Borràs FE, Bosch S, Boulanger CM, Breakefield X, Breglio AM, Brennan M, Brigstock DR, Brisson A, Broekman ML, Bromberg JF, Bryl-Górecka P, Buch S, Buck AH, Burger D, Busatto S, Buschmann D, Bussolati B, Buzás EI, Byrd JB, Camussi G, Carter DR, Caruso S, Chamley LW, Chang YT, Chen C, Chen S, Cheng L, Chin AR, Clayton A, Clerici SP, Cocks A, Cocucci E, Coffey RJ, Cordeiro-da-Silva A, Couch Y, Coumans FA, Coyle B, Crescitelli R, Criado MF, D'Souza-Schorey C, Das S, Datta Chaudhuri A, de Candia P, De Santana EF, De Wever O, Del Portillo HA, Demaret T, Deville S, Devitt A, Dhondt B, Di Vizio D, Dieterich LC, Dolo V, Dominguez Rubio AP, Dominici M, Dourado MR, Driedonks TA, Duarte FV, Duncan HM, Eichenberger RM, Ekström K, El Andaloussi S, Elie-Caille C, Erdbrügger U, Falcón-Pérez JM, Fatima F, Fish JE, Flores-Bellver M, Försönits A, Frelet-Barrand A, Fricke F, Fuhrmann G, Gabrielsson S, Gámez-Valero A, Gardiner C, Gärtner K, Gaudin R, Gho YS, Giebel B, Gilbert C, Gimona M, Giusti I, Goberdhan DC, Görgens A, Gorski SM, Greening DW, Gross JC, Gualerzi A, Gupta GN, Gustafson D, Handberg A, Haraszti RA, Harrison P, Hegyesi H, Hendrix A, Hill AF, Hochberg FH, Hoffmann KF, Holder B, Holthofer H, Hosseinkhani B, Hu G, Huang Y, Huber V, Hunt S, Ibrahim AG, Ikezu T, Inal JM, Isin M, Ivanova A, Jackson HK, Jacobsen S, Jay SM, Jayachandran M, Jenster G, Jiang L, Johnson SM, Jones JC, Jong A, Jovanovic-Talisman T, Jung S, Kalluri R, Kano SI, Kaur S, Kawamura Y, Keller ET, Khamari D, Khomyakova E, Khvorova A, Kierulf P, Kim KP, Kislinger T, Klingeborn M, Klinke DJ, 2nd, Kornek M, Kosanović MM, Kovács ÁF, Krämer-Albers EM, Krasemann S, Krause M, Kurochkin IV, Kusuma GD, Kuypers S, Laitinen S, Langevin SM, Languino LR, Lannigan J, Lässer C, Laurent LC, Lavieu G, Lázaro-Ibáñez E, Le Lay S, Lee MS, Lee YXF, Lemos DS, Lenassi M, Leszczynska A, Li IT, Liao K, Libregts SF, Ligeti E, Lim R, Lim SK, Linē A, Linnemannstöns K, Llorente A, Lombard CA, Lorenowicz MJ, Lörincz Á M, Lötvall J, Lovett J, Lowry MC, Loyer X, Lu Q, Lukomska B, Lunavat TR, Maas SL, Malhi H, Marcilla A, Mariani J, Mariscal J, Martens-Uzunova ES, Martin-Jaular L, Martinez MC, Martins VR, Mathieu M, Mathivanan S, Maugeri M, McGinnis LK, McVey MJ, Meckes DG, Jr., Meehan KL, Mertens I, Minciacchi VR, Möller A, Møller Jørgensen M, Morales-Kastresana A, Morhayim J, Mullier F, Muraca M, Musante L, Mussack V, Muth DC, Myburgh KH, Najrana T, Nawaz M, Nazarenko I, Nejsum P, Neri C, Neri T, Nieuwland R, Nimrichter L, Nolan JP, Nolte-'t Hoen EN, Noren Hooten N, O'Driscoll L, O'Grady T, O'Loghlen A, Ochiya T, Olivier M, Ortiz A, Ortiz LA, Osteikoetxea X, Østergaard O, Ostrowski M, Park J, Pegtel DM, Peinado H, Perut F, Pfaffl MW, Phinney DG, Pieters BC, Pink RC, Pisetsky DS, Pogge von Strandmann E, Polakovicova I, Poon IK, Powell BH, Prada I, Pulliam L, Quesenberry P, Radeghieri A, Raffai RL, Raimondo S, Rak J, Ramirez MI, Raposo G, Rayyan MS, Regev-Rudzki N, Ricklefs FL, Robbins PD, Roberts DD, Rodrigues SC, Rohde E, Rome S, Rouschop KM, Rughetti A, Russell AE, Saá P, Sahoo S, Salas-Huenuleo E, Sánchez C, Saugstad JA, Saul MJ, Schiffelers RM, Schneider R, Schøyen TH, Scott A, Shahaj E, Sharma S, Shatnyeva O, Shekari F, Shelke GV, Shetty AK, Shiba K, Siljander PR, Silva AM, Skowronek A, Snyder OL 2nd, Soares RP, Sódar BW, Soekmadji C, Sotillo J, Stahl PD, Stoorvogel W, Stott SL, Strasser EF, Swift S, Tahara H, Tewari M, Timms K, Tiwari S, Tixeira R, Tkach M, Toh WS, Tomasini R, Torrecilhas AC, Tosar JP, Toxavidis V, Urbanelli L, Vader P, van Balkom BW, van der Grein SG, Van Deun J, van Herwijnen MJ, Van Keuren-Jensen K, van Niel G, van Royen ME, van Wijnen AJ, Vasconcelos MH, Vechetti IJ, Jr., Veit TD, Vella LJ, Velot É, Verweij FJ, Vestad B, Viñas JL, Visnovitz T, Vukman KV, Wahlgren J, Watson DC, Wauben MH, Weaver A, Webber JP, Weber V, Wehman AM, Weiss DJ, Welsh JA, Wendt S, Wheelock AM, Wiener Z, Witte L, Wolfram J, Xagorari A, Xander P, Xu J, Yan X, Yáñez-Mó M, Yin H, Yuana Y, Zappulli V, Zarubova J, Žėkas V, Zhang JY, Zhao Z, Zheng L, Zheutlin AR, Zickler AM, Zimmermann P, Zivkovic AM, Zocco D, Zuba-Surma EK (2018) Minimal information for studies of extracellular vesicles 2018 (MISEV2018): a position statement of the International Society for Extracellular Vesicles and update of the MISEV2014 guidelines. J Extracell Vesicles 7:1535750</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6322352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30637094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harada Y, Suzuki T, Fukushige T, Kizuka Y, Yagi H, Yamamoto M, Kondo K, Inoue H, Kato K, Taniguchi N, Kanekura T, Dohmae N, Maruyama I. Generation of the heterogeneity of extracellular vesicles by membrane organization and sorting machineries. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General Subjects. 2019;1863:681–691. doi: 10.1016/j.bbagen.2019.01.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2019.01.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30690120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathan M, Fonseka P, Chitti SV, Kang T, Sanwlani R, Van Deun J, Hendrix A, Mathivanan S. Vesiclepedia 2019: a compendium of RNA, proteins, lipids and metabolites in extracellular vesicles. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47:D516–d519. doi: 10.1093/nar/gky1029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6323905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30395310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartel DP. Metazoan MicroRNAs. Cell. 2018;173:20–51. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2018.03.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.03.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6091663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29570994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendell JT. MicroRNAs: critical regulators of development, cellular physiology and malignancy. Cell Cycle. 2005;4:1179–1184. doi: 10.4161/cc.4.9.2032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/cc.4.9.2032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16096373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cullen BR. Viruses and microRNAs: RISCy interactions with serious consequences. Genes Dev. 2011;25:1881–1894. doi: 10.1101/gad.17352611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/gad.17352611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3185961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21896651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kincaid RP, Sullivan CS. Virus-encoded microRNAs: an overview and a look to the future. PLoS Pathog. 2012;8:e1003018. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3534370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23308061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qureshi A, Thakur N, Monga I, Thakur A, Kumar M. VIRmiRNA: a comprehensive resource for experimentally validated viral miRNAs and their targets. Database (Oxford) 2014 doi: 10.1093/database/bau103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/database/bau103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4224276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25380780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meckes DG, Jr, Raab-Traub N. Microvesicles and viral infection. J Virol. 2011;85:12844–12854. doi: 10.1128/JVI.05853-11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.05853-11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3233125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21976651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schorey JS, Cheng Y, Singh PP, Smith VL. Exosomes and other extracellular vesicles in host-pathogen interactions. EMBO Rep. 2015;16:24–43. doi: 10.15252/embr.201439363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15252/embr.201439363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4304727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25488940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittelbrunn M, Gutiérrez-Vázquez C, Villarroya-Beltri C, González S, Sánchez-Cabo F, González M, Bernad A, Sánchez-Madrid F. Unidirectional transfer of microRNA-loaded exosomes from T cells to antigen-presenting cells. Nat Commun. 2011;2:282. doi: 10.1038/ncomms1285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncomms1285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3104548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21505438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin F, Zeng Z, Song Y, Li L, Wu Z, Zhang X, Li Z, Ke X, Hu X. YBX-1 mediated sorting of miR-133 into hypoxia/reoxygenation-induced EPC-derived exosomes to increase fibroblast angiogenesis and MEndoT. Stem Cell Res Ther. 2019;10:263. doi: 10.1186/s13287-019-1377-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13287-019-1377-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6708233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31443679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santangelo L, Giurato G, Cicchini C, Montaldo C, Mancone C, Tarallo R, Battistelli C, Alonzi T, Weisz A, Tripodi M. The RNA-binding protein SYNCRIP is a component of the hepatocyte exosomal machinery controlling microRNA sorting. Cell Rep. 2016;17:799–808. doi: 10.1016/j.celrep.2016.09.031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.09.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27732855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villarroya-Beltri C, Gutierrez-Vazquez C, Sanchez-Cabo F, Perez-Hernandez D, Vazquez J, Martin-Cofreces N, Martinez-Herrera DJ, Pascual-Montano A, Mittelbrunn M, Sanchez-Madrid F. Sumoylated hnRNPA2B1 controls the sorting of miRNAs into exosomes through binding to specific motifs. Nat Commun. 2013;4:2980. doi: 10.1038/ncomms3980.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/ncomms3980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3905700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24356509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKenzie AJ, Hoshino D, Hong NH, Cha DJ, Franklin JL, Coffey RJ, Patton JG, Weaver AM. KRAS-MEK signaling controls Ago2 sorting into exosomes. Cell Rep. 2016;15:978–987. doi: 10.1016/j.celrep.2016.03.085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.03.085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4857875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27117408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cha DJ, Franklin JL, Dou Y, Liu Q, Higginbotham JN, Demory Beckler M, Weaver AM, Vickers K, Prasad N, Levy S, Zhang B, Coffey RJ, Patton JG. KRAS-dependent sorting of miRNA to exosomes. Elife. 2015;4:e07197. doi: 10.7554/eLife.07197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.07197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4510696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26132860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosaka N, Iguchi H, Hagiwara K, Yoshioka Y, Takeshita F, Ochiya T. Neutral sphingomyelinase 2 (nSMase2)-dependent exosomal transfer of angiogenic microRNAs regulate cancer cell metastasis. J Biol Chem. 2013;288:10849–10859. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M112.446831.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.446831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3624465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23439645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapoor A, Simmonds P, Gerold G, Qaisar N, Jain K, Henriquez JA, Firth C, Hirschberg DL, Rice CM, Shields S, Lipkin WI. Characterization of a canine homolog of hepatitis C virus. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2011;108:11608–11613. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1101794108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1101794108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3136326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21610165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drexler JF, Corman VM, Müller MA, Lukashev AN, Gmyl A, Coutard B, Adam A, Ritz D, Leijten LM, van Riel D, Kallies R, Klose SM, Gloza-Rausch F, Binger T, Annan A, Adu-Sarkodie Y, Oppong S, Bourgarel M, Rupp D, Hoffmann B, Schlegel M, Kümmerer BM, Krüger DH, Schmidt-Chanasit J, Setién AA, Cottontail VM, Hemachudha T, Wacharapluesadee S, Osterrieder K, Bartenschlager R, Matthee S, Beer M, Kuiken T, Reusken C, Leroy EM, Ulrich RG, Drosten C. Evidence for novel hepaciviruses in rodents. PLoS Pathog. 2013;9:e1003438. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3688547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23818848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clouston AD, Powell EE, Walsh MJ, Richardson MM, Demetris AJ, Jonsson JR. Fibrosis correlates with a ductular reaction in hepatitis C: roles of impaired replication, progenitor cells and steatosis. Hepatology. 2005;41:809–818. doi: 10.1002/hep.20650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hep.20650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15793848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colombo M, Kuo G, Choo QL, Donato MF, Del Ninno E, Tommasini MA, Dioguardi N, Houghton M. Prevalence of antibodies to hepatitis C virus in Italian patients with hepatocellular carcinoma. Lancet. 1989;2:1006–1008. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(89)91016-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(89)91016-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2572740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew MC, Houghton M, Choo QL, Kuo G. Hepatitis C virus antibodies in southern African blacks with hepatocellular carcinoma. Lancet. 1990;335:873–874. doi: 10.1016/0140-6736(90)90474-J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0140-6736(90)90474-J</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1691422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lonardo A, Adinolfi LE, Loria P, Carulli N, Ruggiero G, Day CP. Steatosis and hepatitis C virus: mechanisms and significance for hepatic and extrahepatic disease. Gastroenterology. 2004;126:586–597. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2003.11.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2003.11.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14762795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bukong TN, Momen-Heravi F, Kodys K, Bala S, Szabo G. Exosomes from hepatitis C infected patients transmit HCV infection and contain replication competent viral RNA in complex with Ago2-miR122-HSP90. PLoS Pathog. 2014;10:e1004424. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1004424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4183590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25275643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szabo G, Bala S. MicroRNAs in liver disease. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2013;10:542–552. doi: 10.1038/nrgastro.2013.87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2013.87</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4091636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23689081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson JA, Zhang C, Huys A, Richardson CD. Human Ago2 is required for efficient microRNA 122 regulation of hepatitis C virus RNA accumulation and translation. J Virol. 2011;85:2342–2350. doi: 10.1128/JVI.02046-10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.02046-10</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3067765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21177824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimakami T, Yamane D, Jangra RK, Kempf BJ, Spaniel C, Barton DJ, Lemon SM. Stabilization of hepatitis C virus RNA by an Ago2-miR-122 complex. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2012;109:941–946. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1112263109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1112263109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3271899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22215596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao TL, Chen YM, Hsieh SL, Tang KT, Chen DY, Yang YY, Liu HJ, Yang SS. Hepatitis C Virus-Induced Exosomal MicroRNAs and Toll-Like Receptor 7 Polymorphism Regulate B-Cell Activating Factor. MBio. 2021;12:e0276421. doi: 10.1128/mBio.02764-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.02764-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8561394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34724826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bala S, Tilahun Y, Taha O, Alao H, Kodys K, Catalano D, Szabo G. Increased microRNA-155 expression in the serum and peripheral monocytes in chronic HCV infection. J Transl Med. 2012;10:151. doi: 10.1186/1479-5876-10-151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-10-151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3477071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22846613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao TL, Hsieh SL, Chen YM, Chen HH, Liu HJ, Lee HC, Chen DY. Rituximab may cause increased hepatitis C virus viremia in rheumatoid arthritis patients through declining exosomal microRNA-155. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2018;70:1209–1219. doi: 10.1002/art.40495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/art.40495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29575671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim OK, Nam DE, Hahn YS. The pannexin 1/purinergic receptor P2X4 Pathway controls the secretion of microRNA-containing exosomes by HCV-infected hepatocytes. Hepatology. 2021;74:3409–3426. doi: 10.1002/hep.32042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hep.32042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8639610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34218459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devhare PB, Sasaki R, Shrivastava S, Di Bisceglie AM, Ray R, Ray RB. Exosome-mediated intercellular communication between hepatitis C virus-infected hepatocytes and hepatic stellate cells. J Virol. 2017 doi: 10.1128/JVI.02225-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.02225-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5331806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28077652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JH, Lee CH, Lee SW. Exosomal transmission of microRNA from HCV replicating cells stimulates transdifferentiation in hepatic stellate cells. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2019;14:483–497. doi: 10.1016/j.omtn.2019.01.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2019.01.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6369229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30753992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian X, Xu C, Fang S, Zhao P, Wang Y, Liu H, Yuan W, Qi Z. Exosomal microRNAs derived from umbilical mesenchymal stem cells inhibit hepatitis C virus infection. Stem Cells Transl Med. 2016;5:1190–1203. doi: 10.5966/sctm.2015-0348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5966/sctm.2015-0348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4996444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27496568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J, Wu J, Fang D, Qiu Y, Zou X, Jia X, Yin Y, Shen L, Mao L. Exosomes cloak the virion to transmit Enterovirus 71 non-lytically. Virulence. 2020;11:32–38. doi: 10.1080/21505594.2019.1705022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21505594.2019.1705022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6961726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31885311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu Y, Zhang L, Zhang F, Tang T, Zhou Q, Feng C, Jin Y, Wu Z. Exosome-mediated miR-146a transfer suppresses type I interferon response and facilitates EV71 infection. PLoS Pathog. 2017;13:e1006611. doi: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1006611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5614653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28910400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin JY, Brewer G, Li ML. HuR and Ago2 bind the internal ribosome entry site of enterovirus 71 and promote virus translation and replication. PLoS ONE. 2015;10:e0140291. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0140291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4599798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26451954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Zhang S, Song W, Zhang W, Li J, Li C, Qiu Y, Fang Y, Jiang Q, Li X, Yan B. Exosomes from EV71-infected oral epithelial cells can transfer miR-30a to promote EV71 infection. Oral Dis. 2020;26:778–788. doi: 10.1111/odi.13283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/odi.13283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31958204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Gu J, Shen L, Fang D, Zou X, Cao Y, Wang S, Mao L. Exosomal microRNA-155 inhibits enterovirus A71 infection by targeting PICALM. Int J Biol Sci. 2019;15:2925–2935. doi: 10.7150/ijbs.36388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7150/ijbs.36388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6909958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31853228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyauchi K, Kim Y, Latinovic O, Morozov V, Melikyan GB. HIV enters cells via endocytosis and dynamin-dependent fusion with endosomes. Cell. 2009;137:433–444. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2009.02.046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.02.046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2696170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19410541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Vega M, Marin M, Kondo N, Miyauchi K, Kim Y, Epand RF, Epand RM, Melikyan GB. Inhibition of HIV-1 endocytosis allows lipid mixing at the plasma membrane, but not complete fusion. Retrovirology. 2011;8:99. doi: 10.1186/1742-4690-8-99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4690-8-99</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3297528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22145853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pegtel DM, Cosmopoulos K, Thorley-Lawson DA, van Eijndhoven MA, Hopmans ES, Lindenberg JL, de Gruijl TD, Wurdinger T, Middeldorp JM. Functional delivery of viral miRNAs via exosomes. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2010;107:6328–6333. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0914843107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0914843107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2851954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20304794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melincovici CS, Boşca AB, Şuşman S, Mărginean M, Mihu C, Istrate M, Moldovan IM, Roman AL, Mihu CM. Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)—key factor in normal and pathological angiogenesis. Rom J Morphol Embryol. 2018;59:455–467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30173249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon C, Kim J, Park G, Kim S, Kim D, Hur DY, Kim B, Kim YS. Delivery of miR-155 to retinal pigment epithelial cells mediated by Burkitt's lymphoma exosomes. Tumour Biol. 2016;37:313–321. doi: 10.1007/s13277-015-3769-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13277-015-3769-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26211004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forte E, Luftig MA. The role of microRNAs in Epstein-Barr virus latency and lytic reactivation. Microbes Infect. 2011;13:1156–1167. doi: 10.1016/j.micinf.2011.07.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2011.07.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4911174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21835261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catalán MA, Nakamoto T, Melvin JE. The salivary gland fluid secretion mechanism. J Med Invest. 2009;56(Suppl):192–196. doi: 10.2152/jmi.56.192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2152/jmi.56.192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20224180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallo A, Jang SI, Ong HL, Perez P, Tandon M, Ambudkar I, Illei G, Alevizos I. Targeting the Ca(2+) Sensor STIM1 by exosomal transfer of Ebv-miR-BART13-3p is associated with Sjögren's Syndrome. EBioMedicine. 2016;10:216–226. doi: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.06.041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.06.041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5006644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27381477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gourzones C, Gelin A, Bombik I, Klibi J, Vérillaud B, Guigay J, Lang P, Témam S, Schneider V, Amiel C, Baconnais S, Jimenez AS, Busson P. Extra-cellular release and blood diffusion of BART viral micro-RNAs produced by EBV-infected nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells. Virol J. 2010;7:271. doi: 10.1186/1743-422X-7-271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-7-271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2974674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20950422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Jiang Q, Faleti OD, Tsang CM, Zhao M, Wu G, Tsao SW, Fu M, Chen Y, Ding T, Chong T, Long Y, Yang X, Zhang Y, Cai Y, Li H, Peng M, Lyu X, Li X. Exosomal delivery of AntagomiRs targeting viral and cellular microRNAs synergistically inhibits cancer angiogenesis. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2020;22:153–165. doi: 10.1016/j.omtn.2020.08.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2020.08.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7494942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32927364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Doare K, Holder B, Bassett A, Pannaraj PS. Mother's milk: a purposeful contribution to the development of the infant microbiota and immunity. Front Immunol. 2018;9:361. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2018.00361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5863526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29599768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahoor MA, Yao XD, Henrick BM, Verschoor CP, Abimiku A, Osawe S, Rosenthal KL. Expression profiling of human milk derived exosomal microRNAs and their targets in HIV-1 infected mothers. Sci Rep. 2020;10:12931. doi: 10.1038/s41598-020-69799-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-69799-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7395778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32737406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes A, Betts AC, Borton EK, Sanders JM, Pruitt SL, Werner C, Bran A, Estelle CD, Balasubramanian BA, Inrig SJ, Halm EA, Skinner CS, Tiro JA. Cervical cancer screening among HIV-infected women in an urban, United States safety-net healthcare system. AIDS. 2018;32:1861–1870. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0000000000001881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAD.0000000000001881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6059987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29762164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Chi X, Li R, Ouyang J, Chen Y. HIV-1-infected cell-derived exosomes promote the growth and progression of cervical cancer. Int J Biol Sci. 2019;15:2438–2447. doi: 10.7150/ijbs.38146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7150/ijbs.38146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6775309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31595161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klase Z, Kale P, Winograd R, Gupta MV, Heydarian M, Berro R, McCaffrey T, Kashanchi F. HIV-1 TAR element is processed by Dicer to yield a viral micro-RNA involved in chromatin remodeling of the viral LTR. BMC Mol Biol. 2007;8:63. doi: 10.1186/1471-2199-8-63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-8-63</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1955452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17663774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouellet DL, Plante I, Landry P, Barat C, Janelle ME, Flamand L, Tremblay MJ, Provost P. Identification of functional microRNAs released through asymmetrical processing of HIV-1 TAR element. Nucleic Acids Res. 2008;36:2353–2365. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkn076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2367715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18299284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narayanan A, Iordanskiy S, Das R, Van Duyne R, Santos S, Jaworski E, Guendel I, Sampey G, Dalby E, Iglesias-Ussel M, Popratiloff A, Hakami R, Kehn-Hall K, Young M, Subra C, Gilbert C, Bailey C, Romerio F, Kashanchi F. Exosomes derived from HIV-1-infected cells contain trans-activation response element RNA. J Biol Chem. 2013;288:20014–20033. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M112.438895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.438895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3707700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23661700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampey GC, Saifuddin M, Schwab A, Barclay R, Punya S, Chung MC, Hakami RM, Zadeh MA, Lepene B, Klase ZA, El-Hage N, Young M, Iordanskiy S, Kashanchi F. Exosomes from HIV-1-infected Cells stimulate production of pro-inflammatory cytokines through trans-activating response (TAR) RNA. J Biol Chem. 2016;291:1251–1266. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M115.662171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.662171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4714213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26553869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivest S. Regulation of innate immune responses in the brain. Nat Rev Immunol. 2009;9:429–439. doi: 10.1038/nri2565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nri2565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19461673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Niu F, Yao H, Liao K, Chen X, Kook Y, Ma R, Hu G, Buch S. Exosomal miR-9 released from HIV tat stimulated astrocytes mediates microglial migration. J Neuroimmune Pharmacol. 2018;13:330–344. doi: 10.1007/s11481-018-9779-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11481-018-9779-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6082702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29497921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W, Li X, Yang B, Song J, Zhao X, Huang B, Shi W, Lu R, Niu P, Zhan F, Ma X, Wang D, Xu W, Wu G, Gao GF, Tan W. A Novel coronavirus from patients with Pneumonia in China, 2019. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:727–733. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2001017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2001017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iroegbu JD, Ifenatuoha CW, Ijomone OM. Potential neurological impact of coronaviruses: implications for the novel SARS-CoV-2. Neurol Sci. 2020;41:1329–1337. doi: 10.1007/s10072-020-04469-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10072-020-04469-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7232928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32424503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra R, Banerjea AC. SARS-CoV-2 spike targets USP33-IRF9 axis via exosomal miR-148a to activate human microglia. Front Immunol. 2021;12:656700. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.656700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.656700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8079643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33936086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofer MJ, Li W, Lim SL, Campbell IL. The type I interferon-alpha mediates a more severe neurological disease in the absence of the canonical signaling molecule interferon regulatory factor 9. J Neurosci. 2010;30:1149–1157. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3711-09.2010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3711-09.2010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6633112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20089923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz IC, Bertoni APS, Wink MR. Mesenchymal stem cell-derived extracellular vesicles carrying miRNA as a potential multi target therapy to COVID-19: an in silico analysis. Stem Cell Rev Rep. 2021;17:341–356. doi: 10.1007/s12015-021-10122-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12015-021-10122-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7842178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33511519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng Y, Xu F, Zhang X, Mu J, Sayed M, Hu X, Lei C, Sriwastva M, Kumar A, Sundaram K, Zhang L, Park JW, Chen SY, Zhang S, Yan J, Merchant ML, Zhang X, McClain CJ, Wolfe JK, Adcock RS, Chung D, Palmer KE, Zhang HG. Plant-derived exosomal microRNAs inhibit lung inflammation induced by exosomes SARS-CoV-2 Nsp12. Mol Ther. 2021;29:2424–2440. doi: 10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.05.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.05.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8110335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33984520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao J, Feng S, Wang X, Long K, Luo Y, Wang Y, Ma J, Tang Q, Jin L, Li X, Li M. Identification of exosome-like nanoparticle-derived microRNAs from 11 edible fruits and vegetables. PeerJ. 2018;6:e5186. doi: 10.7717/peerj.5186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.5186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6074755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30083436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mu J, Zhuang X, Wang Q, Jiang H, Deng ZB, Wang B, Zhang L, Kakar S, Jun Y, Miller D, Zhang HG. Interspecies communication between plant and mouse gut host cells through edible plant derived exosome-like nanoparticles. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2014;58:1561–1573. doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201300729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201300729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4851829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24842810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalarikkal SP, Sundaram GM. Edible plant-derived exosomal microRNAs: Exploiting a cross-kingdom regulatory mechanism for targeting SARS-CoV-2. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. 2021;414:115425. doi: 10.1016/j.taap.2021.115425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2021.115425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7844364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33516820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez-Rojas PP, Quiroz-Garcia E, Monroy-Martinez V, Agredano-Moreno LT, Jimenez-Garcia LF, Ruiz-Ordaz BH. Participation of extracellular vesicles from Zika-virus-infected mosquito cells in the modification of Naive cells' behavior by mediating cell-to-cell transmission of viral elements. Cells. 2020;9:123. doi: 10.3390/cells9010123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells9010123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7016930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31947958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabari D, Scholl C, Steffens M, Weickhardt S, Elgner F, Bender D, Herrlein ML, Sabino C, Semkova V, Peitz M, Till A, Brustle O, Hildt E, Stingl J. Impact of Zika virus infection on human neural stem cell microRNA signatures. Viruses. 2020;12:1219. doi: 10.3390/v12111219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v12111219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33121145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B, Pan X, Cobb GP, Anderson TA. microRNAs as oncogenes and tumor suppressors. Dev Biol. 2007;302:1–12. doi: 10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.08.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.08.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16989803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma D, Liu H, Zhao P, Ye L, Zou H, Zhao X, Dai H, Kong X, Liu P. Programing assembling/releasing multifunctional miRNA nanomedicine to treat prostate cancer. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces. 2020;12:9032–9040. doi: 10.1021/acsami.9b21707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.9b21707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31986004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagachinta S, Bouzo BL, Vazquez-Rios AJ, Lopez R, Fuente M. Sphingomyelin-Based Nanosystems (SNs) for the Development of Anticancer miRNA Therapeutics. Pharmaceutics. 2020;12:189. doi: 10.3390/pharmaceutics12020189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pharmaceutics12020189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7076701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32098309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elfiky AM, Mohamed RH, Abd El-Hakam FE, Yassin MA, ElHefnawi M. Targeted delivery of miR-218 via decorated hyperbranched polyamidoamine for liver cancer regression. Int J Pharm. 2021;610:121256. doi: 10.1016/j.ijpharm.2021.121256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2021.121256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34732362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talluri SV, Kuppusamy G, Karri VV, Tummala S, Madhunapantula SV. Lipid-based nanocarriers for breast cancer treatment—comprehensive review. Drug Deliv. 2016;23:1291–1305. doi: 10.3109/10717544.2015.1092183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/10717544.2015.1092183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26430913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan C, Chen J, Wang C, Yuan M, Kang Y, Wu Z, Li W, Zhang G, Machens HG, Rinkevich Y, Chen Z, Yang X, Xu X. Milk exosomes-mediated miR-31-5p delivery accelerates diabetic wound healing through promoting angiogenesis. Drug Deliv. 2022;29:214–228. doi: 10.1080/10717544.2021.2023699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10717544.2021.2023699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8741248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34985397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villarroya-Beltri C, Baixauli F, Gutierrez-Vazquez C, Sanchez-Madrid F, Mittelbrunn M. Sorting it out: regulation of exosome loading. Semin Cancer Biol. 2014;28:3–13. doi: 10.1016/j.semcancer.2014.04.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.semcancer.2014.04.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4640178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24769058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Li Y, Zhang H, Zhao R, Jing R, Xu Y, He M, Peer J, Kim YC, Luo J, Tong Z, Zheng J. Zika virus propagation and release in human fetal astrocytes can be suppressed by neutral sphingomyelinase-2 inhibitor GW4869. Cell Discov. 2018;4:19. doi: 10.1038/s41421-018-0017-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41421-018-0017-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5913238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29707233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dogrammatzis C, Deschamps T, Kalamvoki M. Biogenesis of Extracellular Vesicles during Herpes Simplex Virus 1 Infection: Role of the CD63 Tetraspanin. J Virol. 2019 doi: 10.1128/JVI.01850-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.01850-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6321934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30355691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinata M, Kunita A, Abe H, Morishita Y, Sakuma K, Yamashita H, Seto Y, Ushiku T, Fukayama M. Exosomes of Epstein-Barr Virus-Associated Gastric Carcinoma Suppress Dendritic Cell Maturation. Microorganisms. 2020;8:1776. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms8111776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8111776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7697542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33198173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu G, Niu F, Liao K, Periyasamy P, Sil S, Liu J, Dravid SM, Buch S. HIV-1 tat-induced astrocytic extracellular vesicle miR-7 impairs synaptic architecture. J Neuroimmune Pharmacol. 2020;15:538–553. doi: 10.1007/s11481-019-09869-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11481-019-09869-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7008083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31401755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>