<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">37024058</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-7492</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>330</Volume><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virus research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virus Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Targeting HDAC11 activity by FT895 restricts EV71 replication.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>199108</StartPage><MedlinePgn>199108</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">199108</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.virusres.2023.199108</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0168-1702(23)00070-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus 71 (EV71) infection mainly causes hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) and remains a serious public health problem to the children under the age of 5. Until now, there is no specific drug to treat HFMD in clinical and there is an urgent to explore the new target and the new drug to address clinical challenges. At present, we found histone deacetylase 11 (HDAC11) involves in supporting EV71 replication. We also used HDAC11 siRNA and an HDAC11 inhibitor FT895 to downregulate HDAC11 expression and found that targeting HDAC11 could significantly restrict EV71 replication in vitro and in vivo. Our results revealed the new role of HDAC11 participating in EV71 replication and broadened our knowledge regarding the functions of HDAC11 and the roles of HDACs in the epigenetic regulation of viral infectious diseases. Our results for the first time identified FT895 as an effective inhibitor of EV71 in vitro and in vivo, which may contribute to be a potential drug to treat HFMD.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Hong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gynecology Nursing, West China Second University Hospital, Sichuan University/West China School of Nursing, Sichuan University, Chengdu, Sichuan, China; Key Laboratory of Birth Defects and Related Diseases of Women and Children (Sichuan University), Ministry of Education, Chengdu, Sichuan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Enhui</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Child Healthcare, Wenzhou People`s Hospital, Wenzhou, Zhejiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Chaoyong</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Medical College of Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, Jiangsu, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peng</LastName><ForeName>Chunyan</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital, Affiliated Drum Tower Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China. Electronic address: springpcy@aliyun.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Lianfu</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Children's Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, 72# Guangzhou Road, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China. Electronic address: jilianfu1223@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Virus Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8410979</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0168-1702</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.5.1.98</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D006655">Histone Deacetylases</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.5.1.98</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C462506">HDAC11 protein, human</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D044127" MajorTopicYN="N">Epigenesis, Genetic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006655" MajorTopicYN="N">Histone Deacetylases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EV71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FT895</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HDAC11</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HFMD</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest to this work</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37024058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10194106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2023.199108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0168-1702(23)00070-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Barneda-Zahonero B., Parra M. Histone deacetylases and cancer. Mol. Oncol. 2012;6(6):579–589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5528343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22963873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi L., Ren Y., Feng M., Meng P., Wang Q., Chen W., Jiao Q., Wang Y., Du L., Zhou F., Jiang Y., Chen F., Wang C., Tang B., Wang Y. HDAC11 regulates glycolysis through the lkb1/ampk signaling pathway to maintain hepatocellular carcinoma stemness. Cancer Res. 2021;81(8):2015–2028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33602787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J., Sun L., Aramsangtienchai P., Spiegelman N.A., Zhang X., Huang W., Seto E., Lin H. HDAC11 regulates type I interferon signaling through defatty-acylation of SHMT2. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2019;116(12):5487–5492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6431144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30819897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen D., Tian X., Zou X., Xu S., Wang H., Zheng N., Wu Z. Harmine, a small molecule derived from natural sources, inhibits enterovirus 71 replication by targeting NF-kappaB pathway. Int. Immunopharmacol. 2018;60:111–120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29730555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chi C., Sun Q., Wang S., Zhang Z., Li X., Cardona C.J., Jin Y., Xing Z. Robust antiviral responses to enterovirus 71 infection in human intestinal epithelial cells. Virus Res. 2013;176(1–2):53–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23685430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chong P., Liu C.C., Chow Y.H., Chou A.H., Klein M. Review of enterovirus 71 vaccines. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2015;60(5):797–803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25352588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duong V., Mey C., Eloit M., Zhu H., Danet L., Huang Z., Zou G., Tarantola A., Cheval J., Perot P., Laurent D., Richner B., Ky S., Heng S., Touch S., Sovann L., van Doorn R., Tan Tran T., Farrar J.J., Wentworth D.E., Das S.R., Stockwell T.B., Manuguerra J.C., Delpeyroux F., Guan Y., Altmeyer R., Buchy P. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus 71 at the origin of an epidemic of fatal hand, foot and mouth disease cases in Cambodia. Emerg. Microbes Infect. 2016;5(9):e104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5113052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27651091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao L., Cueto M.A., Asselbergs F., Atadja P. Cloning and functional characterization of HDAC11, a novel member of the human histone deacetylase family. J. Biol. Chem. 2002;277(28):25748–25755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11948178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goschl L., Preglej T., Hamminger P., Bonelli M., Andersen L., Boucheron N., Gulich A.F., Muller L., Saferding V., Mufazalov I.A., Hirahara K., Seiser C., Matthias P., Penz T., Schuster M., Bock C., Waisman A., Steiner G., Ellmeier W. A T cell-specific deletion of HDAC1 protects against experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. J. Autoimmun. 2018;86:51–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28964722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Y., Wang L., Cui J., Song Y., Luo Z., Chen J., Xiong Y., Zhang Q., Liu F., Ho W., Liu Y., Wu K., Wu J. SIRT1 inhibits EV71 genome replication and RNA translation by interfering with the viral polymerase and 5′UTR RNA. J. Cell. Sci. 2016;129(24):4534–4547.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5201017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27875274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heim C.E., Bosch M.E., Yamada K.J., Aldrich A.L., Chaudhari S.S., Klinkebiel D., Gries C.M., Alqarzaee A.A., Li Y., Thomas V.C., Seto E., Karpf A.R., Kielian T. Lactate production by staphylococcus aureus biofilm inhibits HDAC11 to reprogramme the host immune response during persistent infection. Nat. Microbiol. 2020;5(10):1271–1284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7529909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32661313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho T.C.S., Chan A.H.Y., Ganesan A. Thirty years of hdac inhibitors: 2020 insight and hindsight. J. Med. Chem. 2020;63(21):12460–12484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32608981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang P.Y., Shih I.A., Liao Y.C., You H.L., Lee M.J. A novel HDAC11 inhibitor potentiates the tumoricidal effects of cordycepin against malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumor through the Hippo signaling pathway. Am. J. Cancer Res. 2022;12(2):873–892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8899988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurtado E., Nunez-Alvarez Y., Munoz M., Gutierrez-Caballero C., Casas J., Pendas A.M., Peinado M.A., Suelves M. HDAC11 is a novel regulator of fatty acid oxidative metabolism in skeletal muscle. FEBS J. 2021;288(3):902–919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32563202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji L., Yang E., He S., Jin Y., Chen D. Enterovirus 2c protein suppresses Ikkalpha phosphorylation by recruiting ikkbeta and ikkalpha into viral inclusion bodies. Viral Immunol. 2021;34(4):218–226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33226912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju Y., Tan Z., Huang H., Chen M., Tan Y., Zhang C., Wang J., Wang H., Chen M. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics of Coxsackievirus A6- and Enterovirus 71-associated clinical stage 2 and 3 severe hand, foot, and mouth disease in Guangxi, Southern China, 2017. J. Infect. 2020;80(1):121–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31629866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein M., Chong P. Is a multivalent hand, foot, and mouth disease vaccine feasible? Hum. Vaccin. Immunother. 2015;11(11):2688–2704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4685682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26009802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai M., De Carli A., Filipponi C., Iacono E., La Rocca V., Lottini G., Piazza C.R., Quaranta P., Sidoti M., Pistello M., Freer G. Lipid balance remodelling by human positive-strand RNA viruses and the contribution of lysosomes. Antivir. Res. 2022;206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35985406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H., Bai Z., Li C., Sheng C., Zhao X. EV71 infection induces cell apoptosis through ROS generation and SIRT1 activation. J. Cell. Biochem. 2020;121(10):4321–4331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31898369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S.S., Wu F., Jin Y.M., Chang W.Q., Xu T.M. HDAC11: a rising star in epigenetics. Biomed. Pharmacother. 2020;131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32841898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu M.Y., Lin Y.L., Kuo Y., Chuang C.F., Wang J.R., Liao F. Muscle tissue damage and recovery after EV71 infection correspond to dynamic macrophage phenotypes. Front. Immunol. 2021;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8299204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34305887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q.Y., Wang Y., Bian L., Xu M., Liang Z. EV71 vaccine, a new tool to control outbreaks of hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) Expert Rev. Vaccines. 2016;15(5):599–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26732723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin M.W., Lee J.Y., Lancia D.R., Jr., Ng P.Y., Han B., Thomason J.R., Lynes M.S., Marshall C.G., Conti C., Collis A., Morales M.A., Doshi K., Rudnitskaya A., Yao L., Zheng X. Discovery of novel N-hydroxy-2-arylisoindoline-4-carboxamides as potent and selective inhibitors of HDAC11. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 2018;28(12):2143–2147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29776742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunez-Alvarez Y., Hurtado E., Munoz M., Garcia-Tunon I., Rech G.E., Pluvinet R., Sumoy L., Pendas A.M., Peinado M.A., Suelves M. Loss of HDAC11 accelerates skeletal muscle regeneration in mice. FEBS J. 2021;288(4):1201–1223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32602219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nutsford A.N., Galvin H.D., Ahmed F., Husain M. The Class IV human deacetylase, HDAC11, exhibits anti-influenza A virus properties via its involvement in host innate antiviral response. Cell. Microbiol. 2019;21(4):e12989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30511515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ropero S., Esteller M. The role of histone deacetylases (HDACs) in human cancer. Mol. Oncol. 2007;1(1):19–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5543853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19383284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shvedunova M., Akhtar A. Modulation of cellular processes by histone and non-histone protein acetylation. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell. Biol. 2022;23(5):329–349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35042977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon T., Lewthwaite P., Perera D., Cardosa M.J., McMinn P., Ooi M.H. Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of enterovirus 71. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2010;10(11):778–790.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20961813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su M., Gong X., Liu F. An update on the emerging approaches for histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor drug discovery and future perspectives. Expert Opin. Drug Discov. 2021;16(7):745–761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33530771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun L., Marin de Evsikova C., Bian K., Achille A., Telles E., Pei H., Seto E. Programming and regulation of metabolic homeostasis by HDAC11. EBioMedicine. 2018;33:157–168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6085537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29958910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thole T.M., Lodrini M., Fabian J., Wuenschel J., Pfeil S., Hielscher T., Kopp-Schneider A., Heinicke U., Fulda S., Witt O., Eggert A., Fischer M., Deubzer H.E. Neuroblastoma cells depend on HDAC11 for mitotic cell cycle progression and survival. Cell. Death Dis. 2017;8(3):e2635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5386552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28252645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villagra A., Cheng F., Wang H.W., Suarez I., Glozak M., Maurin M., Nguyen D., Wright K.L., Atadja P.W., Bhalla K., Pinilla-Ibarz J., Seto E., Sotomayor E.M. The histone deacetylase HDAC11 regulates the expression of interleukin 10 and immune tolerance. Nat. Immunol. 2009;10(1):92–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3925685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19011628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu H., Yin X., Zhao X., Wu Z., Xiao Y., Di Q., Sun P., Tang H., Quan J., Chen W. HDAC11 negatively regulates antifungal immunity by inhibiting Nos2 expression via binding with transcriptional repressor STAT3. Redox Biol. 2022;56</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9465110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36087429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L.L., Shan C., Deng C.L., Li X.D., Shang B.D., Ye H.Q., Liu S.Q., Yuan Z.M., Wang Q.Y., Shi P.Y., Zhang B. Development of a stable Gaussia luciferase enterovirus 71 reporter virus. J. Virol. Methods. 2015;219:62–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25843263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan L., Chen X., Cheng L., Rao M., Chen K., Zhang N., Meng J., Li M., Yang L.T., Yang P.C., Wang X., Song J. HDAC11 regulates interleukin-13 expression in CD4+ T cells in the heart. J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol. 2018;122:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30063898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan Y., Zhao K., Yao Y., Liu C., Chen Y., Li J., Wang Y., Pei R., Chen J., Hu X., Zhou Y., Wu C., Chen X. HDAC11 restricts HBV replication through epigenetic repression of cccDNA transcription. Antivir. Res. 2019;172</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31600533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F., Liu Y., Wang S., Yan X., Lin Y., Chen D., Tan Q., Wu Z. Interleukin-25-Mediated-IL-17RB Upregulation Promotes Cutaneous Wound Healing in Diabetic Mice by Improving Endothelial Cell Functions. Front. Immunol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8810642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35126394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang R., Pan Y., Feng W., Zhao Y., Yang Y., Wang L., Zhang Y., Cheng J., Jiang Q., Zheng Z., Jiang M., Yang S., Deng Y., Shi D., Wei Y. HDAC11 regulates the proliferation of bovine muscle stem cells through the notch signaling pathway and inhibits muscle regeneration. J. Agric. Food Chem. 2022;70(29):9166–9178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35837734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>