<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37093042</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-6527</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>36</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Viral meningitis and encephalitis: an update.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>177</StartPage><EndPage>185</EndPage><MedlinePgn>177-185</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/QCO.0000000000000922</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW">The most common infectious etiologies of meningitis and encephalitis are viruses. In this review, we will discuss current epidemiology, prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of the most common causes of viral meningitis and encephalitis worldwide.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS">Viral meningitis and encephalitis are increasingly diagnosed as molecular diagnostic techniques and serologies have become more readily available worldwide but recent progress in novel antiviral therapies remains limited. Emerging and re-emerging viruses that have caused endemic or worldwide outbreaks or epidemics are arboviruses (e.g., West Nile virus, Japanese encephalitis, Tick borne encephalitis, Dengue, Zika, Toscana), enteroviruses (e.g., Enterovirus 71, Enterovirus D68), Parechoviruses, respiratory viruses [e.g., severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), influenza, metapneumoviruses, measles, mumps], and herpes viruses [e.g., herpes simplex virus (HSV) type 1 (HSV-1), HSV-2, human herpes (HV) 6, varicella zoster virus (VZV)]. Future efforts should concentrate in increasing availability for those viruses with effective vaccination [e.g., Japanese encephalitis, Tick borne encephalitis, varicella zoster viruses, SARS-CoV-2, influenza], prompt initiation of those with encephalitis with treatable viruses (e.g., HSV-1, VZV), increasing the diagnostic yield by using novel techniques such as metagenomic sequencing and avoiding unnecessary antibiotics in those with viral meningitis or encephalitis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUMMARY">We review the current epidemiology, clinical presentation, diagnosis, and treatment of the common causative agents of viral meningitis and encephalitis worldwide.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gundamraj</LastName><ForeName>Vaishnavi</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wisconsin Institute of Medical Research, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hasbun</LastName><ForeName>Rodrigo</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Professor of Medicine, Section of Infectious Diseases, UT Health McGovern Medical School, Houston, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8809878</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0951-7375</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="Y">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004660" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014645" MajorTopicYN="N">Herpesvirus 3, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018259" MajorTopicYN="Y">Herpesvirus 1, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071244" MajorTopicYN="Y">Zika Virus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071243" MajorTopicYN="Y">Zika Virus Infection</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37093042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QCO.0000000000000922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00001432-202306000-00006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sulaiman T, Salazar L, Hasbun R. Acute versus subacute community-acquired meningitis in adults: an analysis of 611 patients. Medicine (Baltimore) 2017; 96:e7984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aksamit AJ. Chronic meningitis. N Engl J Med 2021; 385:930–936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesan A, Tunkel AR, Bloch KC, et al. Case definitions, diagnostic algorithms, and priorities in encephalitis: consensus statement of the international encephalitis consortium. Clin Infect Dis 2013; 57:1114–1128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla B, Aguilera EA, Salazar L, et al. Aseptic meningitis in adults and children: diagnostic and management challenges. J Clin Virol 2017; 94:110–114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaewpoowat Q, Salazar L, Aguilera E, et al. Herpes simplex and varicella zoster CNS infections: clinical presentations, treatment, and outcomes. Infection 2016; 44:337–345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakobsen A, Skov MT, Larsen L, et al. Herpes simplex virus 2 meningitis in adults: a prospective, nationwide, population-based cohort study. Clin Infect Dis 2022; 75:753–760.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handley G, Pankow S, Bard JD, et al. Distinguishing cytomegalovirus meningoencephalitis from other viral central nervous system infections. J Clin Virol 2021; 142:104936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martelius T, Lappalainen M, Palomäki M, Anttila V-J. Clinical characteristics of patients with Epstein–Barr virus in cerebrospinal fluid. BMC Infect Dis 2011; 11:1–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright WF, Pinto CN, Palisoc K, Baghli S. Viral (aseptic) meningitis: a review. J Neurol Sci 2019; 398:176–183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen BA, Rowley AH, Long CM. Herpes simplex type 2 in a patient with Mollaret's meningitis: demonstration by polymerase chain reaction. Ann Neurol 1994; 35:112–116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthews E, Beckham JD, Piquet AL, et al. Herpesvirus-associated encephalitis: an update. Curr Trop Med Rep 2022; 9:92–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abedi GR, Watson JT, Nix WA, et al. Enterovirus and parechovirus surveillance — United States, 2014–2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2018; 67:515–518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Setia A, Bhatia J, Bhattacharya S. An overview of acute flaccid myelitis. CNS Neurol Disord Drug Targets 2022; 21:774–794.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGill F, Griffiths MJ, Bonnett LJ, et al. Incidence, aetiology, and sequelae of viral meningitis in UK adults: a multicentre prospective observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18:992–1003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak G, Bhuyan SK, Bhuyan R, et al. Global emergence of enterovirus 71: a systematic review. Beni-Suef Univ J Basic Appl Sci 2022; 11:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Li Y, Yang Z, et al. Effect of enterovirus 71 vaccination on the epidemiological characteristics and etiology in hospitalized children with hand-foot-and-mouth disease: a retrospective study from a tertiary children's hospital. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022; 101:e30356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Dale RC, Blyth CC, et al. Causes and clinical features of childhood encephalitis: a multicenter, prospective cohort study. Clin Infect Dis 2020; 70:2517–2526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olijve L, Jennings L, Walls T. Human parechovirus: an increasingly recognized cause of sepsis-like illness in young infants. Clin Microbiol Rev 2018; 31:5–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ. Kliegman RM, Stanton BF, St. Geme JW. Nonpolio enteroviruses. Nelson textbook of pediatrics 20th ed.Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier; 2016. 1561–1568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chonmaitree T, Baldwin CD, Lucia HL. Role of the virology laboratory in diagnosis and management of patients with central nervous system disease. Clin Microbiol Rev 1989; 2:1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desmond RA, Accortt NA, Talley L, et al. Enteroviral meningitis: natural history and outcome of pleconaril therapy. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 2006; 50:2409–2414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verboon-Maciolek MA, Groenendaal F, Hahn CD, et al. Human parechovirus causes encephalitis with white matter injury in neonates. Ann Neurol 2008; 64:266–273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain S, Patel B, Bhatt GC. Enteroviral encephalitis in children: clinical features, pathophysiology, and treatment advances. Pathog Global Health 2014; 108:216–222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz JS, Sparks H, Beckham JD. Arboviral central nervous system infections. Curr Opin Infect Dis 2021; 34:264–271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bampali M, Konstantinidis K, Kellis EE, et al. West Nile disease symptoms and comorbidities: a systematic review and analysis of cases. Trop Med Infect Dis 2022; 7:236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanichanan J, Salazar L, Wootton SH, et al. Use of testing for West Nile virus and other arboviruses. Emerg Infect Dis 2016; 22:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaijakul S, Arias CA, Hossain M, et al. Toscana meningoencephalitis: a comparison to other viral central nervous system infections. J Clin Virol 2012; 55:204–208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber IB, Lindsey NP, Bunko-Patterson AM, et al. Completeness of West Nile virus testing in patients with meningitis and encephalitis during an outbreak in Arizona, USA. Epidemiol Infect 2012; 140:1632–1636.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasbun R, Rosenthal N, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. Epidemiology of meningitis and encephalitis in infants and children in the United States from 2011–2014. Clin Infect Dis 2017; 65:359–363.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LP, Yuan Y, Liu YL, et al. Chinese Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Etiology of Acute Meningitis and Encephalitis Surveillance Study Team. Etiological and epidemiological features of acute meningitis or encephalitis in China: a nationwide active surveillance study. Lancet Reg Health West Pac 2022; 20:100361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma B, Vigil KJ, Hasbun R. HIV testing in adults presenting with central nervous system infections. Open Forum Infect Dis 2020; 7:ofaa217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser R. Tick-borne encephalitis. Infect Dis Clin N Am 2008; 22:561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogovic P, Strle F. Tick-borne encephalitis: a review of epidemiology, clinical characteristics, and management. World J Clin Cases 2015; 3:430–441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucas SB, Wong KT, Nightingale S, Miller RF. HIV-associated CD8 encephalitis: a UK case series and review of histopathologically confirmed cases. Front Neurol 2021; 12:628296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vigil KJ, Salazar L, Hasbun R. Community-acquired meningitis in HIV-infected patients in the United States. AIDS Patient Care STDs 2018; 32:42–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legay V, Chomel JJ, Lina B. Specific RT-PCR procedure for the detection of human parechovirus type 1 genome in clinical samples. J Virol Methods 2002; 102:157–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pugh SJ, Moïsi JC, Kundi M, et al , Effectiveness of two doses of tick-borne encephalitis (TBE) vaccine. J Travel Med 2022;29taab193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erlanger TE, Weiss S, Keiser J, et al. Past, present, and future of Japanese encephalitis. Emerg Infect Dis 2009; 15:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furlong M, Adamu AM, Hoskins A, et al. Japanese encephalitis enzootic and epidemic risks across Australia. Viruses 2023; 15:450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinapati KK, Tandon R, Tripathi P, Srivastava N. Recent advances to overcome the burden of Japanese encephalitis: a zoonotic infection with problematic early detection. Rev Med Virol 2023; 33:e2383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dersch R, Sophocleous A, Cadar D, et al. Toscana virus encephalitis in Southwest Germany: a retrospective study. BMC Neurol 2021; 21:495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bohmwald K, Gálvez NMS, Ríos M, Kalergis AM. Neurologic alterations due to respiratory virus infections. Front Cell Neurosci 2018; 12:386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siow I, Lee KS, Zhang JJY, et al. Encephalitis as a neurological complication of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis of incidence, outcomes, and predictors. Eur J Neurol 2021; 28:3491–3502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park A, Suh SI, Son GR, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus-related encephalitis: magnetic resonance imaging findings with diffusion-weighted study. Neuroradiology 2014; 56:163–168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferren M, Horvat B, Mathieu C. Measles encephalitis: towards new therapeutics. Viruses 2019; 11:1017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (n.d.). Herpes simplex virus . World Health Organization. Retrieved March 2, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyler KL. Herpes simplex virus infections of the central nervous system: encephalitis and meningitis, including Mollaret's. Herpes 2004; 11: (Suppl 2): 57A–64A.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pangprasertkul S, Sanguansermsri C, Sudjaritruk T. Epstein–Barr virus meningoencephalitis in a young immunocompetent child: a case report. Heliyon 2022; 8:1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maniam GB, Wilkerson H, Milton JS. Human herpesvirus 6 meningitis in an adult. Proceedings 2020; 33:246–247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gnoni M, Zaheer K, Vasser MM, et al. Varicella Zoster aseptic meningitis: report of an atypical case in an immunocompetent patient treated with oral valacyclovir. IDCases 2018; 13:e00446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maschke M, Kastrup O, Diener HC. CNS manifestations of cytomegalovirus infections: diagnosis and treatment. CNS drugs 2002; 16:303–315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Cloud G, Bradley J, et al. Double blind placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril in infants with enterovirus meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2003; 22:335–340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debiasi RL, Tyler KL. West Nile virus meningoencephalitis. Nat Clin Pract Neurol 2006; 2:264–275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta R, Gerardin P, de Brito CAA, et al. The neurological complications of chikungunya virus: a systematic review. Rev Med Virol 2018; 28:e1978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G-H, Ning Z-J, Liu Y-M, Li X-H. Neurological manifestations of dengue infection. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 2017; 7:1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Almeida Oliveira Evangelista G, Hughes Carvalho R, Sant’Ana Menezes G, et al. Meningoencephalitis associated with Zika virus and chikungunya virus infection. Japanese J Infect Dis 2021; 74:584–586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2022, June 2. Eastern equine encephalitis. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Retrieved March 2, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2022, November 7. La Crosse Encephalitis Virus. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Retrieved March 2, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2022, November 7. Jamestown Canyon Virus. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Retrieved March 2, 2023, from https://www.cdc.gov/jamestown-canyon/index.html .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastula DM, Hoang Johnson DK, White JL, et al. Jamestown Canyon virus disease in the United States-2000–2013. Am J Trop Med Hyg -2000-2013; 93:384–389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonthius DJ. Lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus: an underrecognized cause of neurologic disease in the fetus, child, and adult. Semin Pediatr Neurol 2012; 19:89–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhie K, Park HK, Kim YS, et al. Factors associated with mumps meningitis and the possible impact of vaccination. Korean J Pediatr 2016; 59:24–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashemian S, Ashrafzadeh F, Akhondian J, Beiraghi Toosi M. Epstein-barr virus encephalitis: a case report. Iranian J Child Neurol 2015; 9:107–110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakai R, Kanamori H, Motohashi K, et al. Long-term outcome of human herpesvirus-6 encephalitis after allogeneic stem cell transplantation. Biol Blood and Marrow Transplant 2011; 17:1389–1394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lizzi J, Hill T, Jakubowski J. Varicella Zoster virus encephalitis. Clin Pract Cases Emerg Med 2019; 3:380–382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huff JL, Barry PA. B-virus (Cercopithecine herpesvirus 1) infection in humans and macaques: potential for zoonotic disease. Emerg Infect Dis 2003; 9:246–250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diwan MN, Samad S, Mushtaq R, et al. Measles induced encephalitis: recent interventions to overcome the obstacles encountered in the management amidst the COVID-19 pandemic. Diseases 2022; 10:104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2021, May 21. Rabies. World Health Organization. Retrieved March 2, 2023, from https://apps.who.int/rabies/en/ .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birge J, Sonnesyn S. Powassan virus encephalitis, Minnesota, USA. Emerg Infect Dis 2012; 18:1669–1671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapoor AK, Zash R. Powassan virus. In: StatPearls . StatPearls Publishing; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill CM, Kapadia RK, Beckham JD, et al. Usutu virus disease: a potential problem for North America? J Neurovirol 2020; 26:149–154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam AM. Nipah virus, an emerging zoonotic disease causing fatal encephalitis. Clin Med 2022; 22:348–352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizzi MA. Acute neurologic manifestations of respiratory viruses. CONTINUUM: Lifelong Learn Neurol 2021; 27:1365–1381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson MR, Sample HA, Zorn KC, et al. Clinical metagenomic sequencing for diagnosis of meningitis and encephalitis. N Engl J Med 2019; 380:2327–2340.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>