<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37072100</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-7492</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>330</Volume><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virus research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virus Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Global quantitative proteomic analysis profiles of host protein expression in response to enterovirus A71 infection in bronchial epithelial cells based on tandem mass tag (TMT) peptide labeling coupled with LC-MS/MS uncovers the key role of proteasome in virus replication.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>199118</StartPage><MedlinePgn>199118</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">199118</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.virusres.2023.199118</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0168-1702(23)00080-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus A71 (EV-A71) is a neurotropic human pathogen which mainly caused hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) mostly in children under 5 years-old. Generally, EV-A71-associated HFMD is a relatively self-limiting febrile disease, but there will still be a small percentage of patients with rapid disease progression and severe neurological complications. To date, the underlying mechanism of EV-A71 inducing pathological injury of central nervous system (CNS) remains largely unclear. It has been investigated and discussed the changes of mRNA, miRNA and circRNA expression profile during infection by EV-A71 in our previous studies. However, these studies were only analyzed at the RNA level, not at the protein level. It's the protein levels that ultimately do the work in the body. Here, to address this, we performed a tandem mass tag (TMT) peptide labeling coupled with LC-MS/MS approach to quantitatively identify cellular proteome changes at 24 h post-infection (hpi) in EV-A71-infected 16HBE cells. In total, 6615 proteins were identified by using TMT coupled with LC-MS/MS in this study. In the EV-A71- and mock-infected groups, 210 differentially expressed proteins were found, including 86 upregulated and 124 downregulated proteins, at 24 hpi. To ensure the validity and reliability of the proteomics data, 3 randomly selected proteins were verified by Western blot and Immunofluorescence analysis, and the results were consistent with the TMT results. Subsequently, functional enrichment analysis indicated that the up-regulated and down-regulated proteins were individually involved in various biological processes and signaling pathways, including metabolic process, AMPK signaling pathway, Neurotrophin signaling pathway, Viral myocarditis, GABAergic synapse, and so on. Moreover, among these enriched functional analysis, the "Proteasome" pathway was up-regulated, which has caught our attention. Inhibition of proteasome was found to obviously suppress the EV-A71 replication. Finally, further in-depth analysis revealed that these differentially expressed proteins contained distinct domains and localized in different subcellular components. Taken together, our data provided a comprehensive view of host cell response to EV-A71 and identified host proteins may lead to better understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms and host responses to EV-A71 infection, and also to the identification of new therapeutic targets for EV-A71 infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yajie</LastName><ForeName>Hu</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China; Yunnan Provincial Key Laboratory of Clinical Virology, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shenglan</LastName><ForeName>Wang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Zhao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rufang</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tingting</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yunhui</LastName><ForeName>Zhang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province, China; The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, Yunnan, China. Electronic address: zhangyh123kh@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jie</LastName><ForeName>Song</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Science and Peking Union Medical College, Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research and Development on Severe Infectious Diseases, Kunming, China. Electronic address: songjiekm@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Virus Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8410979</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0168-1702</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.4.25.1</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D046988">Proteasome Endopeptidase Complex</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010455">Peptides</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D020543">Proteome</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002853" MajorTopicYN="N">Chromatography, Liquid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D046988" MajorTopicYN="N">Proteasome Endopeptidase Complex</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D040901" MajorTopicYN="N">Proteomics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053719" MajorTopicYN="N">Tandem Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014779" MajorTopicYN="N">Virus Replication</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004847" MajorTopicYN="N">Epithelial Cells</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010455" MajorTopicYN="N">Peptides</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020543" MajorTopicYN="N">Proteome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus A71 (EV-A71)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Host response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Proteasome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tandem mass tag (TMT)-based quantitative proteomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus replication</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37072100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10194169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2023.199118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0168-1702(23)00080-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahn J., Chung K.S., Kim D.U., Won M., Kim L., Kim K.S., Nam M., Choi S.J., Kim H.C., Yoon M., Chae S.K., Hoe K.L. Systematic identification of hepatocellular proteins interacting with NS5A of the hepatitis C virus. J. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 2004;37(6):741–748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15607035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aslam B., Basit M., Nisar M.A., Khurshid M., Rasool M.H. Proteomics: technologies and their applications. J. Chromatogr. Sci. 2017;55(2):182–196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28087761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aswathyraj S., Arunkumar G., Alidjinou E.K., Hober D. Hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD): emerging epidemiology and the need for a vaccine strategy. Med. Microbiol. Immunol. 2016;205(5):397–407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27406374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basbous J., Arpin C., Gaudray G., Piechaczyk M., Devaux C., Mesnard J.M. The HBZ factor of human T-cell leukemia virus type I dimerizes with transcription factors JunB and c-Jun and modulates their transcriptional activity. J. Biol. Chem. 2003;278(44):43620–43627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12937177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buccitelli C., Selbach M. mRNAs, proteins and the emerging principles of gene expression control. Nat. Rev. Genet. 2020;21(10):630–644.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32709985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang Y.K., Chen K.H., Chen K.T. Hand, foot and mouth disease and herpangina caused by enterovirus A71 infections: a review of enterovirus A71 molecular epidemiology, pathogenesis, and current vaccine development. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo. 2018;60:e70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6223252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30427405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L., Li Z., Zeng T., Zhang Y.H., Zhang S., Huang T., Cai Y.D. Predicting human protein subcellular locations by using a combination of network and function features. Front. Genet. 2021;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8603309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34804131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng M.L., Weng S.F., Kuo C.H., Ho H.Y. Enterovirus 71 induces mitochondrial reactive oxygen species generation that is required for efficient replication. PLoS ONE. 2014;9(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4234665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25401329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi A.G., Wong J., Marchant D., Luo H. The ubiquitin-proteasome system in positive-strand RNA virus infection. Rev. Med. Virol. 2013;23(2):85–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7169083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22782620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choy M.M., Zhang S.L., Costa V.V., Tan H.C., Horrevorts S., Ooi E.E. Proteasome inhibition suppresses dengue virus egress in antibody dependent Infection. PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis. 2015;9(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4643959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26565697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cobbin J.C., Charon J., Harvey E., Holmes E.C., Mahar J.E. Current challenges to virus discovery by meta-transcriptomics. Curr. Opin. Virol. 2021;51:48–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34592710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coombs K.M. Update on Proteomic approaches to uncovering virus-induced protein alterations and virus -host protein interactions during the progression of viral infection. Expert Rev. Proteom. 2020;17(7–8):513–532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32910682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng X., Cong Y., Yin R., Yang G., Ding C., Yu S., Liu X., Wang C., Ding Z. Proteomic analysis of chicken peripheral blood mononuclear cells after infection by Newcastle disease virus. J. Vet. Sci. 2014;15(4):511–517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4269593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25234324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding X., Li S., Zhu L. Potential effects of HMGB1 on viral replication and virus infection-induced inflammatory responses: a promising therapeutic target for virus infection-induced inflammatory diseases. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2021;62:54–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34503914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du P., Xu C. Predicting multisite protein subcellular locations: progress and challenges. Expert Rev. Proteom. 2013;10(3):227–237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23777214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellisdon A.M., Stewart M. Structural biology of the PCI-protein fold. Bioarchitecture. 2012;2(4):118–123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3675071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22960705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S., Principi N. Hand, foot and mouth disease: current knowledge on clinical manifestations, epidemiology, aetiology and prevention. Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2018;37(3):391–398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29411190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fagerberg L., Hallstrom B.M., Oksvold P., Kampf C., Djureinovic D., Odeberg J., Habuka M., Tahmasebpoor S., Danielsson A., Edlund K., Asplund A., Sjostedt E., Lundberg E., Szigyarto C.A., Skogs M., Takanen J.O., Berling H., Tegel H., Mulder J., Nilsson P., Schwenk J.M., Lindskog C., Danielsson F., Mardinoglu A., Sivertsson A., von Feilitzen K., Forsberg M., Zwahlen M., Olsson I., Navani S., Huss M., Nielsen J., Ponten F., Uhlen M. Analysis of the human tissue-specific expression by genome-wide integration of transcriptomics and antibody-based proteomics. Mol. Cell. Proteom. 2014;13(2):397–406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3916642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24309898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frenguelli B.G. The glutamatergic synapse - a key hub in neuronal metabolism, signalling and plasticity. Neuropharmacology. 2022;207</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34999011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo L., Lee A.A., Rizvi T.A., Ratner N., Kirschner L.S. The protein kinase A regulatory subunit R1A (Prkar1a) plays critical roles in peripheral nerve development. J. Neurosci. 2013;33(46):17967–17975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3828453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24227708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habermacher C., Angulo M.C., Benamer N. Glutamate versus GABA in neuron-oligodendroglia communication. Glia. 2019;67(11):2092–2106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30957306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J., Liu X., Duan S., Ye R., Yang Y., Wang J., He N. Untargeted plasma metabolomics reveals extensive metabolic alterations among treatment-naive human immunodeficiency virus/hepatitis C virus co-infected patients with liver disease progression. AIDS Res. Hum. Retrovir. 2022;38(5):378–393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35383478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hivin P., Basbous J., Raymond F., Henaff D., Arpin-Andre C., Robert-Hebmann V., Barbeau B., Mesnard J.M. The HBZ-SP1 isoform of human T-cell leukemia virus type I represses JunB activity by sequestration into nuclear bodies. Retrovirology. 2007;4:14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1805765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17306025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou L., Chen X., Wang J., Li J., Yang H. A tandem mass tag-based quantitative proteomic analysis of fowl adenovirus serotype 4-infected LMH cells. Vet. Microbiol. 2021;255</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33743407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y., Song J., Liu L., Li J., Tang B., Zhang Y., Wang J., Wang L., Fan S., Feng M., Li Q. Comparison analysis of microRNAs in response to EV71 and CA16 infection in human bronchial epithelial cells by high-throughput sequencing to reveal differential infective mechanisms. Virus Res. 2017;228:90–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27890633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y., Song J., Liu L., Zhang Y., Wang L., Li Q. microRNA-4516 contributes to different functions of epithelial permeability barrier by targeting poliovirus receptor related protein 1 in enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A16 infections. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2018;8:110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5900049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29686973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y., Xu Y., Huang Z., Deng Z., Fan J., Yang R., Ma H., Song J., Zhang Y. Transcriptome sequencing analysis of SH-SY5Y cells infected with EV71 reveals the potential neuropathic mechanisms. Virus Res. 2020;282</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iio E., Matsuura K., Nishida N., Maekawa S., Enomoto N., Nakagawa M., Sakamoto N., Yatsuhashi H., Kurosaki M., Izumi N., Hiasa Y., Masaki N., Ide T., Hino K., Tamori A., Honda M., Kaneko S., Mochida S., Nomura H., Nishiguchi S., Okuse C., Itoh Y., Yoshiji H., Sakaida I., Yamamoto K., Watanabe H., Hige S., Matsumoto A., Tanaka E., Tokunaga K., Tanaka Y. Genome-wide association study identifies a PSMD3 variant associated with neutropenia in interferon-based therapy for chronic hepatitis C. Hum. Genet. 2015;134(3):279–289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25515861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H., Schwertz H., Schmid D.I., Jones B.B., Kriesel J., Martinez M.L., Weyrich A.S., Zimmerman G.A., Kraiss L.W. Different mechanisms preserve translation of programmed cell death 8 and JunB in virus-infected endothelial cells. Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol. 2012;32(4):997–1004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3310396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22328780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Judge A., Dodd M.S. Metabolism. Essays Biochem. 2020;64(4):607–647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7545035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32830223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapusinszky B., Szomor K.N., Farkas A., Takacs M., Berencsi G. Detection of non-polio enteroviruses in Hungary 2000-2008 and molecular epidemiology of enterovirus 71, coxsackievirus A16, and echovirus 30. Virus Genes. 2010;40(2):163–173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20044791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur J., Debnath J. Autophagy at the crossroads of catabolism and anabolism. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 2015;16(8):461–472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26177004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein M., Chong P. Is a multivalent hand, foot, and mouth disease vaccine feasible? Hum. Vaccin. Immunother. 2015;11(11):2688–2704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4685682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26009802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni A., Anderson A.G., Merullo D.P., Konopka G. Beyond bulk: a review of single cell transcriptomics methodologies and applications. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2019;58:129–136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6710112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30978643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo R.L., Lin Y.H., Wang R.Y., Hsu C.W., Chiu Y.T., Huang H.I., Kao L.T., Yu J.S., Shih S.R., Wu C.C. Proteomics analysis of EV71-infected cells reveals the involvement of host protein NEDD4L in EV71 replication. J. Proteome Res. 2015;14(4):1818–1830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25785312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuzirian M.S., Paradis S. Emerging themes in GABAergic synapse development. Prog. Neurobiol. 2011;95(1):68–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3166545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21798307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence T. The nuclear factor NF-kappaB pathway in inflammation. Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol. 2009;1(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2882124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20457564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K.Y. Enterovirus 71 infection and neurological complications. Korean J. Pediatr. 2016;59(10):395–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5099286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27826325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lees J.G., Dawson N.L., Sillitoe I., Orengo C.A. Functional innovation from changes in protein domains and their combinations. Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol. 2016;38:44–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27309309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H.Y., Zhang L.K., Zhu X.J., Shang J., Chen X., Zhu Y., Guo L. Analysis of EV71 infection progression using triple-SILAC-based proteomics approach. Proteomics. 2015;15(21):3629–3643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26306425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin C.Y., Liu J.C. Modular protein domains: an engineering approach toward functional biomaterials. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2016;40:56–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4975669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26971463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu S., Wang Y. Nonmetabolic functions of metabolic enzymes in cancer development. Cancer Commun. (Lond.) 2018;38(1):63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6235390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30367676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q.Y., Wang Y., Bian L., Xu M., Liang Z. EV71 vaccine, a new tool to control outbreaks of hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) Expert Rev. Vaccines. 2016;15(5):599–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26732723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morens D.M., Folkers G.K., Fauci A.S. The challenge of emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases. Nature. 2004;430(6996):242–249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15241422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mun D.G., Vanderboom P.M., Madugundu A.K., Garapati K., Chavan S., Peterson J.A., Saraswat M., Pandey A. DIA-based proteome profiling of nasopharyngeal swabs from COVID-19 patients. J. Proteome Res. 2021;20(8):4165–4175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34292740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nassef C., Ziemer C., Morrell D.S. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease: a new look at a classic viral rash. Curr. Opin. Pediatr. 2015;27(4):486–491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26087425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paez-Franco J.C., Maravillas-Montero J.L., Mejia-Dominguez N.R., Torres-Ruiz J., Tamez-Torres K.M., Perez-Fragoso A., German-Acacio J.M., Ponce-de-Leon A., Gomez-Martin D., Ulloa-Aguirre A. Metabolomics analysis identifies glutamic acid and cystine imbalances in COVID-19 patients without comorbid conditions. Implications on redox homeostasis and COVID-19 pathophysiology. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9488784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36126080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pattanakitsakul S.N., Rungrojcharoenkit K., Kanlaya R., Sinchaikul S., Noisakran S., Chen S.T., Malasit P., Thongboonkerd V. Proteomic analysis of host responses in HepG2 cells during dengue virus infection. J. Proteome Res. 2007;6(12):4592–4600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17979228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pick E., Hofmann K., Glickman M.H. PCI complexes: beyond the proteasome, CSN, and eIF3 Troika. Mol. Cell. 2009;35(3):260–264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19683491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu Y., Zhan Y., Yang S., Ren S., Qiu X., Rehamn Z.U., Tan L., Sun Y., Meng C., Song C., Yu S., Ding C. Newcastle disease virus infection triggers HMGB1 release to promote the inflammatory response. Virology. 2018;525:19–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30216776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reichardt L.F. Neurotrophin-regulated signalling pathways. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci. 2006;361(1473):1545–1564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1664664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16939974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley L.W., Blanton R.E. Advances in molecular epidemiology of infectious diseases: definitions, approaches, and scope of the field. Microbiol. Spectr. 2018;6(6):10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6343655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30387413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocha D.C.P., Souza T.M.A., Nunes P.C.G., Mohana-Borges R., Paes M.V., Guimaraes G.M.C., Arcila J.C.S., Paiva I.A., Azeredo E.L., Damasco P.V., de Souza L.J., Dos Santos F.B., Allonso D. Increased circulating levels of High Mobility Group Box 1 (HMGB1) in acute-phase Chikungunya virus infection: potential disease biomarker. J. Clin. Virol. 2022;146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34920373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Pena R., Mounadi K.E., Garcia-Ruiz H. Changes in subcellular localization of host proteins induced by plant viruses. Viruses. 2021;13(4):677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8071230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33920930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruff W.E., Greiling T.M., Kriegel M.A. Host-microbiota interactions in immune-mediated diseases. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2020;18(9):521–538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32457482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saguil A., Kane S.F., Lauters R., Mercado M.G. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease: rapid evidence review. Am. Fam. Physician. 2019;100(7):408–414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31573162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider S.M., Pritchard S.M., Wudiri G.A., Trammell C.E., Nicola A.V. Early steps in herpes simplex virus infection blocked by a proteasome inhibitor. mBio. 2019;10(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6520451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31088925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson J., Loh Z., Ullah M.A., Lynch J.P., Werder R.B., Collinson N., Zhang V., Dondelinger Y., Bertrand M.J.M., Everard M.L., Blyth C.C., Hartel G., Van Oosterhout A.J., Gough P.J., Bertin J., Upham J.W., Spann K.M., Phipps S. Respiratory syncytial virus infection promotes necroptosis and HMGB1 release by airway epithelial cells. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 2020;201(11):1358–1371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32105156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song J., Hu Y., Li J., Zheng H., Wang J., Guo L., Ning R., Li H., Yang Z., Fan H., Liu L. Different microRNA profiles reveal the diverse outcomes induced by EV71 and CA16 infection in human umbilical vein endothelial cells using high-throughput sequencing. PLoS ONE. 2017;12(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5439704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28531227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sperk M., van Domselaar R., Rodriguez J.E., Mikaeloff F., Sa Vinhas B., Saccon E., Sonnerborg A., Singh K., Gupta S., Vegvari A., Neogi U. Utility of proteomics in emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases caused by RNA viruses. J. Proteome Res. 2020;19(11):4259–4274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7640957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33095583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Too I.H.K., Bonne I., Tan E.L., Chu J.J.H., Alonso S. Prohibitin plays a critical role in enterovirus 71 neuropathogenesis. PLoS Pathog. 2018;14(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5764453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29324904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C., Yin Y., Sun Z., Wang Y., Li F., Wang Y., Zhang Z., Chen X. ATAD2 upregulation promotes tumor growth and angiogenesis in endometrial cancer and is associated with its immune infiltration. Dis. Markers. 2022;2022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9722300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36479043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G., Xiong Z., Yang F., Zheng X., Zong W., Li R., Bao Y. Identification of COVID-19-associated DNA methylation variations by integrating methylation array and scRNA-Seq data at cell-type resolution. Genes. 2022;13(7):1109. (Basel)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9322889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35885892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Hu Y., Zheng M. Enterovirus A71 antivirals: past, present, and future. Acta Pharm. Sin. B. 2022;12(4):1542–1566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9279511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35847514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin Z., Kirschner L.S. The Carney complex gene PRKAR1A plays an essential role in cardiac development and myxomagenesis. Trends Cardiovasc. Med. 2009;19(2):44–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2716068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19577711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu L., Zeng Z., Tan H., Feng Q., Zhou Q., Hu J., Li Y., Wang J., Yang W., Feng J., Xu B. Significant metabolic alterations in patients with hepatitis B virus replication observed via serum untargeted metabolomics shed new light on hepatitis B virus infection. J. Drug Target. 2022;30(4):442–449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34844491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Z., Ma X., Zhang W., Chang X., An L., Niu M., Chen Y., Sun C., Yang Y. Microarray data mining and preliminary bioinformatics analysis of hepatitis D virus-associated hepatocellular carcinoma. Biomed. Res. Int. 2021;2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7867452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33564675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M., Manchanda P.K., Wu D., Wang Q., Kirschner L.S. Knockdown of PRKAR1A, the gene responsible for Carney complex, interferes with differentiation in osteoblastic cells. Mol. Endocrinol. 2014;28(3):295–307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3938543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24506536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng J., Sugrue R.J., Tang K. Mass spectrometry based proteomic studies on viruses and hosts–a review. Anal. Chim. Acta. 2011;702(2):149–159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21839192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>