<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37078665</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-6551</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>36</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Threat of resurgence or hope for global eradication of poliovirus?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>229</StartPage><EndPage>237</EndPage><MedlinePgn>229-237</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/WCO.0000000000001156</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW">Recent outbreaks of poliomyelitis in countries that have been free of cases for decades highlight the challenges of eradicating polio in a globalized interconnected world beset with a novel viral pandemic. We provide an epidemiological update, advancements in vaccines, and amendments in public health strategy of poliomyelitis in this review.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS">Last year, new cases of wild poliovirus type 1 (WPV1) were documented in regions previously documented to have eradicated WPV1 and reports of circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 (cVDPV2) and 3 (cVDPV3) in New York and Jerusalem made international headlines. Sequencing of wastewater samples from environmental surveillance revealed that the WPV1 strains were related to WPV1 lineages from endemic countries and the cVDPV2 strains from New York and Jerusalem were not only related to each other but also to environmental isolates found in London. The evidence of importation of WPV1 cases from endemic countries, and global transmission of cVDPVs justifies renewed efforts in routine vaccination programs and outbreak control measures that were interrupted by the COVID-19 pandemic. After the novel oral poliovirus vaccine type 2 (nOPV2) received emergency authorization for containment of cVDPV2 outbreaks in 2021, subsequent reduced incidence, transmission rates, and vaccine adverse events, alongside increased genetic stability of viral isolates substantiates the safety and efficacy of nOPV2. The nOPV1 and nOPV3 vaccines, against type 1 and 3 cVDPVs, and measures to increase accessibility and efficacy of inactivated poliovirus vaccine (IPV) are in development.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUMMARY">A revised strategy utilizing more genetically stable vaccine formulations, with uninterrupted vaccination programs and continued active surveillance optimizes the prospect of global poliomyelitis eradication.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Carla Y</ForeName><Initials>CY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Columbia University Irving Medical Center-New York Presbyterian Hospital, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piamonte</LastName><ForeName>Bernadeth</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of the Philippines - Philippine General Hospital, Manila, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allen</LastName><ForeName>Rebecca</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thakur</LastName><ForeName>Kiran T</ForeName><Initials>KT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Columbia University Irving Medical Center-New York Presbyterian Hospital, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9319162</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1350-7540</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37078665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/WCO.0000000000001156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00019052-202306000-00010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Nathanson N, Kew OM. From emergence to eradication: the epidemiology of poliomyelitis deconstructed. Am J Epidemiol 2010; 172:1213–1229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Polio eradication strategy 2022-2026: delivering on a promise. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercader-Barceló J, Otu A, Townley TA, et al. Rare recurrences of poliomyelitis in nonendemic countries after eradication: a call for global action. Lancet Microbe 2022; 3:e891–e892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martini M, Orsini D. The fight against poliomyelitis through the history: past, present and hopes for the future. Albert Sabin's missing Nobel and his ‘gift to all the world's children’. Vaccine 2022; 40:6802–6805.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Neurologic Disorders and Stroke. Post-Polio Syndrome Fact Sheet [online]. Available at: https://www-ninds-nih-gov.ezproxy.cul.columbia.edu/postpolio-syndrome-fact-sheet . [Accessed 22 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew O, Pallansch M. Breaking the last chains of poliovirus transmission: progress and challenges in global polio eradication. Annu Rev Virol 2018; 5:427–451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdullahi AM, Sarmast ST, Singh R. Molecular biology and epidemiology of neurotropic viruses. Cureus 2020; 12:e9674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukerji SS, Martinez-Lage M, Thakur KT. Louis ED, Noble JM. Viral infections. Merritt's neurology 14th edPhiladelphia: Wolters Kluwer; 2021. 663–664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Poliomyeltiis Factsheet [online]. Available at: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/poliomyelitis#:∼:text=Initial%20symptoms%20are%20fever%2C%20fatigue,under%205%20years%20of%20age . [Accessed 22 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GPEI. Vaccine-Derived Polioviruses [online]. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-prevention/the-virus/vaccine-derived-polio-viruses/ . [Accessed 22 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin G, Diop OM, Humayun A, et al. Update on immunodeficiency-associated vaccine-derived polioviruses - Worldwide, July 2018-December 2019. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020; 69:913–917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rachlin A, Patel JC, Burns CC, et al. Progress toward polio eradication - worldwide, January 2020-April 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:650–655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GPEI. Guidelines for Implementing PID Surveillance [online]. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Guidelines-for-Implementing-PID-Suveillance_EN.pdf . [Accessed 23 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy OC, Messacar K, Benson L, et al. AFM working group. Acute flaccid myelitis: cause, diagnosis, and management. Lancet 2021; 397:334–346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo GB, Goyal T, Tyler K, Thakur KT. Re-emergence of poliovirus in the United States: considerations and implications. Ann Neurol 2022; 92:725–728.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helfferich J, Roodbol J, de Wit MC, et al. 2016 Enterovirus D68 Acute Flaccid Myelitis Working Group and the Dutch Pediatric GBS Study Group. Acute flaccid myelitis and Guillain-Barré syndrome in children: a comparative study with evaluation of diagnostic criteria. Eur J Neurol 2022; 29:593–604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Hi Shing S, Lope J, Chipika RH, et al. Extra-motor manifestations in postpolio syndrome (PPS): fatigue, cognitive symptoms and radiological features. Neurol Sci 2021; 42:4569–4581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendebourg MJ, Weigel M, Richter L, et al. Spinal cord gray matter atrophy is associated with functional decline in postpolio syndrome. Eur J Neurol 2022; 29:1435–1445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Poliomyelitis [online]. Available at: https://www.who.int/teams/health-product-policy-and-standards/standards-and-specifications/vaccines-quality/poliomyelitis . [Accessed 5 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns CC, Diop OM, Sutter RW, Kew OM. Vaccine-derived polioviruses. J Infect Dis 2014; 210: (Suppl 1): S283–S293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henderson DA, Witte JJ, Morris L, Langmuir AD. Paralytic disease associated with oral polio vaccines. JAMA 1964; 190:41–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew OM, Sutter RW, de Gourville EM, et al. Vaccine-derived polioviruses and the endgame strategy for global polio eradication. Annu Rev Microbiol 2005; 59:587–635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GPEI. OPV [online]. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-prevention/the-vaccines/opv/ . [Accessed 5 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlin JF, Bandyopadhyay AS, Sutter R. Immunization against poliomyelitis and the challenges to worldwide poliomyelitis eradication. J Infect Dis 2021; 224:S398–s404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martini M, Orsini D. Armed conflict in the world threatens the eradication of poliomyelitis: risks of humanitarian crises. Pathog Glob Health 2022; 116:267–268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed A, Tomori O, Nkengasong JN. Lessons from the elimination of poliomyelitis in Africa. Nat Rev Immunol 2021; 21:823–828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uwishema O, Elebesunu EE, Bouaddi O, et al. Poliomyelitis amidst the COVID-19 pandemic in Africa: efforts, challenges and recommendations. Clin Epidemiol Glob Health 2022; 16:101073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Leary A. Overcoming challenges en route to polio eradication. Lancet 2022; 400:1191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesan P. Global polio eradication set back by COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet Microbe 2022; 3:e172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbaeyi C, Baig S, Safdar MR, et al. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication — Pakistan, January 2021–July 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1313–1318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed A, Akbar IE, Chaudhury S, et al. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication - Afghanistan, January 2021-September 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1541–1546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts L. Africa battles out-of-control polio outbreaks. Science 2022; 375:1079–1080.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chunda P, Chisema MN, Mwale A, et al. The 2022 Malawi Polio outbreak. Malawi Med J 2022; 34:223–224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franco-Paredes C, Rodriguez-Morales AJ, Henao-Martínez AF, et al. The growing threat of wild poliovirus 1 and vaccine-derived cases in the COVID-19 era. Lancet Infect Dis 2022; 22:1412–1414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davlantes E. Malawi Ministry of Health, Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Notes from the field: initial outbreak response activity following wild poliovirus type 1 detection - Malawi, February 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:776–777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Javed H, Rizvi MA, Fahim Z, et al. Global polio eradication; can we replicate the smallpox success story? Rev Med Virol 2022. e2409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Wild poliovirus type 1 (WPV1) – Malawi. Disease Outbreak News. March 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Wild poliovirus type 1 (WPV1) – Mozambique. Disease Outbreak News. June 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryerson AB, Lang D, Alazawi MA, et al. 2022 U.S. Poliovirus Response Team. Wastewater testing and detection of poliovirus type 2 genetically linked to virus isolated from a paralytic polio case - New York, March 9-October 11, 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1418–1424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Link-Gelles R, Lutterloh E, Schnabel Ruppert P, et al. 2022 U.S. Poliovirus Response Team. Public health response to a case of paralytic poliomyelitis in an unvaccinated person and detection of poliovirus in wastewater - New York, June-August 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1065–1068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Detection of circulating vaccine derived polio virus 2 (cVDPV2) in environmental samples– the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the United States of America. Disease Outbreak News. September 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuckerman NS, Bar-Or I, Sofer D, et al. Emergence of genetically linked vaccine-originated poliovirus type 2 in the absence of oral polio vaccine, Jerusalem, April to July 2022. Euro Surveill 2022; 27:2200694.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weil M, Sofer D, Shulman LM, et al. Environmental surveillance detected type 3 vaccine-derived polioviruses in increasing frequency at multiple sites prior to detection of a poliomyelitis case. Sci Total Environ 2023; 871:161985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>New York State Department of Health. New York State Department of Health and Rockland County Department of Health Alert the Public to a case of Polio in the County. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao N, Liu Y, Xu JW, et al. Detection of a highly divergent type 3 vaccine-derived poliovirus in a child with a severe primary immunodeficiency disorder - Chongqing, China, 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2022; 71:1148–1150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay AS, Zipursky S. A novel tool to eradicate an ancient scourge: the novel oral polio vaccine type 2 story. Lancet Infect Dis 2023; 23:e67–e71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sáez-Llorens X, Bandyopadhyay AS, Gast C, et al. Safety and immunogenicity of two novel type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine candidates compared with a monovalent type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine in children and infants: two clinical trials. Lancet 2021; 397:27–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaman K, Bandyopadhyay AS, Hoque M, et al. Evaluation of the safety, immunogenicity, and faecal shedding of novel oral polio vaccine type 2 in healthy newborn infants in Bangladesh: a randomised, controlled, phase 2 clinical trial. Lancet 2023; 401:131–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin G, Peak C, Eisenhawer M, et al. Enabling accelerated vaccine roll-out for Public Health Emergencies of International Concern (PHEICs): Novel Oral Polio Vaccine type 2 (nOPV2) experience. Vaccine 2023; 41: (Suppl 1): A122–A127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GPEI. Affordable IPV [online]. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/tools-and-library/current-research-areas/affordable-ipv/ . [Accessed 22 February 2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar P, Bird C, Holland D, et al. Current and next-generation formulation strategies for inactivated polio vaccines to lower costs, increase coverage, and facilitate polio eradication. Hum Vaccin Immunother 2022; 18:2154100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR, Gomez-Go GD, Oberdorfer P, et al. Safety and immunogenicity of a new inactivated polio vaccine made from sabin strains: a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled, phase 2/3 seamless study. J Infect Dis 2022; 226:308–318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mashunye TR, Ndwandwe DE, Dube KR, et al. Fractional dose compared with standard dose inactivated poliovirus vaccine in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Infect Dis 2021; 21:1161–1174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem AF, Mach O, Yousafzai MT, et al. One-year decline of poliovirus antibodies following fractional-dose inactivated poliovirus vaccine. J Infect Dis 2021; 223:1214–1221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norton EB, Bauer DL, Weldon WC, et al. The novel adjuvant dmLT promotes dose sparing, mucosal immunity and longevity of antibody responses to the inactivated polio vaccine in a murine model. Vaccine 2015; 33:1909–1915.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crothers JW, Ross Colgate E, Cowan KJ, et al. Intradermal fractional-dose inactivated polio vaccine (fIPV) adjuvanted with double mutant enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli heat labile toxin (dmLT) is well tolerated and augments a systemic immune response to all three poliovirus serotypes in a randomized placebo-controlled trial. Vaccine 2022; 40:2705–2713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polio dashboard. European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control [online]. Available at: https://gis.ecdc.europa.eu/portal/apps/dashboards/fc1d8b9f4a8740808935600db9a96057 . [Accessed 17 February 2023]</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>