<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37090140</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0974-777X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Season>Jan-Mar</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of global infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Glob Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinico Virological Characterization of Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease in a Tertiary Care Hospital, South India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>13</StartPage><EndPage>18</EndPage><MedlinePgn>13-18</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jgid.jgid_145_22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) is a common childhood infectious disease, caused by enteroviruses (EVs) which can present with typical or atypical lesions. Although the disease is self-limiting, it can also lead to serious complications. In the era of polio eradication, it is important to understand the population dynamics of enteroviruses causing HFMD as one of the circulating strains may become dominant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">It was a collaborative study carried out in the Department of Dermatology and Microbiology of a tertiary care teaching hospital. The throat swabs were collected from 132 suspected HFMD cases. Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed to detect the presence of pan enteroviruses, followed by genotype-specific PCR targeting Human Enterovirus 71 (HEV-71) and Coxsackie virus A16 (CVA-16) and CVA-6 for pan Enterovirus-positive samples. Follow-up samples were collected from 14 children in the 2<sup>nd</sup> week and subjected to molecular testing to detect enteroviruses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Among 132 children suspected to have HFMD, 44 were girls and 88 were boys, and the majority of them 76.5% (101/132) were under 2 years of age. A history of exposure to a similar clinical presentation was present in 15 children. Of 132 suspected cases, 60 samples (45.5%) were positive for pan Enterovirus. The predominantly circulating genotype was found to be CVA-6 (31.6% [19/60]). There were about 10 cases (16.6%) which had co-infection with both HEV71 and CVA-6. Rash with fever was the most common presentation (57%). In most of the cases with HEV 71, 92.3% (12/13) presented within 3 days of illness to the health-care facility. Of 60 positive cases, 25% (15/60) of children had the atypical distribution of rashes in the face, trunk, genitalia, thigh, neck, and axilla and 16.7% of children (10/60) had the atypical type of lesion either only papular lesions or erythema multiforme. Out of 14 follow-up samples, 13 were negative for EVs; one was positive for pan EV in the 2<sup>nd</sup> week, however, the patient lost to follow-up after that.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">HFMD outbreaks in our region were caused by various genotypes of enteroviruses. No severe complications were seen in the affected children. Nearly 30% had atypical presentation either in the form of lesion or site. Robust molecular epidemiological surveillance of HFMD is required to know the strain variations and other emerging genotypes in our setup.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2023 Journal of Global Infectious Diseases.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rajaseker</LastName><ForeName>Christi</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>District Head Quarters Hospital, Cuddalore, Tamil Nadu, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharmila</LastName><ForeName>P Ferdinamarie</ForeName><Initials>PF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jawaharlal Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and Research, Puducherry, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Munisamy</LastName><ForeName>Malathi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology and Venereology, Jawaharlal Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and Research, Puducherry, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kandhasamy</LastName><ForeName>Vanathy</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Mahatma Gandhi Medical College and Research Institute, Sri Balaji Vidyapeeth, Puducherry, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sundaramurthy</LastName><ForeName>Raja</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, AIIMS, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dhodapkar</LastName><ForeName>Rahul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Jawaharlal Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and Research, Puducherry, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Glob Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101521436</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0974-777X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackie virus-A16</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackie virus-A6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human Enterovirus-71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enteroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hand- foot and mouth disease</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37090140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10118210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jgid.jgid_145_22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JGID-15-13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kumar KB, Kiran AG, Kumar BU. Hand, foot and mouth disease in children: A clinico epidemiological study. Indian J Paediatr Dermatol. 2016;17:7–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarma N, Chakraborty S, Dutta A, Sadhukhan PC. Hand, foot and mouth disease in West Bengal, India: A preliminary report on clinicovirological trend over 3 successive years (2013-2015) Indian J Dermatol. 2017;62:486–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5618835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28979010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu LJ, Xu HM, Li XJ, Wang J, Wang XJ, Ding SJ, et al. Co-detection in the pathogenesis of severe hand-foot-mouth disease. Arch Virol. 2012;157:2219–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3488190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22791110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He SJ, Han JF, Ding XX, Wang YD, Qin CF. Characterization of enterovirus 71 and Coxsackievirus A16 isolated in hand, foot, and mouth disease patients in Guangdong, 2010. Int J Infect Dis. 2013;17:e1025–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23791223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan H, Wang J, Wang C, Yang M, Liu L, Yang G, et al. Etiology of multiple non-EV71 and non-CVA16 enteroviruses associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Jinan, China, 2009-June 2013. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0142733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4642993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26562154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Su L, Cao L, Zhong H, Dong N, Xu J. Enterovirus genotypes causing hand foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, China: A molecular epidemiological analysis. BMC Infect Dis. 2013;13:489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24148902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Sun Y, Lin C, Jia L, Wu Q, Li X, et al. Acase-control study to identify environmental risk factors for hand, foot, and mouth disease outbreaks in Beijing. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2014;67:95–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24647250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasidharan CK, Sugathan P, Agarwal R, Khare S, Lal S, Jayaram Paniker CK. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Calicut. Indian J Pediatr. 2005;72:17–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15684442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijayaraghavan PM, Chandy S, Selvaraj K, Pulimood S, Abraham AM. Virological investigation of hand, foot, and mouth disease in a tertiary care center in South India. J Glob Infect Dis. 2012;4:153–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3459432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23055646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kar BR, Dwibedi B, Kar SK. An outbreak of hand, foot and mouth disease in Bhubaneswar, Odisha. Indian Pediatr. 2013;50:139–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22728634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao DC, Naidu JR, Maiya PP, Babu A, Bailly JL. Large-scale HFMD epidemics caused by Coxsackievirus A16 in Bangalore, India during 2013 and 2015. Infect Genet Evol. 2017;55:228–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28864155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopalkrishna V, Patil PR, Patil GP, Chitambar SD. Circulation of multiple enterovirus serotypes causing hand, foot and mouth disease in India. J Med Microbiol. 2012;61:420–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22052995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi M, Makino T, Hanaoka N, Shimizu H, Enomoto M, Okabe N, et al. Clinical manifestations of Coxsackievirus A6 infection associated with a major outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Japan. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2013;66:260–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23698493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao PK, Veena K, Jagadishchandra H, Bhat SS, Shetty SR. Hand, foot and mouth disease: Changing Indian scenario. Int J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2012;5:220–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4155884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25206173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Sun Y, Du Y, Yan Y, Huo D, Liu Y, et al. Characterization of Coxsackievirus A6 and enterovirus 71-associated hand foot and mouth disease in Beijing, China, from 2013 to 2015. Front Microbiol. 2016;7:391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4812011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27065963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreuter JD, Barnes A, McCarthy JE, Schwartzman JD, Oberste MS, Rhodes CH, et al. Afatal central nervous system enterovirus 68 infection. Arch Pathol Lab Med. 2011;135:793–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21631275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee CJ, Huang YC, Yang S, Tsao KC, Chen CJ, Hsieh YC, et al. Clinical features of Coxsackievirus A4, B3 and B4 infections in children. PLoS One. 2014;9 e87391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3913601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24504149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Lin C, Qu M, Li X, Gao Z, Zhang X, et al. Excretion of enterovirus 71 in persons infected with hand, foot and mouth disease. Virol J. 2013;10:31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3560202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23343115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu WS, Kang B, Hong J, Hwang S, Kim J, Cheon DS. Clinical and etiological characteristics of enterovirus 71-related diseases during a recent 2-year period in Korea. J Clin Microbiol. 2010;48:2490–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2897491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20463159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang S, Wang J, Yan Q, He S, Zhou W, Ge S, et al. Aone-step, triplex, real-time RT-PCR assay for the simultaneous detection of enterovirus 71, coxsackie A16 and pan-enterovirus in a single tube. PLoS One. 2014;9:e102724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4100918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25029500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Wu S, Xiong Y, Li T, Wen Z, Yan M, et al. Co-circulation and genomic recombination of Coxsackievirus A16 and enterovirus 71 during a large outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Central China. PLoS One. 2014;9:e96051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4002479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24776922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang YC, Chu YH, Yen TY, Huang WC, Huang LM, Cheng AL, et al. Clinical features and phylogenetic analysis of Coxsackievirus A9 in Northern Taiwan in 2011. BMC Infect Dis. 2013;13:33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3565879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23347781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatproedprai S, Theanboonlers A, Korkong S, Thongmee C, Wananukul S, Poovorawan Y. Clinical and molecular characterization of hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Thailand, 2008-2009. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2010;63:229–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20657060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dharmapalan D, Saxena VK, Pawar SD, Qureshi TH, Surve P. Clinical and molecular investigations of hand, foot and mouth disease outbreak in Navi Mumbai, India. Indian Pediatr. 2019;56:1052–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31884439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, le Sage FV, Pereira B, Cohen R, Levy C, Archimbaud C, et al. Ambulatory pediatric surveillance of hand, foot and mouth disease as signal of an outbreak of Coxsackievirus A6 infections, France, 2014-2015. Emerg Infect Dis. 2016;22:1884–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5088007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27767012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen YJ, Chang SC, Tsao KC, Shih SR, Yang SL, Lin TY, et al. Comparative genomic analysis of Coxsackievirus A6 strains of different clinical disease entities. PLoS One. 2012;7:e52432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3530459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23300669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teng S, Zhao SY, Wei Y, Shao QM, Jiang MY, Cui DW, et al. Observation on virus shedding periods of enterovirus-71 and Coxsackievirus A 16 monitored by nucleic acids determination in stool samples of children with hand, foot and mouth disease. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi. 2013;51:787–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24406235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi MH, Solomon T, Podin Y, Mohan A, Akin W, Yusuf MA, et al. Evaluation of different clinical sample types in diagnosis of human enterovirus 71-associated hand-foot-and-mouth disease. J Clin Microbiol. 2007;45:1858–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1933032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17446325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>