<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37038731</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2093-2340</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>55</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection &amp; chemotherapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Chemother</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Wastewater Knows Pathogen Spread: Analysis of Residential Wastewater for Infectious Microorganisms including SARS-CoV-2.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>214</StartPage><EndPage>225</EndPage><MedlinePgn>214-225</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3947/ic.2022.0152</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">We aimed to identify the genes of 35 pathogens, including viruses, bacteria, and protozoa that cause waterborne infectious diseases, and to assess the feasibility of a wastewater-based surveillance system.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Wastewater was aseptically sampled once a month from 2 sites. A total of 1 L of wastewater from each site underwent 0.2 µm filtration to generate the sample A. Subsequently, 200 ul of the filtered water was ultra-filtered and concentrated to generate the sample B, which was mixed with sample A in a 1:1 ratio. We performed a Filmarray<sup>®</sup> Gastrointestinal (GI) panel (BioFire Diagnnostics', Salt Lake City, UT, USA) test to simultaneously detect 13 enterobacteria, 5 enterovirus, and 4 protozoa. RNA was extracted to assess 18 types of viruses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 adenovirus, bocavirus, and rhinovirus was detected at both site. Norovirus GI/GII was continuously detected at both sites. Moreover, adenovirus, group A rotaviruses, and hepatitis A virus were frequently detected; however, hepatitis E virus was absent at either site. <i>Campylobacter,</i> enteroaggregative <i>Escherichia coli</i>, enterotoxigenic <i>E. coli</i>, Shiga toxin-producing <i>E. coli</i>, and <i>Clostridioides difficile</i> toxin A/B were detected at both sites. <i>Giardia lamblia</i> was also detected in both sites.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We analyze multiple infectious disease pathogens under sample surveillance with incidence. Further in-depth studies on wastewater-based surveillance will be feasible and important.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 by The Korean Society of Infectious Diseases, Korean Society for Antimicrobial Therapy, and The Korean Society for AIDS.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Nam-Yee</ForeName><Initials>NY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2050-3356</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Emerging Infectious Diseases, Department of Diseases Research, Incheon Metropolitan City Institute of Public Health and Environment, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Hye Jin</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7571-8485</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Gachon University College of Medicine, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oh</LastName><ForeName>Sung-Suck</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3867-6271</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Emerging Infectious Diseases, Department of Diseases Research, Incheon Metropolitan City Institute of Public Health and Environment, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Young-Woo</ForeName><Initials>YW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2234-6235</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Emerging Infectious Diseases, Department of Diseases Research, Incheon Metropolitan City Institute of Public Health and Environment, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kwon</LastName><ForeName>Mun-Ju</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9556-9950</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Emerging Infectious Diseases, Department of Diseases Research, Incheon Metropolitan City Institute of Public Health and Environment, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eom</LastName><ForeName>Joong Sik</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2744-1159</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Gachon University College of Medicine, Incheon, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Yoonseon</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2644-3606</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Gachon University College of Medicine, Incheon, Korea. yoonseony@gilhospital.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>HE20C0022060022</GrantID><Agency>Korea Health Industry Development Institute</Agency><Country>Republic of Korea</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Chemother</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101531537</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1598-8112</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental microbiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food-water borne pathogens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">One-health surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater-based epidemiology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>No conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37038731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10323530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3947/ic.2022.0152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">55.e10</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hristovski M, Cvetkovik A, Cvetkovik I, Dukoska V. Concept of one health - a new professional imperative. Maced J Med Sci. 2010;3:229–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lodder WJ, de Roda Husman AM. Presence of noroviruses and other enteric viruses in sewage and surface waters in The Netherlands. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2005;71:1453–1461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1065170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15746348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Global Water Pathogens Project (GWPP) The Global Water Pathogens Project (GWPP) is a knowledge resource on pathogens supporting sanitation and safe water and promoting quantitative information via monitoring of sewage, fecal sludges and freshwaters to inform public health measures.  [Accessed 15 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.waterpathogens.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Q, Wang Y, Hulth A, Xiao Y, Nilsson LE, Li X, Bi Z, Liu Y, Yin H, Luo Y, Nilsson M, Sun C, Zhu Y, Zheng B, Chen B, Sun P, Ding L, Xia X, Ottoson J, Löfmark S, Dyar OJ, Börjesson S, Lundborg CS IMPACT Consortium. Study protocol for One Health data collections, analyses and intervention of the Sino-Swedish integrated multisectoral partnership for antibiotic resistance containment (IMPACT) BMJ Open. 2018;8:e017832</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5780695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29358424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savin M, Bierbaum G, Schmithausen RM, Heinemann C, Kreyenschmidt J, Schmoger S, Akbaba I, Käsbohrer A, Hammerl JA. Slaughterhouse wastewater as a reservoir for extended-spectrum β-lactamase (ESBL)-producing, and colistin-resistant Klebsiella spp. and their impact in a “One Health” perspective. Sci Total Environ. 2022;804:150000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34517324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) National wastewater surveillance system (NWSS)  [Accessed 15 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.cdc.gov/healthywater/surveillance/wastewater-surveillance/wastewater-surveillance.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID19WBEC.ORG; COVID-19 WBE collaborative.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.covid19wbec.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debra T, Feng H, Inna L. China Water Risk (CWR) 8 facts on China's wastewater.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.chinawaterrisk.org/resources/analysis-reviews/8-facts-on-china-wastewater/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goverment of South Australia. COVID-19 wastewater surveillance program.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.sahealth.sa.gov.au/wps/wcm/connect/Public+Content/SA+Health+Internet/Conditions/Infectious+diseases/COVID-19/Response/COVID-19+wastewater+surveillance+program/COVID-19+wastewater+surveillance+program?mr-sort=date-desc&amp;mr-pg=1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Korea. Change in sewerage penetration rate, Korea, 2012-2020.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.index.go.kr/unity/potal/main.do;jsessionid=ovUcakXW0Vvh5V9x2uCQqz8f2RSxFcG6xQqIShjI.node11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Korea. Korea's sewerage Act. Korea: Goverment of republic of Korea; 2022.  [Accessed November 16 2022].  Available at:  https://law.go.kr/eng/engLsAstSc.do?menuId=1&amp;dataCls=lsAstSc&amp;cptOfiCd=1352000#cptOfi1352000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KY, Oh JE. Evaluation of pharmaceutical abuse and illicit drug use in South Korea by wastewater-based epidemiology. J Hazard Mater. 2020;396:122622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32388180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin H, Kim Y, Han D, Hur HG. Emergence of high level carbapenem and extensively drug resistant Escherichia coli ST746 producing NDM-5 in influent of wastewater treatment plant, Seoul, South Korea. Front Microbiol. 2021;12:645411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8021692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33833746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency (KDCA) 2022 guidelines for the diagnosis and report system of legal infectious disease, Korea.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://kdca.go.kr/contents.es?mid=a30301000000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incheon Metropolitan City. Situation of Sewage treatment facilities, Incheon, Korea.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.incheon.go.kr/env/ENV030301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buss SN, Leber A, Chapin K, Fey PD, Bankowski MJ, Jones MK, Rogatcheva M, Kanack KJ, Bourzac KM. Multicenter evaluation of the BioFire FilmArray gastrointestinal panel for etiologic diagnosis of infectious gastroenteritis. J Clin Microbiol. 2015;53:915–925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4390666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25588652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency (KDCA) Situation dashboards of COVID-19 in Korea.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  http://ncov.mohw.go.kr/bdBoardList_Real.do?brdId=1&amp;brdGubun=11&amp;ncvContSeq=&amp;contSeq=&amp;board_id=&amp;gubun=</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vo V, Tillett RL, Chang CL, Gerrity D, Betancourt WQ, Oh EC. SARS-CoV-2 variant detection at a university dormitory using wastewater genomic tools. Sci Total Environ. 2022;805:149930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8421076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34536875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Bivins A, Simpson SL, Bertsch PM, Ehret J, Hosegood I, Metcalfe SS, Smith WJM, Thomas KV, Tynan J, Mueller JF. Wastewater surveillance demonstrates high predictive value for COVID-19 infection on board repatriation flights to Australia. Environ Int. 2022;158:106938.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8514683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34735954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acosta N, Bautista MA, Hollman J, McCalder J, Beaudet AB, Man L, Waddell BJ, Chen J, Li C, Kuzma D, Bhatnagar S, Leal J, Meddings J, Hu J, Cabaj JL, Ruecker NJ, Naugler C, Pillai DR, Achari G, Ryan MC, Conly JM, Frankowski K, Hubert CR, Parkins MD. A multicenter study investigating SARS-CoV-2 in tertiary-care hospital wastewater. viral burden correlates with increasing hospitalized cases as well as hospital-associated transmissions and outbreaks. Water Res. 2021;201:117369.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8214445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34229222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim HM, Lee EJ, Lee NJ, Woo SH, Kim JM, Rhee JE, Kim EJ. Impact of coronavirus disease 2019 on respiratory surveillance and explanation of high detection rate of human rhinovirus during the pandemic in the Republic of Korea. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15:721–731.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8446939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34405546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan SG, Carlson S, Cheng AC, Chilver MB, Dwyer DE, Irwin M, Kok J, Macartney K, MacLachlan J, Minney-Smith C, Smith D, Stocks N, Taylor J, Barr IG. Where has all the influenza gone? The impact of COVID-19 on the circulation of influenza and other respiratory viruses, Australia, March to September 2020. Euro Surveill. 2020;25:2001847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33243355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trenholme A, Webb R, Lawrence S, Arrol S, Taylor S, Ameratunga S, Byrnes CA. COVID-19 and infant hospitalizations for seasonal respiratory virus infections, New Zealand, 2020. Emerg Infect Dis. 2021;27:641–643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7853573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33263515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agca H, Akalin H, Saglik I, Hacimustafaoglu M, Celebi S, Ener B. Changing epidemiology of influenza and other respiratory viruses in the first year of COVID-19 pandemic. J Infect Public Health. 2021;14:1186–1190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34399190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency (KDCA) Total surveillance infectious disease statistical information.  [Accessed 16 November 2022].  Available at:  https://www.kdca.go.kr/npt/biz/npp/ist/simple/simplePdStatsMain.do.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Angel N, Edson J, Bibby K, Bivins A, O’Brien JW, Choi PM, Kitajima M, Simpson SL, Li J, Tscharke B, Verhagen R, Smith WJM, Zaugg J, Dierens L, Hugenholtz P, Thomas KV, Mueller JF. First confirmed detection of SARS-CoV-2 in untreated wastewater in Australia: A proof of concept for the wastewater surveillance of COVID-19 in the community. Sci Total Environ. 2020;728:138764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7165106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32387778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prado T, Fumian TM, Mannarino CF, Resende PC, Motta FC, Eppinghaus ALF, Chagas do Vale VH, Braz RMS, de Andrade JDSR, Maranhão AG, Miagostovich MPG. Wastewater-based epidemiology as a useful tool to track SARS-CoV-2 and support public health policies at municipal level in Brazil. Water Res. 2021;191:116810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33434709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhabra P, de Graaf M, Parra GI, Chan MC, Green K, Martella V, Wang Q, White PA, Katayama K, Vennema H, Koopmans MP, Vinjé J. Updated classification of norovirus genogroups and genotypes. J Gen Virol. 2019;100:1393–1406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7011714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31483239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartsch SM, Lopman BA, Ozawa S, Hall AJ, Lee BY. Global economic burden of norovirus gastroenteritis. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0151219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4846012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27115736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon JH, Cho SH, Kim DY, Yu SJ, Han KH. Epidemiological and clinical history of viral hepatitis in Korea. Infect Chemother. 2021;53:159–165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8032906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33538133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chacón L, Morales E, Valiente C, Reyes L, Barrantes K. Wastewater-based epidemiology of enteric viruses and surveillance of acute gastrointestinal illness outbreaks in a resource-limited region. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2021;105:1004–1012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8592140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34339385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westrell T, Dusch V, Ethelberg S, Harris J, Hjertqvist M, Jourdan-da Silva N, Koller A, Lenglet A, Lisby M, Vold L. Norovirus outbreaks linked to oyster consumption in the United Kingdom, Norway, France, Sweden and Denmark, 2010. Euro Surveill. 2010;15:19524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20350499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavakoli Nick S, Mohebbi SR, Hosseini SM, Mirjalali H, Alebouyeh M. Monitoring of rotavirus in treated wastewater in Tehran with a monthly interval, in 2017-2018. J Water Health. 2020;18:1065–1072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33328375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Neyvaldt J, Enache L, Sikora P, Mattsson A, Johansson A, Lindh M, Bergstedt O, Norder H. Variations among Viruses in Influent Water and Effluent Water at a Wastewater Plant over One Year as Assessed by Quantitative PCR and Metagenomics. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2020;86:e02073–e02020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7688244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33036988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh SS, Han SJ, Gong YW, Nam HJ, Kim KA, Kim NY, Kim KS, Lee DG, Shin HK, Lee HB, Kwon MJ, Chae JS. Investigation of pathogenic Escherichia coli contamination of vegetables distributed in a Korean agricultural wholesale market. Foodborne Pathog Dis. 2021;18:887–893.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34388355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meinersmann RJ, Berrang ME, Jackson CR, Fedorka-Cray P, Ladely S, Little E, Frye JG, Mattsson B. Salmonella, Campylobacter and Enterococcus spp.: their antimicrobial resistance profiles and their spatial relationships in a synoptic study of the Upper Oconee River basin. Microb Ecol. 2008;55:444–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17687594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jokinen C, Edge TA, Ho S, Koning W, Laing C, Mauro W, Medeiros D, Miller J, Robertson W, Taboada E, Thomas JE, Topp E, Ziebell K, Gannon VP. Molecular subtypes of Campylobacter spp., Salmonella enterica, and Escherichia coli O157:H7 isolated from faecal and surface water samples in the Oldman River watershed, Alberta, Canada. Water Res. 2011;45:1247–1257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20971491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Sivakumar M, Jiang G. Decay of four enteric pathogens and implications to wastewater-based epidemiology: Effects of temperature and wastewater dilutions. Sci Total Environ. 2022;819:152000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34843787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong H, Kang S, Cho HJ. Prevalence of multidrug-resistant organisms and risk factors for carriage among patients transferred from long-term care facilities. Infect Chemother. 2020;52:183–193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7335643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32468740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thangjui S, Sripirom N, Titichoatrattana S, Mekmullica J. Accuracy and cross-reactivity of rapid diagnostic tests for norovirus and rotavirus in a real clinical setting. Infect Chemother. 2020;52:360–368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7533216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32869549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>