<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37080396</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0984</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>317</Volume><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of virological methods</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Virol Methods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of membrane pore-size on the recovery of endogenous viruses from wastewater using an adsorption-extraction method.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>114732</StartPage><MedlinePgn>114732</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jviromet.2023.114732</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0166-0934(23)00057-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The ongoing COVID-19 pandemic has emphasized the significance of wastewater surveillance in monitoring and tracking the spread of infectious diseases, including SARS-CoV-2. The wastewater surveillance approach detects genetic fragments from viruses in wastewater, which could provide an early warning of outbreaks in communities. In this study, we determined the concentrations of four types of endogenous viruses, including non-enveloped DNA (crAssphage and human adenovirus 40/41), non-enveloped RNA (enterovirus), and enveloped RNA (SARS-CoV-2) viruses, from wastewater samples using the adsorption-extraction (AE) method with electronegative HA membranes of different pore sizes (0.22, 0.45, and 0.80 µm). Our findings showed that the membrane with a pore size of 0.80 µm performed comparably to the membrane with a pore size of 0.45 µm for virus detection/quantitation (repeated measurement one-way ANOVA; p &gt; 0.05). We also determined the recovery efficiencies of indigenous crAssphage and pepper mild mottle virus, which showed recovery efficiencies ranging from 50% to 94% and from 20% to 62%, respectively. Our results suggest that the use of larger pore size membranes may be beneficial for processing larger sample volumes, particularly for environmental waters containing low concentrations of viruses. This study offers valuable insights into the application of the AE method for virus recovery from wastewater, which is essential for monitoring and tracking infectious diseases in communities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Warish</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia. Electronic address: Warish.Ahmed@csiro.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Wendy J M</ForeName><Initials>WJM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sirikanchana</LastName><ForeName>Kwanrawee</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Laboratory of Biotechnology, Chulabhorn Research Institute, 54 Kampangpetch 6 Road, Laksi, Bangkok 10210, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kitajima</LastName><ForeName>Masaaki</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Environmental Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Hokkaido University, North 13 West 8, Kita-ku, Sapporo, Hokkaido 060 -8628, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bivins</LastName><ForeName>Aaron</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Louisiana State University, 3255 Patrick F. Taylor Hall, Baton Rouge, LA 70803, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simpson</LastName><ForeName>Stuart L</ForeName><Initials>SL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Lucas Heights, NSW 2234, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Virol Methods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8005839</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0166-0934</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>63231-63-0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012313">RNA</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000327" MajorTopicYN="N">Adsorption</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000079686" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater-Based Epidemiological Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012313" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adsorption-extraction method</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Endogenous viruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic material detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Membrane pore size</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus recovery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater-based epidemiology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37080396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10111872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2023.114732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0166-0934(23)00057-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Harwood V.J., Gyawali P., Sidhu J.P., Toze S. Comparison of concentration methods for quantitative detection of sewage-associated viral markers in environmental waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2015;81:2042–2049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4345397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25576614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Payyappat S., Cassidy M., Harrison N., Besley C. Microbial source tracking of untreated human wastewater and animal scats in urbanized estuarine waters. Sci. Total Environ. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36907409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Bivins A., Korajkic A., Metcalfe S., Smith W.J.M., Simpson S.L. Comparative analysis of adsorption-extraction (AE) and Nanotrap® Magnetic Virus Particles (NMVP) workflows for the recovery of endogenous enveloped and non-enveloped viruses in wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2023;859</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10823496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36356768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Bivins A., Simpson S.L., Smith W.J.M., Metcalfe S., McMinn B., Symonds E.M., Korajkic A. Comparative analysis of rapid concentration methods for the recovery of SARS-CoV-2 and quantification of human enteric viruses and a sewage-associated marker gene in untreated wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;799</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8325557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34388890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Bivins A., Stephens M., Metcalfe S., Smith W.J.M., Sirikanchana K., Kitajima M., Simpson S.L. Potential for community disease surveillance,; Australia: 2023. Occurrence of multiple respiratory viruses in wastewater in Queensland. (Sci. Total Environ.).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9759456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36539100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Smith W.J.M., Metcalfe S., Jackson G., Choi P.M., Morrison M., Field D., Gyawali P., Bivins A., Bibby K., Simpson S.L. Comparison of RT-qPCR and RT-dPCR platforms for the trace detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in Wastewater. ACS EST. Water. 2022;2:1871–1880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8848507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36380768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Bertsch P.M., Bivins A., Bibby K., Farkas K., Gathercole A., Haramoto E., Gyawali P., Korajkic A., McMinn B.R., Mueller J.F., Simpson S.L., Smith W.J.M., Symonds E.M., Thomas K.V., Verhagen R., Kitajima M. Comparison of virus concentration methods for the RT-qPCR- based recovery of murine hepatitis virus a surrogate for SARS- CoV-2 from untreated wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;739</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7273154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32758945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W., Angel N., Edson J., Bibby K., Bivins A., O’Brien J.W., Choi P.M., Kitajima M., Simpson S.L., Li J., Tscharke B., Verhagen R., Smith W.J.M., Zaugg J., Dierens L., Hugenholtz P., Thomas K.V., Mueller J.F. First confirmed detection of SARS-CoV-2 in untreated wastewater in Australia: a proof of concept for the wastewater surveillance of COVID-19 in the community. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;728</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7165106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32387778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed, W., Simpson, S.L., Bertsch, P.M., Bibby, K., Bivins, A., Linda, L., Bofill-mas, S., Bosch, A., Brandão, J., Choi, P.M., Ciesielski, M., Donner, E., D’Souza, N., Farnleitner, A.H., Gerrity, D., Gonzalez, R., Griffith, J.F., Gyawali, P., Haas, C.N., Hamilton, K.A., Hapuarachchi, C., Harwood, V.J., Haque, S.R., Jackson, G., Khan, S., Khan, W., Kitajima, M., Korajkic, A., Rosa, G. La, Layton, B.A., Lipp, E., McLellan, S., McMinn, B., Medema, G., Metcalfe, S., Meijer, W., Mueller, J., Murphy, H., Naughton, C.C., Noble, R.T., Payyappat, S., Petterson, S., Pitkänen, T., Rajal, V.B., Reyneke, B., Jr., F.A.R., Rose, J.B., Rusiñol, M., Sadowsky, M., Sala-Comorera, L., Setoh, Y.X., Sherchan, S., Sirikanchana, K., Smith, W., Steele, J., Subburg, R., Symonds, E.M., Thai, P., Thomas, K., Tynan, J., Toze, S., Thompson, J., Whitely, A.S., Wong, J., Sano, D., Wuertz, S., Xagoraraki, I., Zhang, Q., Zimmer-Faust, A.G., Shanks, O., 2022a. Minimizing errors in RT-PCR detection and quantification of SARS-CoV-2 RNA for Wastewater Surveillance. Sci. Total Environ. 805, 149877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8386095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34818780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ando H., Murakami M., Ahmed W., Iwamoto R., Okabe S., Kitajima M. Wastewater-based prediction of COVID-19 cases using a highly sensitive SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection method combined with mathematical modeling. Environ. Int. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9824953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36867995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ando H., Ahmed W., Iwamoto R., Ando Y., Okabe S., Kitajima M. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the prevalence of influenza a and respiratory synctial viruses elucidated by wastewater-based epidemiology. Sci. Total Environ. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9991320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36894088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Besselsen D.G., Wagner A.M., Loganbill J.K. Detection of rodent coronaviruses by use of fluorogenic reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction analysis. Comp. Med. 2002;52:111–116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12022389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bivins A., Greaves J., Fischer R., Yinda K.C., Ahmed W., Kitajima M., Munster V., Bibby K. Persistence of SARS-CoV-2 in water and wastewater. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2020;7:937–942.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37566354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin S.A., Benes V., Garson J.A., Hellemans J., Huggett J., Kubista M., Mueller R., Nolan T., Pfaffl M.W., Shipley G.L., Vandesompele J., Wittwer C.T. The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments. Clin. Chem. 2009;55:611–622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19246619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cashdollar J.L., Brinkman N.E., Griffin S.M., McMinn B.R., Rhodes E.R., Varughese E.A., Grimm A.C., Parshionikar S.U., Wymer L., Fout G.S. Development and evaluation of EPA method 1615 for detection of enterovirus and norovirus in water. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2013;79 215-23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23087037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC 2019-novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) real-time RT-PCR diagnostic panel, n.d.CDC 2019-novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) real-time RT-PCR diagnostic panel (n.d.). https://www.fda.gov/media/134922/download.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8673615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34910739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)., 2021. National Wastewater Surveillance System (NWSS). https://www.cdc.gov/healthywater/surveillance/wastewater-surveillance/wastewater-surveillance.html. [WWW Document].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chik, A.H.S., Glier, M.B., Servos, M., Mangat, C.S., Pang, X.L., Qiu, Y., D'Aoust, P.M., Burnet, J.B., Delatolla, R., Dorner, S., Geng, Q., Giesy, J.P., Jr, McKay, R.M., Mulvey, M.R., Prystajecky, N., Srikanthan, N., Xie, Y., Conant, B., Hrudey, S.E., Canadian SARS-CoV-2 Inter- Laboratory Consortium., 2021. Comparison of approaches to quantify SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater using RT-qPCR: Results and implications from a collaborative inter-laboratory study in Canada. J. Environ. Sci. (China), 107, 218–229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7929783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34412784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corpuz M.V.A., Buonerba A., Vigliotta G., Zarra T., Ballesteros F., Jr, Campiglia P., Belgiorno V., Korshin G., Naddeo V. Viruses in wastewater: occurrence abundance and detection methods. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;745</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7368910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32758747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jonge E.F., Peterse C.M., Koelewijn J.M., Drift A.R., Van Der, van der Beek R., Nagelkerke E., Lodder W.J. The detection of monkeypox virus DNA in wastewater samples in the Netherlands. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;852</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9558568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36057309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira L.C., Torres-Franco A.F., Lopes B.C., Santos B.S.Á., da S., Costa E.A., Costa M.S., Reis M.T.P., Melo M.C., Polizzi R.B., Teixeira M.M., Mota C.R. Viability of SARS-CoV-2 in river water and wastewater at different temperatures and solids content. Water Res. 2021;195</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumke R., Geissler M., Skupin A., Helm B., Mayer R., Schubert S., Oertel R., Renner B., Dalpke A.H. Simultaneous detection of SARS-CoV-2 and influenza virus in wastewater of two cities in Southeastern Germany, January to May 2022. Int. J. Environ. Heal. Res. Public Heal. 2022;19:13374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9603229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36293955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission, 2021. Commission Recommendation of 17.3.2021 on a common approach to establish a systematic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 and its variants in wastewaters in the EU.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farkas K., McDonald J.E., Malham S.K., Jones D.L. Two-step concentration of complex water samples for the detection of viruses. Methods Protoc. 2018;1:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6481077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31164575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman M. The use of ranks to avoid the assumption of normality implicit in the analysis of variance. J. Am. Stat. Assoc. 1937;32:675–701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garg A., Pattamadilok S., Bahl S. Successes and challenges of expansion of environmental poliovirus surveillance in the WHO South-East Asia Region. WHO South-East Asia. J. Public Heal. 2018;7:122–128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30136671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba C.P., Betancourt W.Q., Kitajima M. How much reduction of virus is needed for recycled water: a continuous changing need for assessment? Water Res. 2017;108:25–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27838026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhouse S.W., Geisser S. On methods in the analysis of profile data. Psychometrika. 1959;24:95–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E., Kitajima M., Kishida N., Konno Y., Katayama H., Asami M., Akiba M. Occurrence of pepper mild mottle virus in drinking water sources in Japan. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2013;79(23):7413–7418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3837739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24056461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E., Kitajima M., Hata A., Torrey J.R., Masago Y., Sano D., Katayama H. A review on recent progress in the detection methods and prevalence of human enteric viruses in water. Water Res. 2018;135:168–186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwamoto R., Yamaguchi K., Arakawa C., Ando H., Haramoto E., Setsukinai K.I., Katayama K., Yamagishi T., Sorano S., Murakami M., Kyuwa S., Kobayashi H., Okabe S., Imoto S., Kitajima M. The detectability and removal efficiency of SARS-CoV-2 in a large-scale septic tank of a COVID-19 quarantine facility in Japan. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;849</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9356757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35944642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama H., Shimasaki A., Ohgaki S. Development of a virus concentration method and its application to detection of enterovirus and norwalk virus from coastal seawater. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2002;68:1033–1039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC123733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11872447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya D., Niemeier D., Ahmed W., Kjellerup B.V. Evaluation of multiple analytical methods for SARS-CoV-2 surveillance in wastewater samples. Sci. Total Environ. 2022;808</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8648376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34883175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H.Y. Statistical notes for clinical researchers: a one-way repeated measures ANOVA for data with repeated observations. Restor. Dent. Endod. 2015;40:91–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4320283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25671219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M., Sassi H.P., Torrey J.R. Pepper mild mottle virus as a water quality indicator. npj Clean. Water. 2018;1:19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko G., Jothikumar N., Hill V.R., Sobsey M. Rapid detection of infectious adenovirus by mRNA real-time RT-PCR. J. Virol. Methods. 2005;127:148–153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15967237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kongprajug A., Chyerochana N., Rattanakul S., Denpetkul T., Sangkaew W., Somnark P., Patarapongsant Y., Tomyim K., Sresang M., Mongkolsuk S., Sirikanchana K. Integrated analyses of fecal indicator bacteria microbial source tracking markers and pathogens for Southeast Asian beach water quality assessment. Water Res. 2021;203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34365192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LaTurner Z.W., Zong D.M., Kalvapalle P., Gamas K.R., Terwilliger A., Crosby T., Ali P., Avadhanula V., Santos H.H., Weesner K., Hopkins L., Piedra P.A., Maresso A.W., Stadler L.B. Evaluating recovery cost and throughput of different concentration methods for SARS-CoV-2 wastewater-based epidemiology. Water Res. 2021;197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7957301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33784608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louten J. Virus structure and classification. Essent. Hum. Virol. 2016;2016:19–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn B.R., Ashbolt N.J., Korajkic A. Bacteriophages as indicators of faecal pollution and enteric virus removal. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 2017;65:11–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6089083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28304098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn B.R., Korajkic A., Kelleher J., Herrmann M.P., Pemberton A.C., Ahmed W., Villegas E.N., Oshima K. Development of a large volume concentration method for recovery of coronavirus from wastewater. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;774</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7870434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33607441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medema G., Heijnen L., Italiaander R., Brouwer A. Presence of SARS-Coronavirus ‑ 2 RNA in sewage and correlation with reported COVID-19 prevalence in the early stage of the epidemic in The Netherlands. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2020 doi: 10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37566285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miura T., Takino H., Gima A., Haramoto E., Akiba M. Recovery of nucleic acids of enteric viruses and host-specific bacteroidales from groundwater by using an adsorption-direct extraction method. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2021;87:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8388822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34232739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson K. Notes on regression and inheritance in the case of two parents Proceed. R. Soc. Lond. 1895;58:240–242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pecson B.M., Darby E., Haas C.N., Amha Y.M., Bartolo M., Danielson R., Dearborn Y., Di Giovanni G., Ferguson C., Fevig S., Gaddis E., Gray D., Lukasik G., Mull B., Olivas L., Olivieri A., Qu Y. SARS-CoV-2 interlaboratory consortium Reproducibility and sensitivity of 36 methods to quantify the SARS-CoV-2 genetic signal in raw wastewater: findings from an interlaboratory methods evaluation in the U.S. Environ. Sci. Water Res. Technol. 2021;7:504–520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8129921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34017594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plaza-Garrido A., Limaico M., Villamar-Ayala C.A. Influence of wastewater treatment technologies on virus removal under a bibliometric-statistical analysis. J. Water Process Eng. 2022;47</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosario K., Symonds E.M., Sinigalliano C., Stewart J., Breitbart M. Pepper mild mottle virus as an indicator of fecal pollution. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2009;75:7261–7267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2786529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19767474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rusiñol M., Martínez-puchol S., Forés E., Itarte M., Girones R., Bofill-mas S. Concentration methods for the quantification of coronavirus and other potentially pandemic enveloped virus from wastewater. Curr. Opin. Environ. Sci. Health. 2020;17:21–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabar M.A., Honda R., Haramoto E. CrAssphage as an indicator of human-fecal contamination in water environment and virus reduction in wastewater treatment. Water Res. 2022;221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35820313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangsanont J., Rattanakul S., Makkaew P., Precha N., Rukthanapitak P., Sresung M., Siri Y., Kitajima M., Takeda T., Haramoto E., Puenpa J., Wanlapakorn N., Mongkolsuk S., Sirikanchana K. Wastewater monitoring in tourist cities as potential sentinel sites for near real-time dynamics of imported SARS- CoV-2 variants. Sci. Total Environ. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9691270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36436629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E., Kelty C., Sivaganesan M., Li X., Bibby K., Shanks O.C. Quantitative CrAssphage PCR Assays for human fecal pollution measurement. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2017;51:9146–9154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28700235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbyla M.E., Symonds E.M., Kafle R.C., Cairns M.R., Iriarte M., Mercado Guzmán A., Coronado O., Breitbart M., Ledo C., Mihelcic J.R. Managing microbial risks from indirect wastewater reuse for irrigation in urbanizing Watersheds. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2016;50:6803–6813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26992352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO., 2003. Guidelines for environmental surveillance of poliovirus circulation. WHO/V&amp;B/03.03.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Regional Office for Europe., 2020. Rapid Expert Consultation on environmental surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater. Summary Report.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wurtzer S., Levert M., Dhenain E., Boni M., Tournier J.N., Londinsky N., Lefranc A., SIG O., Ferraris O., Moulin L. First detection of Monkeypox virus genome in sewersheds in France. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2022;9:991–996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Y., Ellenberg R.M., Graham K.E., Wigginton K.R. Survivability partitioning and recovery of enveloped viruses in untreated municipal wastewater. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2016;50:5077–5085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27111122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y., Chen R., Li Y.Y., Sano D. Virus removal by membrane bioreactors: a review of mechanism investigation and modeling efforts. Water Res. 2021;188</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33091802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>