<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37192571</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-2448</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>239</Volume><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Water research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Water Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Temporal and spatial relationships of CrAssphage and enteric viral and bacterial pathogens in wastewater in North Carolina.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>120008</StartPage><MedlinePgn>120008</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.watres.2023.120008</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0043-1354(23)00444-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteric disease remains one of the most common concerns for public health, particularly when it results from human exposure to surface and recreational waters contaminated with wastewater. Characterizing the temporal and spatial variation of enteric pathogens prevalent in wastewater is critical to develop approaches to mitigate their distribution in the environment. In this study, we aim to characterize pathogen variability and test the applicability of the human-associated wastewater indicator crAssphage as an indicator of enteric viral and bacterial pathogens. We conducted weekly samplings for 14 months from four wastewater treatment plants in North Carolina, USA. Untreated wastewater samples were processed using hollow fiber ultrafiltration, followed by secondary concentration methods. Adenovirus, norovirus, enterovirus, Salmonella, Shiga toxin 2 (stx<sub>2</sub>), Campylobacter, and crAssphage were measured by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) and reverse transcriptase (rt)-qPCR. Our results revealed significant correlations between crAssphage and human adenovirus, enterovirus, norovirus, Salmonella, and Campylobacter (p&lt;0.01). Pathogens and crAssphage concentrations in untreated wastewater showed distinct seasonal patterns, with peak concentrations of crAssphage and viral pathogens in fall and winter, while bacterial pathogens showed peaked concentrations in either winter (Campylobacter), fall (Salmonella), or summer (stx<sub>2</sub>). This study enhances the understanding of crAssphage as an alternative molecular indicator for both bacterial and viral pathogens. The findings of this study can also inform microbial modeling efforts for the prediction of the impact of wastewater pathogens on surface waters due to increased flooding events and wastewater overflows associated with climate change.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Huiyun</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development, RTP, NC, 27709, USA; Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education, PO Box 117, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831 USA; Department of Environmental Health Sciences, Tulane University, 1440 Canal Street, Suite 2100, New Orleans, LA 70112, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Juel</LastName><ForeName>Md Ariful Islam</ForeName><Initials>MAI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of North Carolina Charlotte, 9201 University City Boulevard, Charlotte, NC 28223, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eytcheson</LastName><ForeName>Stephanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education, PO Box 117, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831 USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aw</LastName><ForeName>Tiong Gim</ForeName><Initials>TG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, Tulane University, 1440 Canal Street, Suite 2100, New Orleans, LA 70112, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Munir</LastName><ForeName>Mariya</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of North Carolina Charlotte, 9201 University City Boulevard, Charlotte, NC 28223, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Molina</LastName><ForeName>Marirosa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development, RTP, NC, 27709, USA. Electronic address: molina.marirosa@epa.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>EPA999999</GrantID><Acronym>ImEPA</Acronym><Agency>Intramural EPA</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Water Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0105072</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0043-1354</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009657" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">North Carolina</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029322" MajorTopicYN="Y">Norovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005243" MajorTopicYN="N">Feces</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014871" MajorTopicYN="N">Water Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">And viruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enteric pathogens correlations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Municipal untreated wastewater</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spatial variations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Temporal variations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crAssphage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">qPCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rt-qPCR</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37192571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1952185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10896230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2023.120008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0043-1354(23)00444-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adegoke AA, Amoah ID, Stenström TA, Verbyla ME, Mihelcic JR, 2018. Epidemiological evidence and health risks associated with agricultural reuse of partially treated and untreated wastewater: a Review. Front. Public Health 6, 337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6292135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30574474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Bivins A, Bertsch PM, Bibby K, Gyawali P, Sherchan SP, Simpson SL, Thomas KV, Verhagen R, Kitajima M, Mueller JF, Korajkic A, 2021. Intraday variability of indicator and pathogenic viruses in 1-h and 24-h composite wastewater samples: implications for wastewater-based epidemiology. Environ. Res 193, 110531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8267967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33249042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Lobos A, Senkbeil J, Peraud J, Gallard J, Harwood VJ, 2018a. Evaluation of the novel crAssphage marker for sewage pollution tracking in storm drain outfalls in Tampa, Florida. Water Res 131, 142–150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29281808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Besley C, Power K, 2018b. Novel crAssphage marker genes ascertain sewage pollution in a recreational lake receiving urban stormwater runoff. Water Res. 145, 769–778.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30223182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernabeu M, Sanchez-Herrero JF, Huedo P, Prieto A, Huttener M, Rozas J, Juarez A, 2019. Gene duplications in the E. coli genome: common themes among pathotypes. BMC Genomics 20 (1), 313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6480617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31014240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibby K, Peccia J, 2013. Identification of viral pathogen diversity in sewage sludge by metagenome analysis. Environ. Sci. Technol 47 (4), 1945–1951.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3963146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23346855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer AF, Eisenberg MC, Shulman LM, Famulare M, Koopman JS, Kroiss SJ, Hindiyeh M, Manor Y, Grotto I, Eisenberg JNS, 2022. The role of time-varying viral shedding in modelling environmental surveillance for public health: revisiting the 2013 poliovirus outbreak in Israel. J. R. Soc. Interface 19 (190), 20220006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9114981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35582812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buzby JC, Roberts T, 2009. The economics of enteric infections: human foodborne disease costs. Gastroenterology 136 (6), 1851–1862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19457414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cashdollar JL, Brinkman NE, Griffin SM, McMinn BR, Rhodes ER, Varughese EA, Grimm AC, Parshionikar SU, Wymer L, Fout GS, 2013. Development and evaluation of EPA method 1615 for detection of enterovirus and norovirus in water. Appl. Environ. Microbiol 79 (1), 215–223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23087037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC 2020. Interim laboratory biosafety guidelines for handling and processing specimens associated with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Challberg MD, Kelly TJ, 1989. Animal virus DNA replication. Annu. Rev. Biochem 58 (1), 671–713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2549858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C, Kostakis C, Gerber JP, Tscharke BJ, Irvine RJ, White JM, 2014. Towards finding a population biomarker for wastewater epidemiology studies. Sci. Total Environ 487.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24300482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crank K, Li X, North D, Ferraro GB, Iaconelli M, Mancini P, La Rosa G, Bibby K, 2020. CrAssphage abundance and correlation with molecular viral markers in Italian wastewater. Water Res. 184, 116161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32810770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crank K, Petersen S, Bibby K, 2019. Quantitative microbial risk assessment of swimming in sewage impacted waters using CrAssphage and pepper mild mottle virus in a customizable model. Environ Sci. Technol. Lett 6 (10), 571–577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diemert S, Yan T, 2020. Municipal Wastewater Surveillance Revealed a High Community Disease Burden of a Rarely Reported and Possibly Subclinical Salmonella enterica Serovar Derby Strain. Appl. Environ. Microbiol 86 (17).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32591375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eftim SE, Hong T, Soller J, Boehm A, Warren I, Ichida A, Nappier SP, 2017. Occurrence of norovirus in raw sewage - a systematic literature review and meta- analysis. Water Res. 111, 366–374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28110140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA, U.S. 2009. Method 1600: Enterococci in Water by Membrane Filtration Using membrane- Enterococcus Indoxyl-$-D-Glucoside Agar (mEI).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA, U.S. 2009. Method 1603: Escherichia coli (E. coli) in Water by Membrane Filtration Using Modified Membrane-Thermotolerant Escherichia coli Agar (Modified mTEC).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA, U.S. 2018. Method 1642: Male-specific (F+) and Somatic Coliphage in Recreational Waters and Wastewater by Ultrafiltration (UF) and Single Agar Layer (SAL) Procedure.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA, U.S. 2019. Method 1696: Characterization of Human Fecal Pollution in Water By HF183/BacR287 TaqMan quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction (qPCR) Assay, Washington, DC.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhadkhani M, Nikaeen M, Hadi M, Gholipour S, Yadegarfar G, 2020. Campylobacter risk for the consumers of wastewater-irrigated vegetables based on field experiments. Chemosphere 251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farkas K, Adriaenssens EM, Walker DI, McDonald JE, Malham SK, Jones DL, 2019. Critical evaluation of CrAssphage as a molecular marker for human-derived wastewater contamination in the aquatic environment. Food Environ. Virol 11 (2), 113–119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6513805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30758724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh A, Lin J, 2013. Waterborne human pathogenic viruses of public health concern. Int. J. Environ. Health Res 23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23432800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao R, Zhu Y, Kong C, Xia K, Li H, Zhu Y, Zhang X, Liu Y, Zhong H, Yang R, Chen C, Qin N, Qin H, 2021. Alterations, interactions, and diagnostic potential of gut bacteria and viruses in colorectal cancer. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol 11, 657867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8294192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34307189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Aljaro C, Muniesa M, Jofre J, Blanch AR, 2004. Prevalence of the stx(2) gene in coliform populations from aquatic environments. Appl. Environ. Microbiol 70 (6), 3535–3540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC427775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15184154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Aljaro C, Muniesa M, Jofre J, Blanch AR, 2006. Newly identified bacteriophages carrying the stx2g Shiga toxin gene isolated from Escherichia coli strains in polluted waters. FEMS Microbiol. Lett 258 (1), 127–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16630267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Aljaro C, Muniesa M, Jofre J, Blanch AR, 2009. Genotypic and phenotypic diversity among induced, stx2-carrying bacteriophages from environmental Escherichia coli strains. Appl. Environ. Microbiol 75 (2), 329–336.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2620696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19011056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginn O, Rocha-Melogno L, Bivins A, Lowry S, Cardelino M, Nichols D, Tripathi SN, Soria F, Andrade M, Bergin M, Deshusses MA, Brown J, 2021. Detection and quantification of enteric pathogens in aerosols near open wastewater canals in cities with poor sanitation. Environ. Sci. Technol 55 (21), 14758–14771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34669386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goettle A, Krauth K, 1981. Total pollution loads considering urban storm runoff. Water Sci. Technol 13 (3), 155–173, 19819 Fig, 11 Tab, 22 Ref.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopinath S, Carden S, Monack D, 2012. Shedding light on Salmonella carriers. Trends Microbiol. 20 (7), 320–327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22591832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hata A, Shirasaka Y, Ihara M, Yamashita N, Tanaka H, 2021. Spatial and temporal distributions of enteric viruses and indicators in a lake receiving municipal wastewater treatment plant discharge. Sci. Total Environ 780, 146607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honap TP, Sankaranarayanan K, Schnorr SL, Ozga AT, Warinner C, Lewis CM Jr., 2020. Biogeographic study of human gut-associated crAssphage suggests impacts from industrialization and recent expansion. PLoS ONE 15 (1), e0226930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6961876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31940321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoorfar J, Ahrens P, Radstrom P, 2000. Automated 5′ nuclease PCR assay for identification of Salmonella enterica. J. Clin. Microbiol 38 (9), 3429–3435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC87399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10970396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchins DA, Jansson JK, Remais JV, Rich VI, Singh BK, Trivedi P, 2019. Climate change microbiology - problems and perspectives. Nat. Rev. Microbiol 17 (6), 391–396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31092905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagai JS, DeFlorio-Barker S, Lin CJ, Hilborn ED, Wade TJ, 2017. Sanitary sewer overflows and emergency room visits for gastrointestinal illness: analysis of Massachusetts data, 2006–2007. Environ. Health Perspect 125 (11).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5947952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29187322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama H, Haramoto E, Oguma K, Yamashita H, Tajima A, Nakajima H, Ohgaki S, 2008. One-year monthly quantitative survey of noroviruses, enteroviruses, and adenoviruses in wastewater collected from six plants in Japan. Water Res. 42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17996920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kukkula M, Maunula L, Silvennoinen E, Bonsdorff CH, 1999. Outbreak of viral gastroenteritis due to drinking water contaminated by Norwalk-like viruses. J. Infect. Dis 180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10558930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, Gu AZ, Zeng SY, Yang W, He M, Shi HC, 2011. Monitoring and evaluation of infectious rotaviruses in various wastewater effluents and receiving waters revealed correlation and seasonal pattern of occurrences. J. Appl. Microbiol 110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21276144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malla B, Makise K, Nakaya K, Mochizuki T, Yamada T, Haramoto E, 2019. Evaluation of human- and animal-specific viral markers and application of CrAssphage, pepper mild mottle virus, and tobacco mosaic virus as potential fecal pollution markers to river water in Japan. Food Environ. Virol 11 (4), 446–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31376023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maunula L, Klemola P, Kauppinen A, Söderberg K, Nguyen T, Pitkänen T, Kaijalainen S, Simonen ML, Miettinen IT, Lappalainen M, Laine J, Vuento R, Kuusi M, Roivainen M, 2008. Enteric viruses in a large waterborne outbreak of acute gastroenteritis in Finland. Food Environ. Virol 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCall C, Wu H, Miyani B, Xagoraraki I, 2020. Identification of multiple potential viral diseases in a large urban center using wastewater surveillance. Water Res. 184, 116160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7342010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32738707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCall C, Wu H, O’Brien E, Xagoraraki I, 2021. Assessment of enteric viruses during a hepatitis outbreak in Detroit MI using wastewater surveillance and metagenomic analysis. J. Appl. Microbiol 131 (3), 1539–1554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLellan SL, Hollis EJ, Depas MM, Van Dyke M, Harris J, Scopel CO, 2007. Distribution and fate of Escherichia coli in Lake Michigan following contamination with urban stormwater and combined sewer overflows. J. Great Lakes Res 33 (3).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn BR, Cashdollar JL, Grimm AC, Fout GS, 2012. Evaluation of the celite secondary concentration procedure and an alternate elution buffer for the recovery of enteric adenoviruses 40 and 41. J. Virol. Methods 179 (2), 423–428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22138439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn BR, Korajkic A, Kelleher J, Herrmann MP, Pemberton AC, Ahmed W, Villegas EN, Oshima K, 2021. Development of a large volume concentration method for recovery of coronavirus from wastewater. Sci. Total Environ 774, 145727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7870434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33607441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukhopadhya I, Sarkar R, Menon VK, Babji S, Paul A, Rajendran P, Sowmyanarayanan TV, Moses PD, Iturriza-Gomara M, Gray JJ, Kang G, 2013. Rotavirus shedding in symptomatic and asymptomatic children using reverse transcription-quantitative PCR. J. Med. Virol 85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3758921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23775335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien E, Nakyazze J, Wu H, Kiwanuka N, Cunningham W, Kaneene JB, Xagoraraki I, 2017. Viral diversity and abundance in polluted waters in Kampala, Uganda. Water Res. 127, 41–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29031798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien E, Xagoraraki I, 2019. Understanding temporal and spatial variations of viral disease in the US: the need for a one-health-based data collection and analysis approach. One Health 8, 100105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6831848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31709295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogidan O. and Giacomoni M. (2015) Sanitary sewer overflow reduction optimization using genetic algorithm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papapetropoulou M, Vantarakis AC, 1998. Detection of adenovirus outbreak at a municipal swimming pool by nested PCR amplification. J. Infect 36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9515677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes-Lamothe R, Nicolas E, Sherratt DJ, 2012. Chromosome replication and segregation in bacteria. Annu. Rev. Genet 46, 121–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22934648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabar MA, Honda R, Haramoto E, 2022. CrAssphage as an indicator of human-fecal contamination in water environment and virus reduction in wastewater treatment. Water Res. 221, 118827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35820313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansalone JJ, Buchberger SG, 1997. Partitioning and first flush of metals in urban roadway storm water. J. Environ. Eng 123 (2), 134–143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedmak G, Bina D, MacDonald J, Couillard L, 2005. Nine-year study of the occurrence of culturable viruses in source water for two drinking water treatment plants and the influent and effluent of a wastewater treatment plant in Milwaukee, Wisconsin (August 1994 through July 2003). Appl. Environ. Microbiol 71 (2), 1042–1050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC546740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15691964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seurinck S, Defoirdt T, Verstraete W, Siciliano SD, 2005. Detection and quantification of the human-specific HF183 Bacteroides 16S rRNA genetic marker with real-time PCR for assessment of human faecal pollution in freshwater. Environ. Microbiol 7 (2), 249–259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15658992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh KP, Malik A, Mohan D, Sinha S, 2004. Multivariate statistical techniques for the evaluation of spatial and temporal variations in water quality of Gomti River (India)–a case study. Water Res. 38 (18), 3980–3992.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15380988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sommerfeld J, Kroeger A, 2012. Eco-bio-social research on dengue in Asia: a multicountry study on ecosystem and community-based approaches for the control of dengue vectors in urban and peri-urban Asia. Pathog. Glob Health 106 (8), 428–435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3541880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23318234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spears KJ, Roe AJ, Gally DL, 2006. A comparison of enteropathogenic and enterohaemorrhagic Escherichia coli pathogenesis. FEMS Microbiol. Lett 255 (2), 187–202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16448495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E, Bibby K, 2014. Metagenomic evaluation of the highly abundant human gut bacteriophage CrAssphage for source tracking of human fecal pollution. Environ Sci. Technol. Lett 1 (10), 405–409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E, Kelty C, Sivaganesan M, Li X, Bibby K, Shanks OC, 2017. Quantitative CrAssphage PCR assays for human fecal pollution measurement. Environ. Sci. Technol 51 (16), 9146–9154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28700235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thwiny HT, Alsalih NJ, Saeed ZF, Al-Yasari AMR, Al-Saadawe MAA, Alsaadawi MAE, 2022. Prevalence and seasonal pattern of enteric viruses among hospitalized children with acute gastroenteritis in Samawah, Iraq. J. Med. Life 15 (1), 52–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8852632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35186136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turgeon N, Toulouse MJ, Martel B, Moineau S, Duchaine C, 2014. Comparison of five bacteriophages as models for viral aerosol studies. Appl. Environ. Microbiol 80 (14), 4242–4250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4068686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24795379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchii K, Doi H, Okahashi T, Katano I, Yamanaka H, Sakata MK, Minamoto T, 2019. Comparison of inhibition resistance among PCR reagents for detection and quantification of environmental DNA. Environ. DNA 1 (4), 359–367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Victoria JG, Kapoor A, Li L, Blinkova O, Slikas B, Wang C, Naeem A, Zaidi S, Delwart E, 2009. Metagenomic analyses of viruses in stool samples from children with acute flaccid paralysis. J. Virol 83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2668503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19211756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu HY, Oun A, Kline-Robach R, Xagoraraki I, 2018. Microbial pollution characterization at a TMDL site in Michigan: effect of hydrological conditions on pollution loading. J. Great Lakes Res 44 (3), 421–427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xagoraraki I. and O’Brien E. (2020) Women in water quality, pp. 75–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan T, O’Brien P, Shelton JM, Whelen AC, Pagaling E, 2018. Municipal wastewater as a microbial surveillance platform for enteric diseases: a case study for Salmonella and Salmonellosis. Environ. Sci. Technol 52 (8), 4869–4877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29630348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yezli S, Otter JA, 2011. Minimum infective dose of the major human respiratory and enteric viruses transmitted through food and the environment. Food Environ. Virol 3 (1), 1–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7090536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35255645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>