<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37140767</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>14</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-0342</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food and environmental virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Environ Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Detection of Enteroviruses and SARS-CoV-2 in Tunisian Wastewater.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>224</StartPage><EndPage>235</EndPage><MedlinePgn>224-235</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12560-023-09557-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Monitoring the circulation of enteric viruses in environmental wastewater is a valuable tool for preventing the emergence of waterborne and food-borne diseases in humans. The detection of viruses was performed in five Tunisian wastewater treatment plants, three located in the Grand Tunis City (WWTP 1, WWTP 2, WWTP 3) and two in the Sahel of Tunisia (WWTP 4, WWTP 4), known as very developed and crowded zones, to assess the effectiveness of three biological wastewater treatment procedures namely natural oxidizing lagoons, rotating biodisks procedure, activated sludge procedure, and one tertiary sewage treatment using UV-C<sub>254</sub> reactor for this enteric viruses' removal. Thus, 242 sewage samples were collected between June 2019 and May 2020 from different lines of wastewater treatment procedures implemented in the five wastewater treatment plants investigated. SARS-CoV-2 was analyzed using real-time multiplex reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (multiplex real-time RT-PCR) and enteroviruses using reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). The enteroviruses detection showed 93% and 73% respective high frequencies only in the two WWTPs of the Grand Tunis (WWTP 1 and WWTP 2). SARS-CoV-2 was detected in 58% of the all wastewater samples collected from the five studied WWTPs with a respective dominance of N gene (47%), S gene (42%), RdRp gene (42%) and at last E gene (20%). These enteroviruses and SARS-CoV-2 detection were revealed in all steps of the wastewater treatment procedures, so poor virological quality is found at the exit of each biological and tertiary step of treatment investigated. For the first time in Tunisia, these results highlighted the enterovirus and SARS-CoV-2 detection with high rates, and the ineffectiveness of the biological and UV-C254 treatment implemented to remove these viruses. The preliminary results of SARS-CoV-2 circulation in Tunisian wastewater confirmed the wide positivity rate underlined by other works worldwide and allowed showing a move towards integrating wastewater as a way for this virus to spread in different areas and environments. So, this last result about SARS-CoV-2 circulation allowed us to caution about the strong probability of diffusion of this hazardous virus through water and sewage; despite its enveloped character and nature, as a labile and sensitive virus in these environments. Thus, establishing a national surveillance strategy is needed to improve the sanitary quality of treated wastewater and prevent public health problems related to these viruses in treated wastewater.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ibrahim</LastName><ForeName>Chourouk</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1721-0699</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Research and Water Technologies (CERTE), Laboratory of Treatment and Valorization of Water Rejects (LTVRH), Techno Park of Borj-Cédria, 8020, Tunis, Tunisia. ibrahimchourouk@yahoo.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Mathematical, Physical and Natural Sciences of Tunis, University of Tunis El Manar, 2092, Tunis, Tunisia. ibrahimchourouk@yahoo.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microbiology Laboratory, Beja University Hospital, Beja, Tunisia. ibrahimchourouk@yahoo.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hammami</LastName><ForeName>Salah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National School of Veterinary Medicine at Sidi Thabet, IRESA, University of Manouba, 2020, Tunis, Tunisia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khelifi</LastName><ForeName>Nesserine</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Research and Water Technologies (CERTE), Laboratory of Treatment and Valorization of Water Rejects (LTVRH), Techno Park of Borj-Cédria, 8020, Tunis, Tunisia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassen</LastName><ForeName>Abdennaceur</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Research and Water Technologies (CERTE), Laboratory of Treatment and Valorization of Water Rejects (LTVRH), Techno Park of Borj-Cédria, 8020, Tunis, Tunisia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Food Environ Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101483831</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-0334</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012722">Sewage</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012722" MajorTopicYN="N">Sewage</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enteroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RT-PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surveillance strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UV-C254 treatment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virological quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that might appear to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37140767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10157586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-023-09557-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12560-023-09557-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adefisoye MA, Nwodo UU, Green E, Okoh AI. Quantitative PCR detection and characterization of human adenovirus, rotavirus, and hepatitis a virus in discharged effluents of two wastewater treatment facilities in the eastern cape. South Africa. Food and Environmental Virology. 2016;8(4):262–274. doi: 10.1007/s12560-016-9246-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-016-9246-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5093187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27236707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adeniji JA, Faleye TOC. Isolation and identification of enteroviruses from sewage and sewage-contaminated water in Lagos Nigeria. Food and Environmental Virology. 2014;6(2):75–86. doi: 10.1007/s12560-014-9137-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-014-9137-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24566762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amdiouni H, Faouzi A, Fariat N, Hassar M, Soukri A, Nourlil J. Detection and molecular identification of human adenoviruses and enteroviruses in wastewater from Morocco. Letters Applied in Microbiology. 2012;54(4):359–366. doi: 10.1111/j.1472-765X.2012.03220.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2012.03220.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22324352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amereh F, Jahangiri-rad M, Mohseni-Bandpei A, Mohebbi SR, Asadzadeh-Aghdaei H, Dabiri H, Eslami A, Roostaei K, Aali R, Hamian P, Rafiee M. Association of SARS-CoV-2 presence in sewage with public adherence to precautionary measures and reported COVID-19 prevalence in Tehran. Science Total Environment. 2022;812(152):597.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8697476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34954185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antona D, Kossorottoff M, Schuffenecker I, Mirand A, Leruez-ville M, Bassi C, Aubart M, Moulin F, Lévy-Bruhl D, Henquell C, Lina B, Desguerre I. Severe pediatric conditions linked with EV-A71 and EV-D68, France, May to October 2016. Eurosurveillance. 2016 doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5144948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27918268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battistone A, Buttinelli G, Bonomo P, Fiore S, Amato C, Mercurio P, Cicala A, Simeoni J, Foppa A, Triassi M, Pennino F, Fiore L. Detection of enteroviruses in influent and effluent flow samples from wastewater treatment plants in Italy. Food Environmental Virology. 2014;6(01):13–22. doi: 10.1007/s12560-013-9132-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-013-9132-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24277051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belguith K, Hassen A, Bouslama L, Khira S, Aouni M. Enterovirus circulation in wastewater and behavior of some serotypes during sewage treatment in Monastir. Tunisia. Journal of Environmental Health. 2007;69(10):52–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17583297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisseux M, Colombetn J, Mirand A, Roque-Afonso AM, Abravanel F, Izopet J, Archimbaud C, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Debroas D, Bailly JL, Henquell C. Monitoring human enteric viruses in wastewater and relevance to infections encountered in the clinical setting: A one-year experiment in central France, 2014 to 2015. Eurosurveillance. 2018;23(7):00217–00237. doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.7.17-00237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.7.17-00237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5824128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisseux M, Debroas D, Mirand A, Archimbaud C, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Bailly JL, Henquell C. Monitoring of enterovirus diversity in wastewater by ultra-deep sequencing: An effective complementary tool for clinical enterovirus surveillance. Water Research. 2020;1(169):115–246. doi: 10.1016/j.waters.2019.115246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.waters.2019.115246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31710918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas A, Bhattacharjee U, Chakrabarti AK, Tewari DN, Banu H, Dutta S. Emergence of novel coronavirus and COVID-19: Whether to stay or die out? Critical Reviews in Microbiology. 2020;46(2):182–193. doi: 10.1080/1040841X.2020.1739001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1040841X.2020.1739001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7157960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32282268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnet MC, Dutta A. Worldwide experience with inactivated poliovirus vaccine. Vaccine. 2008;26(39):4978–4983. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.07.026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.07.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18680777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boussaid I, Boumiza A, Zemni R, Chabchoub E, Gueddah L, Slim I, Slama BHF. The role of enterovirus infections in type 1 diabetes in Tunisia. Journal of Paediatric Endocrinology and Metabolism. 2017;30(12):1245–1250. doi: 10.1515/jpeg-2017-0044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/jpeg-2017-0044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29176023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casas-Alba D, de Sevilla MF, Valero-Rello A, Fortuny C, Garcia-Garcia JJ, Ortez C, Muchart J, Armangué T, Jordan I, Luaces C, Barrabeig I, Gonzalez-Sanz R, Cabrerizo M, Muñoz-AlmagroLaunes CC. The outbreak of brainstem encephalitis associated with enterovirus-A71 in Catalonia, Spain (2016): A clinical observational study in a children’s reference centre in Catalonia. Clinical Microbiology and Infections. 2017;23(11):874–881. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2017.03.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2017.03.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28344164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Tracy S, Gaunt CJ, Fortmueller U. Molecular detection and identification of enteroviruses using enzymatic amplification and nucleic acid hybridization. Journal of Clinical Microbiology. 1990;28(5):843–850. doi: 10.1128/jcm.28.5.843-850.1990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.28.5.843-850.1990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC267821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2161866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Liu Q, Guo D. Emerging coronaviruses: Genome structure, replication, and pathogenesis. Journal of Medical Virology. 2020;92(4):418–423. doi: 10.1002/jmv.25681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.25681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31967327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox JA, Hiscox JA, Solomon T, Ooi MH, Ng L. Virus-host interactions of enterovirus 71 in patients with hand, foot, and mouth disease. Frontiers Microbiology. 2017;8:2249–2263. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2017.02249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5713468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29238324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Sousa ARV, Do CarmoSilva L, De Curcio JS, Dae Silva HD, EduardoAnunciação C, MariaSalemIzacc S, Neto FOS, Dae PaulaSilveiraLacerda E. “By sewage”: a hybrid approach to predict the number of SARS-CoV-2-infected people from wastewater in Brazil. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. 2022;6:1–10. doi: 10.1007/s11356-022-20609-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-20609-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9075719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35524091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donia A, Furqan Shahid M, Hassan SU, Shahid R, Ahmad A, Javed A, Nawaz A, Yaqub T, Bokhari H. Integration of RT-LAMP and microfluidic technology for detection of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater as an advanced point-of-care platform. Food and Environmental Virology. 2022;4:1–10. doi: 10.1007/s12560-022-09522-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-022-09522-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9067896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35508752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn JJ. Enteroviruses and parechoviruses. Microbiology Spectrum. 2016 doi: 10.1128/microbiolspec.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27337462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EPA Environmental protection agency. The standard for the disposal of sewage sludge. In Federal Register, Part. 1992;503:9387–9404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorbalenya AE, Baker SC, Baric RS, de Groot RJ, Drosten C, Gulyaeva AA, Haagmans BL, Lauber C, Leontovich AM, Neuman BW, Penzar D, Perlman S, Poon LLM, Samborskiy DV, Sidorov IA, Sola I, Ziebuhr J. Coronaviridae study group of the international committee on taxonomy of V the species severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus: Classifying 2019-nCoV and naming it SARS-CoV-2. Nature Microbiology. 2020;5:536–544. doi: 10.1038/s41564-020-0695-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41564-020-0695-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32123347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutierrez L, Mylon SE, Nash B, Nguyen TH. Deposition and aggregation kinetics of rotavirus in divalent cation solutions. Environmental Science and Technology. 2010;44(12):4552–4557. doi: 10.1021/es100120k.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es100120k</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20481597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamouda M, Mustafa F, Maraqa M, Rizvi T, Hassan A. Wastewater surveillance for SARS-CoV-2: Lessons learned from recent studies to define future applications. Science of the Total Environment. 2021 doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7648500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33190883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Broberg E, Benschop K, Berginc N, Ladhani S, Susi P, Christiansen C. Recommendations for enterovirus diagnostics and characterization within and beyond Europe. Journal of Clinical Virology. 2018;101:11–17. doi: 10.1016/j.jcv.2018.01.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2018.01.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29414181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Calvert J, Van Nguyen D, Clasper L, Gadsby N, Molyneaux P, Templeton K, McWilliams Leitch C, Simmonds P. Comparison of clinical diagnostic samples and environmental sampling for enterovirus and parechovirus surveillance in Scotland, 2010 to 2012. Euro-Surveillance. 2014;19(15):20772–20781. doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.es2014.19.15.20772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.es2014.19.15.20772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24762664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassine M, Sdiri K, Riabi S, Beji A, Aouni Z, Aouni M. Détection des virus entériques dans les eaux usées de la région de Monastir par RT-PCR. La Tunisie Médicale. 2010;88(2):57–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20415161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heijnen L, Elsinga G, de Graaf M, Molenkamp R, Koopmans MPG, Medema G. Droplet digital RT-PCR to detect SARS-CoV-2 signature mutations of variants of concern in wastewater. Science of the Total Environment. 2021;799(149):456. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8332926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34371414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hmaied F, Keskes S, Jebri S, Amri I, Yahya M, Loisy-Hamon F, Lebeau B, Hamdi M. Removal of rotavirus and bacteriophages by membrane bioreactor technology from sewage. Current Microbiology. 2015;71(5):540–545. doi: 10.1007/s00284-015-0882-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00284-015-0882-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26210901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho J, Stange C, Suhrborg R, Wurzbacher C, Drewes JE, Tiehm A. SARS-CoV-2 wastewater surveillance in Germany: Long-term RT-digital droplet PCR monitoring, suitability of primer/probe combinations and biomarker stability. Water Research. 2022;210(117):977. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2021.117977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2021.117977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8684593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34968879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm-Hansen CC, Midgley SE, Fischer TK. Global emergence of enterovirus D68: A systematic review. Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2016;16(5):e64–e75. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00543-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00543-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26929196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Chérif N, Hammami S, Pothier P, Hassen A. Quantification and molecular characterization of norovirus after two wastewater treatment procedures. Water Air and Soil Pollution. 2015;226(6):187–193. doi: 10.1007/s11270-015-2402-x.pdf.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11270-015-2402-x.pdf</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hammami S, Cherif N, Mejri S, Pothier P, Hassen A. Detection of Sapoviruses in two biological lines of Tunisian hospital wastewater treatment. International Journal of Environmental Health Research. 2019;26:1–14. doi: 10.1080/09603123.2018.1546835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09603123.2018.1546835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30474395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hammami S, Hassen A. Processes, Uses, and Importance. Nova Science Publishers; 2019. Performance of municipal wastewater treatment procedures. Wastewater Treatment; pp. 31–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hammami S, Mejri S, Mehri I, Pothier P, Hassen A. Detection of Aichi virus genotype B in two lines of wastewater treatment processes. Microbial Pathogenesis. 2017;109:305–312. doi: 10.1016/j.micpath.2017.06.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2017.06.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28596124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hammami S, Pothier P, Hassen A. Quantification and genotyping of rotavirus within two wastewater treatment processes. Clean: Soil, Air, Water. 2016;44(4):393–401. doi: 10.1002/clen.201400588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/clen.201400588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hammami S, Pothier P, Khelifi N, Hassen A. The performance of biological and tertiary wastewater treatment procedures for rotavirus A removal. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. 2019;27(6):5718–5729. doi: 10.1007/s11356-019-05487-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-05487-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7223008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31177419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Hassen A, Mejri S, Pothier P, Hammami S. Molecular detection and genotypic characterization of Enteric Adenoviruses in hospital wastewater. Environmental Science and Pollution Research. 2018;25(11):10977–10987. doi: 10.1007/s11356-018-1399-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-1399-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29404949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim C, Mehri I, Hammami S, Mejri S, Hassen A, Pothier P. Removal of human astroviruses from hospital wastewater by two biological treatment methods: Natural oxidizing lagoons and rotating biodisks. Desalination Water Treatment. 2017;89:287–296. doi: 10.5004/dwt.2017.21356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5004/dwt.2017.21356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson CB, Farzan M, Chen B, Choe H. Mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2 entry into cells. Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology. 2022;23(1):3–20. doi: 10.1038/s41580-021-00418-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41580-021-00418-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8491763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34611326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaïdane H, Chouchane C, Gharbi J, Chouchane S, March Z, Ben Meriem C, Aouni M, Guediche MN. Neuro-meningeal enterovirus infections in Tunisia: Epidemiology, clinical presentation, and outcome of 26 pediatric cases. Medicine Et Maladies Infectieuses. 2005;35(1):33–38. doi: 10.1016/j.medmal.2004.09.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medmal.2004.09.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15695031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kopecka H, Brown B, Pallansch M. Genotypic variation in coxsackievirus B5 isolates from three different outbreaks in the United States. Virus Research. 1995;38(2–3):125–136. doi: 10.1016/0168-1702(95)00055-u.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0168-1702(95)00055-u</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8578854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei X, Xiao X, Wang J. Innate immunity evasion by enteroviruses: Insights into virus-host interaction. Viruses. 2016;8(1):22–35. doi: 10.3390/v8010022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v8010022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4728582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26784219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumdar M, Sharif S, Klapsa D, Wilton T, Alam MM, Fernandez-Garcia MD, Rehman L, Mujtaba G, McAllister G, Harvala H, Templeton KT, Mee E, Asghar H, Ndiaye KD, Minor P, Martin J. Environmental surveillance reveals complex enterovirus circulation patterns in human populations. Open Forum Infectious Diseases. 2018 doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofy250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofy250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6201154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30377626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medema G, Heijnen L, Elsinga G, Italiaander R, Brouwer A. Presence of SARS-CORONAVIRUS-2 RNA in sewage and correlation with reported COVID-19 prevalence in the early stage of the epidemic in the Netherlands. Environmental Science and Technology Letters. 2020;7(7):511–516. doi: 10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37566285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merhi G, Koweyes J, Salloum T, Khoury CA, Haidar S, Tokajian S. SARS-CoV-2 genomic epidemiology: Data and sequencing infrastructure. Future Microbiology. 2022;17:1001–1007. doi: 10.2217/fmb-2021-0207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2217/fmb-2021-0207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9332909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35899481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Henquell C, Archimbaud C, Chambon M, Charbonne F, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Bailly JL. Prospective identification of enteroviruses involved in meningitis in 2006 through direct genotyping in cerebrospinal fluid. Journal of Clinical Microbiology. 2008;46(1):87–96. doi: 10.1128/JCM.01020-07.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01020-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2224282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17977989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyah Y, Benjelloun M, Lairini S, Lahrichi A. COVID-19 impact on public health, environment, human psychology, global socioeconomy, and education. The Scientific World Journal. 2022 doi: 10.1155/2022/5578284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/5578284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35069037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molteni E, Sudre CH, Canas LS, Bhopal SS, Hughes RC, Antonelli M, Murray B, Kläser K, Kerfoot E, Chen L, Deng J, Hu C, Selvachandran S, Read K, Capdevila Pujol J, Hammers A, Spector TD, Ourselin S, Steves CJ, Modat M, Absoud M, Duncan EL. Illness duration and symptom profile in symptomatic UK school-aged children tested for SARS-CoV-2. El.lancet Child and Adolescent Health. 2021;5(10):708–718. doi: 10.1016/S2352-4642(21)00198-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(21)00198-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8443448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34358472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikonov OS, Chernykh ES, Garber MB, Nikonova EY. Enteroviruses: classification, diseases they cause, and approaches to development of antiviral drugs. Biochemistry (moscow) 2017;82(13):1615–1631. doi: 10.1134/S0006297917130041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1134/S0006297917130041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7087576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29523062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Othman I, Mirand A, Slama I, Mastouri M, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Aouni M, Bailly JL. Enterovirus migration patterns between France and Tunisia. PLoS ONE. 2015 doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0145674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4692522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26709514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Othman I, Volle R, Elargoubi A, Guediche MN, Chakroun M, Sfar MT, Pereira B, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Aouni M, Archimbaud C, Bailly JL. Enterovirus meningitis in Tunisia (Monastir, Mahdia, 2011–2013): Identification of virus variants recirculating in France. Diagnostic Microbiology and Infectious Diseases. 2016;84(2):116–122. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.10.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.10.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26643063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrinelli L, Galli C, Binda S, Primache V, Tagliacarne C, Pizza F, Mazzini R, Pariani E, Romanò L. Molecular characterization and phylogenetic analysis of enteroviruses and hepatitis A virus in sewage samples, Northern Italy, 2016. Food and Environmental Virology. 2019;11(4):393–399. doi: 10.1007/s12560-019-09401-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-019-09401-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31420848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pennino F, Nardone A, Montuori P, Aurino S, Torre I, Battistone A, Delogu R, Buttinelli G, Fiore S, Amato C, Triassi M. Large-scale survey of human enteroviruses in wastewater treatment plants of a metropolitan area of Southern Italy. Food and Environmental Virology. 2017;10(2):187–192. doi: 10.1007/s12560-017-9331-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-017-9331-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29248990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prévost B, Lucas FS, Goncalves A, Richard F, Moulin L, Wurlitzer S. A large-scale survey of enteric viruses in the river and wastewater underlines the health status of the local population. Environment International. 2015;79:42–50. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2015.03.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2015.03.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25795193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Y, Lee BE, Neumann N, Ashbolt N, Craik S, Maal-Bared R, Pang XL. Assessment of human virus removal during municipal wastewater treatment in Edmonton Canada. Journal of Applied Microbiology. 2015;119(6):1729–1739. doi: 10.1111/jam.12971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.12971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26473649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajtar B, Majek M, Polański Ł, Polz-Dacewicz M. Enteroviruses in the water environment—a potential threat to public health. Annals of Agricultural and Environmental Medicine. 2008;15(2):199–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19061255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen H. Recombination analysis of Coxsackievirus B5 genogroup C. Archives of Virology. 2018;163(2):539–544. doi: 10.1007/s00705-017-3608-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-017-3608-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29134337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabari P, Amini M, Moghadami M, Moosavi M. International public health responses to COVID-19 Outbreak: A rapid review. Iranian Journal of Medical Sciences. 2020;45(3):157–169. doi: 10.30476/ijms.2020.85810.1537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30476/ijms.2020.85810.1537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7253494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32546882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C, Siegrist F, Petty Tom J. Laurent Kaiser Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity associated with human diseases. Infection Genetics and Evolution. 2013;14:282–293. doi: 10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23201849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C, Siegrist F, Petty Tom J. Laurent Kaiser Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity with associated human diseases. Infection Genetics and Evolution. 2013;14:282–293. doi: 10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23201849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toledo DM, Robbins AA, Gallagher TL, Hershberger KC, Barney RE, Salmela SM, Pilcher D, Cervinski MA, Nerenz RD, Szczepiorkowski ZM, Tsongalis GJ, Lefferts JA, Martin IW, Hubbard J, A, Wastewater-based SARS-CoV-2 surveillance in Northern New England. Microbiology Spectru. 2022 doi: 10.1128/spectrum.02207-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02207-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9045146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35412387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong K, Mukherjee B, Kahler AM, Zeep R, Molina M. Influence of inorganic ions on aggregation and adsorption behaviors of human Adenovirus. Environmental Science and Technology. 2012;46(20):11145–11153. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.9b05993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.9b05993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22950445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) situation report - 1 21 january 2020. WHO Bull. 2020:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. COVID-19 weekly epidemiological update, edition 78, 8 February 2022, World Health Organization (2022). www.who.int/publications/m/item/weekly-epidemiological-update-on-covid-19---8-february-2022 Situation report on SARS-CoV-2 by region.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Zhao S, Yu B, Chen YM, Wang W, Song ZG, Hu Y, Tao ZW, Tian JH, Pei YY, Yuan ML, Zhang YL, Dai FH, Liu Y, Wang QM, Zheng JJ, Xu L, Holmes EC, Zhang YZ. A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China. Nature. 2020;579:265–269. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W, Liao Q, Viboud C, Zhang J, Sun J, Wu TJ, Chang Z, Liu FJ, Fang VJ, Zheng Y, Cowling BJ, Varma JK, Farrar JJ, Leung GM, Yu H. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008–12: An epidemiological study. Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2014;14(4):308–318. doi: 10.14016/S1473-3099(13)70342-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14016/S1473-3099(13)70342-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4035015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24485991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarza E, Diego-García E, García LV, Castro R, Mejía G, Herrera D, Cuevas R, Palomeque Á, Iša P, Guillén K. Monitoring SARS-CoV-2 in the wastewater and rivers of tapachula, a migratory hub in Southern Mexico. Food and Environmental Virology. 2022 doi: 10.1007/s12560-022-09523-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-022-09523-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9067545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35508751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Ji, Xiaochang CW, Limei Xu, Zhang C, Funamizu N, Okabe S, Sano D. Estimation of contamination sources of human enteroviruses in wastewater treatment and reclamation system by PCR-DGGE. Food and Environmental ViroLogy. 2014;6(2):99–109. doi: 10.1007/s12560-014-9140-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-014-9140-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24715657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W, Li X, Yang B, Song J, Zhao X, Huang B, Shi W, Lu R. A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019. The New England Journal of Medicine. 2020;382(8):727–733. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2001017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2001017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>