<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37132155</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2701-0198</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Biol (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Natural Oncolysis of Enterovirus 71 in Antitumor Therapy of Colorectal Cancer.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2200336</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2200336</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/adbi.202200336</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is an intestinal malignant tumor with high morbidity and mortality worldwide. Inoperability or resistanance to radiation and chemotherapy occur in the conventional treatments against CRC. Oncolytic viruses (OVs) are one kind of virus that selectively infects and lyses cancer cells, which is considered to be a new anticancer therapy with biological and immune-based approaches. Enterovirus 71 (EV71), belonging to the enterovirus genus in the family Picornaviridae, is a single positive-stranded RNA virus. EV71 is transmitted in a fetal-oral route and infects gastrointestinal tract in infants. Here, EV71 is exploited to be a novel oncolytic virus in colorectal cancer. It is revealed that EV71 infection can selectively cause colorectal cancer cells cytotoxicity but not primary intestinal epithelial cells. Consistently, EV71 injection significantly inhibits tumor growth in nude mice xenografted colorectal cancer cells. In detail, EV71 infects colorectal cancer cells to repress the expression of Ki67 and B-cell leukemia 2 (Bcl-2) leading to the inhibition of cell proliferation, while activating the cleavage of poly-adenosine diphosphatase-ribose polymerase and Caspase-3 protein resulting in the promotion of cell apoptosis. The findings demonstrate the oncolytic feature of EV71 in CRC treatment and may provide a potential clue for clinical anticancer therapy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruan</LastName><ForeName>Zhihui</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Foshan Institute of Medical Microbiology, Foshan, 528315, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chi</LastName><ForeName>Jiangyang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiovascular Surgery, Union Hospital, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, 430022, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kong</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, College of Basic Medicine and Public Hygiene, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Chengcheng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruan</LastName><ForeName>Xiaolan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Xing</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yanxi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yongkui</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Foshan Institute of Medical Microbiology, Foshan, 528315, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1142-2845</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Foshan Institute of Medical Microbiology, Foshan, 528315, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Biol (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101775319</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2701-0198</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008819" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice, Nude</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D050504" MajorTopicYN="Y">Oncolytic Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015179" MajorTopicYN="Y">Colorectal Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus 71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anticancer therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cell apoptosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">colorectal cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oncolytic virus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37132155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adbi.202200336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>H. Sung, J. Ferlay, R. L. Siegel, M. Laversanne, I. Soerjomataram, A. Jemal, F. Bray, Ca-Cancer J. Clin. 2021, 71, 209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Dekker, P. J. Tanis, J. L. A. Vleugels, P. M. Kasi, M. B. Wallace, Lancet 2019, 394, 1467.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Buccafusca, I. Proserpio, A. C. Tralongo, S. Rametta Giuliano, P. Tralongo, Crit. Rev. Oncol. Hematol. 2019, 136, 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Robinson, M. M. Xu, S. K. Nair, G. M. Beasley, K. E. Rhodin, Front. Biosci.-Landmark 2022, 27, 063.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. M. Chan, G. Mcfadden, Annu. Rev. Virol. 2014, 1, 191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. J. Russell, K.-W. Peng, J. C. Bell, Nat. Biotechnol. 2012, 30, 658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Melcher, K. Parato, C. M. Rooney, J. C. Bell, Mol. Ther. 2011, 19, 1008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Ressler, M. Karasek, L. Koch, R. Silmbrod, J. Mangana, S. Latifyan, V. Aedo-Lopez, H. Kehrer, F. Weihsengruber, P. Koelblinger, C. Posch, J. Kofler, O. Michielin, E. Richtig, C. Hafner, C. Hoeller, J. Immunother. Cancer 2021, 9, e001701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Dummer, D. E. Gyorki, J. Hyngstrom, A. C. Berger, R. Conry, L. Demidov, A. Sharma, S. A. Treichel, H. Radcliffe, K. S. Gorski, A. Anderson, E. Chan, M. Faries, M. I. Ross, Nat. Med. 2021, 27, 1789.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. L. Kaufman, F. J. Kohlhapp, A. Zloza, Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery 2015, 14, 642.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. McCarthy, N. Jayawardena, L. N. Burga, M. Bostina, Cancers (Basel) 2019, 11, 685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Solomon, P. Lewthwaite, D. Perera, M. J. Cardosa, P. Mcminn, M. H. Ooi, Lancet Infect. Dis. 2010, 10, 778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhang, H. Wang, Y. Sun, M. Qi, W. Li, Z. Zhang, X.-E. Zhang, Z. Cui, Mol. Ther. 2020, 28, 1533.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Yamayoshi, K. Fujii, S. Koike, Emerging Microbes Infect. 2014, 3, e53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Miller, A. Oleksy, O. Perisic, R. L. Williams, Autophagy 2010, 6, 805.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. P. Friedmann Angeli, M. Schneider, B. Proneth, Y. Y. Tyurina, V. A. Tyurin, V. J. Hammond, N. Herbach, M. Aichler, A. Walch, E. Eggenhofer, D. Basavarajappa, O. Rådmark, S. Kobayashi, T. Seibt, H. Beck, F. Neff, I. Esposito, R. Wanke, H. Förster, O. Yefremova, M. Heinrichmeyer, G. W. Bornkamm, E. K. Geissler, S. B. Thomas, B. R. Stockwell, V. B. O'Donnell, V. E. Kagan, J. A. Schick, M. Conrad, Nat. Cell Biol. 2014, 16, 1180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Kanthasamy, V. Anantharam, D. Zhang, C. Latchoumycandane, H. Jin, S. Kaul, A. Kanthasamy, Free Radical Biol. Med. 2006, 41, 1578.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. W. Davies, J. Chaney, G. Korbel, D. Ringe, G. A. Petsko, H. Ploegh, C. Das, Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 2012, 22, 3900.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. T. Li, G. Jiang, Q. Chen, J. N. Zheng, Mol. Med. Rep. 2015, 11, 1566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Tsujimoto, Prog. Mol. Subcell. Biol. 1996, 16, 72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Pascal, DNA Repair 2018, 71, 177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Porter, R. U. Jänicke, Cell Death Differ. 1999, 6, 99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Vodenkova, T. Buchler, K. Cervena, V. Veskrnova, P. Vodicka, V. Vymetalkova, Pharmacol. Ther. 2020, 206, 107447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. L. Kaufman, F. J. Kohlhapp, A. Zloza, Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery 2016, 15, 660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. R. Jhawar, A. Thandoni, P. K. Bommareddy, S. Hassan, F. J. Kohlhapp, S. Goyal, J. M. Schenkel, A. W. Silk, A. Zloza, Front. Oncol. 2017, 7, 202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. H. t. Stewart, M. Ahmed, S. A. Northrup, M. Willingham, D. S. Lyles, Cancer Gene Ther. 2011, 18, 837.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Song, L.-P. Zhong, J. He, Y. Huang, Y.-X. Zhao, World J. Clin. Cases 2019, 7, 2143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. K. Geevarghese, D. A. Geller, H. A. De Haan, M. Hörer, A. E. Knoll, A. Mescheder, J. Nemunaitis, T. R. Reid, D. Y. Sze, K. K. Tanabe, H. Tawfik, Hum. Gene Ther. 2010, 21, 1119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Errington, L. Steele, R. Prestwich, K. J. Harrington, H. S. Pandha, L. Vidal, J. De Bono, P. Selby, M. Coffey, R. Vile, A. Melcher, J. Immunol. 2008, 180, 6018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Jiffry, T. Thavornwatanayong, D. Rao, E. J. Fogel, D. Saytoo, R. Nahata, H. Guzik, I. Chaudhary, T. Augustine, S. Goel, R. Maitra, Clin. Cancer Res. 2021, 27, 865.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. K. Bommareddy, M. Shettigar, H. L. Kaufman, Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2018, 18, 498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Song, X. Yu, T. Zhong, Z. Wang, X. Meng, Z. Li, S. Zhang, W. Huo, X. Liu, Y. Zhang, W. Zhang, J. Yu, Front. Microbiol. 2018, 9, 817.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Critchley-Thorne, D. L. Simons, N. Yan, A. K. Miyahira, F. M. Dirbas, D. L. Johnson, S. M. Swetter, R. W. Carlson, G. A. Fisher, A. Koong, S. Holmes, P. P. Lee, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2009, 106, 9010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Packiriswamy, D. Upreti, Y. Zhou, R. Khan, A. Miller, R. M. Diaz, C. M. Rooney, A. Dispenzieri, K.-W. Peng, S. J. Russell, Leukemia 2020, 34, 3310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Ma, T. Lu, Z. Li, K.-Y. Teng, A. G. Mansour, M. Yu, L. Tian, B. Xu, S. Ma, J. Zhang, T. Barr, Y. Peng, M. A. Caligiuri, J. Yu, Cancer Res. 2021, 81, 3635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. I. Kana, K. Essani, Mol. Diagn. Ther. 2021, 25, 301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Ylösmäki, V. Cerullo, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2020, 65, 25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Wang, X. Kang, K. S. Chen, T. Jehng, L. Jones, J. Chen, X. F. Huang, S.-Y. Chen, Nat. Commun. 2020, 11, 1395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Zuo, M. Wei, T. Xu, L. Kong, B. He, S. Wang, S. Wang, J. Wu, J. Dong, J. Wei, J. Immunother. Cancer 2021, 9, e002843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhu, W. Xu, J. Xia, Z. Liang, Y. Liu, X. Zhang, X. Tan, L. Wang, Q. Mao, J. Wu, Y. Hu, T. Ji, L. Song, Q. Liang, B. Zhang, Q. Gao, J. Li, S. Wang, Y. Hu, S. Gu, J. Zhang, G. Yao, J. Gu, X. Wang, Y. Zhou, C. Chen, M. Zhang, M. Cao, J. Wang, H. Wang, N. Wang, N. Engl. J. Med. 2014, 370, 818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Ricca, A. Oseledchyk, T. Walther, C. Liu, L. Mangarin, T. Merghoub, J. D. Wolchok, D. Zamarin, Mol. Ther. 2018, 26, 1008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Tähtinen, S. Feola, C. Capasso, N. Laustio, C. Groeneveldt, E. O. Ylösmäki, L. Ylösmäki, B. Martins, M. Fusciello, M. Medeot, M. Tagliamonte, J. Chiaro, F. Hamdan, K. Peltonen, T. Ranki, L. Buonaguro, V. Cerullo, Cancer Res. 2020, 80, 2575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. J. Ilett, R. J. Prestwich, T. Kottke, F. Errington, J. M. Thompson, K. J. Harrington, H. S. Pandha, M. Coffey, P. J. Selby, R. G. Vile, A. A. Melcher, Gene Ther. 2009, 16, 689.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Luo, X. Dong, Y. Li, Q. Zhang, C. Kim, Y. Song, L. Kang, Y. Liu, K. Wu, J. Wu, PLoS One 2014, 9, e87491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Pan, M. Shen, Z. Yu, W. Ge, K. Chen, M. Tian, F. Xiao, Z. Wang, J. Wang, Y. Jia, W. Wang, P. Wan, J. Zhang, W. Chen, Z. Lei, X. Chen, Z. Luo, Q. Zhang, M. Xu, G. Li, Y. Li, J. Wu, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 4664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Huang, Z. Liu, J. Hu, Z. Luo, C. Zhang, L. Wang, Z. Wang, Pharmacol. Res. 2020, 156, 104774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Luo, R. Su, W. Wang, Y. Liang, X. Zeng, M. A. Shereen, N. Bashir, Q. Zhang, L. Zhao, K. Wu, Y. Liu, J. Wu, PLoS Pathog. 2019, 15, e1008142.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>