<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37154751</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5514</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>97</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Telaprevir Treatment Reduces Paralysis in a Mouse Model of Enterovirus D68 Acute Flaccid Myelitis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0015623</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0015623</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00156-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/jvi.00156-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In 2014, 2016, and 2018, the United States experienced unprecedented spikes in pediatric cases of acute flaccid myelitis (AFM), which is a poliomyelitis-like paralytic illness. Accumulating clinical, immunological, and epidemiological evidence has identified enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) as a major causative agent of these biennial AFM outbreaks. There are currently no available FDA-approved antivirals that are effective against EV-D68, and the treatment for EV-D68-associated AFM is primarily supportive. Telaprevir is an food and drug administration (FDA)-approved protease inhibitor that irreversibly binds the EV-D68 2A protease and inhibits EV-D68 replication <i>in vitro</i>. Here, we utilize a murine model of EV-D68 associated AFM to show that early telaprevir treatment improves paralysis outcomes in Swiss Webster (SW) mice. Telaprevir reduces both viral titer and apoptotic activity in both muscles and spinal cords at early disease time points, which results in improved AFM outcomes in infected mice. Following intramuscular inoculation in mice, EV-D68 infection results in a stereotypic pattern of weakness that is reflected by the loss of the innervating motor neuron population, in sequential order, of the ipsilateral (injected) hindlimb, the contralateral hindlimb, and then the forelimbs. Telaprevir treatment preserved motor neuron populations and reduced weakness in limbs beyond the injected hindlimb. The effects of telaprevir were not seen when the treatment was delayed, and toxicity limited doses beyond 35 mg/kg. These studies are a proof of principle, provide the first evidence of benefit of an FDA-approved antiviral drug with which to treat AFM, and emphasize both the need to develop better tolerated therapies that remain efficacious when administered after viral infections and the development of clinical symptoms. <b>IMPORTANCE</b> Recent outbreaks of EV-D68 in 2014, 2016, and 2018 have resulted in over 600 cases of a paralytic illness that is known as AFM. AFM is a predominantly pediatric disease with no FDA-approved treatment, and many patients show minimal recovery from limb weakness. Telaprevir is an FDA-approved antiviral that has been shown to inhibit EV-D68 <i>in vitro</i>. Here, we demonstrate that a telaprevir treatment that is given concurrently with an EV-D68 infection improves AFM outcomes in mice by reducing apoptosis and viral titers at early time points. Telaprevir also protected motor neurons and improved paralysis outcomes in limbs beyond the site of viral inoculation. This study improves understanding of EV-D68 pathogenesis in the mouse model of AFM. This study serves as a proof of principle for the first FDA-approved drug that has been shown to improve AFM outcomes and have <i>in vivo</i> efficacy against EV-D68 as well as underlines the importance of the continued development of EV-D68 antivirals.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frost</LastName><ForeName>Joshua</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6517-4966</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology &amp; Microbiology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rudy</LastName><ForeName>Michael J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leser</LastName><ForeName>J Smith</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Haozhou</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Ernest Mario School of Pharmacy, Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, Piscataway, New Jersey, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Yanmei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Ernest Mario School of Pharmacy, Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, Piscataway, New Jersey, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4845-4621</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Ernest Mario School of Pharmacy, Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, Piscataway, New Jersey, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Clarke</LastName><ForeName>Penny</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5540-2910</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tyler</LastName><ForeName>Kenneth L</ForeName><Initials>KL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3294-5888</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology &amp; Microbiology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology Service, Rocky Mountain VA Medical Center, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI157046</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 NS101208</GrantID><Acronym>NS</Acronym><Agency>NINDS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI147325</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI158775</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI179926</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0113724</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-538X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>655M5O3W0U</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C486464">telaprevir</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000998">Antiviral Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C000629404">acute flaccid myelitis</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030016" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus D, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004195" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Models, Animal</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010243" MajorTopicYN="N">Paralysis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020805" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Viral Diseases</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000998" MajorTopicYN="N">Antiviral Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EV-D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute flaccid myelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">paralysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telaprevir</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">treatment</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37154751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10231134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.00156-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Schieble JH, Fox VL, Lennette EH. 1967. A probable new human picornavirus associated with respiratory diseases. Am J Epidemiol 85:297–310. doi:10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a120693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a120693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4960233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Lamonte-Fowlkes A, Oberst S, Pallansch MA. 2006. C. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, enterovirus surveillance–United States, 1970–2005. MMWR Surveill Summ 55:1–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16971890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown BA, Nix WA, Sheth M, Frace M, Oberste MS. 2014. Seven strains of enterovirus D68 Detected in the United States during the 2014 severe respiratory disease outbreak. Genome Announc 2. doi:10.1128/genomeA.01201-14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/genomeA.01201-14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4239358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25414503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley CM, Jackson MA, Selvarangan R, Turabelidze G, Obringer E, Johnson D, Giles BL, Patel A, Echols F, Oberste MS, et al.. 2014. Severe respiratory illness associated with enterovirus D68 - Missouri and Illinois, 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 63:798–799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25211545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley CM, Watson JT, Nix WA, Curns AT, Rogers SL, Brown BA, Conover C, Dominguez SR, Feikin DR, Gray S, Hassan F, Hoferka S, Jackson MA, Johnson D, Leshem E, Miller L, Nichols JB, Nyquist A-C, Obringer E, Patel A, Patel M, Rha B, Schneider E, Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Seward JF, Turabelidze G, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA, Gerber SI, EV-D68 Working Group . 2015. Severe respiratory illness associated with a nationwide outbreak of enterovirus D68 in the USA (2014): a descriptive epidemiological investigation. Lancet Respir Med 3:879–887. doi:10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00335-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00335-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5693332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26482320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oermann CM, Schuster JE, Conners GP, Newland JG, Selvarangan R, Jackson MA. 2015. Enterovirus d68. A focused review and clinical highlights from the 2014 U.S. outbreak. Ann Am Thorac Soc 12:775–781. doi:10.1513/AnnalsATS.201412-592FR.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201412-592FR</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25714788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute Flaccid Myelitis (AFM). 2021. Available from: https://ndc.services.cdc.gov/case-definitions/acute-flaccid-myelitis-2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Acute flaccid myelitis - AFM confirmed U.S. cases. 2019. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/acute-flaccid-myelitis/afm-cases.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Frost J, Rudy MJ, Messacar K, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2019. Understanding enterovirus D68-induced neurologic disease: a basic science review. Viruses 11:821. doi:10.3390/v11090821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v11090821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6783995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31487952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastula DM, Aliabadi N, Haynes AK, Messacar K, Schreiner T, Maloney J, Dominguez SR, Davizon ES, Leshem E, Fischer M, et al.. 2014. Acute neurologic illness of unknown etiology in children - Colorado, August–September 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 63:901–902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25299607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sejvar JJ, Lopez AS, Cortese MM, Leshem E, Pastula DM, Miller L, Glaser C, Kambhampati A, Shioda K, Aliabadi N, Fischer M, Gregoricus N, Lanciotti R, Nix WA, Sakthivel SK, Schmid DS, Seward JF, Tong S, Oberste MS, Pallansch M, Feikin D. 2016. Acute flaccid myelitis in the United States, August-December 2014: results of nationwide surveillance. Clin Infect Dis 63:737–745. doi:10.1093/cid/ciw372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciw372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5709818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27318332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra N, Ng TFF, Marine RL, Jain K, Ng J, Thakkar R, Caciula A, Price A, Garcia JA, Burns JC, Thakur KT, Hetzler KL, Routh JA, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Nix WA, Tokarz R, Briese T, Oberste MS, Lipkin WI. 2019. Antibodies to enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid of patients with acute flaccid myelitis. mBio 10. doi:10.1128/mBio.01903-19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.01903-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6692520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31409689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schubert RD, Hawes IA, Ramachandran PS, Ramesh A, Crawford ED, Pak JE, Wu W, Cheung CK, O'Donovan BD, Tato CM, Lyden A, Tan M, Sit R, Sowa GM, Sample HA, Zorn KC, Banerji D, Khan LM, Bove R, Hauser SL, Gelfand AA, Johnson-Kerner BL, Nash K, Krishnamoorthy KS, Chitnis T, Ding JZ, McMillan HJ, Chiu CY, Briggs B, Glaser CA, Yen C, Chu V, Wadford DA, Dominguez SR, Ng TFF, Marine RL, Lopez AS, Nix WA, Soldatos A, Gorman MP, Benson L, Messacar K, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Oberste MS, DeRisi JL, Wilson MR. 2019. Pan-viral serology implicates enteroviruses in acute flaccid myelitis. Nat Med 25:1748–1752. doi:10.1038/s41591-019-0613-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-019-0613-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6858576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31636453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogt MR, Wright PF, Hickey WF, De Buysscher T, Boyd KL, Crowe JE, Jr.. 2022. Enterovirus D68 in the anterior horn cells of a child with acute flaccid myelitis. N Engl J Med 386:2059–2060. doi:10.1056/NEJMc2118155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2118155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9321432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35613028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah MM, Perez A, Lively JY, Avadhanula V, Boom JA, Chappell J, Englund JA, Fregoe W, Halasa NB, Harrison CJ, Hickey RW, Klein EJ, McNeal MM, Michaels MG, Moffatt ME, Otten C, Sahni LC, Schlaudecker E, Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Staat MA, Stewart LS, Weinberg GA, Williams JV, Ng TFF, Routh JA, Gerber SI, McMorrow ML, Rha B, Midgley CM. 2021. Enterovirus D68-associated acute respiratory illness – New Vaccine Surveillance Network, United States, July–November 2018–2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 70:1623–1628. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7047a1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7047a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8612514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34818320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kidd S, Yee E, English R, Rogers S, Emery B, Getachew H, Routh JA, Lopez AS. 2021. National surveillance for acute flaccid myelitis — United States, 2018–2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 70:1534–1538. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7044a2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7044a2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8568096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34735423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirolos A, Mark K, Shetty J, Chinchankar N, McDougall C, Eunson P, Stevenson J, Templeton K. and N.H.S.L.E.-D.A.A.S. Group. 2019. Outcome of paediatric acute flaccid myelitis associated with enterovirus D68: a case series. Dev Med Child Neurol 61:376–380. doi:10.1111/dmcn.14096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dmcn.14096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30417347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin JA, Messacar K, Yang ML, Maloney JA, Lindwall J, Carry T, Kenyon P, Sillau SH, Oleszek J, Tyler KL, Dominguez SR, Schreiner TL. 2017. Outcomes of Colorado children with acute flaccid myelitis at 1 year. Neurology 89:129–137. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000004081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5501931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28615421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yea C, Bitnun A, Robinson J, Mineyko A, Barton M, Mah JK, Vajsar J, Richardson S, Licht C, Brophy J, Crone M, Desai S, Hukin J, Jones K, Muir K, Pernica JM, Pless R, Pohl D, Rafay MF, Selby K, Venkateswaran S, Bernard G, Yeh EA. 2017. Longitudinal outcomes in the 2014 acute flaccid paralysis cluster in Canada. J Child Neurol 32:301–307. doi:10.1177/0883073816680770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0883073816680770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28193112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Musharrafieh R, Zheng M, Wang J. 2020. Enterovirus D68 antivirals: past, present, and future. ACS Infect Dis 6:1572–1586. doi:10.1021/acsinfecdis.0c00120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsinfecdis.0c00120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8055446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32352280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurst BL, Evans WJ, Smee DF, Van Wettere AJ, Tarbet EB. 2019. Evaluation of antiviral therapies in respiratory and neurological disease models of Enterovirus D68 infection in mice. Virology 526:146–154. doi:10.1016/j.virol.2018.10.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2018.10.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6309259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30390563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Yu G, Leser JS, Yagi S, Clarke P, Chiu CY, Tyler KL. 2017. A mouse model of paralytic myelitis caused by enterovirus D68. PLoS Pathog 13:e1006199. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1006199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5322875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28231269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2019. Contemporary circulating enterovirus D68 strains infect and undergo retrograde axonal transport in spinal motor neurons independent of sialic acid. J Virol 93. doi:10.1128/JVI.00578-19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00578-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6675884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31167912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2017. Evaluating treatment efficacy in a mouse model of enterovirus D68-associated paralytic myelitis. J Infect Dis 216:1245–1253. doi:10.1093/infdis/jix468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jix468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5853295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28968718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telaprevir. 2007. Available from: https://go.drugbank.com/drugs/DB05521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musharrafieh R, Ma C, Zhang J, Hu Y, Diesing JM, Marty MT, Wang J. 2019. Validating enterovirus D68-2A(pro) as an antiviral drug target and the discovery of telaprevir as a potent D68-2A(pro) inhibitor. J Virol 93:e02221-18. doi:10.1128/JVI.02221-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.02221-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6430540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30674624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perni RB, Almquist SJ, Byrn RA, Chandorkar G, Chaturvedi PR, Courtney LF, Decker CJ, Dinehart K, Gates CA, Harbeson SL, Heiser A, Kalkeri G, Kolaczkowski E, Lin K, Luong Y-P, Rao BG, Taylor WP, Thomson JA, Tung RD, Wei Y, Kwong AD, Lin C. 2006. Preclinical profile of VX-950, a potent, selective, and orally bioavailable inhibitor of hepatitis C virus NS3-4A serine protease. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 50:899–909. doi:10.1128/AAC.50.3.899-909.2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AAC.50.3.899-909.2006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1426435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16495249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Zhang X, Dai W, Liu Q, Xiong P, Wang S, Geng L, Gong S, Huang Z. 2018. A mouse model of enterovirus D68 infection for assessment of the efficacy of inactivated vaccine. Viruses 10:58. doi:10.3390/v10020058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v10020058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29385753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gromeier M, Wimmer E. 1998. Mechanism of injury-provoked poliomyelitis. J Virol 72:5056–5060. doi:10.1128/JVI.72.6.5056-5060.1998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.72.6.5056-5060.1998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC110068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9573275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstaub D, Gradi A, Bercovitch Z, Grosmann Z, Nophar Y, Luria S, Sonenberg N, Kahana C. 2000. Poliovirus 2A protease induces apoptotic cell death. Mol Cell Biol 20:1271–1277. doi:10.1128/MCB.20.4.1271-1277.2000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/MCB.20.4.1271-1277.2000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC85262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10648613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo RL, Kung SH, Hsu YY, Liu WT. 2002. Infection with enterovirus 71 or expression of its 2A protease induces apoptotic cell death. J Gen Virol 83:1367–1376. doi:10.1099/0022-1317-83-6-1367.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-83-6-1367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12029152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Nervous System. SecondLook. Available from: https://histology.medicine.umich.edu/resources/central-nervous-system#i-spinal-cord.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walpole SC, Prieto-Merino D, Edwards P, Cleland J, Stevens G, Roberts I. 2012. The weight of nations: an estimation of adult human biomass. BMC Public Health 12:439. doi:10.1186/1471-2458-12-439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3408371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22709383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wylie TN, Wylie KM, Buller RS, Cannella M, Storch GA. 2015. Development and evaluation of an enterovirus D68 real-time reverse transcriptase PCR assay. J Clin Microbiol 53:2641–2647. doi:10.1128/JCM.00923-15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00923-15</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4508392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26063859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>