<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37170790</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>06</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1468-1331</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>30</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European journal of neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur J Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of acute flaccid myelitis and transverse myelitis in children and evaluation of diagnostic criteria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2430</StartPage><EndPage>2441</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2430-2441</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/ene.15861</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND PURPOSE">Acute flaccid myelitis (AFM) and transverse myelitis (TM) are serious conditions that may be difficult to differentiate, especially at onset of disease. In this study, we compared clinical features of pediatric AFM and TM and evaluated current diagnostic criteria, aiming to improve early and accurate diagnosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">Two cohorts of children with enterovirus D68-associated AFM and clinically diagnosed TM were compared regarding presenting clinical features, additional investigations, and outcome. Current diagnostic criteria for AFM and TM were applied to evaluate their specificity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Children with AFM (n = 21) compared to those with TM (n = 36) were younger (median 3 vs. 10 years), more often had a prodromal illness (100% vs. 39%), predominant proximal weakness (69% vs. 17%), and hyporeflexia (100% vs. 44%), and less often had sensory deficits (0% vs. 81%), bowel and/or bladder dysfunction (12% vs. 69%), and hyperreflexia (0% vs. 44%). On magnetic resonance imaging, brainstem involvement was more common in AFM (74% vs. 21%), whereas supratentorial abnormalities were only seen in TM (0% vs. 40%). When omitting the criterion of a sensory level, 11 of 15 (73%) children with AFM fulfilled the diagnostic criteria for TM. Of children with TM, four of 33 (12%) fulfilled the diagnostic criteria for probable/definite AFM.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Although there is considerable overlap between AFM and TM in children, we found important early differentiating clinical and diagnostic features. Meeting diagnostic criteria for AFM in children with TM and vice versa underlines the importance of thorough clinical examination and early and accurate diagnostic studies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors. European Journal of Neurology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of European Academy of Neurology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Helfferich</LastName><ForeName>Jelte</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4022-6162</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bruijstens</LastName><ForeName>Arlette L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7990-5894</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knoester</LastName><ForeName>Marjolein</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology and Infection Prevention, University Medical Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brouwer</LastName><ForeName>Oebele F</ForeName><Initials>OF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Neuteboom</LastName><ForeName>Rinze F</ForeName><Initials>RF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, Erasmus University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>2016 Enterovirus D68 Acute Flaccid Myelitis Working Group and the Dutch Study Group for Pediatric Multiple Sclerosis and Acute Disseminated Encephalomyelitis</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Eur J Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9506311</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1351-5101</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C000629404">acute flaccid myelitis</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009188" MajorTopicYN="Y">Myelitis, Transverse</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009468" MajorTopicYN="Y">Neuromuscular Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009187" MajorTopicYN="Y">Myelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020805" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Viral Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute flaccid myelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute flaccid paralysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transverse myelitis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37170790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ene.15861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Murphy OC, Messacar K, Benson L, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis: cause, diagnosis, and management. Lancet. 2020;397:334-346. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32723-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knoester M, Helfferich J, Poelman R, et al. Twenty-nine cases of enterovirus-D68-associated acute flaccid myelitis in Europe 2016: a case series and epidemiologic overview. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2019;38(1):16-21. doi:10.1097/INF.0000000000002188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Asturias EJ, Hixon AM, et al. Enterovirus D68 and acute flaccid myelitis-evaluating the evidence for causality. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18:e239-e247. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30094-X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyda A, Stelzer-Braid S, Adam D, Chughtai AA, MacIntyre CR. The association between acute flaccid myelitis (AFM) and enterovirus D68 (EV-D68)-what is the evidence for causation? Euro Surveill. 2018;23(3):17-00310. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.3.17-00310</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Spence-Davizon E, Osborne C, et al. Clinical characteristics of enterovirus A71 neurological disease during an outbreak in children in Colorado, USA, in 2018: an observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20(2):230-239. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30632-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transverse Myelitis Consortium Working Group. Proposed diagnostic criteria and nosology of acute transverse myelitis. Neurology. 2002;59(4):499-505. doi:10.1212/WNL.60.4.730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deiva K, Absoud M, Hemingway C, et al. Acute idiopathic transverse myelitis in children: early predictors of relapse and disability. Neurology. 2015;84(4):341-349. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000001179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Absoud M, Greenberg BM, Lim M, Lotze T, Thomas T, Deiva K. Pediatric transverse myelitis. Neurology. 2016;87(9 Suppl 2):S46-S52. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000002820</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theroux LM, Brenton JN. Acute transverse and flaccid myelitis in children. Curr Treat Options Neurol. 2019;21(12):64. doi:10.1007/s11940-019-0603-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helfferich J, Roodbol J, de Wit M-C, Brouwer OF, Jacobs BC. Acute flaccid myelitis and Guillain-Barré syndrome in children: a comparative study with evaluation of diagnostic criteria. Eur J Neurol. 2022;29(2):593-604. doi:10.1111/ene.15170</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Acute Flaccid Myelitis - Case Definitions. 2021. Accessed August 16, 2022. https://ndc.services.cdc.gov/case-definitions/acute-flaccid-myelitis-2018/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ketelslegers IA, Catsman-Berrevoets CE, Neuteboom RF, et al. Incidence of acquired demyelinating syndromes of the CNS in Dutch children: a nationwide study. J Neurol. 2012;259(9):1929-1935. doi:10.1007/s00415-012-6441-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helfferich J, Bruijstens AL, Wong YYM, van Pelt ED, Boon M, Neuteboom RF. Prognostic factors for relapse and outcome in pediatric acute transverse myelitis. Brain Dev. 2021;43:626-636. doi:10.1016/j.braindev.2020.12.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yiu EM, Kornberg AJ, Ryan MM, Coleman LT, Mackay MT. Acute transverse myelitis and acute disseminated encephalomyelitis in childhood: spectrum or separate entities? J Child Neurol. 2009;24(3):287-296. doi:10.1177/0883073808323522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy OC, Messacar K, Benson L, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis: cause, diagnosis, and management. Lancet (London, England). 2021;397(10271):334-346. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32723-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer P, Leboucq N, Molinari N, et al. Partial acute transverse myelitis is a predictor of multiple sclerosis in children. Mult Scler J. 2014;20(11):1485-1493. doi:10.1177/1352458514526943</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pidcock FS, Salorio CF, Trovato M, Krishnan C, Kerr DA, Crawford TO. Acute transverse myelitis in childhood: center-based analysis of 47 cases. Neurology. 2007;68(18):1474-1480. doi:10.1212/01.wnl.0000260609.11357.6f</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Goede CGEL, Holmes EM, Pike MG. Acquired transverse myelopathy in children in the United Kingdom-a 2 year prospective study. Eur J Paediatr Neurol. 2010;14(6):479-487. doi:10.1016/j.ejpn.2009.12.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Schreiner TL, Van HK, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis: a clinical review of US cases 2012-2015. Ann Neurol. 2016;80(3):326-338. doi:10.1002/ana.24730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chong PF, Kira R, Mori H, et al. Clinical features of acute flaccid myelitis temporally associated with an enterovirus D68 outbreak: results of a nationwide survey of acute flaccid paralysis in Japan, August-December 2015. Clin Infect Dis. 2018;66(5):653-664. doi:10.1093/cid/cix860</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg B, Plumb P, Cutter G, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis: long-term outcomes recorded in the CAPTURE study compared with paediatric transverse myelitis. BMJ Neurol Open. 2021;3(1):e000127. doi:10.1136/bmjno-2021-000127</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elrick MJ, Gordon-Lipkin E, Crawford TO, et al. Clinical subpopulations in a sample of North American children diagnosed with acute flaccid myelitis, 2012-2016. JAMA Pediatr. 2019;173(2):134-139. doi:10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.4890</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. Evaluating treatment efficacy in a mouse model of enterovirus D68-associated paralytic myelitis. J Infect Dis. 2017;216(10):1245-1253. doi:10.1093/infdis/jix468</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin JA, Messacar K, Yang ML, et al. Outcomes of Colorado children with acute flaccid myelitis at 1 year. Neurology. 2017;89(2):129-137. doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000004081</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer TK, Simmonds P, Harvala H. The importance of enterovirus surveillance in a post-polio world. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):e35-e40. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30852-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackburn KM, Greenberg BM. Revisiting transverse myelitis: moving toward a new nomenclature. Front Neurol. 2020;11:519468. doi:10.3389/fneur.2020.519468</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>