<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37131936</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>101</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Poliovirus surveillance in patients with primary immunodeficiencies, India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>346</StartPage><EndPage>354</EndPage><MedlinePgn>346-354</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.22.289066</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Individuals with primary immunodeficiencies who are infected with vaccine-derived polioviruses may continue to shed poliovirus for months and go undetected by surveillance programmes of acute flaccid paralysis. These patients therefore pose a risk of initiating poliovirus outbreaks that jeopardize efforts towards global polio eradication. To identify these individuals, we designed a study protocol for the establishment of a network for surveillance of immunodeficiency-related vaccine-derived poliovirus in India. In the first step we identified recognized centres in India that could diagnose and enrol patients with primary immunodeficiency disorder into the study. Stool sample collection from study sites, culture, isolation, characterization of enteroviruses and reporting to study sites was carried out at the National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, as per the WHO national polio surveillance project protocol. In the first phase of the study from January 2020 to December 2021, we implemented the protocol at seven study sites at different medical institutes to determine the proportion of poliovirus infections in primary immunodeficiency disorder patients of India. We later expanded the study by including an additional 14 medical institutes across the country in the second phase running from January 2022 to December 2023. We believe this study protocol will help other countries to initiate immunodeficiency-related vaccine-derived poliovirus surveillance to identify and follow up patients who are long-term excretors of vaccine-derived poliovirus. Integration of immunodeficiency-related poliovirus surveillance with acute flaccid paralysis surveillance of the existing poliovirus network will enhance continuous screening of patients with primary immunodeficiency disorder in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohanty</LastName><ForeName>Madhu Chhanda</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, Indian Council of Medical Research, Haffkine Institute Campus, Acharya Donde Marg, Parel, Mumbai-400012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohammad</LastName><ForeName>Ahmad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization Country Office, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verma</LastName><ForeName>Harish</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Polio Eradication, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Arun</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization Country Office, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madkaikar</LastName><ForeName>Manisha Ranjan</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Immunohaematology, Indian Council of Medical Research, Mumbai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Desai</LastName><ForeName>Mukesh</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bai Jerbai Wadia Hospital for Children, Mumbai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Varose</LastName><ForeName>Swapnil Yashwant</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, Indian Council of Medical Research, Haffkine Institute Campus, Acharya Donde Marg, Parel, Mumbai-400012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sawant</LastName><ForeName>Unnati</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, Indian Council of Medical Research, Haffkine Institute Campus, Acharya Donde Marg, Parel, Mumbai-400012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yadav</LastName><ForeName>Reetika Malik</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Immunohaematology, Indian Council of Medical Research, Mumbai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taur</LastName><ForeName>Prasad</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bai Jerbai Wadia Hospital for Children, Mumbai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kathuria</LastName><ForeName>Rachana</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization Country Office, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tatkare</LastName><ForeName>Manogat</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, Indian Council of Medical Research, Haffkine Institute Campus, Acharya Donde Marg, Parel, Mumbai-400012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Murhekar</LastName><ForeName>Megh</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, Indian Council of Medical Research, Haffkine Institute Campus, Acharya Donde Marg, Parel, Mumbai-400012, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haldar</LastName><ForeName>Pradeep</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abraham</LastName><ForeName>Priya</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Virology, Indian Council of Medical Research, Pune, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>001</GrantID><Acronym>WHO_</Acronym><Agency>World Health Organization</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C000629404">acute flaccid myelitis</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007194" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">India</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007153" MajorTopicYN="Y">Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000081207" MajorTopicYN="Y">Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>Certains individus qui présentent des immunodéficiences primaires et sont infectés par des poliovirus dérivés d'une souche vaccinale pourraient continuer à excréter le poliovirus pendant des mois sans que ce dernier ne soit détecté par le biais d'une surveillance de la paralysie flasque aiguë. Ces patients risquent donc de déclencher des épidémies de poliovirus qui mettent en péril les efforts visant à éradiquer la poliomyélite dans le monde. En vue d'identifier ces individus, nous avons élaboré un protocole d'étude pour établir, en Inde, un réseau de surveillance du poliovirus d'origine vaccinale lié à une immunodéficience. Au cours de la première étape, nous avons repéré des centres reconnus dans le pays, capables de diagnostiquer des patients atteints d'un syndrome d'immunodéficience primaire et de les recruter dans le cadre de l'étude. Le prélèvement des échantillons de selles auprès des sites participant à l'étude, la culture, l'isolement, la caractérisation des entérovirus et la communication des résultats à ces sites ont été pris en charge par le National Institute of Virology Mumbai Unit, conformément au protocole du Projet national de surveillance de la poliomyélite de l'OMS. Nous avons consacré la première phase de l'étude, qui s'est déroulée entre janvier 2020 et décembre 2021, à la mise en œuvre du protocole au sein de différents établissements médicaux sur sept sites participants, afin de déterminer le nombre d'infections au poliovirus chez les patients souffrant d'un syndrome d'immunodéficience primaire en Inde. Nous avons ensuite, durant la deuxième phase comprise entre janvier 2022 et décembre 2023, élargi l'étude en incluant 14 établissements supplémentaires à travers le pays. Nous sommes convaincus que ce protocole d'étude aidera d'autres pays à instaurer une surveillance du poliovirus dérivé d'une souche vaccinale et lié à une immunodéficience, qui leur servira à identifier et suivre les patients responsables d'une excrétion prolongée du poliovirus d'origine vaccinale. L'intégration, au sein du réseau existant dédié au poliovirus, d'une surveillance de ce type couplée à une surveillance de la paralysie flasque aiguë améliorera le dépistage systématique des patients atteints d'un syndrome d'immunodéficience primaire à l'avenir.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>Las personas con inmunodeficiencias primarias infectadas por los poliovirus de origen vacunal pueden seguir excretando poliovirus durante meses sin que la vigilancia de la parálisis flácida aguda los detecte. Por lo tanto, estos pacientes suponen un riesgo de iniciar brotes de poliovirus que pongan en peligro los esfuerzos hacia la erradicación mundial de la poliomielitis. Para identificar a estas personas, diseñamos un protocolo de estudio para el establecimiento de una red de vigilancia de poliovirus de origen vacunal relacionados con inmunodeficiencias en la India. En el primer paso identificamos centros reconocidos en la India que pudieran diagnosticar e inscribir en el estudio a pacientes con trastorno de inmunodeficiencia primaria. La recogida de muestras de heces de los centros de estudio, el cultivo, el aislamiento, la caracterización de los enterovirus y la notificación a los centros de estudio se llevaron a cabo en el Instituto Nacional de Virología, Unidad de Mumbai, según el protocolo del Proyecto Nacional de Vigilancia de la Poliomielitis de la OMS. En la primera fase del estudio, de enero de 2020 a diciembre de 2021, aplicamos el protocolo en siete centros de estudio de diferentes institutos médicos para determinar la proporción de infecciones por poliovirus en pacientes con trastorno de inmunodeficiencia primaria de la India. A continuación, ampliamos el estudio con la inclusión de otros 14 institutos médicos de todo el país en la segunda fase, de enero de 2022 a diciembre de 2023. Creemos que este protocolo de estudio ayudará a otros países a iniciar la vigilancia de poliovirus de origen vacunal relacionados con la inmunodeficiencia para identificar y hacer un seguimiento de los pacientes que son excretores a largo plazo de poliovirus de origen vacunal. La integración de la vigilancia del poliovirus asociado a la inmunodeficiencia con la vigilancia de la parálisis flácida aguda de la red de poliovirus existente mejorará el cribado continuo de pacientes con trastorno por inmunodeficiencia primaria en el futuro.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText>إن الأفراد الذين يعانون من نقص المناعة الأولية، المصابين بفيروس شلل الأطفال المشتق من اللقاح، يمكنهم الاستمرار في التخلص من فيروس شلل الأطفال على مدار عدة أشهر، ولا يتم اكتشافهم من خلال مراقبة الشلل الرخو الحاد. وبالتالي، فإن هؤلاء المرضى يشكلون خطرًا لبدء حالات تفشي فيروس شلل الأطفال، والتي من شأنها أن تعرض الجهود المبذولة لاستئصال شلل الأطفال عالميًا للخطر. لتحديد هؤلاء الأفراد، قمنا بتصميم بروتوكول دراسة لإنشاء شبكة لمراقبة فيروس شلل الأطفال المرتبط بنقص المناعة، والمشتق من اللقاح في الهند. في الخطوة الأولى، قمنا بتحديد مراكز معروفة في الهند يمكنها تشخيص وتسجيل المرضى المصابين باضطراب نقص المناعة الأولية في الدراسة. تم جمع عينات البراز من مواقع الدراسة والانتشار والعزل، وتوصيف الفيروسات المعوية، وتقديم التقارير إلى مواقع الدراسة في المعهد الوطني للفيروسات، وذلك عن طريق وحدة مومباي وفقًا لبروتوكول المشروع الوطني لمراقبة شلل الأطفال التابع لمنظمة الصحة العالمية. في المرحلة الأولى من الدراسة من يناير/كانون الثاني 2020 إلى ديسمبر/كانون الأول 2021، طبقنا البروتوكول في سبعة مواقع للدراسة في معاهد طبية مختلفة لتحديد نسبة حالات عدوى فيروس شلل الأطفال في مرضى اضطراب نقص المناعة الأولية في الهند. فيما بعد، قمنا بتوسيع الدراسة من خلال تضمين 14 معهدًا طبيًا إضافيًا في جميع أنحاء الدولة في المرحلة الثانية الممتدة من يناير/كانون الثاني 2022 إلى ديسمبر/كانون الأول 2023. نحن نعتقد أن هذا البروتوكول للدراسة سوف يساعد الدول الأخرى على تدشين مراقبة فيروس شلل الأطفال المشتق من اللقاح، المتعلق بنقص المناعة، لتحديد ومتابعة المرضى الذين يظهر لديهم فيروس شلل الأطفال المشتق من اللقاح على المدى البعيد. إن تكامل مراقبة فيروس شلل الأطفال المرتبط بنقص المناعة، مع مراقبة الشلل الرخو الحاد في شبكة فيروس شلل الأطفال الحالية، سوف يعزز من الفحص المستمر للمرضى المصابين باضطراب نقص المناعة الأولية في المستقبل.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText>感染了疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒的原发性免疫缺陷患者可能继续传播脊髓灰质炎病毒数月而未在急性弛缓性麻痹监测中被发现。因此，这些患者有可能导致脊髓灰质炎病毒的爆发，从而影响全球根除脊髓灰质炎行动。为了识别这些患者，我们设计了一个研究方案，即在印度建立一个与免疫缺陷相关的疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒监测网络。在第一步中，我们确定了印度公认的可以诊断原发性免疫缺陷病并将患者纳入研究的中心。孟买国家病毒学研究所根据《世卫组织国家脊髓灰质炎监测项目》方案，从研究场所采集粪便样本，进行肠道病毒的培养、分离、鉴定并向研究场所报告。在 2020 年 1 月至 2021 年 12 月的第一阶段研究中，我们在不同医疗机构的 7 个研究场所实施了该方案，以确定印度原发性免疫缺陷病患者中脊髓灰质炎病毒感染的比例。后来，我们扩大了研究的范围，在 2022 年 1 月至 2023 年 12月 的第二阶段研究中，纳入了全国另外 14 家医疗机构。我们相信，该研究方案将有助于其他国家实施与免疫缺陷相关的疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒监测，以识别和随访长期携带和排出疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒的患者。将与免疫缺陷相关的脊髓灰质炎病毒监测与现有脊髓灰质炎病毒网络中的急性弛缓性麻痹监测相结合，将有助于加强未来对原发性免疫缺陷并患者的持续筛查。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText>Лица с первичными иммунодефицитами, инфицированные полиовирусами вакцинного происхождения, могут продолжать выделять полиовирус в течение нескольких месяцев и оставаться невыявленными в ходе эпиднадзора за острым вялым параличом. Поэтому эти пациенты представляют риск возникновения вспышек полиовируса, которые ставят под угрозу усилия по ликвидации полиомиелита в мире. Для выявления таких лиц был разработан протокол исследования для создания сети эпиднадзора за полиовирусом вакцинного происхождения, связанным с иммунодефицитом, в Индии. На первом этапе были определены признанные центры в Индии, которые могли диагностировать и включить в исследование пациентов с первичным иммунодефицитом. Сбор образцов кала в исследовательских центрах, культивирование, выделение, характеристика энтеровирусов и предоставление отчетов в исследовательские центры проводились в Национальном институте вирусологии, подразделение Мумбаи, в соответствии с протоколом Национального проекта ВОЗ по эпиднадзору за полиомиелитом. На первом этапе исследования с января 2020 года по декабрь 2021 года протокол был внедрен в семи исследовательских центрах при различных медицинских учреждениях для определения доли полиовирусных инфекций у пациентов с первичным иммунодефицитом в Индии. В дальнейшем исследование было расширено за счет включения еще 14 медицинских учреждений по всей стране на втором этапе, который продлится с января 2022 года по декабрь 2023 года. Считается, что данный протокол исследования поможет другим странам начать эпиднадзор за полиовирусом вакцинного происхождения, связанным с иммунодефицитом, с целью выявления и последующего наблюдения за пациентами, длительно выделяющими полиовирус вакцинного происхождения. Интеграция эпиднадзора за полиовирусом, связанным с иммунодефицитом, с эпиднадзором за острым вялым параличом в рамках существующей сети по борьбе с полиовирусом обеспечит непрерывный скрининг пациентов с первичным иммунодефицитом в будущем.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37131936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10140681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.22.289066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.22.289066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Chong CY, Kam KQ, Yung CF. Combating a resurgence of poliomyelitis through public health surveillance and vaccination. Ann Acad Med Singap. 2023. Jan;52(1):17–26. 10.47102/annals-acadmedsg.2022390</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.47102/annals-acadmedsg.2022390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36730802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Detection of circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus 2 (cVDPV2) in environmental samples – the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the United States of America [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2022-DON408 [cited 2023 Feb 21].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Update on vaccine-derived polioviruses – worldwide, April 2011–June 2012. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2012. Sep 21;61:741–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22992572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pliaka V, Kyriakopoulou Z, Markoulatos P. Risks associated with the use of live-attenuated vaccine poliovirus strains and the strategies for control and eradication of paralytic poliomyelitis. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2012. May;11(5):609–28. 10.1586/erv.12.28</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1586/erv.12.28</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22827246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine-derived poliviruses: circulating vaccine-derived polioviruses [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2013. Available from: http://www.polioeradication.org/Polioandprevention/Thevirus/Vaccinederivedpolioviruses.aspx [cited 2023 Feb 2].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macklin G, Liao Y, Takane M, Dooling K, Gilmour S, Mach O, et al.; iVDPV Working Group. Prolonged excretion of poliovirus among individuals with primary immunodeficiency disorder: an analysis of the World Health Organization registry. Front Immunol. 2017. Sep 25;8:1103. 10.3389/fimmu.2017.01103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2017.01103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5622164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28993765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tangye SG, Al-Herz W, Bousfiha A, Chatila T, Cunningham-Rundles C, Etzioni A, et al. Human inborn errors of immunity: 2019 update on the classification from the International Union of Immunological Societies Expert Committee. [published correction appears in J Clin Immunol. 2020 Feb 22]. J Clin Immunol. 2020. Jan;40(1):24–64. 10.1007/s10875-019-00737-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10875-019-00737-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7082301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31953710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tangye SG, Al-Herz W, Bousfiha A, Cunningham-Rundles C, Franco JL, Holland SM, et al. Human inborn errors of immunity: 2022 update on the classification from the International Union of Immunological Societies Expert Committee. J Clin Immunol. 2022. Oct;42(7):1473–507. 10.1007/s10875-022-01289-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10875-022-01289-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9244088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35748970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Zelm MC, Condino-Neto A, Barbouche MR. Editorial: primary immunodeficiencies worldwide. Front Immunol. 2020. Jan 22;10:3148. 10.3389/fimmu.2019.03148</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.03148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6987400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32038648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polio this week as of 19 July 2022 [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-now/this-week/ [cited 2021 Dec 2].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jindal AK, Pilania RK, Rawat A, Singh S. Primary immunodeficiency disorders in India – a situational review. Front Immunol. 2017. Jun 19;8:714. 10.3389/fimmu.2017.00714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2017.00714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5474457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28674536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indian Society for Primary Immune Deficiency [internet]. Chandigarh: Indian Society for Primary Immune Deficiency; 2017. Available from: https://ispid.org.in/ [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foundation for Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases [internet]. Irvine: Foundation for Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases; 2020. Available from: https://fpid.org/wp/ [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indian Patients Society for Primary Immunodeficiency [internet]. Bhubaneswar: Indian Patients Society for Primary Immunodeficiency; 2015. Available from: https://www.ipspiindia.org/ [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Primary Immunodeficiency Patients’ Welfare Society [internet]. Bangalore: Primary Immunodeficiency Patients’ Welfare Society; 2020. Available from: https://www.facebook.com/PIDPWS/ [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global polio eradication action plan 2022–2024. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2022. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/GPSAP-2022-2024-EN.pdf [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohanty MC, Madkaikar MR, Desai M, Taur P, Nalavade UP, Sharma DK, et al. Poliovirus excretion in children with primary immunodeficiency disorders, India. Emerg Infect Dis. 2017. Oct;23(10):1664–70. 10.3201/eid2310.170724</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2310.170724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5621533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28930011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohanty MC, Madkaikar MR, Desai M, Aluri J, Varose SY, Taur P, et al. Natural clearance of prolonged VDPV infection in a child with primary immunodeficiency disorder. Front Immunol. 2019. Jul 23;10:1567. 10.3389/fimmu.2019.01567</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.01567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6663979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31396204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Draft guidelines for implementing poliovirus surveillance among patients with primary immunodeficiency disorders (PIDs). Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2019. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Guidelines-for-Implementing-PID-Suveillance_EN.pdf [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidelines for implementing poliovirus surveillance among patients with primary immunodeficiency disorders (PIDs). Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2022. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Guidelines-for-Implementing-PID-Suveillance_EN.pdf [cited 2023 Mar 11].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>10 warning signs of primary immunodeficiency [internet]. New York: Jeffrey Modell Foundation; 1993. Available from: https://info4pi.org/library/educational-materials/ [cited 2021 Nov 24].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polio laboratory manual, 4th ed. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2004. Available from: https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/68762/WHO_IVB_04.10.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y [cited 2023 Mar 11].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohanty MC, Mohammad A, Verma H, Kumar A, Madkaikar MR, Desai M, et al. Poliovirus surveillance in patients with primary immunodeficiencies, India. Supplementary files [online repository]. London: figshare; 2023. 10.6084/m9.figshare.22626874.v2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.6084/m9.figshare.22626874.v2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10140681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37131936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>