<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37274621</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2053-1400</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science : water research &amp; technology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci (Camb)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Selective elimination of enterovirus genotypes by activated sludge and chlorination.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1620</StartPage><EndPage>1633</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1620-1633</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1039/d3ew00050h</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses, which are commonly circulating viruses shed in the stool, are released into the sewage system and only partially removed or inactivated, resulting in the discharge of infectious enteroviruses into the environment. Activated sludge and chlorination remove or inactivate enterovirus genotypes to different extents, and thus have the potential to shape the population that will be discharged. The goal of this study was to evaluate how activated sludge and chlorination treatment shape an enterovirus population at the genotype level, using a population of eight genotypes commonly found in sewage: CVA9, CVB1, CVB2, CVB3, CVB4, CVB5, E25, E30. Our results show that the extent of inactivation varied among genotypes, but also across sludge samples. We find that the effluent of activated sludge systems will be depleted in CVA9, CVB1 and CVB2 while E25 together with CVB3, CVB4 and CVB5 will be prevalent. Furthermore, we found that microbial inactivation was the main mechanism of infectivity loss in the activated sludge, while adsorption to the sludge flocs was not significant. During effluent chlorination, we also observed that CVB5, CVB3 and to a lesser extent E25 were less susceptible to chlorination while E30 was readily inactivated, and activated sludge-derived EPS provided further protection against chlorination. This study contributes to a better understanding of the variability of sewage treatment efficacy against different enteroviruses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>This journal is © The Royal Society of Chemistry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Larivé</LastName><ForeName>Odile</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry, School of Architecture, Civil and Environmental Engineering, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) CH-1015 Lausanne Switzerland tamar.kohn@epfl.ch +41 21 69 30891.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Torii</LastName><ForeName>Shotaro</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6655-7440</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry, School of Architecture, Civil and Environmental Engineering, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) CH-1015 Lausanne Switzerland tamar.kohn@epfl.ch +41 21 69 30891.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Derlon</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4240-9827</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eawag, Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology Überlandstrasse 133 CH-8600 Dübendorf Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kohn</LastName><ForeName>Tamar</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0395-6561</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry, School of Architecture, Civil and Environmental Engineering, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) CH-1015 Lausanne Switzerland tamar.kohn@epfl.ch +41 21 69 30891.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci (Camb)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101676376</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2053-1400</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37274621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10233425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/d3ew00050h</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">d3ew00050h</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hewitt J. Leonard M. Greening G. E. Lewis G. D. Influence of wastewater treatment process and the population size on human virus profiles in wastewater. Water Res. 2011;45:6267–6276. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2011.09.029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2011.09.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21962483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costán-Longares A. Mocé-Llivina L. Avellón A. Jofre J. Lucena F. Occurrence and distribution of culturable enteroviruses in wastewater and surface waters of north-eastern Spain. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2008;105:1945–1955. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.03954.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.03954.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19120641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Y. Lee B. E. Neumann N. Ashbolt N. Craik S. Maal-Bared R. Pang X. L. Assessment of human virus removal during municipal wastewater treatment in Edmonton, Canada. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2015;119:1729–1739. doi: 10.1111/jam.12971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.12971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26473649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama H. Haramoto E. Oguma K. Yamashita H. Tajima A. Nakajima H. Ohgaki S. One-year monthly quantitative survey of noroviruses, enteroviruses, and adenoviruses in wastewater collected from six plants in Japan. Water Res. 2008;42:1441–1448. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2007.10.029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2007.10.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17996920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soller J. A. Eftim S. E. Nappier S. P. Direct Potable Reuse Microbial Risk Assessment Methodology: Sensitivity Analysis and Application to State log Credit Allocations. Water Res. 2018;128:286–292. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2017.10.034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.10.034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6816270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29107913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Rosa G. Pourshaban M. Iaconelli M. Muscillo M. Quantitative real-time PCR of enteric viruses in influent and effluent samples from wastewater treatment plants in Italy. Ann. Ist. Super. Sanita. 2010;46:266–273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20847459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop K. S. M. Rahamat-Langendoen J. C. van der Avoort H. G. A. M. Claas E. C. J. Pas S. D. Schuurman R. Verweij J. J. Wolthers K. C. Niesters H. G. M. Koopmans M. P. G. VIRO-TypeNed, systematic molecular surveillance of enteroviruses in the Netherlands between 2010 and 2014. Eurosurveillance. 2016;21:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5069426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27719752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delogu R. Battistone A. Buttinelli G. Fiore S. Fontana S. Amato C. Cristiano K. Gamper S. Simeoni J. Frate R. Pellegrinelli L. Pennino F. Germinario C. Balena V. Cicala A. Mercurio P. Fiore L. Poliovirus and Other Enteroviruses from Environmental Surveillance in Italy, 2009 – 2015. Food Environ. Virol. 2018;10:333–342. doi: 10.1007/s12560-018-9350-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-018-9350-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29948963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hovi T. Stenvik M. Rosenlew M. Relative abundance of enterovirus serotypes in sewage differs from that in patients: Clinical and epidemiological implications. Epidemiol. Infect. 1996;116:91–97. doi: 10.1017/S0950268800058982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268800058982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2271245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8626008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu O. C. and McGowan F., Effect of chlorination on human enteric viruses in partially treated water from the Potomac river estuary, Environ. Prot. Agency Water supply programs Div. Northeast. Water Supply Lab, 1971</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba C. Goyal S. Hurst C. Labelle R. Type and strain dependence of enterovirus adsorption to activated sludge, soils and estuarine sediments. Water Res. 1980;14:1197–1198. doi: 10.1016/0043-1354(80)90176-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0043-1354(80)90176-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim T.-D. Unno H. The roles of microbes in the removal and inactivation of viruses in a biological wastewater treatment system. Water Sci. Technol. 1996;33:243–250. doi: 10.2166/wst.1996.0681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.1996.0681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly S. Sanderson W. W. Neidl C. Removal of Enteroviruses from Sewage by Activated Sludge. J. - Water Pollut. Control Fed. 1961;33:1056–1062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowlton D. R. Ward R. L. Characterization of virucidal agents in activated sludge. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1987;53:621–626. doi: 10.1128/aem.53.4.621-626.1987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.53.4.621-626.1987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC203725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3034153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z. Wang Z. Lin X. Wang S. Wang H. Yoshida H. Xu A. Song Y. One-year Survey of human enteroviruses from sewage and the factors affecting virus adsorption to the suspended solids. Sci. Rep. 2016;6:1–9. doi: 10.1038/s41598-016-0001-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-016-0001-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4980594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27510810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olive M. Moerman F. Fernandez-Cassi X. Altermatt F. Kohn T. Removal of Waterborne Viruses by Tetrahymena pyriformis Is Virus-Specific and Coincides with Changes in Protist Swimming Speed. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2022;56:4062–4070. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.1c05518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c05518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8988290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35258957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corre M. H. Bachmann V. Kohn T. Bacterial matrix metalloproteases and serine proteases contribute to the extra-host inactivation of enteroviruses in lake water. ISME J. 2022;16:1970–1979. doi: 10.1038/s41396-022-01246-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41396-022-01246-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9296489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35545659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cliver D. O. Hermann J. E. Proteolytic and Microbial inactivation of Enteroviruses. Water Res. 1972;6:797–805. doi: 10.1016/0043-1354(72)90032-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0043-1354(72)90032-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beychok M. R. Performance of surface-aerated basins. Chem. Eng. Prog., Symp. Ser. 1971;67:322–339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo S. Gilbert J. Hetrick F. Stability of Human Enteroviruses in Estuarine and Marine Waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1976;32:245–249. doi: 10.1128/aem.32.2.245-249.1976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.32.2.245-249.1976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC170043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">184736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waldman P. Meseguer A. Lucas F. Moulin L. Wurtzer S. Interaction of Human Enteric Viruses with Microbial Compounds: Implication for Virus Persistence and Disinfection Treatments. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2017;51:13633–13640. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.7b03875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.7b03875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29116763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson C. M. Jesudhasan P. R. Pfeiffer J. K. Bacterial lipopolysaccharide binding enhances virion stability and promotes environmental fitness of an enteric virus. Cell Host Microbe. 2014;15:36–46. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2013.12.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2013.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3920179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24439896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meister S. Verbyla M. E. Klinger M. Kohn T. Variability in Disinfection Resistance between Currently Circulating Enterovirus B Serotypes and Strains. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2018;52:3696–3705. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.8b00851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b00851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29466658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torii S. Corre M.-H. Miura F. Itamochi M. Haga K. Katayama K. Katayama H. Kohn T. Genotype-dependent kinetics of enterovirus inactivation by free chlorine and ultraviolet (UV) irradiation. Water Res. 2022;220:118712. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2022.118712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2022.118712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35691190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payment P. Tremblay M. Trudel M. Relative resistance to chlorine of poliovirus and coxsackievirus isolates from environmental sources and drinking water. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1985;49:981–983. doi: 10.1128/aem.49.4.981-983.1985.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.49.4.981-983.1985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC238481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2988441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cromeans T. L. Kahler A. M. Hill V. R. Inactivation of adenoviruses, enteroviruses, and murine norovirus in water by free chlorine and monochloramine. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2010;76:1028–1033. doi: 10.1128/AEM.01342-09.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01342-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2820971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20023080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harakeh S. The behavior of viruses on disinfection by chlorine dioxide and other disinfectants in effluent. FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 1987;44:335–341. doi: 10.1111/j.1574-6968.1987.tb02311.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1987.tb02311.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larivé O. Brandani J. Dubey M. Kohn T. An integrated cell culture reverse transcriptase quantitative PCR (ICC-RTqPCR) method to simultaneously quantify the infectious concentrations of eight environmentally relevant enterovirus serotypes. J. Virol. Methods. 2021;296:114225. doi: 10.1016/j.jviromet.2021.114225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2021.114225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34216645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Environmental Protection Agency, Most Probable Number (MPN) Calculator Version 2.0 - User and System Installation and Administration Manual, 2013, pp. 3–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klymus K. E. Merkes C. M. Allison M. J. Jackson C. A. Goldberg C. S. Helbing C. C. Hunter M. E. Lance R. F. Mangan A. M. Monroe E. M. Piaggio A. J. Stokdyk J. P. Wilson C. C. Richter C. A. Reporting the limits of detection and quantification for environmental DNA assays. Environ. DNA. 2020;2:271–282. doi: 10.1002/edn3.29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/edn3.29</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin S. A. Benes V. Garson J. A. Hellemans J. Huggett J. Kubista M. Mueller R. Nolan T. Pfaffl M. W. Shipley G. L. The MIQE Guidelines : Minimum Information for Publication of Quantitative Real-Time PCR Experiments. Clin. Chem. 2009;55:611–622. doi: 10.1373/clinchem.2008.112797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1373/clinchem.2008.112797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19246619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>APHA, in Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater, American Public Health Association, American Water Works Association, Water Environment Federation, Washington, DC, 21st edn, 2005, pp. 55–61</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felz S. Al-Zuhairy S. Aarstad O. A. van Loosdrecht M. C. M. Lin Y. M. Extraction of structural extracellular polymeric substances from aerobic granular sludge. J. Visualized Exp. 2016;2016:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5092066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27768085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felz S. Vermeulen P. van Loosdrecht M. C. M. Lin Y. M. Chemical characterization methods for the analysis of structural extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) Water Res. 2019;157:201–208. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2019.03.068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2019.03.068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30953855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubois M. Gilles K. A. Hamilton J. K. Rebers P. A. Smith F. Colorimetric Method for Determination of Sugars and Related Substances. Anal. Chem. 1956;28:350–356. doi: 10.1021/ac60111a017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac60111a017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team, R: A language and environment for statistical computing, R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muggeo V. M. Interval estimation for the breakpoint in segmented regression: a smoothed score-based approach. Aust. N. Z. J. Stat. 2017;59:311–322. doi: 10.1111/anzs.12200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/anzs.12200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bischel H. N. Schertenleib A. Fumasoli A. Udert K. M. Kohn T. Inactivation kinetics and mechanisms of viral and bacterial pathogen surrogates during urine nitrification. Environ. Sci.: Water Res. Technol. 2015;1:65–76. doi: 10.1039/C4EW00065J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C4EW00065J</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guellil A. Boualam M. Quiquampoix H. Ginestet P. Audic J. Block J. Hydrolysis of wastewater colloidal organic matter by extracellular enzymes extracted from activated sludge flocs. Water Sci. Technol. 2001;43:33–40. doi: 10.2166/wst.2001.0334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.2001.0334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11381970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frolund B. Griebe T. Nielsen P. H. Enzymatic activity in the activated-sludge floc matrix. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 1995;43:755–761. doi: 10.1007/s002530050481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s002530050481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7546613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goel R. Mino T. Satoh H. Matsuo T. Enzyme activities under anaerobic and aerobic conditions in activated sludge sequencing batch reactor. Water Res. 1998;32:2081–2088. doi: 10.1016/S0043-1354(97)00425-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0043-1354(97)00425-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>State of Maine Department of Environmental Protection, Notes on Activated Sludge Process Control, 2009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haun E. Ulbricht K. Nogueira R. Rosenwinkel K.-H. Virus elimination in activated sludge systems: from batch tests to mathematical modeling. Water Sci. Technol. 2014;70:1115–1121. doi: 10.2166/wst.2014.349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.2014.349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25259502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhry R. M. Nelson K. L. Drewes J. E. Mechanisms of Pathogenic Virus Removal in a Full-Scale Membrane Bioreactor. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2015;49:2815–2822. doi: 10.1021/es505332n.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es505332n</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25642587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carratalà A. Bachmann V. Julian T. R. Kohn T. Adaptation of Human Enterovirus to Warm Environments Leads to Resistance against Chlorine Disinfection. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2020;54:11292–11300. doi: 10.1021/acs.est.0c03199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.0c03199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32875801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>