<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37349989</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diversity of picornaviruses detected in diarrheal samples from children in Belém, Brazilian Amazon (1982-2019).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28873</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28873</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28873</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this investigation, fecal specimens from children with diarrhea were collected from four community studies conducted between 1982 and 2019 in Belém, Brazilian Amazon. A total of 234 samples were tested by quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) to detect infections by picornaviruses of the Enterovirus (EV), Parechovirus (HPeV), Cosavirus (HCoSV), Kobuvirus (Aichivirus - AiV) and Salivirus (SalV) genera. The positive samples were subjected to different amplification protocols of the VP1 region of the genome, such as nested PCR or snPCR, and were subsequently genotyped by sequencing VP1 and VP3 of the viral genome. Positivity was observed in 76.5% (179/234) of the samples tested using RT-qPCR for at least one virus, and co-infection was observed in 37.4% (67/179) of the cases. EV was detected in 50.8% (119/234), HPeV in 29.9% (70/234), HCoSV in 27.3% (64/234), and AiV/SalV in 2.1% (5/234) of the specimens tested by RT-qPCR. Using nested PCR and/or snPCR techniques, the positivity rates were 94.11% (112/119) for EV, 72.85% (51/70) for HPeV, and 20.31% (13/64) for HCoSV. It was not possible to amplify the samples that were positive for AiV/SalV. Sequencing revealed 67.2% (80/119) EV, 51.4% (36/70) HPeV, and 20.31% (13/64) HCoSV. Forty-five different types of EV were found among species A, B, and C; HCoSV identified five species, including a possible recombinant strain; all HPeV were identified as belonging to species A, in two samples a possible recombination involving three different strains was verified. This study demonstrated the high circulation and diversity of different types of picornaviruses in fecal samples, including those collected more than 30 years ago. This endorsed the evaluation of important points in the epidemiology of these viruses, such as the presence of co-infection and the possibility of knowing more about these agents, considering that some were recently described; therefore, their detection in older samples can provide more data about their ancestry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Coutinho</LastName><ForeName>Carla Rafaela Monteiro</ForeName><Initials>CRM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programa de Pós-graduação em Biologia Parasitária na Amazônia, Universidade do Estado do Pará-UEPA, Belém, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cardoso</LastName><ForeName>Jedson Ferreira</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Bioinformática-BIOINFO, Seção de Virologia-SAVIR, Instituto Evandro Chagas-IEC, Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde e Ambiente-SVSA, Ministério da Saúde, Ananindeua, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Siqueira</LastName><ForeName>Jones Anderson Monteiro</ForeName><Initials>JAM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Vírus Gastroentéricos-LVG, Seção de Virologia-SAVIR, Instituto Evandro Chagas-IEC, Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde e Ambiente-SVSA, Ministério da Saúde, Ananindeua, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Machado</LastName><ForeName>Raiana Scerni</ForeName><Initials>RS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Programa de Pós-graduação em Medicina Tropical, Instituto Oswaldo Cruz-FIOCRUZ, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chagas Júnior</LastName><ForeName>Wanderley Dias das</ForeName><Initials>WDD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Enterovírus-LEV, Seção de Virologia-SAVIR, Instituto Evandro Chagas-IEC, Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde e Ambiente-SVSA, Ministério da Saúde, Ananindeua, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tavares</LastName><ForeName>Fernando Neto</ForeName><Initials>FN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Enterovírus-LEV, Seção de Virologia-SAVIR, Instituto Evandro Chagas-IEC, Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde e Ambiente-SVSA, Ministério da Saúde, Ananindeua, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gabbay</LastName><ForeName>Yvone Benchimol</ForeName><Initials>YB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Vírus Gastroentéricos-LVG, Seção de Virologia-SAVIR, Instituto Evandro Chagas-IEC, Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde e Ambiente-SVSA, Ministério da Saúde, Ananindeua, Pará, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010849" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060085" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coinfection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003967" MajorTopicYN="N">Diarrhea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Picornaviridae</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">child</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diarrhea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genotyping techniques</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37349989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Posovszky C, Buderus S, Classen M, Lawrenz B, Keller KM, Koletzko S. Acute infectious gastroenteritis in infancy and childhood. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2020;117(37):615-624. doi:10.3238/arztebl.2020.0615</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Picornavirus Home. The Picornaviridae Homepage. 2022. Accessed August 17, 2022. https://www.picornaviridae.com/enterovirus/enterovirus.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowles NJ, Hovi T, Hyypiä T, et al. 2012. Picornaviridae. In: Virus Taxonomy: Classification and Nomenclature of Viruses: Ninth Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses. Ed: King, A.M.Q., Adams, M.J., Carstens, E.B. and Lefkowitz, E.J. San Diego: Elsevier, pp 855-880.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams MJ, Lefkowitz EJ, King AMQ, et al. Ratification vote on taxonomic proposals to the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (2016). Arch Virol. 2016;161:2921-2949.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King AMQ, Lefkowitz EJ, Mushegian AR, et al. Changes to taxonomy and the international code of virus classification and nomenclature ratified by the international committee on taxonomy of viruses (2018). Arch Virol. 2018;163:2601-2631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker PJ, Siddell SG, Lefkowitz EJ, et al. Changes to virus taxonomy and to the International Code of Virus Classification and Nomenclature ratified by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (2021). Arch Virol. 2021;166(9):2633-2648. doi:10.1007/s00705-021-05156-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ICTV. Accessed September 3, 2020. https://talk.ictvonline.org/taxonomy/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parashar UD, Bresee JS, Glass RI. The global burden of diarrhoeal disease in children. Bull World Health Organ. 2003;81:236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanway G, Joki-Korpela P, Hyypiä T. Human parechoviruses-biology and clinical significance. Rev Med Virol. 2000;10(1):57-69. doi:10.1002/(sici)1099-1654(200001/02)10:1&lt;57::aid-rmv266&gt;3.0.co;2-h</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Wolthers KC, Simmonds P. Parechoviruses in children: understanding a new infection. Curr Opin Infect Dis. 2010;23:224-230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drexler JF, Grywna K, Stöcker A, et al. Novel human parechovirus from Brazil. Emerging Infect Dis. 2009;15:310-313. doi:10.3201/eid1502.081028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivadulla E, Romalde JL. A comprehensive review on human aichi virus. Virologica Sinica. 2020;35(5):501-516. doi:10.1007/s12250-020-00222-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapusinszky B, Phan TG, Kapoor A, Delwart E. Genetic diversity of the genus Cosavirus in the family Picornaviridae: a new species, recombination, and 26 new genotypes. PLoS One. 2012;7(5):e36685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayouni S, Estienney M, Hammami S, et al. Cosavirus, salivirus and bufavirus in diarrheal Tunisian infants. PLoS One. 2016;11(9):e0162255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Victoria J, Kapoor A, et al. A novel picornavirus associated with gastroenteritis. J Virol. 2009;83:12002-12006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapoor A, Victoria J, Simmonds P, et al. A highly prevalent and genetically diversified Picornaviridae genus in South Asian children. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2008;105:20482-20487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng TFF, Marine R, Wang C, et al. High variety of known and new RNA and DNA viruses of diverse origins in untreated sewage. J Virol. 2012;86(22):12161-12175. doi:10.1128/JVI.00869-12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C, Siegrist F, Petty TJ, Kaiser L. Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity with associated human diseases. Infect Genet Evol. 2013;14:282-293. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linhares AC, Gabbay YB, Freitas RB, Travassos da Rosa ES, Mascarenhas JDP, Loureiro ECB. Longitudinal study of rotavirus infections among children from Belém, Brazil. Epidemiol Infect. 1989;102(1):129-145. doi:10.1017/s0950268800029769</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siqueira JAM, Júnior ECS, Linhares AC, Gabbay YB. Molecular analysis of norovirus in specimens from children enrolled in a 1982-1986 study in Belém, Brazil: a community-based longitudinal study. J Med Virol. 2017;89(11):1894-1903. doi:10.1002/jmv.24812</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linhares AC, Gabbay YB, Mascarenhas JD, et al. Immunogenicity, safety and efficacy of tetravalent rhesus-human, reassortant rotavirus vaccine in Belém, Brazil. Bull World Health Organ. 1996;74(5):491-500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Araújo EC, Clemens SAC, Oliveira CS, et al. Safety, immunogenicity, and protective efficacy of two doses of RIX4414 live attenuated human rotavirus vaccine in healthy Brazilian infants. J Pediatr. 2007;83:217-224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilpatrick DR, Yang CF, Ching K, et al. Rapid group-, serotype-, and vaccine strain-specific identification of poliovirus isolates by real-time reverse transcription-PCR using degenerate primers and probes containing deoxyinosine residues. J Clin Microbiol. 2009;47(6):1939-1941.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Maher K, Johansson ES, et al. Detection of all known parechoviruses by real time-PCR. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46:2519-2524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44(8):2698-2704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Peñaranda S, Rogers SL, Henderson E, Nix WA. Comparative evaluation of Taqman real-time PCR and semi-nested VP1 PCR for detection of enteroviruses in clinical specimens. J Clin Virol. 2010;49:73-74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Maher K, Pallansch MA, Oberste MS. Parechovirus typing in clinical specimens by nested or semi-nested PCR coupled with sequencing. J Clin Virol. 2010;48:202-207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamashita T, Kobayashi S, Sakae K, et al. Isolation of cytopathic small round viruses with BS-C-1 cells from patients with gastroenteritis. J Infect Dis. 2000;164:954-957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham NTK, Trinh QD, Chan-IT W, et al. A novel RT-multiplex PCR for detection of Aichi virus, human parechovirus, enteroviruses, and human bocavirus among infants and children with acute gastroenteritis. J Virol Methods. 2010;169(1):193-197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Khetsuriani N, Peñaranda S, et al. Diversity of picornaviruses in rural Bolivia. J Gen Virol. 2013;94(09):2017-2028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harjeet SM, Rashmi CC, Akhalesh KS, Tapan ND. Genetic diversity of cosaviruses in nonpolio acute flaccid paralysis cases of etiology, Northern India, 2010-2011. J Clin Virol. 2013;58:183-187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond A, Ashton B, Buxton S, et al. Geneious v10.0.8. 2014; Accessed 13 June 2023. https://www.geneious.com/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ. Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol. 1990;215:403-410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Standley DM. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30:772-780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price MN, Dehal PS, Arkin AP. FastTree 2-approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments. PLoS One. 2010;5(3):e9490. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0009490</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rambaut A. FigTree-Molecular Evolution, phylogenetics and Epidemiology. 2007. Accessed 14 February 2015. https://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coutinho CRM, Siqueira JAM, Machado RS, et al. Enterovirus detection and serotyping of fecal material collected from three children living on the outskirts of Belém city, Amazon region, Brazil, during the first 3 years of life (1983-1986). J Med Virol. 2020;92(8):1075-1084. doi:10.1002/jmv.25656</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Wu F, Liang M, et al. Parechovirus A infection and risk of gastroenteritis in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Rev Med Virol. 2022;32:e2380. doi:10.1002/rmv.2380</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham NTK, Trinh QD, Khamrin P, et al. Diversity of human parechoviruses isolated from stool samples collected from Thai children with acute gastroenteritis. J Clin Microbiol. 2010;48(1):115-119. doi:10.1128/JCM.01015-09</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mashaly MES, Alkasaby NM, Bakr A, Zaki MES, Montasser K. Viral pathogens of acute gastroenteritis in Egyptian children: role of the parechovirus. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):584. doi:10.1186/s12879-022-07562-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham NTK, Thongprachum A, Shimizu Y, et al. Diversity of human parechovirus in infants and children with acute gastroenteritis in Japan during 2014-2016. Infect Genet Evol. 2019;75:104001. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2019.104001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okitsu S, Khamrin P, Thongprachum A, et al. Detection and molecular characterization of human cosavirus in a pediatric patient with acute gastroenteritis, Japan. Infect Genet Evol. 2014;28:125-129. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2014.09.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoshbazan S, Ivani Z, Mousavi Nasab SD, et al. High viral load detection of human Cosavirus in Iranian pediatric patients with acute gastroenteritis. Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench. 2021;14(suppl):S82-S86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stöcker A, de Carvalho Dominguez Souza BF, Ribeiro TCM, et al. Cosavirus infection in persons with and without gastroenteritis, Brazil. Emerging Infect Dis. 2012;18:656-659.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Costa AC, Luchs A, Milagres FAP, et al. Near full length genome of a recombinant (E/D) cosavirus strain from a rural area in the central region of Brazil. Sci Rep. 2018;8(1):12304. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-30214-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J, Ao Y, Liu N, Li L, Duan Z. Salivirus in children and its association with childhood acute gastroenteritis: a paired case-control study. PLoS One. 2015;10(7):e0130977.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuter G, Pankovics P, Boros Á. Saliviruses-the first knowledge about a newly discovered human picornavirus. Rev Med Virol. 2017;27(1):e1904.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan T, Wang C, Cui L, et al. Picornavirus Salivirus/Klassevirus in children with diarrhea, China. Emerging Infect Dis. 2010;16(8):1303-1305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daprà V, Galliano I, Montanari P, et al. Bufavirus, Cosavirus, and Salivirus in diarrheal Italian infants. Intervirology. 2021;64(3):165-168. doi:10.1159/000514384</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Japhet MO, Famurewa O, Adesina OA, et al. Viral gastroenteritis among children of 0-5 years in Nigeria: characterization of the first Nigerian aichivirus, recombinant noroviruses and detection of a zoonotic astrovirus. J Clin Virol. 2019;111:4-11. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2018.12.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>do Socorro Fôro Ramos E, de Oliveira Ribeiro G, Villanova F, et al. Composition of eukaryotic viruses and bacteriophages in individuals with acute gastroenteritis. Viruses. 2021;13(12):2365. doi:10.3390/v13122365</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>