<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">37409616</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mechanism of RNA m<sup>6</sup> A methylation modification regulating NLRP3 inflammasome activation for hand, foot, and mouth disease progression.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28939</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28939</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28939</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Some children infected with hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) caused by enterovirus 71 (EV71) progressed to severe disease with various neurological complications in the short term, with a poor prognosis and high mortality. Studies had revealed that RNA N<sup>6</sup> -methyladenosine (m<sup>6</sup> A) modification had a significant impact on EV71 replication, but it was unknown how m<sup>6</sup> A modification regulated the host cell's innate immune response brought on by EV71 infection. We used MeRIP-seq (methylation RNA immunoprecipitation sequencing), RNA-seq (RNA sequencing), cell transfection, and other techniques. MeRIP-seq and RNA-seq results showed the m<sup>6</sup> A methylation modification map of control and EV71-infected groups of RD cells. And multilevel validation indicated that decreased expression of demethylase FTO (fat mass and obesity-associated protein) was responsible for the elevated total m<sup>6</sup> A modification levels in EV71-infected RD cells and that thioredoxin interacting protein (TXNIP) may be a target gene for demethylase FTO action. Further functional experiments showed that demethylase knockdown of FTO promoted TXNIP expression, activation of NLRP3 inflammasome and promoted the release of proinflammatory factors in vitro, and the opposite result occurred with demethylase FTO overexpression. And further tested in an animal model of EV71 infection in vitro, with results consistent with in vitro. Our findings elucidated that depletion of the demethylase FTO during EV71 infection increased the m<sup>6</sup> A modification level of TXNIP mRNA 3' untranslated region (UTR), enhancing mRNA stability, and promoting TXNIP expression. Consequently, the NLRP3 inflammasome was stimulated, leading to the release of proinflammatory factors and facilitating HFMD progression.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Quanman</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Yanlei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhengzhou Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Yaqi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dong</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>An</LastName><ForeName>Tongyan</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Long</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Wangquan</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Yuefei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Long</LastName><ForeName>Jinzhao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Haiyan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1797-304X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duan</LastName><ForeName>Guangcai</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Shuaiyin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6129-0310</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Public Health, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D058847">Inflammasomes</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000071199">NLR Family, Pyrin Domain-Containing 3 Protein</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>63231-63-0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012313">RNA</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058847" MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammasomes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008745" MajorTopicYN="N">Methylation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071199" MajorTopicYN="N">NLR Family, Pyrin Domain-Containing 3 Protein</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012313" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EV71 infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FTO</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HFMD progression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NLRP3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TXNIP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">m6A modification</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37409616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ooi MH, Wong SC, Lewthwaite P, Cardosa MJ, Solomon T. Clinical features, diagnosis, and management of enterovirus 71. Lancet Neurol. 2010;9(11):1097-1105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon T, Lewthwaite P, Perera D, Cardosa MJ, McMinn P, Ooi MH. Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of enterovirus 71. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10(11):778-790.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt NJ, Lennette EH, Ho HH. An apparently new enterovirus isolated from patients with disease of the central nervous system. J Infect Dis. 1974;129(3):304-309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi L, Lu J, Kung H, He ML. The virology and developments toward control of human enterovirus 71. Crit Rev Microbiol. 2011;37(4):313-327.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W, Liao Q, Viboud C, et al. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008-12: an epidemiological study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14(4):308-318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Liu F, Liao Q, et al. Epidemiology of hand, foot and mouth disease in China, 2008 to 2015 prior to the introduction of EV-A71 vaccine. Euro Surveill. 2017;22(50):16-00824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee M, Kim B, Kim VN. Emerging roles of RNA modification: m(6)A and u-tail. Cell. 2014;158(5):980-987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alarcón CR, Lee H, Goodarzi H, Halberg N, Tavazoie SF. N6-methyladenosine marks primary microRNAs for processing. Nature. 2015;519(7544):482-485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachtergaele S, He C. Chemical modifications in the life of an mRNA transcript. Annu Rev Genet. 2018;52:349-372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao G, Li HB, Yin Z, Flavell RA. Recent advances in dynamic m6A RNA modification. Open Biol. 2016;6(4):160003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krug RM, Morgan MA, Shatkin AJ. Influenza viral mRNA contains internal N6-methyladenosine and 5′-terminal 7-methylguanosine in cap structures. J Virol. 1976;20(1):45-53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kane SE, Beemon K, Kane SE, Beemon K. Precise localization of m6A in Rous sarcoma virus RNA reveals clustering of methylation sites: implications for RNA processing. Mol Cell Biol. 1985;5(9):2298-2306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imam H, Khan M, Gokhale NS, et al. N6-methyladenosine modification of hepatitis B virus RNA differentially regulates the viral life cycle. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2018;115(35):8829-8834.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imam H, Kim GW, Mir SA, Khan M, Siddiqui A. Interferon-stimulated gene 20 (ISG20) selectively degrades N6-methyladenosine modified hepatitis B virus transcripts. PLoS Pathog. 2020;16(2):e1008338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim GW, Imam H, Khan M, et al. HBV-induced increased N6 methyladenosine modification of PTEN RNA affects innate immunity and contributes to HCC. Hepatology. 2021;73(2):533-547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Zhu M, Pan R, et al. The tumor suppressor PTEN has a critical role in antiviral innate immunity. Nat Immunol. 2016;17(3):241-249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao H, Hao S, Chen H, et al. N6-methyladenosine modification and METTL3 modulate enterovirus 71 replication. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47(1):362-374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Zhang C, Zhang R, et al. Pulmonary edema following central nervous system lesions induced by a non- mouse-adapted EV71 strain in neonatal BALB/c mice. Virol J. 2017;14(1):243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Chen LQ, Zhao YL, et al. Single-base mapping of m(6)A by an antibody-independent method. Sci Adv. 2019;5(7):eaax0250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Campos MA, Edelheit S, Toth U, et al. Deciphering the “m(6)A code” via Antibody-Independent quantitative profiling. Cell. 2019;178(3):731-747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lum LCS, Wong KT, Lam SK, et al. Fatal enterovirus 71 encephalomyelitis. J Pediatr. 1998;133(6):795-798.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei CM, Moss B. Nucleotide sequences at the N6-methyladenosine sites of HeLa cell messenger ribonucleic acid. Biochemistry. 1977;16(8):1672-1676.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer KD, Saletore Y, Zumbo P, Elemento O, Mason CE, Jaffrey SR. Comprehensive analysis of mRNA methylation reveals enrichment in 3′ UTRs and near stop codons. Cell. 2012;149(7):1635-1646.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Speakman JR. The ‘fat mass and obesity related’ (FTO) gene: mechanisms of impact on obesity and energy balance. Curr Obes Rep. 2015;4(1):73-91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aravind L, Koonin EV. The DNA-repair protein AlkB, EGL-9, and leprecan define new families of 2-oxoglutarate- and iron-dependent dioxygenases. Genome Biol. 2001;2(3):1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Z, Yu G, Zhu X, Peng T, Lv Y. Critical roles of FTO-mediated mRNA m6A demethylation in regulating adipogenesis and lipid metabolism: implications in lipid metabolic disorders. Genes Dis. 2022;9(1):51-61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Y, Chen K, Song B, et al. m6A-Atlas: a comprehensive knowledgebase for unraveling the N6-methyladenosine (m6A) epitranscriptome. Nucleic Acids Res. 2021;49(D1):D134-D143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim GS, Jung JE, Narasimhan P, Sakata H, Chan PH. Induction of thioredoxin-interacting protein is mediated by oxidative stress, calcium, and glucose after brain injury in mice. Neurobiol Dis. 2012;46(2):440-449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abderrazak A, Syrovets T, Couchie D, et al. NLRP3 inflammasome: from a danger signal sensor to a regulatory node of oxidative stress and inflammatory diseases. Redox Biol. 2015;4:296-307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qayyum N, Haseeb M, Kim MS, Choi S. Role of thioredoxin-interacting protein in diseases and its therapeutic outlook. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(5):2754.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou R, Tardivel A, Thorens B, Choi I, Tschopp J. Thioredoxin-interacting protein links oxidative stress to inflammasome activation. Nat Immunol. 2010;11(2):136-140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S, Kumar S, Espada CE, et al. N6-methyladenosine modification of HIV-1 RNA suppresses type-I interferon induction in differentiated monocytic cells and primary macrophages. PLoS Pathog. 2021;17(3):e1009421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFadden MJ, Sacco MT, Murphy KA, et al. FTO suppresses STAT3 activation and modulates proinflammatory interferon-stimulated gene expression. J Mol Biol. 2022;434(6):167247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y, Zhang R, Wu W, Duan G. Antiviral and inflammatory cellular signaling associated with enterovirus 71 infection. Viruses. 2018;10(4):155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Xiao F, Wan P, et al. EV71 3D protein binds with NLRP3 and enhances the assembly of inflammasome complex. PLoS Pathog. 2017;13(1):e1006123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Lei X, Xiao X, et al. Reciprocal regulation between enterovirus 71 and the NLRP3 inflammasome. Cell Rep. 2015;12(1):42-48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Church C, Moir L, McMurray F, et al. Overexpression of Fto leads to increased food intake and results in obesity. Nat Genet. 2010;42(12):1086-1092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Su R, Sheng Y, et al. Small-molecule targeting of oncogenic FTO demethylase in acute myeloid leukemia. Cancer Cell. 2019;35(4):677-691.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>