<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37477797</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Acute orchitis deciphered: Coxsackievirus B strains are the main etiology and their presence in semen is associated with acute inflammation and risk of persistent oligozoospermia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28970</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28970</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28970</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Although various viruses are considered to be the clinical cause for acute orchitis, it is completely unclear to what extent and which viruses are etiologically involved in acute orchitis and what the clinic and course of these patients are like. Therefore, a prospective study was set up to decipher acute isolated orchitis. Between July 2007 and February 2023, a total of 26 patients with isolated orchitis were recruited and compared with 530 patients with acute epididymitis. We were able to show for isolated orchitis, that (1) orchitis is usually of viral origin (20/26, 77%) and enteroviruses with coxsackievirus B strains (16/26, 62%) are predominant, (2) virus isolates could be received from semen indicating the presence of replication-competent virus particles, (3) a polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for enteroviruses should be conducted using semen provided at the onset of disease, because the virus is not detectable in serum/urine, (4) there is a circannual occurrence with the maximum in summer, (5) orchitis is associated with a characteristic inflammatory cytokine panel in the semen and systemic inflammation, (6) orchitis is usually rapidly self-limiting, and (7) about 30% of patients (6/20) suffer ongoing oligozoospermia. These seven emerging aspects are likely to fundamentally change thinking and clinical practice regarding acute isolated orchitis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors. Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pilatz</LastName><ForeName>Adrian</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8072-1841</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Urology, Pediatric Urology and Andrology, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arneth</LastName><ForeName>Borros</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiochemistry, Molecular Diagnostics, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaiser</LastName><ForeName>Rolf</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Virology, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heger</LastName><ForeName>Eva</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Virology, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pirkl</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6986-0813</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Virology, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Böttcher</LastName><ForeName>Sindy</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Reference Centre for Poliomyelitis and Enteroviruses, Robert Koch-Institute, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fritzenwanker</LastName><ForeName>Moritz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Microbiology, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Renz</LastName><ForeName>Harald</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiochemistry, Molecular Diagnostics, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mankertz</LastName><ForeName>Annette</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Reference Center Measles, Mumps, Rubella, Robert Koch-Institute, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schuppe</LastName><ForeName>Hans-Christian</ForeName><Initials>HC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Urology, Pediatric Urology and Andrology, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wagenlehner</LastName><ForeName>Florian</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Urology, Pediatric Urology and Andrology, Justus Liebig University Giessen, Giessen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009920" MajorTopicYN="Y">Orchitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012661" MajorTopicYN="N">Semen</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009845" MajorTopicYN="Y">Oligospermia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007249" MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammation</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Orchitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epididymitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fertility</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mumps</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37477797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Schuppe HC, Meinhardt A, Allam JP, Bergmann M, Weidner W, Haidl G. Chronic orchitis: a neglected cause of male infertility? Andrologia. 2008;40(2):84-91. doi:10.1111/j.1439-0272.2008.00837.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilatz A, Wagenlehner F, Bschleipfer T, et al. Acute epididymitis in ultrasound: results of a prospective study with baseline and follow-up investigations in 134 patients. Eur J Radiol. 2013;82(12):e762-e768. doi:10.1016/j.ejrad.2013.08.050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamopoulos DA, Lawrence DM, Vassilopoulos P, Contoyiannis PA, Swyer GIM. Pituitary-testicular interrelationships in mumps orchitis and other viral infections. BMJ. 1978;1(6121):1177-1180. doi:10.1136/bmj.1.6121.1177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artul S, Abu Rahmah Y, Abu Shkara H, Yamini A. Inferno: colour Doppler ultrasound sign of orchitis. Case Reports. 2014;2014:bcr2014203613. doi:10.1136/bcr-2014-203613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craighead JE, Mahoney EM, Carver DH, Nafic K, Fremont-Smith P. Orchitis due to coxsackie virus group B, type 5: report of a case with isolation of virus from the testis. N Engl J Med. 1962;267:498-500. doi:10.1056/nejm196209062671008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison RJG, Baird JP. Orchitis in bornholm disease. BMJ. 1952;1(4751):198-199. doi:10.1136/bmj.1.4751.198</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tae BS, Ham BK, Kim JH, Park JY, Bae JH. Clinical features of mumps orchitis in vaccinated postpubertal males: a single-center series of 62 patients. Korean J Urol. 2012;53(12):865-869. doi:10.4111/kju.2012.53.12.865</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wesselhoeft C. Orchitis in mumps. Boston Med Surg J. 1920;183(17):491-494. doi:10.1056/NEJM192010211831704</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wharton IP, Chaudhry AH, French ME. A case of mumps epididymitis. Lancet. 2006;367(9511):702. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68274-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willems W, Hornig C, Bauer H, Klingmüller V. Orchitis caused by coxsackie A9. Lancet. 1977;310(8052-8053):1350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Tortorec A, Matusali G, Mahé D, et al. From ancient to emerging infections: the odyssey of viruses in the male genital tract. Physiol Rev. 2020;100(3):1349-1414. doi:10.1152/physrev.00021.2019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertschat FL, Alexander M. [Infertility after mumps orchitis (author's transl)]. MMW Munch Med Wochenschr. 1981;123(15):606-608.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalal H, Bahadur G, Knowles W, Jin L, Brink N. Mumps epididymo-orchitis with prolonged detection of virus in semen and the development of anti-sperm antibodies. J Med Virol. 2004;73(1):147-150. doi:10.1002/jmv.10544</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emerson C, Dinsmore WW, Quah SP. Are we missing mumps epididymo-orchitis? Int J STD AIDS. 2007;18(5):341-342. doi:10.1258/095646207780749754</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sylvest E. A Bornholm epidemic-myositis epidemica. Ugeskr Lag. 1930;92:798-801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huss R. La myalgie epidemique en suede. Bull office internat d'hyg pub. 1934;26:1083-1098.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curnen EC. Disease resembling nonparalytic poliomyelitis associated with a virus pathogenic for infant mice. JAMA. 1949;141(13):894-901. doi:10.1001/jama.1949.02910130008003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel LN, Arciuolo RJ, Fu J, et al. Mumps outbreak among a highly vaccinated university community-New York city, January-April 2014. Clin Infect Dis. 2016;64(4):ciw762. doi:10.1093/cid/ciw762</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willocks LJ, Guerendiain D, Austin HI, et al. An outbreak of mumps with genetic strain variation in a highly vaccinated student population in Scotland. Epidemiol Infect. 2017;145(15):3219-3225. doi:10.1017/s0950268817002102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veneti L, Borgen K, Borge KS, et al. Large outbreak of mumps virus genotype G among vaccinated students in Norway, 2015 to 2016. Euro Surveill. 2018;23(38):1700642. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.es.2018.23.38.1700642</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artenstein MS. Epidemic coxsackie virus infection with mixed clinical manifestations. Ann Intern Med. 1964;60:196-203. doi:10.7326/0003-4819-60-2-196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piantadosi A, Mukerji SS, Chitneni P, et al. Metagenomic sequencing of an echovirus 30 genome from cerebrospinal fluid of a patient with aseptic meningitis and orchitis. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2017;4(3):ofx138. doi:10.1093/ofid/ofx138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerget F, Demirdöğen ŞO, Kerget B. Case report: a rare case of Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever associated with Epididymo-Orchitis. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2021;104(3):1055-1057. doi:10.4269/ajtmh.20-1143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kloping YP, Hidayatullah F, Rahman ZA, Chung E, Hakim L. Male reproductive tract involvement and sperm parameters in SARS-CoV-2 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis.World J. Men's Health. 2023;41:538. doi:10.5534/wjmh.220019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gazibera B, Gojak R, Drnda A, et al. Spermiogram part of population with the manifest orchtis during an ongoing epidemic of mumps. Med Arch. 2012;66(3 suppl 1):27-29. doi:10.5455/medarh.2012.66.s27-s29</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyu Z, Feng X, Li N, et al. Human papillomavirus in semen and the risk for Male infertility: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Infect Dis. 2017;17(1):714. doi:10.1186/s12879-017-2812-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohseni M, Mollaei HR, Arabzadeh SA, Mirshekari TR, Ghorbani P. Frequency of cytomegalovirus in fertile and infertile men, referring to Afzalipour hospital IVF research center, kerman, Iran: a case-control study. Int J Reprod Biomed. Jul 2018;16(7):443-446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SJ, Kim HC, Lim JW, Moon SK, Ahn SE. Distribution of epididymal involvement in mumps epididymo-orchitis. J Ultrasound Med. 2015;34(6):1083-1089. doi:10.7863/ultra.34.6.1083</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarantino L, Giorgio A, de Stefano G, Farella N. Echo color Doppler findings in postpubertal mumps epididymo-orchitis. J Ultrasound Med. 2001;20(11):1189-1195. doi:10.7863/jum.2001.20.11.1189</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Başekim CÇ, Kizilkaya E, Pekkafali Z, Baykal KV, Karsli AF. Mumps epididymo-orchitis: sonography and color Doppler sonographic findings. Abdom Imaging. 2000;25(3):322-325. doi:10.1007/s002610000039</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilatz A, Hudemann C, Wolf J, et al. Metabolic syndrome and the seminal cytokine network in morbidly obese males. Andrology. 2017;5(1):23-30. doi:10.1111/andr.12296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilatz A, Hossain H, Kaiser R, et al. Acute epididymitis revisited: impact of molecular diagnostics on etiology and contemporary guideline recommendations. Eur Urol. 2015;68(3):428-435. doi:10.1016/j.eururo.2014.12.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domann E, Hong G, Imirzalioglu C, et al. Culture-independent identification of pathogenic bacteria and polymicrobial infections in the genitourinary tract of renal transplant recipients. J Clin Microbiol. 2003;41(12):5500-5510. doi:10.1128/JCM.41.12.5500-5510.2003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otto W, Mankertz A, Santibanez S, et al. Ongoing outbreak of mumps affecting adolescents and young adults in Bavaria, Germany, August to October 2010. Euro Surveill. 2010;15(50):19748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeren K, Böttcher S, Diedrich S. Enterovirus surveillance (EVSurv) in Germany. Microorganisms. 2021;9(10):2005. doi:10.3390/microorganisms9102005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bohm MK, Gift TL, Tao G. Patterns of single and multiple claims of epididymitis among young privately-insured males in the United States, 2001 to 2004. Sex Transm Dis. 2009;36(8):490-492. doi:10.1097/OLQ.0b013e3181a396d8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Huang X, Yi Z, et al. Ultrasound imaging findings of acute testicular infection in patients with coronavirus disease 2019: a single-center-based study in Wuhan, China. J Ultrasound Med. 2021;40(9):1787-1794. doi:10.1002/jum.15558</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Österback R, Kuisma J, Ylipalosaari P. Epididymitis caused by coxsackievirus A6 in association with hand, foot, and mouth disease. J Clin Microbiol. 2014;52(12):4412-4413. doi:10.1128/JCM.02441-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warin JF, Davies JBM, Sanders FK, Vizoso AD. Oxford epidemic of bornholm disease, 1951. BMJ. 1953;1(4824):1345-1351. doi:10.1136/bmj.1.4824.1345</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Townes CL, Ali A, Gross N, et al. Prostate specific antigen enhances the innate defence of prostatic epithelium against Escherichia coli infection. Prostate. 2013;73(14):1529-1537. doi:10.1002/pros.22700</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Lella E, Angelini F, Campagnano S, Messineo D, Drudi FM. An unusual location of hand, foot and mouth disease. J Ultrasound. 2022;25(2):361-364. doi:10.1007/s40477-021-00558-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Somekh E, Gorenstein A, Serour F. Acute epididymitis in boys: evidence of a post-infectious etiology. J Urol. 2004;171(1):391-394. doi:10.1097/01.ju.0000102160.55494.1f</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bjorvatn B. Mumps virus recovered from testicles by fine-needle aspiration biopsy in cases of mumps orchitis. Scand J Infect Dis. 1973;5(1):3-5. doi:10.3109/inf.1973.5.issue-1.02</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hook, Jr. EW, Poole SO, Friedewald WF. Virus isolation and serologic studies on patients with clinical mumps. J Infect Dis. 1949;84(3):230-234. doi:10.1093/infdis/84.3.230</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirza M, Petersen C, Nordqvist K, Sollerbrant K. Coxsackievirus and adenovirus receptor is up-regulated in migratory germ cells during passage of the blood-testis barrier. Endocrinology. 2007;148(11):5459-5469. doi:10.1210/en.2007-0359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamieson WM, Prinsley DM. Bornholm disease in the tropics. BMJ. Jul 12 1947;2(4514):47-50. doi:10.1136/bmj.2.4514.47</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huebner RJ, Risser JA, Bell JA, Beeman EA, Beigelman PM, Strong JC. Epidemic pleurodynia in Texas; a study of 22 cases. N Engl J Med. 1953;248(7):267-274. doi:10.1056/nejm195302122480701</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torge D, Bernardi S, Arcangeli M, Bianchi S. Histopathological features of SARS-CoV-2 in extrapulmonary organ infection: a systematic review of literature. Pathogens. 2022;11(8):867. doi:10.3390/pathogens11080867</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gall EA. The histopathology of acute mumps orchitis. Am J Pathol. 1947;23(4):637-651.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilatz A, Boecker M, Schuppe HC, Diemer T, Wagenlehner F. Infektionen und infertilität. Urologe. 2016;55(7):883-889. doi:10.1007/s00120-016-0151-0</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>