<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">37417384</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enterovirus 71 enters human brain microvascular endothelial cells through an ARF6-mediated endocytic pathway.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e28915</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e28915</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.28915</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Infection of the central nervous system caused by enterovirus 71 (EV71) remains the main cause of death in hand-foot-and-mouth disease. However, the mechanism responsible for how EV71 breaks through the blood-brain barrier to infect brain cells has yet to be elucidated. By performing a high-throughput small interfering RNA (siRNA) screening and validation, we found that the infection of human brain microvascular endothelial cells (HBMECs) by EV71 was independent of the endocytosis pathways mediated by caveolin, clathrin, and macropinocytosis but dependent on ADP-ribosylation factor 6 (ARF6), a small guanosinetriphosphate (GTP)-binding protein of the Ras superfamily. The specific siRNA targeting ARF6 markedly inhibited HBMECs susceptibility to EV71. EV71 infectivity was inhibited by NAV-2729, a specific inhibitor of ARF6, in a dose-dependent manner. The subcellular analysis demonstrated the co-localization of the endocytosed EV71 and ARF6, while knockdown of ARF6 with siRNA remarkably influenced EV71 endocytosis. By immunoprecipitation assays, we found a direct interaction of ARF6 with EV71 viral protein. Furthermore, ARF1, another small GTP-binding protein, was also found to participate in ARF6-mediated EV71 endocytosis. Murine experiments demonstrated that NAV-2729 significantly alleviated mortality caused by EV71 infection. Our study revealed a new pathway by which EV71 enters the HBMECs and provides new targets for drug development.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Yongzhe</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1529-6807</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaohang</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2589-1260</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Zhiwei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Ping</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1289-326X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qi</LastName><ForeName>Zhongtian</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Naval Medicine, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000089982">ADP-Ribosylation Factor 6</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C000623233">NAV-2729</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D034741">RNA, Small Interfering</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 3.6.5.2</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C000715348">ARF6 protein, human</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000089982" MajorTopicYN="Y">ADP-Ribosylation Factor 6</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001921" MajorTopicYN="N">Brain</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D042783" MajorTopicYN="N">Endothelial Cells</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D034741" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Small Interfering</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ADP-ribosylation factor 6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">endocytosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus 71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human brain microvascular endothelial cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral entry</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37417384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Nayak G, Bhuyan SK, Bhuyan R, Sahu A, Kar D, Kuanar A. Global emergence of enterovirus 71: a systematic review. Beni Suef Univ J Basic Appl Sci. 2022;11(1):78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malekmohammad K, Rafieian-Kopaei M, Sardari S, Sewell RDE. Effective antiviral medicinal plants and biological compounds against central nervous system infections: a mechanistic review. Curr Drug Discov Technol. 2020;17(4):469-483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim ZQ, Ng QY, Oo Y, et al. Enterovirus-A71 exploits peripherin and Rac1 to invade the central nervous system. EMBO Rep. 2021;22(6):e51777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohka S, Hao Tan S, Kaneda S, Fujii T, Schiavo G. Retrograde axonal transport of poliovirus and EV71 in motor neurons. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2022;626:72-78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadry H, Noorani B, Cucullo L. A blood-brain barrier overview on structure, function, impairment, and biomarkers of integrity. Fluids Barriers CNS. 2020;17(1):69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo W, Zhong J, Zhao W, et al. Proteomic analysis of human brain microvascular endothelial cells reveals differential protein expression in response to enterovirus 71 infection. BioMed Res Int. 2015;2015:1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J, Zhao Y, Wu J, et al. Enterovirus-71 utilizes small extracellular vesicles to cross the blood-brain barrier for infecting the central nervous system via transcytosis. J Med Virol. 2023;95(1). doi:10.1002/jmv.28120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng T. Strategies for antiviral screening targeting early steps of virus infection. Virol Sin. 2010;25(4):281-293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katen LJ, Januszeski MM, Anderson WF, Hasenkrug KJ, Evans LH. Infectious entry by amphotropic as well as ecotropic murine leukemia viruses occurs through an endocytic pathway. J Virol. 2001;75(11):5018-5026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin HY, Yang YT, Yu SL, et al. Caveolar endocytosis is required for human PSGL-1-mediated enterovirus 71 infection. J Virol. 2013;87(16):9064-9076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen SL, Liu YG, Zhou YT, et al. Endophilin-A2-mediated endocytic pathway is critical for enterovirus 71 entry into Caco-2 cells. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2019;8(1):773-786.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YG, Chen Y, Wang X, Zhao P, Zhu Y, Qi Z. Ezrin is essential for the entry of Japanese encephalitis virus into the human brain microvascular endothelial cells. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2020;9(1):1330-1341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo RH, Im YJ, Shin SI, Jeong K, Rhee JH, Kim YR. Vibrio vulnificus RtxA1 cytotoxin targets filamin A to regulate PAK1- and MAPK-dependent cytoskeleton reorganization and cell death. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2019;8(1):934-945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heiska L, Carpén O. Src phosphorylates ezrin at tyrosine 477 and induces a phosphospecific association between ezrin and a kelch-repeat protein family member. J Biol Chem. 2005;280(11):10244-10252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Mao Q, Yao X, et al. Development and evaluation of a pseudovirus-luciferase assay for rapid and quantitative detection of neutralizing antibodies against enterovirus 71. PLoS One. 2013;8(6):e64116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan S, Yin X, Meng X, et al. Clofazimine broadly inhibits coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2. Nature. 2021;593(7859):418-423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniel JA, Chau N, Abdel-Hamid MK, et al. Phenothiazine-derived antipsychotic drugs inhibit dynamin and clathrin-mediated endocytosis. Traffic. 2015;16(6):635-654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao L, Liu D, Zuo S, Zhu X, Wang Y, Dong C. Urea-modulated UT-B urea transporter internalization is clathrin- and caveolae-dependent in infantile hemangioma-derived vascular endothelial cells. J Cell Biochem. 2019;120(4):5128-5136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maddila SC, Voshavar C, Arjunan P, et al. Cholesterol sequestration from caveolae/lipid rafts enhances cationic liposome-mediated nucleic acid delivery into endothelial cells. Molecules. 2021;26(15):4626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ménétrey J, Perderiset M, Cicolari J, et al. Structural basis for ARF1-mediated recruitment of ARHGAP21 to Golgi membranes. EMBO J. 2007;26(7):1953-1962.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padovani D, Folly-Klan M, Labarde A, et al. EFA6 controls Arf1 and Arf6 activation through a negative feedback loop. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2014;111(34):12378-12383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humphreys D, Davidson AC, Hume PJ, Makin LE, Koronakis V. Arf6 coordinates actin assembly through the WAVE complex, a mechanism usurped by Salmonella to invade host cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2013;110(42):16880-16885.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donaldson JG, Jackson CL. ARF family G proteins and their regulators: roles in membrane transport, development and disease. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2011;12(6):362-375.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang M, Wang X, Wang Q, et al. Molecular mechanism of SCARB2-mediated attachment and uncoating of EV71. Protein Cell. 2014;5(9):692-703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin YW, Yu SL, Shao HY, et al. Human SCARB2 transgenic mice as an infectious animal model for enterovirus 71. PLoS One. 2013;8(2):e57591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou YQ, Wang K, Wang XY, et al. SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus enters the host cells through spike protein-CD147 in an Arf6-dependent manner. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2022;11(1):1135-1144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain KM, Leong KLJ, Ng MML, Chu JJH. The essential role of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in the infectious entry of human enterovirus 71. J Biol Chem. 2011;286(1):309-321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schelhaas M. Come in and take your coat off - how host cells provide endocytosis for virus entry. Cell Microbiol. 2010;12(10):1378-1388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moghimi S, Viktorova E, Zimina A, Szul T, Sztul E, Belov GA. Enterovirus infection induces massive recruitment of all isoforms of small cellular Arf GTPases to the replication organelles. J Virol. 2020;95(2):e01629-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherfils J. Arf GTPases and their effectors: assembling multivalent membrane-binding platforms. Curr Opin Struct Biol. 2014;29:67-76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dun Y, Yan J, Wang M, et al. Rac1-dependent endocytosis and Rab5-dependent intracellular trafficking are required by enterovirus A71 and coxsackievirus A10 to establish infections. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2020;529(1):97-103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coyne CB, Kim KS, Bergelson JM. Poliovirus entry into human brain microvascular cells requires receptor-induced activation of SHP-2. EMBO J. 2007;26(17):4016-4028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamayoshi S, Iizuka S, Yamashita T, et al. Human SCARB2-dependent infection by coxsackievirus A7, A14, and A16 and enterovirus 71. J Virol. 2012;86(10):5686-5696.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>