<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37523578</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Congenital Echovirus 11 Infection in a Neonate.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1002</StartPage><EndPage>1006</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1002-1006</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004052</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Neonates infected with enterovirus in utero would be fulminant at birth or develop symptoms within a few days. Echovirus 11 causes life-threatening hepatic necrosis with coagulopathy and adrenal hemorrhagic necrosis. The prognosis depends on the enterovirus serotype and the absence of serotype-specific maternal antibodies at the time of delivery. We describe a fatal neonatal case of congenital echovirus 11 infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hirade</LastName><ForeName>Tomohiro</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8056-3756</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abe</LastName><ForeName>Yasuhiro</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ito</LastName><ForeName>Satoko</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neonatology, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suzuki</LastName><ForeName>Tadaki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katano</LastName><ForeName>Harutaka</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takahashi</LastName><ForeName>Naoto</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Tokyo Hospital, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koike</LastName><ForeName>Daisuke</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nariai</LastName><ForeName>Akiyoshi</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kato</LastName><ForeName>Fumihide</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neonatology, Shimane Prefectural Central Hospital, Shimane, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37523578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-990000000-00534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rittichier KR, Bryan PA, Bassett KE, et al. Diagnosis and outcomes of enterovirus infections in young infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:546–550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roda D, Perez-Martinez E, Cabrerizo M, et al. Clinical characteristics and molecular epidemiology of enterovirus infection in infants &lt;3 months in a referral paediatric hospital of Barcelona. Eur J Pediatr. 2015;174:1549–1553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callon D, Guedra A, Lebreil AL, et al. Fulminant myocardial involvement in neonatal echovirus-induced sepsis. two autopsy cases. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2022;41:148–150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tebruegge M, Curtis N. Enterovirus infections in neonates. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2009;14:222–227.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haston JC, Dixon TC. Nonpolio enterovirus infections in neonates. Pediatr Ann. 2015;44:e103–e107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlin JF, Polk BF, Horton P, et al. Perinatal echovirus infection: risk of transmission during a community outbreak. N Engl J Med. 1981;305:368–371.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlin JF. Perinatal echovirus infection: insights from a literature review of 61 cases of serious infection and 16 outbreaks in nurseries. Rev Infect Dis. 1986;8:918–926.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henter JI, Horne A, Arico M, et al. HLH-2004: Diagnostic and therapeutic guidelines for hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2007;48:124–131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotani O, Iwata-Yoshikawa N, Suzuki T, et al. Establishment of a panel of in-house polyclonal antibodies for the diagnosis of enterovirus infections. Neuropathology. 2015;35:107–121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki Y, Takahashi N, Yada Y, et al. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a newborn infant born to a mother with sjögren syndrome antibodies. J Perinatol. 2013;33:569–571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin TY, Kao HT, Hsieh SH, et al. Neonatal enterovirus infections: emphasis on risk factors of severe and fatal infections. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2003;22:889–894.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlin JF. Fatal echovirus 11 disease in premature neonates. Pediatrics. 1980;66:775–780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostoufizadeh M, Lack EE, Gang DL, et al. Postmortem manifestations of echovirus 11 sepsis in five newborn infants. Hum Pathol. 1983;14:818–823.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry PJ, Nagington J. Fatal infection with echovirus 11. Arch Dis Child. 1982;57:22–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ventura KC, Hawkins H, Smith MB, et al. Fatal neonatal echovirus 6 infection: autopsy case report and review of the literature. Mod Pathol. 2001;14:85–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willems A, Benne CA, Timmer A, et al. Fatal illness associated with pulmonary hypertension in a neonate caused by intrauterine echovirus 11 infection. Am J Perinatol. 2006;23:59–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meerbach A, Sauerbrei A, Meerbach W, et al. Fatal outcome of herpes simplex virus type 1-induced necrotic hepatitis in a neonate. Med Microbiol Immunol. 2006;195:101–105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandrakasan S, Filipovich AH. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: advances in pathophysiology, diagnosis, and treatment. J Pediatr. 2013;163:1253–1259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imashuku S, Ueda I, Teramura T, et al. Occurrence of haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis at less than 1 year of age: analysis of 96 patients. Eur J Pediatr. 2005;164:315–319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki N, Morimoto A, Ohga S, et al.; HLH/LCH Committee of the Japanese Society of Pediatric Hematology. Characteristics of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in neonates: a nationwide survey in Japan. J Pediatr. 2009;155:235–8.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morimoto A, Nakazawa Y, Ishii E. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: pathogenesis, diagnosis, and management. Pediatr Int. 2016;58:817–825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindamood KE, Fleck P, Narla A, et al. Neonatal enteroviral sepsis/meningoencephalitis and hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: diagnostic challenges. Am J Perinatol. 2011;28:337–346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vladescu IA, Browning WL, Thomsen IP. Massive ferritin elevation in neonatal herpes simplex virus infection: hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis or herpes simplex virus alone? J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2015;4:e48–e52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasumi T, Hori M, Hiejima E, et al. Laboratory parameters identify familial haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis from other forms of paediatric haemophagocytosis. Br J Haematol. 2015;170:532–538.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundaram SS, Alonso EM, Narkewicz MR, et al.; Pediatric Acute Liver Failure Study Group. Characterization and outcomes of young infants with acute liver failure. J Pediatr. 2011;159:813–818.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shanmugam NP, Bansal S, Greenough A, et al. Neonatal liver failure: aetiologies and management--state of the art. Eur J Pediatr. 2011;170:573–581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen CE, Yu X, Kozinetz CA, et al. Highly elevated ferritin levels and the diagnosis of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2008;50:1227–1235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu XJ, Tang YM, Song H, et al. Diagnostic accuracy of a specific cytokine pattern in hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in children. J Pediatr. 2012;160:984–90.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Huang Z, Huang M, et al. Predicting severe enterovirus 71-infected hand, foot, and mouth disease: cytokines and chemokines. Mediators Inflamm. 2020;2020:9273241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuovo G. The utility of immunohistochemistry and in situ hybridization in placental pathology. Arch Pathol Lab Med. 2006;130:979–983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muehlenbachs A, Bhatnagar J, Zaki SR. Tissue tropism, pathology and pathogenesis of enterovirus infection. J Pathol. 2015;235:217–228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Euscher E, Davis J, Holzman I, et al. Coxsackie virus infection of the placenta associated with neurodevelopmental delays in the newborn. Obstet Gynecol. 2001;98:1019–1026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Lamonte A, Oberste MS, et al. Neonatal enterovirus infections reported to the national enterovirus surveillance system in the United States, 1983-2003. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2006;25:889–893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Keyserling HL, Lee ML, et al. Neonatal enterovirus infection: virology, serology, and effects of intravenous immune globulin. Clin Infect Dis. 1995;20:1201–1206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abzug MJ, Michaels MG, Wald E, et al.; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of pleconaril for the treatment of neonates with enterovirus sepsis. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2016;5:53–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baggen J, Thibaut HJ, Strating J, et al. The life cycle of non-polio enteroviruses and how to target it. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2018;16:368–381.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>