<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37526413</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cardiac macrophages undergo dynamic changes after coxsackievirus B3 infection and promote the progression of myocarditis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29004</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29004</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29004</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Although most patients with acute viral myocarditis recover spontaneously, some patients progress to heart failure. Perturbations in innate immunity may partially explain the heterogeneity of clinical outcomes. As the most abundant immune cells in the heart, cardiac macrophages have heterogeneous origins, including embryonic-derived resident macrophages (ResMϕs) and monocyte-derived macrophages (MoMFs). However, the time course change and role of cardiac macrophage subsets has not been fully explored. In the present study, we found that BALB/c mice had prolonged MoMF accumulation and low proportions of ResMϕs that could not be restored to normal levels. MoMFs of BALB/c mice generally exhibit an M1-dominant functional phenotype. Moreover, the preferential depletion of MoMF by a C-C chemokine receptor type 2 (CCR2) inhibitor resulted in improved acute myocarditis and chronic fibrosis, as well as the recovery of ResMϕs number and reduced CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell expansion. Hence, immunomodulatory therapy that targets the balance among cardiac macrophages and modulates their function is expected to prevent the progression of cardiac injury to overt heart failure and improve adverse outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dong</LastName><ForeName>Jingwei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5904-0793</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cen</LastName><ForeName>Zhihong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2142-6495</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Quan</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5579-6614</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coronary Care Unit, Nanning First People's Hospital, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qin</LastName><ForeName>Lin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0326-842X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coronary Care Unit, Nanning First People's Hospital, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yan</LastName><ForeName>Yuluan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Feiyu</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Weifeng</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Centre of Regenerative Medicine and Medical BioResource Development and Application Co-constructed by the Province and Ministry, Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009205" MajorTopicYN="Y">Myocarditis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006321" MajorTopicYN="N">Heart</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008264" MajorTopicYN="N">Macrophages</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003384" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coxsackievirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006333" MajorTopicYN="Y">Heart Failure</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiac macrophages</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">monocyte-derived macrophages</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">resident macrophages</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral myocarditis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37526413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Pollack A, Kontorovich AR, Fuster V, Dec GW. Viral myocarditis-diagnosis, treatment options, and current controversies. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2015;12(11):670-680. doi:10.1038/nrcardio.2015.108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tschöpe C, Ammirati E, Bozkurt B, et al. Myocarditis and inflammatory cardiomyopathy: current evidence and future directions. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2021;18(3):169-193. doi:10.1038/s41569-020-00435-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto AR, Ilinykh A, Ivey MJ, et al. Revisiting cardiac cellular composition. Circ Res. 2016;118(3):400-409. doi:10.1161/circresaha.115.307778</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revelo XS, Parthiban P, Chen C, et al. Cardiac resident macrophages prevent fibrosis and stimulate angiogenesis. Circ Res. 2021;129(12):1086-1101. doi:10.1161/circresaha.121.319737</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valaperti A, Nishii M, Liu Y, et al. Innate immune interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase 4 exacerbates viral myocarditis by reducing CCR5(+) CD11b(+) monocyte migration and impairing interferon production. Circulation. 2013;128(14):1542-1554. doi:10.1161/circulationaha.113.002275</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Giusti CJ, Ure AE, Rivadeneyra L, Schattner M, Gomez RM. Macrophages and galectin 3 play critical roles in CVB3-induced murine acute myocarditis and chronic fibrosis. J Mol Cell Cardiol. 2015;85:58-70. doi:10.1016/j.yjmcc.2015.05.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anzai A, Mindur JE, Halle L, et al. Self-reactive CD4(+) IL-3(+) T cells amplify autoimmune inflammation in myocarditis by inciting monocyte chemotaxis. J Exp Med. 2019;216(2):369-383. doi:10.1084/jem.20180722</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barin JG, Baldeviano GC, Talor MV, et al. Macrophages participate in IL-17-mediated inflammation. Eur J Immunol. 2012;42(3):726-736. doi:10.1002/eji.201141737</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosser DM, Edwards JP. Exploring the full spectrum of macrophage activation. Nat Rev Immunol. 2008;8(12):958-969. doi:10.1038/nri2448</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cocker MS, Abdel-Aty H, Strohm O, Friedrich MG. Age and gender effects on the extent of myocardial involvement in acute myocarditis: a cardiovascular magnetic resonance study. Heart. 2009;95(23):1925-1930. doi:10.1136/hrt.2008.164061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNamara DM, Starling RC, Cooper LT, et al. Clinical and demographic predictors of outcomes in recent onset dilated cardiomyopathy. JACC. 2011;58(11):1112-1118. doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2011.05.033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairweather D, Rose NR. Coxsackievirus-induced myocarditis in mice: a model of autoimmune disease for studying immunotoxicity. Methods. 2007;41(1):118-122. doi:10.1016/j.ymeth.2006.07.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li K, Xu W, Guo Q, et al. Differential macrophage polarization in male and female BALB/c mice infected with coxsackievirus B3 defines susceptibility to viral myocarditis. Circ Res. 2009;105(4):353-364. doi:10.1161/circresaha.109.195230</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barcena ML, Jeuthe S, Niehues MH, et al. Sex-specific differences of the inflammatory state in experimental autoimmune myocarditis. Front Immunol. 2021;12:686384. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2021.686384</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stables MJ, Shah S, Camon EB, et al. Transcriptomic analyses of murine resolution-phase macrophages. Blood. 2011;118(26):e192-e208. doi:10.1182/blood-2011-04-345330</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epelman S, Lavine KJ, Beaudin AE, et al. Embryonic and adult-derived resident cardiac macrophages are maintained through distinct mechanisms at steady state and during inflammation. Immunity. 2014;40(1):91-104. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2013.11.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaman R, Hamidzada H, Epelman S. Exploring cardiac macrophage heterogeneity in the healthy and diseased myocardium. Curr Opin Immunol. 2021;68:54-63. doi:10.1016/j.coi.2020.09.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto D, Chow A, Noizat C, et al. Tissue-resident macrophages self-maintain locally throughout adult life with minimal contribution from circulating monocytes. Immunity. 2013;38(4):792-804. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2013.04.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yona S, Kim KW, Wolf Y, et al. Fate mapping reveals origins and dynamics of monocytes and tissue macrophages under homeostasis. Immunity. 2013;38(1):79-91. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2012.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molawi K, Wolf Y, Kandalla PK, et al. Progressive replacement of embryo-derived cardiac macrophages with age. J Exp Med. 2014;211(11):2151-2158. doi:10.1084/jem.20140639</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajpai G, Bredemeyer A, Li W, et al. Tissue resident CCR2- and CCR2+ cardiac macrophages differentially orchestrate monocyte recruitment and fate specification following myocardial injury. Circ Res. 2019;124(2):263-278. doi:10.1161/circresaha.118.314028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulz C, Perdiguero EG, Chorro L, et al. A lineage of myeloid cells independent of Myb and hematopoietic stem cells. Science. 2012;336(6077):86-90. doi:10.1126/science.1219179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajpai G, Schneider C, Wong N, et al. The human heart contains distinct macrophage subsets with divergent origins and functions. Nature Med. 2018;24(8):1234-1245. doi:10.1038/s41591-018-0059-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel B, Bansal SS, Ismahil MA, et al. CCR2(+) Monocyte-derived infiltrating macrophages are required for adverse cardiac remodeling during pressure overload. JACC: Basic Translat Sci. 2018;3(2):230-244. doi:10.1016/j.jacbts.2017.12.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu L, Ong S, Talor MV, et al. Cardiac fibroblasts mediate IL-17A-driven inflammatory dilated cardiomyopathy. J Exp Med. 2014;211(7):1449-1464. doi:10.1084/jem.20132126</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan CT, Moore JP, Budzyn K, et al. Reversal of vascular macrophage accumulation and hypertension by a CCR2 antagonist in deoxycorticosterone/salt-treated mice. Hypertension. 2012;60(5):1207-1212. doi:10.1161/hypertensionaha.112.201251</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezkalla S, Kloner RA, Khatib G, Khatib R. Beneficial effects of captopril in acute coxsackievirus B3 murine myocarditis. Circulation. 1990;81(3):1039-1046. doi:10.1161/01.cir.81.3.1039</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teichholz LE, Kreulen T, Herman MV, Gorlin R. Problems in echocardiographic volume determinations: echocardiographic-angiographic correlations in the presence or absence of asynergy. Am J Cardiol. 1976;37(1):7-11. doi:10.1016/0002-9149(76)90491-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covarrubias R, Ismahil MA, Rokosh G, et al. Optimized protocols for isolation, fixation, and flow cytometric characterization of leukocytes in ischemic hearts. Am J Physiol-Heart Circ Physiol. 2019;317(3):H658-H666. doi:10.1152/ajpheart.00137.2019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou X, Chen G, Bracamonte-Baran W, et al. The cardiac microenvironment instructs divergent monocyte fates and functions in myocarditis. Cell Rep. 2019;28(1):172-189. doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2019.06.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong NR, Mohan J, Kopecky BJ, et al. Resident cardiac macrophages mediate adaptive myocardial remodeling. Immunity. 2021;54(9):2072-2088. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2021.07.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldeviano GC, Barin JG, Talor MV, et al. Interleukin-17A is dispensable for myocarditis but essential for the progression to dilated cardiomyopathy. Circ Res. 2010;106(10):1646-1655. doi:10.1161/circresaha.109.213157</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingel K, Stephan S, Sauter M, et al. Pathogenesis of murine enterovirus myocarditis: virus dissemination and immune cell targets. J Virol. 1996;70(12):8888-8895. doi:10.1128/jvi.70.12.8888-8895.1996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofmann P, Schmidtke M, Stelzner A, Gemsa D. Suppression of proinflammatory cytokines and induction of IL-10 in human monocytes after coxsackievirus B3 infection. J Med Virol. 2001;64(4):487-498. doi:10.1002/jmv.1076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang CH, Vallejo JG, Kollias G, Mann DL. Role of the innate immune system in acute viral myocarditis. Basic Res Cardiol. 2009;104(3):228-237. doi:10.1007/s00395-008-0765-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kindermann I, Kindermann M, Kandolf R, et al. Predictors of outcome in patients with suspected myocarditis. Circulation. 2008;118(6):639-648. doi:10.1161/circulationaha.108.769489</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenzo JC, Fairweather D, Shellam GR, Lawson CM. Immunomodulation of murine cytomegalovirus-induced myocarditis in mice treated with lipopolysaccharide and tumor necrosis factor. Cell Immunol. 2001;213(1):52-61. doi:10.1006/cimm.2001.1859</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng G, Bajpai G, Ma P, et al. CCL17 aggravates myocardial injury by suppressing recruitment of regulatory T cells. Circulation. 2022;145(10):765-782. doi:10.1161/circulationaha.121.055888</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Hsiao HM, Higashikubo R, et al. Heart-resident CCR2(+) macrophages promote neutrophil extravasation through TLR9/MyD88/CXCL5 signaling. JCI Insight. 2016;1(12). doi:10.1172/jci.insight.87315</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dick SA, Macklin JA, Nejat S, et al. Self-renewing resident cardiac macrophages limit adverse remodeling following myocardial infarction. Nature Immunol. 2019;20(1):29-39. doi:10.1038/s41590-018-0272-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao X, Shen Y, Zhang R, et al. Distinct roles of resident and nonresident macrophages in nonischemic cardiomyopathy. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2018;115(20):E4661-e4669. doi:10.1073/pnas.1720065115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hulsmans M, Clauss S, Xiao L, et al. Macrophages facilitate electrical conduction in the heart. Cell. 2017;169(3):510-522. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2017.03.050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leid J, Carrelha J, Boukarabila H, Epelman S, Jacobsen SEW, Lavine KJ. Primitive embryonic macrophages are required for coronary development and maturation. Circ Res. 2016;118(10):1498-1511. doi:10.1161/circresaha.115.308270</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavine KJ, Epelman S, Uchida K, et al. Distinct macrophage lineages contribute to disparate patterns of cardiac recovery and remodeling in the neonatal and adult heart. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2014;111(45):16029-16034. doi:10.1073/pnas.1406508111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaman R, Hamidzada H, Kantores C, et al. Selective loss of resident macrophage-derived insulin-like growth factor-1 abolishes adaptive cardiac growth to stress. Immunity. 2021;54(9):2057-2071. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2021.07.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiu K, Shibata M, Nakayama Y, et al. A heart-brain-kidney network controls adaptation to cardiac stress through tissue macrophage activation. Nature Med. 2017;23(5):611-622. doi:10.1038/nm.4326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zouggari Y, Ait-Oufella H, Bonnin P, et al. B lymphocytes trigger monocyte mobilization and impair heart function after acute myocardial infarction. Nature Med. 2013;19(10):1273-1280. doi:10.1038/nm.3284</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao J, He S, Wang Y, et al. Regulatory B cells improve ventricular remodeling after myocardial infarction by modulating monocyte migration. Basic Res Cardiol. 2021;116(1):46. doi:10.1007/s00395-021-00886-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Do DC, Mu J, Ke X, et al. miR-511-3p protects against cockroach allergen-induced lung inflammation by antagonizing CCL2. JCI Insight. 2019;4(20). doi:10.1172/jci.insight.126832</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan X, Hu L, Shu Z, et al. Role of CCR2 in the development of streptozotocin-treated diabetic cardiomyopathy. Diabetes. 2019;68(11):2063-2073. doi:10.2337/db18-1231</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Xue Y, Dong D, et al. CCR2(-) and CCR2(+) corneal macrophages exhibit distinct characteristics and balance inflammatory responses after epithelial abrasion. Mucosal Immunol. 2017;10(5):1145-1159. doi:10.1038/mi.2016.139</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toor IS, Rückerl D, Mair I, et al. Enhanced monocyte recruitment and delayed alternative macrophage polarization accompanies impaired repair following myocardial infarction in C57BL/6 compared to BALB/c mice. Clin Exp Immunol. 2019;198(1):83-93. doi:10.1111/cei.13330</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epelman S, Lavine KJ, Randolph GJ. Origin and functions of tissue macrophages. Immunity. 2014;41(1):21-35. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2014.06.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidt T, Courties G, Dutta P, et al. Differential contribution of monocytes to heart macrophages in steady-state and after myocardial infarction. Circ Res. 2014;115(2):284-295. doi:10.1161/circresaha.115.303567</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leuschner F, Courties G, Dutta P, et al. Silencing of CCR2 in myocarditis. Eur Heart J. 2015;36(23):1478-1488. doi:10.1093/eurheartj/ehu225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Georgakis MK, de Lemos JA, Ayers C, et al. Association of circulating monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 levels with cardiovascular mortality: a meta-analysis of population-based studies. JAMA Cardiol. 2021;6(5):587-592. doi:10.1001/jamacardio.2020.5392</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanco-Colio LM, Méndez-Barbero N, Pello Lázaro AM, et al. MCP-1 predicts recurrent cardiovascular events in patients with persistent inflammation. J Clin Med. 2021;10(5):1137. doi:10.3390/jcm10051137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashburn NP, Snavely AC, Allen BR, et al. Monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 is not predictive of cardiac events in patients with non-low-risk chest pain. Emerg Med J. 2021. doi:10.1136/emermed-2021-211266</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu H, Chen R, Barnie PA, et al. Fibroblast transdifferentiation promotes conversion of M1 macrophages and replenishment of cardiac resident macrophages following cardiac injury in mice. Eur J Immunol. 2020;50(6):795-808. doi:10.1002/eji.201948414</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>