<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37535397</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2150-7511</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>mBio</Title><ISOAbbreviation>mBio</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Contemporary enterovirus-D68 isolates infect human spinal cord organoids.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0105823</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0105823</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e01058-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/mbio.01058-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) is a nonpolio enterovirus associated with severe respiratory illness and acute flaccid myelitis (AFM), a polio-like illness causing paralysis in children. AFM outbreaks have been associated with increased circulation and genetic diversity of EV-D68 since 2014, although the virus was discovered in the 1960s. The mechanisms by which EV-D68 targets the central nervous system are unknown. Since enteroviruses are human pathogens that do not routinely infect other animal species, establishment of a human model of the central nervous system is essential for understanding pathogenesis. Here, we describe two human spinal cord organoid (hSCO)-based models for EV-D68 infection derived from induced, pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) lines. One hSCO model consists primarily of spinal motor neurons, while the another model comprises multiple neuronal cell lineages, including motor neurons, interneurons, and glial cells. These hSCOs can be productively infected with contemporary strains, but not a historic strain, of EV-D68 and produce extracellular virus for at least 2 weeks without appreciable cytopathic effect. By comparison, infection with hSCO with another enterovirus, echovirus 11, causes significant structural destruction and apoptosis. Together, these findings suggest that EV-D68 infection is not the sole mediator of neuronal cell death in the spinal cord in those with AFM and that secondary injury from the immune response likely contributes to pathogenesis. IMPORTANCE AFM is a rare condition that causes significant morbidity in affected children, often contributing to life-long sequelae. It is unknown how EV-D68 causes paralysis in children, and effective therapeutic and preventative strategies are not available. Mice are not native hosts for EV-D68, and thus, existing mouse models use immunosuppressed or neonatal mice, mouse-adapted viruses, or intracranial inoculations. To complement existing models, we report two hSCO models for EV-D68 infection. These three-dimensional, multicellular models comprised human cells and include multiple neural lineages, including motor neurons, interneurons, and glial cells. These new hSCO models for EV-D68 infection will contribute to understanding how EV-D68 damages the human spinal cord, which could lead to new therapeutic and prophylactic strategies for this virus.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aguglia</LastName><ForeName>Gabrielle</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Coyne</LastName><ForeName>Carolyn B</ForeName><Initials>CB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1884-6309</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Duke University School of Medicine , Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dermody</LastName><ForeName>Terence S</ForeName><Initials>TS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1853-8741</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Infection, Inflammation, and Immunity (i4Kids), UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Molecular Genetics, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Williams</LastName><ForeName>John V</ForeName><Initials>JV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8377-5175</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Infection, Inflammation, and Immunity (i4Kids), UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Molecular Genetics, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Freeman</LastName><ForeName>Megan Culler</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3389-6731</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Infection, Inflammation, and Immunity (i4Kids), UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh , Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>K08 AI171177</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>mBio</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101519231</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C000629404">acute flaccid myelitis</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030016" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus D, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013116" MajorTopicYN="N">Spinal Cord</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010243" MajorTopicYN="N">Paralysis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009046" MajorTopicYN="N">Motor Neurons</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute flaccid myelitis (AFM)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus D68 (EV-D68)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human model systems</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">induced pluripotent stem cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">organoids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spinal cord organoids</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>J.V.W serves on advisory committees for GlaxoSmithKline and Quidel, which did not impact the work contained in this paper. Other authors are without conflicts.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37535397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10470749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mbio.01058-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Abzug MJ, Dominguez SR. 2016. The emergence of EVD-68. Microbiol Spectrum 4:105–119. doi:10.1128/9781555819453</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/9781555819453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27337448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Tyler KL. 2019. Enterovirus D68–associated acute flaccid myelitis. JAMA 321:831. doi:10.1001/jama.2019.1016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.1016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30768149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schieble JH, Fox VL, Lennette EH. 1967. A probable new human picornavirus associated with respiratory diseases. Am J Epidemiol 85:297–310. doi:10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a120693</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a120693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4960233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah MM, Perez A, Lively JY, Avadhanula V, Boom JA, Chappell J, Englund JA, Fregoe W, Halasa NB, Harrison CJ, Hickey RW, Klein EJ, McNeal MM, Michaels MG, Moffatt ME, Otten C, Sahni LC, Schlaudecker E, Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Staat MA, Stewart LS, Weinberg GA, Williams JV, Ng TFF, Routh JA, Gerber SI, McMorrow ML, Rha B, Midgley CM. 2021. Enterovirus D68-associated acute respiratory illness ─ new vaccine surveillance network, United States, July-November 2018-2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 70:1623–1628. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7047a1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7047a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8612514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34818320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen SJ, Winn AK, Budd AP, Prill MM, Steel J, Midgley CM, Kniss K, Burns E, Rowe T, Foust A, Jasso G, Merced-Morales A, Davis CT, Jang Y, Jones J, Daly P, Gubareva L, Barnes J, Kondor R, Sessions W, Smith C, Wentworth DE, Garg S, Havers FP, Fry AM, Hall AJ, Brammer L, Silk BJ. 2021. Changes in influenza and other respiratory virus activity during the COVID-19 pandemic - United States, 2020-2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 70:1013–1019. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7029a1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7029a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34292924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma KC, Winn A, Moline HL, Scobie HM, Midgley CM, Kirking HL, Adjemian J, Hartnett KP, Johns D, Jones JM, Lopez A, Lu X, Perez A, Perrine CG, Rzucidlo AE, McMorrow ML, Silk BJ, Stein Z, Vega E, New Vaccine Surveillance Network Collaborators, Hall AJ. 2022. Increase in acute respiratory illnesses among children and adolescents associated with rhinoviruses and enteroviruses, including enterovirus D68 - United States, July-September 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 71:1265–1270. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7140e1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7140e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9541033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36201400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC . 2020. AFM cases and outbreaks. AFM Cases and Outbreaks.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra N, Ng TFF, Marine RL, Jain K, Ng J, Thakkar R, Caciula A, Price A, Garcia JA, Burns JC, Thakur KT, Hetzler KL, Routh JA, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Nix WA, Tokarz R, Briese T, Oberste MS, Lipkin WI, Biron CA, Whitley R, Jacobson S. 2019. Antibodies to enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid of patients with acute flaccid myelitis. mBio 10:e01903-19. doi:10.1128/mBio.01903-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.01903-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6692520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31409689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schubert RD, Hawes IA, Ramachandran PS, Ramesh A, Crawford ED, Pak JE, Wu W, Cheung CK, O’Donovan BD, Tato CM, Lyden A, Tan M, Sit R, Sowa GM, Sample HA, Zorn KC, Banerji D, Khan LM, Bove R, Hauser SL, Gelfand AA, Johnson-Kerner BL, Nash K, Krishnamoorthy KS, Chitnis T, Ding JZ, McMillan HJ, Chiu CY, Briggs B, Glaser CA, Yen C, Chu V, Wadford DA, Dominguez SR, Ng TFF, Marine RL, Lopez AS, Nix WA, Soldatos A, Gorman MP, Benson L, Messacar K, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Oberste MS, DeRisi JL, Wilson MR. 2019. Pan-viral serology implicates enteroviruses in acute flaccid myelitis. Nat Med 25:1748–1752. doi:10.1038/s41591-019-0613-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-019-0613-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6858576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31636453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogt MR, Wright PF, Hickey WF, De Buysscher T, Boyd KL, Crowe JE. 2022. Enterovirus D68 in the anterior horn cells of a child with acute flaccid myelitis. N Engl J Med 386:2059–2060. doi:10.1056/NEJMc2118155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2118155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9321432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35613028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman MC, Wells AI, Ciomperlik-Patton J, Myerburg MM, Yang L, Konopka-Anstadt J, Coyne CB. 2021. Respiratory and intestinal epithelial cells exhibit differential susceptibility and innate immune responses to contemporary EV-D68 isolates. Elife 10:e66687. doi:10.7554/eLife.66687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.66687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34196272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Yu G, Leser JS, Yagi S, Clarke P, Chiu CY, Tyler KL. 2017. A mouse model of paralytic myelitis caused by enterovirus D68. PLoS Pathog 13:e1006199. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1006199</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5322875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28231269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans WJ, Hurst BL, Peterson CJ, Van Wettere AJ, Day CW, Smee DF, Tarbet EB. 2019. Development of a respiratory disease model for enterovirus D68 in 4-week-old mice for evaluation of antiviral therapies. Antiviral Res 162:61–70. doi:10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6997929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30521834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown DM, Hixon AM, Oldfield LM, Zhang Y, Novotny M, Wang W, Das SR, Shabman RS, Tyler KL, Scheuermann RH, Griffin DE, Nath A, Morrey J. 2018. Contemporary circulating enterovirus D68 strains have acquired the capacity for viral entry and replication in human neuronal cells. mBio 9:e01954-18. doi:10.1128/mBio.01954-18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.01954-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6191546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30327438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2019. Contemporary circulating enterovirus D68 strains infect and undergo retrograde axonal transport in spinal motor neurons independent of sialic acid. J Virol 93:1–39. doi:10.1128/JVI.00578-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00578-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6675884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31167912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenfeld AB, Warren AL, Racaniello VR. 2019. Neurotropism of enterovirus D68 isolates is independent of sialic acid and is not a recently acquired phenotype. mBio 10:e02370-19. doi:10.1128/mBio.02370-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.02370-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6805996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31641090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudy MJ, Coughlan C, Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2022. Density analysis of enterovirus D68 shows viral particles can associate with exosomes. Microbiol Spectr 10:e0245221. doi:10.1128/spectrum.02452-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02452-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8849102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35170992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jassey A, Wagner MA, Galitska G, Paudel B, Miller K, Jackson WT. 2023. Starvation after infection restricts enterovirus D68 replication. Autophagy 19:112–125. doi:10.1080/15548627.2022.2062888</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15548627.2022.2062888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9809931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35446171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridhar A, Depla JA, Mulder LA, Karelehto E, Brouwer L, Kruiswijk L, Vieira de Sá R, Meijer A, Evers MM, van Kuppeveld FJM, Pajkrt D, Wolthers KC. 2022. Enterovirus D68 infection in human primary airway and brain organoids: no additional role for Heparan sulfate binding for neurotropism. Microbiol Spectr 10:e0169422. doi:10.1128/spectrum.01694-22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.01694-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9603061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36154279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogura T, Sakaguchi H, Miyamoto S, Takahashi J. 2018. Three-dimensional induction of dorsal, intermediate and ventral spinal cord tissues from human pluripotent stem cells. Development 145:dev162214. doi:10.1242/dev.162214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1242/dev.162214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6124545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30061169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maury Y, Côme J, Piskorowski RA, Salah-Mohellibi N, Chevaleyre V, Peschanski M, Martinat C, Nedelec S. 2015. Combinatorial analysis of developmental cues efficiently converts human pluripotent stem cells into multiple neuronal subtypes. Nat Biotechnol 33:89–96. doi:10.1038/nbt.3049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nbt.3049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25383599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu DC, Niu T, Alaynick WA. 2015. Molecular and cellular development of spinal cord locomotor circuitry. Front Mol Neurosci 8:25. doi:10.3389/fnmol.2015.00025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnmol.2015.00025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4468382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26136656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2017. Evaluating treatment efficacy in a mouse model of enterovirus D68-associated paralytic myelitis. J Infect Dis 216:1245–1253. doi:10.1093/infdis/jix468</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jix468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5853295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28968718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Zhang X, Dai W, Liu Q, Xiong P, Wang S, Geng L, Gong S, Huang Z. 2018. A mouse model of enterovirus D68 infection for assessment of the efficacy of inactivated vaccine. Viruses 10:58–13. doi:10.3390/v10020058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v10020058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29385753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morosky S, Wells AI, Lemon K, Evans AS, Schamus S, Bakkenist CJ, Coyne CB. 2019. The neonatal FC receptor is a pan-echovirus receptor. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 116:3758–3763. doi:10.1073/pnas.1817341116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1817341116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6397586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30808762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf BB, Green DR. 1999. Suicidal tendencies: apoptotic cell death by caspase family proteinases. J Biol Chem 274:20049–20052. doi:10.1074/jbc.274.29.20049</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.29.20049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10400609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porter AG, Jänicke RU. 1999. Emerging roles of Caspase-3 in apoptosis. 2. Cell Death Differ 6:99–104. doi:10.1038/sj.cdd.4400476</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.cdd.4400476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10200555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyrylkova K, Kyryachenko S, Leid M, Kioussi C. 2012. Detection of apoptosis by TUNEL assay, p 41–47. In Kioussi C (ed), Odontogenesis: methods and protocols. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ. doi:10.1007/978-1-61779-860-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-61779-860-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22566045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simian M, Bissell MJ. 2017. Organoids: a historical perspective of thinking in three dimensions. J Cell Biol 216:31–40. doi:10.1083/jcb.201610056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1083/jcb.201610056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5223613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28031422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato T, Vries RG, Snippert HJ, van de Wetering M, Barker N, Stange DE, van Es JH, Abo A, Kujala P, Peters PJ, Clevers H. 2009. Single Lgr5 stem cells build crypt-villus structures in vitro without a mesenchymal niche. Nature 459:262–265. doi:10.1038/nature07935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature07935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19329995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi K, Tanabe K, Ohnuki M, Narita M, Ichisaka T, Tomoda K, Yamanaka S. 2007. Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors. Cell 131:861–872. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2007.11.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.11.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18035408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winanto, Khong Z-J, Hor J-H, Ng S-Y. 2019. Spinal cord organoids add an extra dimension to traditional motor neuron cultures. Neural Regen Res 14:1515–1516. doi:10.4103/1673-5374.255966</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.255966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6557099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31089045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J-H, Shin H, Shaker MR, Kim HJ, Park S-H, Kim JH, Lee N, Kang M, Cho S, Kwak TH, Kim JW, Song M-R, Kwon S-H, Han DW, Lee S, Choi S-Y, Rhyu IJ, Kim H, Geum D, Cho I-J, Sun W. 2022. Production of human spinal-cord organoids recapitulating neural-tube morphogenesis. Nat Biomed Eng 6:435–448. doi:10.1038/s41551-022-00868-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41551-022-00868-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35347276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira JD, DuBreuil DM, Devlin A-C, Held A, Sapir Y, Berezovski E, Hawrot J, Dorfman K, Chander V, Wainger BJ. 2021. Human sensorimotor organoids derived from healthy and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis stem cells form neuromuscular junctions. Nat Commun 12:4744. doi:10.1038/s41467-021-24776-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24776-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8346474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hor JH, Soh E-Y, Tan LY, Lim VJW, Santosa MM, Ho BX, Fan Y, Soh B-S, Ng S-Y. 2018. Cell cycle inhibitors protect motor neurons in an organoid model of spinal muscular atrophy. Cell Death Dis 9:1100. doi:10.1038/s41419-018-1081-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41419-018-1081-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6204135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30368521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcez PP, Loiola EC, Madeiro da Costa R, Higa LM, Trindade P, Delvecchio R, Nascimento JM, Brindeiro R, Tanuri A, Rehen SK. 2016. Zika virus impairs growth in human neurospheres and brain organoids. Science 352:816–818. doi:10.1126/science.aaf6116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aaf6116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27064148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Chen Z, Zhang X, Li S, Hui Y, Feng H, Du Y, Jin G, Zhou X, Zhang X. 2019. Protection of ZIKV infection-induced neuropathy by abrogation of acute antiviral response in human neural progenitors. Cell Death Differ 26:2607–2621. doi:10.1038/s41418-019-0324-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41418-019-0324-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7224299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30952992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kidd S, Lopez A, Nix WA, Anyalechi G, Itoh M, Yee E, Oberste MS, Routh J. 2020. Vital signs: clinical characteristics of patients with confirmed acute flaccid Myelitis, United States, 2018. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 69:1031–1038. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm6931e3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6931e3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7454900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32759919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeh MT, Capponi S, Catching A, Bianco S, Andino R. 2020. Mapping attenuation determinants in enterovirus-D68. Viruses 12:867. doi:10.3390/v12080867</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v12080867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7472100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32784424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright PF, Ikizler MR, Gonzales RA, Carroll KN, Johnson JE, Werkhaven JA. 2005. Growth of respiratory syncytial virus in primary epithelial cells from the human respiratory tract. J Virol 79:8651–8654. doi:10.1128/JVI.79.13.8651-8654.2005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.79.13.8651-8654.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1143745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15956607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Peeples ME, Boucher RC, Collins PL, Pickles RJ. 2002. Respiratory syncytial virus infection of human airway epithelial cells is polarized, specific to ciliated cells, and without obvious cytopathology. J Virol 76:5654–5666. doi:10.1128/jvi.76.11.5654-5666.2002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.76.11.5654-5666.2002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC137037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11991994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daley JK, Gechman LA, Skipworth J, Rall GF. 2005. Poliovirus replication and spread in primary neuron cultures. Virology 340:10–20. doi:10.1016/j.virol.2005.05.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2005.05.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16009390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belov GA, Romanova LI, Tolskaya EA, Kolesnikova MS, Lazebnik YA, Agol VI. 2003. The major apoptotic pathway activated and suppressed by poliovirus. J Virol 77:45–56. doi:10.1128/jvi.77.1.45-56.2003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jvi.77.1.45-56.2003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC140567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12477809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Yang S, Liu S, Chen Y, Liu H, Su Y, Liu R, Cui Y, Song Y, Teng Y, Wang T. 2021. Transcriptomic profiling reveals a role for TREM-1 activation in enterovirus D68 infection-induced proinflammatory responses. Front Immunol 12:749618. doi:10.3389/fimmu.2021.749618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.749618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8650217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34887856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morosky S, Lennemann NJ, Coyne CB. 2016. Bpifb6 regulates secretory pathway trafficking and enterovirus replication. J Virol 90:5098–5107. doi:10.1128/JVI.00170-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00170-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4859712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26962226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Nix WA, Maher K, Pallansch MA. 2003. Improved molecular identification of enteroviruses by RT-PCR and amplicon sequencing. J Clin Virol 26:375–377. doi:10.1016/s1386-6532(03)00004-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s1386-6532(03)00004-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12637088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekkers JF, Alieva M, Wellens LM, Ariese HCR, Jamieson PR, Vonk AM, Amatngalim GD, Hu H, Oost KC, Snippert HJG, Beekman JM, Wehrens EJ, Visvader JE, Clevers H, Rios AC. 2019. High-resolution 3D imaging of fixed and cleared organoids. Nat Protoc 14:1756–1771. doi:10.1038/s41596-019-0160-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41596-019-0160-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31053799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>