<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37521225</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2229-5178</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Season>Jul-Aug</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Indian dermatology online journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Indian Dermatol Online J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease (HFMD) in India: A Review on Clinical Manifestations, Molecular Epidemiology, Pathogenesis, and Prevention.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>475</StartPage><EndPage>481</EndPage><MedlinePgn>475-481</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/idoj.idoj_423_22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>HFMD is a childhood viral disease initiated by enteroviruses (EVs). Symptoms are initiated with mild-to-moderate fever of short duration followed by oral and skin lesions. Skin lesions are papulovesicular which appears on palms/soles of feet, hands, knees, and elbows. Oral lesions appear as vesicles producing multiple small superficial ulcers. Disease is usually mild illness but sometimes progresses in severe form as meningitis, encephalitis, and polio-like paralysis. Etiological agents of the disease belong to <i>Picornaviridae</i> family. The causative viral agents are from genus human enterovirus (HEV) such as enterovirus-A 71 (EV-A71), coxsackievirus -A6 (CV-A6), CV-A10, CV-A16. Coxsackievirus A-16 (CV-A16) and enterovirus A-71 (EV-A71) are the major etiological agents of this disease, among children reported globally. In India, studies conducted on HFMD cases revealed CV-A16 as a major EV type and under circulation over a period of time. Molecular studies of different CV-A16 isolates and the viral kinetic studies conducted on organ tissues of experimental mouse model with complete VP1 gene sequencing revealed presence of B1c sub genotype which is currently in circulation. Genetic changes observed at nucleotide and amino acid level in vital organs of experimental infected mice model might predict some targets and can act as markers of virulence. Mice infected with CV-A16 strains revealed progressive pathological changes in mice organs. Major affected organs were to be as brain, heart, intestine, and skeletal muscles. The present review focuses on HFMD caused by CV-A16 with epidemiological, molecular, pathogenesis and need of antivirals against the disease.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2023 Indian Dermatology Online Journal.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tikute</LastName><ForeName>Sanjaykumar</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Viruses Group, ICMR-National Institute of Virology, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lavania</LastName><ForeName>Mallika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Viruses Group, ICMR-National Institute of Virology, Pune, Maharashtra, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Indian Dermatol Online J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101586880</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2229-5178</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackievirus A-16</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HFMD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus A-71</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37521225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10373810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/idoj.idoj_423_22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">IDOJ-14-475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wong SSY, Yip CCY, Lau SKP, Yuen KY. Human enterovirus 71 and hand, foot and mouth disease. Epidemiol Infect. 2010;138(8):1071–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20056019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pallansch MA, Roos RP. Fields Virology. 4th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp;Wilkins; Philadelphia: 2001. pp. 723–775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan F, Yang T, Ma K, Jin Y, Song S, Fontaine RE. Risk factors of hand, foot and mouth disease and herpangia and the preventive effect of hand-washing. Pediatrics. 2011;127:e898–904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21422083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Press Release. 2009.  Available from:www.wpro.who.int/media_centre/news/news_20090713.htm) </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saoji VA. Hand foot and mouth disease: Emerging epidemics. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol. 2008;74:503–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19052420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterback R, Koskinen S, Merilahti P, Pursiheimo J-P, Blomqvist S, Roivainen M, et al. Genome sequence of coxsackievirus A6, isolated during a hand-foot-and-mouth disease outbreak in Finland in 2008. Gen Announc. 2014;2:e01004–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4200147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25323709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kar BR, Dwibedi B, Kar SK. An outbreak of hand, foot and mouth disease in Bhubaneshwar, Odisa. Indian Pediatr. 2013;50:139–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22728634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi MH, Wong SC, Podin Y, Akin W, Sel S, Mohan A. Human enterovirus 71 disease in Sarawak, Malaysia: A prospective clinical, virological and molecular epidemiological study. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;44:646–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17278054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esporito S, Principi N. Hand, foot and mouth disease: Current knowledge on clinical manifestations, epidemiology, aetiology and prevention. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2018;37:391–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29411190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho M, Chen ER, Hsu KH, Twu SJ, Chen KT, Tsai SF, et al. An epidemic of enterovirus 71 infection in Taiwan. Tiwan Enterovirus Epidemic Working Group. N Engl J Med. 1999;341:929–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10498487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SM, Liu CC, Tseng HW, Wang JR, Huang CC, Chen YJ, et al. Clinical spectrum of enterovirus 71 infection in children in Southern Taiwan with an emphasis on neurological complications. Clin Infect Dis. 1999;29:184–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10433583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu SL, Pan H, Liu P, Amer S, Chan TC, Zhan J. Comparative epidemiology and virology of fatal and nonfatal cases of hand, foot and mouth disease in mainland China from 2008 to 2014. Rev Med Virol. 2014;25:115–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25704797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goto K, Sanefuji M, Kusuhara K, Nishimura Y, Shimizu H, Kira R, et al. Rhombencephalitis and coxsackievirus A16. Emerg Infect Dis. 2009;15:1689–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2866411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19861078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright HT, Jr, Langing BH, Lennette EH, McAllister RM. Fatal infection in an infant associated with Coxsackie virus group A, type 16. N Engl J Med. 1963;268:1041–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14001956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferson MJ, Bell SM. Outbreak of Coxsackievirus A16 hand, foot, and mouth disease in a child day-care center. Am J Public Health. 1991;81:1675–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1405294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1746672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bendig JW, Fleming DM. Epidemiological, virological, and clinical features of an epidemic of hand, foot, and mouth disease in England and Wales. Commun Dis Rep CDR Rev. 1996;6:R81–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8664928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ang LW, Koh BK, Chan KP, Chua LT, James L, Goh KT. Epidemiology and control of hand, foot and mouth disease in Singapore, 2001-2007. Ann Acad Med Singap. 2009;38:106–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19271036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo DH, Luchs A, Machado BC, de Cássia Carmona R, do Carmo Sampaio Timenetsky M. Echovirus 4 associated to hand, foot and mouth disease. Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo. 2006;48:197–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17119674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Z, Xu WB, Xu AQ, Wang HY, Zhang Y, Song LZ, et al. Molecular epidemiological analysis of echovirus 19 isolated from an outbreak associated with Hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) in Shandong Province of china. Biomed Environ Sci. 2007;20:321–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17948768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishimaru Y, Nakano S, Yamaoka K, Takami S. Outbreaks of hand, foot, and mouth disease by enterovirus 71. High incidence of complication disorders of central nervous system. Arch Dis Child. 1980;55:583–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1627055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6254449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson CR, Doane FW, Rhodes AJ. Report of an outbreak of febrile illness with pharyngeal lesions and exanthem: Toronto, summer 1957- Isolation of group A Coxsackie virus. Canad Med Assoc J. 1958;79:615–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1830188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13585281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh KT, Doraisingham S, Tan JL, Lim GN, Chew SE. An outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Singapore. Bull World Health Organ. 1982;60:965–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2535982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6297819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua KB, Kasri AR. Hand foot and mouth disease due to enterovirus 71 in Malaysia. Virol Sin. 2011;26:221–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8222466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21847753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang LY. Enterovirus 71 in Taiwan. Pediatr Neonatol. 2008;49:103–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19054914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasidharan CK, Sugathan P, Agarwal R, Khare S, Lal S, Jayaram Paniker CK. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Calicut. Indian J Pediatr. 2005;72:17–21. doi:10.1007/BF02760573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15684442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora S, Arora G, Tiwari V. Hand foot and mouth disease: Emerging epidemics. Indian J Der Ven Lep. 2008;74:503–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19052420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopalkrishna V, Patil PR, Patil GP, Chitambar SD. Circulation of multiple enterovirus serotypes causing hand, foot and mouth disease in India. J Med Microbiol. 2012;61:420–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22052995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijayaraghavan PM, Chandy S, Selvaraj K, Pulimood S, Abraham AM. Virological investigation of hand, foot, and mouth disease in a tertiary care center in South India. J Glob Infect Dis. 2012;4:153–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3459432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23055646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao DC, Naidu JR, Maiya PP, Babu A, Bailly J-L. Large-scale HFMD epidemics caused by Coxsackievirus A16 in Bangalore, India during 2013 and 2015. Infect Genet Evol. 2017;55:228–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28864155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganorkar NN, Patil PR, Tikute SS, Gopalkrishna V. Genetic characterization of enterovirus strains identified in Hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD): Emergence of B1c, C1 subgenotypes, E2 sublineage of CVA16, EV71 and CVA6 strains in India. Infect Genet Evol. 2017;54:192–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28577914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma A, Mahajan VK, Mehta KS, Chauhan PS, Manvi S, Chauhan A. Hand, foot and mouth disease: A single centre retrospective study of 403 new cases and brief review of relevant indian literature to understand clinical, epidemiological, and virological attributes of a long-lasting Indian epidemic. Indian Dermatol Online J. 2022;13:310–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9549533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36226004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pallansch MA, Roos RP. Enteroviruses: Polioviruses, coxsackieviruses, echoviruses, and newer enteroviruses. In: Knipe DM, Howley PM, editors. Fields Virology. 4th ed. Chapter 24. Vol. 1. Lippincott Williams &amp;Wilkins; Philadelphia: 2007. pp. 796–839.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zoll GJ, Melchers WJ, Kopecka H, Jambroes G, van der Poel HJ, Galama JM. General primer-mediated polymerase chain reaction for detection of enteroviruses: Application for diagnostic routine and persistent infections. J Clin Microbiol. 1992;30:160–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC265013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1370845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmid NJ, Lennette EH, Ho HH. An apparently new enterovirus isolated from patients with disease of the central nervous system. J Infect Dis. 1974;129:304–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4361245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt NJ, Ho HH, Lennette EH. Propagation and isolation of group A coxsackieviruses in RD cells. J Clin Microbiol. 1975;2:183–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC274168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1176625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray Patrick R., Rosenthal Ken S, Pfaller Michael A. Medical Microbiology. 8th ed. Chapter 39. ELSEIVER; Philadelpheia, PA: 2015. Laboratory Diagnosis of Viral Diseases; pp. 392–399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y-F, Chou C-T, Lei H-Y, Liu C-C, Wang S-M, Yan J-J, et al. A mouse-adapted enterovirus 71 strain causes neurological disease in mice after oral infection. J Virol. 2004;78:7916–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC446098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15254164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Q, Shi J, Huang X, Liu F, Cai Y, Lan K, et al. A murine model of coxsackievirus A16 infection for anti-viral evaluation. Antiviral Res. 2014;105:26–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24583030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tikute SS, Wangikar PB, Varanasi G. Pathological and molecular studies on Coxsackie virus A-16 isolated from hand, foot, and mouth disease cases in India: Approach using neonatal mouse model. J Med Virol. 2019;91:1765–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31237683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan S, Yang F, Li Y, Zhao Y, Shi L, Qin M, et al. Pathogenic analysis of coxsackievirus A10 in rhesus macaques. Virol Sin. 2022;37:610–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9437613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35777657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damle DK. Oral acyclovir for severe hand, foot and mouth disease. Indian J Drugs Dermatol. 2018;4:73–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F, Liu Q, Cai Y, Leng Q, Haung Z. Construction and characterization of an infectious clone of coxsackievirus A16. Virol J. 2011;8:534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3283524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22165961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai Y, Liu Q, Huang X, Li D, Ku Z, Zhang Y, et al. Active immunization with a coxsackievirus A16 experimental inactivated vaccine induces neutralizing antibodies and protects mice against lethal infection. Vaccine. 2013;31:2215–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23499596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q, Wang Y, Gao R, Shao J, Yao X, Lang S, et al. A neonatal mouse model of coxsackievirus A16 for vaccine evaluation. J Virol. 2012;86:11967–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3486452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22951825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q, Wang Y, Yao X, Bian L, Wu X, Xu M, et al. Coxsackievirus A16: Epidemiology, diagnosis, and vaccine. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2014;10:360–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4185891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24231751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gopalkrishna V, Ganorkar N. Epidemiological and molecular characteristics of circulating CVA16, CVA6 strains and genotype distribution in hand, foot and mouth disease cases in 2017 to 2018 from Western India. J Med Virol. 2021;93:3572–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32833231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>