<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37589456</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enterovirus Central Nervous System Infection in Infancy, the Value of Routine Testing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1031</StartPage><EndPage>1034</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1031-1034</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004072</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Human nonpolio enterovirus (EV) is a major cause of infection in neonates and infants; however, the clinical presentation and cerebrospinal fluid findings vary significantly. Infection caused by EV in patients under 1 year of age can present with a broad clinical spectrum, from fever to severe systemic and/or neurological disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">Retrospective cohort analysis of infants with EV central nervous system (CNS) infection presenting to a tertiary center between January 2017 and December 2022. We recorded patient demographics, parent-reported symptoms at presentation, and blood and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) testing at presentation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Seventy-eight patients were included in the final study. Forty-one percent of infants with an EV CNS infection had a normal CSF white blood cell count. Clinical presentation was similar in infants with and without CSF pleocytosis. Median C-reactive protein was higher in cases of EV CNS infection without pleocytosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">EV CNS infection commonly presents without CSF pleocytosis. Testing for EV should be considered in febrile infants with no source regardless of CSF parameters.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giva</LastName><ForeName>Sheiniz</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Infectious Diseases, Children's Health Ireland at Temple Street and Crumlin, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barry</LastName><ForeName>Rachel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Virus Reference Laboratory, University College Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Drew</LastName><ForeName>Richard J</ForeName><Initials>RJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Irish Meningitis and Sepsis Reference Laboratory, Children's Health Ireland at Temple St.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Innovation Unit, Rotunda Hospital.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Geoghegan</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7980-5068</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Infectious Diseases, Children's Health Ireland at Temple Street and Crumlin, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007964" MajorTopicYN="N">Leukocytosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000134" MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002494" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37589456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202312000-00001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Maher K, Kilpatrick DR, et al. Molecular evolution of the human enteroviruses: correlation of serotype with VP1 sequence and application to picornavirus classification. J Virol. 1999;73:1941–1948.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enterovirus (Nonpoliovirus) (Group A and B Coxsackieviruses, Echoviruses, Numbered Enteroviruses). Redbook: 2021 Report of the Committee on Infectious Diseases, 32nd Edition</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom SC, van Furth MA, Peeters MF, et al. Characteristics of pediatric patients with enterovirus meningitis and no cerebral fluid pleocytosis. Eur J Pediatr. 2011;171:795–800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lafolie J, Labbé A, L’Honneur AS, et al.; Blood Enterovirus Diagnosis Infection (BLEDI) in paediatric population study team. Assessment of Blood Enterovirus PCR testing in paediatric populations with fever without source, sepsis-like disease, or suspected meningitis: a prospective, multicentre, observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18:1385–1396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko Y, Jeon W, Chae MK, et al. Clinical characteristics of enteroviral meningitis without pleocytosis in children: a retrospective single center observational study in the Republic of Korea. BMC Pediatr. 2014;19:335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallace SS, Lopez MA, Caviness AC. Impact of enterovirus testing on resource use in Febrile young infants: a systematic review. Hosp Pediatr. 2017;7:96–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blachez M, Boussier J, Mariani P, et al. Detection of enterovirus in cerebrospinal fluids without pleocytosis in febrile infants under 3 months old reduces antibiotherapy duration. Front Pediatr. 2023;11:1122460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barry R, Dempsey C, Barry L, et al. On-site multiplex PCR for CSF diagnostics in an acute hospital versus referral to reference laboratories: assessing economic factors, length of stay and antimicrobial stewardship. J Infect. 2021;82:414–451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramgopal S. New AAP guidelines for evaluation and treatment of infants 8-60 days old. J Pediatr. 2021;238:338–342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overview: Fever in under 5S: Assessment and initial management: Guidance. [Internet]. cited Jun 7, 2023. Available at: https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/NG143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindström J, Elfving K, Lindh M, et al. Assessment of the FilmArray me panel in 4199 consecutively tested cerebrospinal fluid samples. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2022;28:79–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanella M-C, Cherkaoui A, Hinic V, et al. Unexpectedly high false-positive rates for haemophilus influenzae using a meningoencephalitis syndromic PCR panel in two tertiary centers. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2021;11:639658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kupila L, Vuorinen T, Vainionpaa R, et al. Diagnosis of enteroviral meningitis by use of polymerase chain reaction of cerebrospinal fluid, stool, and serum specimens. Clin Infect Dis. 2005;40:982–987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myocarditis (acute infective) - united kingdom. [Internet]. World Health Organization. cited Jun 7, 2023. Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2023-DON465</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grapin M, Mirand A, Pinquier D, et al. Severe and fatal neonatal infections linked to a new variant of echovirus 11, France, July 2022 to April 2023. Euro Surveill. 2023;28:2300253.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>