<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37594153</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-0496</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>58</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pediatric pulmonology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Pulmonol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The changing virology and trends in resource utilization for bronchiolitis since COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3171</StartPage><EndPage>3178</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3171-3178</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ppul.26640</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Bronchiolitis is a viral respiratory illness most commonly caused by respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). COVID-19 disrupted typical patterns of viral transmission. Our study aimed to compare low value care for bronchiolitis in a tertiary emergency department (ED) in the United States from March 2017 to March 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">This was a descriptive cohort study through a retrospective chart review from 2017 to 2022 analyzing ED visits for bronchiolitis including disposition, disease severity, chest radiographs, albuterol, and high flow nasal cannula usage. A year was a 12-month period from March to February.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">From 2017 to 2020, there were over 2000 ED visits for bronchiolitis per year (3.1% of all ED visits), which decreased to 450 visits for bronchiolitis (1%) in 2020-2021. Human rhino/enterovirus was the most common virus detected (92%) at that time, and admission rates, albuterol, high flow nasal cannula, and chest radiographs were all higher. The summer of 2021 had the highest visits across the 5-study years with a return to previous rates of resource utilization.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Bronchiolitis ED visits due to RSV dramatically reduced during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020, with over 80% reduction in bronchiolitis visits from 2018 to 2019. While all ED visits fell in 2020, the proportion of visits due to bronchiolitis also decreased. There was an increase in lower value care during the rhinovirus dominant, low census period. As restrictions lifted in 2021, there was a large resurgence of RSV in the atypical summer months with a return of previous rates of resource utilization.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burks</LastName><ForeName>Allison</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>King</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Orr</LastName><ForeName>Mary</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1727-799X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Pulmonol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8510590</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1099-0496</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>QF8SVZ843E</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000420">Albuterol</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018357" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001988" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bronchiolitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018113" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Syncytial Virus, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000420" MajorTopicYN="N">Albuterol</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RSV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bronchiolitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">low-value care</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37594153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ppul.26640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Subcommittee on Diagnosis and Management of Bronchiolitis. Diagnosis and management of bronchiolitis. Pediatrics. 2006;118(4):1774-1793. doi:10.1542/peds.2006-2223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph MM, Edwards A. Acute bronchiolitis: assessment and management in the emergency department. Pediatr Emerg Med Pract. 2019;16(10):1-24. https://www.ebmedicine.net/topics/respiratory/pediatric-bronchiolitis</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ralston SL, Lieberthal AS, Meissner HC, et al. Clinical practice guideline: the diagnosis, management, and prevention of bronchiolitis. Pediatrics. 2014;134(5):e1474-e1502. doi:10.1542/peds.2014-2742</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curatola A, Lazzareschi I, Bersani G, Covino M, Gatto A, Chiaretti A. Impact of COVID-19 outbreak in acute bronchiolitis: lesson from a tertiary Italian emergency department. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2021;56(8):2484-2488. doi:10.1002/ppul.25442</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenmoe S, Kengne-Nde C, Ebogo-Belobo JT, Mbaga DS, Fatawou Modiyinji A, Njouom R. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the prevalence of common respiratory viruses in children &lt; 2 years with bronchiolitis in the pre-COVID-19 pandemic era. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(11):e0242302. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0242302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelletier JH, Au AK, Fuhrman D, Clark RSB, Horvat C. Trends in bronchiolitis ICU admissions and ventilation practices: 2010-2019. Pediatrics. 2021;147(6):e2020039115. doi:10.1542/peds.2020-039115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franklin D, Babl FE, Schlapbach LJ, et al. A randomized trial of high-flow oxygen therapy in infants with bronchiolitis. N Engl J Med. 2018;378(12):1121-1131. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa1714855</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kepreotes E, Whitehead B, Attia J, et al. High-flow warm humidified oxygen versus standard low-flow nasal cannula oxygen for moderate bronchiolitis (HFWHO RCT): an open, phase 4, randomised controlled trial. The Lancet. 2017;389(10072):930-939. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30061-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byrd C, Noelck M, Kerns E, et al. Multicenter study of high-flow nasal cannula initiation and duration of use in bronchiolitis. Hospital pediatrics. 2023;13(4):69. doi:10.1542/hpeds.2022-006965</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeLaroche AM, Rodean J, Aronson PL, et al. Pediatric emergency department visits at US Children's Hospitals during the COVID-19 pandemic. Pediatrics. 2020;147(4):e2020039628. doi:10.1542/peds.2020-039628</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldman RD, Grafstein E, Barclay N, Irvine MA, Portales-Casamar E. Paediatric patients seen in 18 emergency departments during the COVID-19 pandemic. Emergency medicine journal: EMJ. 2020;37(12):773-777. doi:10.1136/emermed-2020-210273</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedrich F, Ongaratto R, Scotta MC, et al. Early impact of social distancing in response to COVID-19 on hospitalizations for acute bronchiolitis in infants in Brazil. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72(12):2071-2075. doi:10.1093/cid/ciaa1458</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moscovich DP, Averbuch D, Kerem E, et al. Pediatric respiratory admissions and related viral infections during the COVID-19 pandemic. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2023;58(7):2076-2084. doi:10.1002/ppul.26434</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flores-Pérez P, Gerig N, Cabrera-López MI, de Unzueta-Roch JL, Del Rosal T, Calvo C. Acute bronchiolitis during the COVID-19 pandemic. Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin (Engl Ed). 2022;40(10):572-575. doi:10.1016/j.eimc.2021.06.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trenholme A, Webb R, Lawrence S, et al. COVID-19 and infant hospitalizations for seasonal respiratory virus infections, New Zealand, 2020. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27(2):641-643. doi:10.3201/eid2702.204041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Brusselen D, De Troeyer K, Ter Haar E, et al. Bronchiolitis in COVID-19 times: a nearly absent disease? Eur J Pediatr. 2021;180(6):1969-1973. doi:10.1007/s00431-021-03968-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabbone I, Monzani A, Scaramuzza AE, Cavalli C. See-sawing COVID-19 and RSV bronchiolitis in children under 2 years of age in Northern Italy. Acta Paediatr (Stockholm). 2022;111(11):2174-2175. doi:10.1111/apa.16512</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risso FM, Cozzi G, Volonnino M, et al. Social distancing during the COVID-19 pandemic resulted in a marked decrease in hospitalisations for bronchiolitis. Acta Paediatr (Stockholm). 2022;111:163-164. doi:10.1111/apa.16075</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castagno E, Raffaldi I, Del Monte F, Garazzino S, Bondone C. New epidemiological trends of respiratory syncytial virus bronchiolitis during COVID-19 pandemic. World Journal of Pediatrics. 2023;19(5):502-504. doi:10.1007/s12519-022-00623-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeoh DK, Foley DA, Minney-Smith CA, et al. The impact of COVID-19 public health measures on detections of influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in children during the 2020 Australian winter. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72(12):2199-2202. doi:10.1093/cid/ciaa1475</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilder JL, Parsons CR, Growdon AS, Toomey SL, Mansbach JM. Pediatric hospitalizations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Pediatrics. 2020;146(6):e2020005983. doi:10.1542/peds.2020-005983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei M, Yuan J, Liu Y, Fu T, Yu X, Zhang ZJ. Novel coronavirus infection in hospitalized infants under 1 year of age in China. JAMA. 2020;323(13):1313-1314. doi:10.1001/jama.2020.2131</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buendía JA, Feliciano-Alfonso JE, Laverde MF. Systematic review and meta-analysis of efficacy and safety of continuous positive airways pressure versus high flow oxygen cannula in acute bronchiolitis. BMC Pediatr. 2022;22(1):696. doi:10.1186/s12887-022-03754-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggerstaff S, Markham JL, Winer JC, Richardson T, Berg KJ. Impact of high flow nasal cannula on resource utilization in bronchiolitis. Hosp Pediatr. 2021;e2021005846. doi:10.1542/hpeds.2021-005846</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews C, L Maxwell S, Kerns E, McCulloh R, Alverson B. The association of seasonality with resource use in a large national cohort of infants with bronchiolitis. Hospital Pediatrics. 2021;11(2):126-134. doi:10.1542/hpeds.2020-0120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shanahan KH, Monuteaux MC, Bachur RG. Severity of illness in bronchiolitis amid unusual seasonal pattern during the COVID-19 pandemic. Hospital Pediatrics. 2022;12(4):e119-e123. doi:10.1542/hpeds.2021-006405</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghirardo S, Cozzi G, Tonin G, et al. Increased use of high-flow nasal cannulas after the pandemic in bronchiolitis: a more severe disease or a changed physician's attitude? Eur J Pediatr. 2022;181(11):3931-3936. doi:10.1007/s00431-022-04601-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghirardo S, Ullmann N, Ciofi Degli Atti ML, Raponi M, Cutrera R. Delayed season's onset and reduction of incidence of bronchiolitis during COVID-19 pandemic. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2021;56(8):2780-2781. doi:10.1002/ppul.25461</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Rose DU, Caoci S, Auriti C, et al. Lessons from SARS-CoV-2 pandemics: how restrictive measures impacted the trend of respiratory infections in neonates and infants up to three months of age. Pathogens. 2022;11(10):1086. doi:10.3390/pathogens11101086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Daleno C, Tagliabue C, et al. Impact of rhinoviruses on pediatric community-acquired pneumonia. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2012;31(7):1637-1645. doi:10.1007/s10096-011-1487-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandini S, Biagi C, Fischer M, Lanari M. Impact of rhinovirus infections in children. Viruses. 2019;11(6):521. doi:10.3390/v11060521</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson DJ, Gangnon RE, Evans MD, et al. Wheezing rhinovirus illnesses in early life predict asthma development in high-risk children. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2008;178(7):667-672. doi:10.1164/rccm.200802-309OC</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotaniemi-Syrjänen A, Vainionpää R, Reijonen TM, Waris M, Korhonen K, Korppi M. Rhinovirus-induced wheezing in infancy-the first sign of childhood asthma? J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2003;111(1):66-71. doi:10.1067/mai.2003.33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piedimonte G, Perez MK. Respiratory syncytial virus infection and bronchiolitis. Pediatr Rev. 2014;35(12):519-530. doi:10.1542/pir.35-12-519</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Mattia G, Nenna R, Mancino E, et al. During the COVID-19 pandemic where has respiratory syncytial virus gone? Pediatr Pulmonol. 2021;56(10):3106-3109. doi:10.1002/ppul.25582</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savolainen-Kopra C, Korpela T, Simonen-Tikka ML, et al. Single treatment with ethanol hand rub is ineffective against human rhinovirus-hand washing with soap and water removes the virus efficiently. J Med Virol. 2012;84(3):543-547. doi:10.1002/jmv.23222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green CA, Sande CJ, de Lara C, et al. Humoral and cellular immunity to RSV in infants, children and adults. Vaccine. 2018;36(41):6183-6190. doi:10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.08.056</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>