<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37674335</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2093-2340</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>55</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection &amp; chemotherapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Chemother</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>First Detection of Enterovirus D68 in Korean Children, September 2022.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>422</StartPage><EndPage>430</EndPage><MedlinePgn>422-430</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3947/ic.2023.0036</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) is a re-emerging pathogen that is particularly common in children and may cause asthma-like respiratory infection and acute flaccid myelitis. However, in Korea, EV-D68 has never been reported thus far. This study aimed to identify EV-D68 from nasopharyngeal aspirates (NPAs) in Korean children with a respiratory tract infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The EV-D68 reference strain was purchased and blindly used to assess the detection ability of three commercial and one in-house mRT-PCR kit in 2018. Then, we selected children whose specimens were positive for human rhinovirus (HRV) and/or enterovirus (EV) by Allplex mRT-PCR (Seegene, Inc., Seoul, Korea) from April to December 2022. Total RNA was extracted from NPAs, and a partial 5'-UTR gene was amplified and sequenced for the identification of HRV/EV species. Additionally, PCR targeting the VP1 gene was performed to assess EV-D68-positive NPAs, followed by sequencing. Phylogenetic analysis and comparison of amino acid sequence alignments were performed using a partial VP1 gene of our and recent international EV-D68 strains.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among the mRT-PCR kits tested, only the in-house kit was able to detect EV-D68 in 2018. However, we detected three EV-D68 strains among children hospitalized with fever and/or respiratory symptoms in September - December 2022 who tested positive for EV by the Allplex kit. Two of them were healthy toddlers with lower respiratory infections accompanied by new-onset wheezing but no neurologic complications. Among 34 children with lower respiratory infection who tested positive for HRV during the same period, EV-D68 was not detected. Phylogenetic analysis revealed that the first Korean EV-D68 belonged to subclade B3. Amino acid sequence alignment of international subclade B3 EV-D68 strains also showed that our strain is genetically more related to those from Europe than those from Japan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We first detected EV-D68 in three Korean children who had EV detected by the Allplex mRT-PCR kit in 2022. EV-D68 also circulated in Korea in fall 2022, but the prevalence and severity seemed to be lower than those in previous reports from other countries.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 by The Korean Society of Infectious Diseases, Korean Society for Antimicrobial Therapy, and The Korean Society for AIDS.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yun</LastName><ForeName>Ki Wook</ForeName><Initials>KW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0798-6779</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University Children's Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahn</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3806-4275</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University Children's Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Sung Hwan</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6340-8260</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University Children's Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kang</LastName><ForeName>Da Yeon</ForeName><Initials>DY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0314-9455</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University Children's Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Taek Soo</ForeName><Initials>TS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2093-1721</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Mi Kyung</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1824-476X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Chung-Ang University Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Kyoung Un</ForeName><Initials>KU</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2402-7633</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, Seongnam, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Eun Hwa</ForeName><Initials>EH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5857-0749</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Seoul National University Children's Hospital, Seoul, Korea. eunchoi@snu.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>04-2018-0430</GrantID><Acronym>SNUBH</Acronym><Agency>Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</Agency><Country>Korea</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Chemother</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101531537</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1598-8112</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Respiratory infection</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>KUP is associate editor of Infect Chemother; however, he did not involve in the peer reviewer selection, evaluation, and decision process of this article. Otherwise, no potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article was reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37674335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10771948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3947/ic.2023.0036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">55.e33</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kidd S, Lopez AS, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Nix WA, Routh JA, Oberste MS. Enterovirus D68-associated acute flaccid myelitis, United States, 2020. Emerg Infect Dis. 2020;26:e201630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7510737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32833616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm-Hansen CC, Midgley SE, Fischer TK. Global emergence of enterovirus D68: a systematic review. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16:e64–e75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26929196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma KC, Winn A, Moline HL, Scobie HM, Midgley CM, Kirking HL, Adjemian J, Hartnett KP, Johns D, Jones JM, Lopez A, Lu X, Perez A, Perrine CG, Rzucidlo AE, McMorrow ML, Silk BJ, Stein Z, Vega E New Vaccine Surveillance Network Collaborators. Hall AJ. Increase in acute respiratory illnesses among children and adolescents associated with rhinoviruses and enteroviruses, including enterovirus D68 - United States, July-September 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:1265–1270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9541033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36201400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer R, Sabatier M, Wirth T, Pichon M, Lina B, Schuffenecker I, Josset L. Molecular diversity and biennial circulation of enterovirus D68: a systematic screening study in Lyon, France, 2010 to 2016. Euro Surveill. 2018;23:1700711.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6144471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30229724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Clusters of acute respiratory illness associated with human enterovirus 68--Asia, Europe, and United States, 2008-2010. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2011;60:1301–1304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21956405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley CM, Jackson MA, Selvarangan R, Turabelidze G, Obringer E, Johnson D, Giles BL, Patel A, Echols F, Oberste MS, Nix WA, Watson JT, Gerber SI. Severe respiratory illness associated with enterovirus D68 - Missouri and Illinois, 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2014;63:798–799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25211545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McAllister SC, Schleiss MR, Arbefeville S, Steiner ME, Hanson RS, Pollock C, Ferrieri P. Epidemic 2014 enterovirus D68 cross-reacts with human rhinovirus on a respiratory molecular diagnostic platform. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0118529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4370466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25799541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatchette TF, Drews SJ, Grudeski E, Booth T, Martineau C, Dust K, Garceau R, Gubbay J, Karnauchow T, Krajden M, Levett PN, Mazzulli T, McDonald RR, McNabb A, Mubareka S, Needle R, Petrich A, Richardson S, Rutherford C, Smieja M, Tellier R, Tipples G, LeBlanc JJ. Detection of enterovirus D68 in Canadian laboratories. J Clin Microbiol. 2015;53:1748–1751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4400745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25740765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Maher K, Schnurr D, Flemister MR, Lovchik JC, Peters H, Sessions W, Kirk C, Chatterjee N, Fuller S, Hanauer JM, Pallansch MA. Enterovirus 68 is associated with respiratory illness and shares biological features with both the enteroviruses and the rhinoviruses. J Gen Virol. 2004;85:2577–2584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15302951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44:2698–2704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1594621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16891480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M, Echevarria JE, González I, de Miguel T, Trallero G. Molecular epidemiological study of HEV-B enteroviruses involved in the increase in meningitis cases occurred in Spain during 2006. J Med Virol. 2008;80:1018–1024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18428125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Sanz R, Taravillo I, Reina J, Navascués A, Moreno-Docón A, Aranzamendi M, Romero MP, Del Cuerpo M, Pérez-González C, Pérez-Castro S, Otero A, Cabrerizo M. Enterovirus D68-associated respiratory and neurological illness in Spain, 2014-2018. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2019;8:1438–1444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6781473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31571527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Todd AK, Hall RJ, Wang J, Peacey M, McTavish S, Rand CJ, Stanton JA, Taylor S, Huang QS. Detection and whole genome sequence analysis of an enterovirus 68 cluster. Virol J. 2013;10:103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3621541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23548106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Hassan F, Briggs KB, Hays L, Miller JO, Pahud B, Puls HT, Queen MA, Thompson MT, Weddle G, Jackson MA. Clinical course of enterovirus D68 in hospitalized children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2017;36:290–295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28187115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang HJ, Lee DY, Han MG. Enteroviruses from acute flaccid paralysis surveillance in the Republic of Korea, 2012–2019. Public Health Wkly Rep. 2021;14:3247–3250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ha J, Lee SW, Yon DK. Ten-year trends and prevalence of asthma, allergic rhinitis, and atopic dermatitis among the Korean population, 2008-2017. Clin Exp Pediatr. 2020;63:278–283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7374008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32023407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korematsu S, Nagashima K, Sato Y, Nagao M, Hasegawa S, Nakamura H, Sugiura S, Miura K, Okada K, Fujisawa T. “Spike” in acute asthma exacerbations during enterovirus D68 epidemic in Japan: a nation-wide survey. Allergol Int. 2018;67:55–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28455155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen L, Gong C, Xiang Z, Zhang T, Li M, Li A, Luo M, Huang F. Upsurge of enterovirus D68 and crculation of the new subclade D3 and subclade B3 in Beijing, China, 2016. Sci Rep. 2019;9:6073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6465342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30988475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang W, Wang G, Zhuge J, Nolan SM, Dimitrova N, Fallon JT. Whole-genome sequence analysis reveals the enterovirus D68 isolates during the United States 2014 outbreak mainly belong to a novel clade. Sci Rep. 2015;5:15223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4606740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26469882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikuse T, Aizawa Y, Yamanaka T, Habuka R, Watanabe K, Otsuka T, Saitoh A. Outbreak of enterovirus D68 among children in Japan-worldwide circulation of enterovirus D68 clade B3 in 2018. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:6–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32947598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Diaz A, Moyer K, Mele-Casas M, Ara-Montojo MF, Torrus I, McCoy K, Mejias A, Leber AL. Molecular and clinical comparison of enterovirus D68 outbreaks among hospitalized children, Ohio, USA, 2014 and 2018. Emerg Infect Dis. 2019;25:2055–2063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6810223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31454311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>