<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37609274</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>SARS-CoV-2 Pandemic Non-Pharmacologic Interventions Temporally Associated with Reduced Pediatric Infections Due to <i>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</i> and Co-Infecting Respiratory Viruses in Arkansas.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2023.08.05.23293566</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2023.08.05.23293566</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Non-pharmacologic interventions (NPIs), such as universal masking, implemented during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic have reduced respiratory infections among children. This study focuses on evaluating the impact of NPIs on <i>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</i> infections in children, analyzing data from two hospitals in Arkansas, and examining age-related differences and coinfections with other viruses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board and included patients aged ≤18 years with upper respiratory tract symptoms. Data from the FilmArray<sup>®</sup> Respiratory Panel (FARP) were collected and divided into pre-NPI and NPI periods for analysis. Total test positivity rate and interval change in the positivity rate were evaluated. Statistical differences were determined by Chi-square (χ<sup>2</sup>-independence) analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 68,949 tests were performed with a statistical increase in testing during the NPI period. The overall test positivity rate for <i>M. pneumoniae</i> decreased by 74% (0.86% to 0.03%) during the NPI period, and the preschool age group had the highest number of positive tests in the pre- and NPI periods (Pre-NPI: n=40, NPI: n=12 positive tests, p=&lt;0.001). The reduction in <i>M. pneumoniae</i> infections was consistent across age groups. Coinfections with other respiratory viruses, particularly human rhinovirus/enterovirus, were observed at much lower levels.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">NPIs effectively reduced <i>M. pneumoniae</i> in pediatric patients in Arkansas, and coinfections with specific viruses still occurred, albeit at lower levels during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. As NPIs are relaxed and the pandemic ends, we expect <i>M. pneumoniae</i> infections to return to pre-pandemic levels within the next 1-2 years.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boyanton</LastName><ForeName>Bobby L</ForeName><Initials>BL</Initials><Suffix>Jr</Suffix><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Pathology, Arkansas Children's Hospital, Little Rock, AR 72202, and University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, AR 72205.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frenner</LastName><ForeName>Rachel A</ForeName><Initials>RA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Arkansas Children's Hospital, Little Rock, AR 72202.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ingold</LastName><ForeName>Ashton</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Arkansas Children's Research Institute, Little Rock, AR 72202.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ambroggio</LastName><ForeName>Lilliam</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sections of Emergency Medicine and Hospital Medicine, Children's Hospital Colorado and Department of Pediatrics, University of Colorado, Aurora, Colorado.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kennedy</LastName><ForeName>Joshua L</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Arkansas Children's Research Institute, Little Rock, AR 72202.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Pediatrics and Internal Medicine, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences Little Rock, AR, 72205.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P20 GM121293</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateIn"><RefSource>Microbiol Spectr. 2024 Apr 2;12(4):e0290823. doi: 10.1128/spectrum.02908-23</RefSource><PMID Version="1">38488365</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NPI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infection control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social distancing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">universal masking</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of Interest: All authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37609274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10441508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2023.08.05.23293566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2023.08.05.23293566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Cowling BJ, Ali ST, Ng TWY, et al. Impact assessment of non-pharmaceutical interventions against coronavirus disease 2019 and influenza in Hong Kong: an observational study. Lancet Public Health. 2020. May;5(5):e279–e288. doi: 10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30090-6. Epub 2020 Apr 17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30090-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32311320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyanton BL Jr, Snowden JN, Frenner RA, et al. SARS-CoV-2 Infection Mitigation Strategies Concomitantly Reduce Group A Streptococcus Pharyngitis. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2022. Dec 10:99228221141534. doi: 10.1177/00099228221141534. Epub ahead of print.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00099228221141534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9747366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36495165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen SJ, Winn AK, Budd AP, et al. Changes in influenza and other respiratory virus activity during the COVID-19 pandemic - United States, 2020–2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1013–1019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34292924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBride JA, Eickhoff J, Wald ER. Impact of COVID-19 quarantine and school cancelation on other common infectious diseases. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2020;39(12):e449–e452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33031142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torretta S, Capaccio P, Coro I, et al. Incidental lowering of otitis-media complaints in otitis-prone children during COVID-19 pandemic: not all evil comes to hurt. Eur J Pediatr. 2021;180:649–652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7370867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32691131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNeil JC, Flores AR, Kaplan SL, et al. The indirect impact of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic on invasive group A Streptococcus, Streptococcus pneumoniae and Staphylococcus aureus infections in Houston area children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:e313–e316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8279221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34250979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalabih A, Young HL, Frenner RA, et al. SARS-CoV-2 prevention measures concomitantly attenuate methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus infection rates. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2022;61:137–140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35132903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatoun J, Correa ET, Donahue SMA, et al. Social distancing for COVID-19 and diagnoses of other infectious diseases in children. Pediatrics. 2020;146(4):e2020006460. doi: 10.1542/peds.2020-006460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2020-006460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32879032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakamoto H, Ishikane M, Ueda P. Seasonal influenza activity during the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak in Japan. JAMA. 2020;323:1969–1971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7149351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32275293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan SG, Carlson S, Cheng AC, et al. Where has all the influenza gone? The impact of COVID-19 on the circulation of influenza and other respiratory viruses, Australia, March to September 2020. Euro Surveill. 2020;25(47):2001847.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7693168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33243355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh DY, Buda S, Biere B, et al. Trends in respiratory virus circulation following COVID-19-targeted nonpharmaceutical interventions in Germany, January - September 2020: Analysis of national surveillance data. Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2021. Jul;6:100112. doi: 10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100112. Epub 2021 Jun 7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8183189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34124707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rybak A, Levy C, Angoulvant F, et al. Association of Nonpharmaceutical Interventions During the COVID-19 Pandemic With Invasive Pneumococcal Disease, Pneumococcal Carriage, and Respiratory Viral Infections Among Children in France. JAMA Netw Open. 2022. Jun 1;5(6):e2218959. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.18959.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.18959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9240903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35763298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angoulvant F, Ouldali N, Yang DD, et al. Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic: Impact Caused by School Closure and National Lockdown on Pediatric Visits and Admissions for Viral and Nonviral Infections-a Time Series Analysis. Clin Infect Dis. 2021. Jan 27;72(2):319–322. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa710.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7314162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33501967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oster Y, Michael-Gayego A, Rivkin M, et al. Decreased prevalence rate of respiratory pathogens in hospitalized patients during the COVID-19 pandemic: possible role for public health containment measures? Clin Microbiol Infect. 2020. Dec 31;27(5):811–2. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2020.12.007. Epub ahead of print.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.12.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33352303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer Sauteur PM, Beeton ML, Uldum SA, et al. ESGMAC–MyCOVID Study Team. Mycoplasma pneumoniae detections before and during the COVID-19 pandemic: results of a global survey, 2017 to 2021. Euro Surveill. 2022. May;27(19):2100746. doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2022.27.19.2100746.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2022.27.19.2100746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9101966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35551702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer Sauteur PM, Chalker VJ, Berger C, et al. ESGMAC and the ESGMAC–MyCOVID study group. Mycoplasma pneumoniae beyond the COVID-19 pandemic: where is it? Lancet Microbe. 2022. Dec;3(12):e897. doi: 10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00190-2. Epub 2022 Aug 11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00190-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9371584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35964636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng Y, Cheng Y, Dai S, et al. The Prevalence of Mycoplasma pneumoniae Among Children in Beijing Before and During the COVID-19 Pandemic. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022. Apr 29;12:854505. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2022.854505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2022.854505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9103471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35573799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Li T, Chen N, et al. Changes of Mycoplasma pneumoniae prevalence in children before and after COVID-19 pandemic in Henan, China. J Infect. 2023. Jan 13:S0163-4453(23)00012-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jinf.2022.12.030. Epub ahead of print.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2022.12.030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9838080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36646141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haapanen M, Renko M, Artama M, et al. The impact of the lockdown and the re-opening of schools and day cares on the epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 and other respiratory infections in children - A nationwide register study in Finland. EClinicalMedicine. 2021. Apr;34:100807. doi: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100807. Epub 2021 Mar 29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8007090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33817612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Huang Y, Ai T, et al. Effect of COVID-19 on childhood Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection in Chengdu, China. BMC Pediatr. 2021. Apr 28;21(1):202. doi: 10.1186/s12887-021-02679-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12887-021-02679-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8079841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33910509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuitunen I. Bordetella pertussis, Chlamydia pneumoniae, and Mycoplasma pneumoniae Findings in Children During COVID-19 Pandemic in Finland. SN Compr Clin Med. 2022;4(1):154. doi: 10.1007/s42399-022-01251-9. Epub 2022 Jul 14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42399-022-01251-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9281357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35856013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waites KB, Xiao L, Liu Y, et al. Mycoplasma pneumoniae from the Respiratory Tract and Beyond. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2017. Jul;30(3):747–809. doi: 10.1128/CMR.00114-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00114-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5475226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28539503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waites KB, Talkington DF. Mycoplasma pneumoniae and its role as a human pathogen. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2004. Oct;17(4):697–728, table of contents. doi: 10.1128/CMR.17.4.697-728.2004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.17.4.697-728.2004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC523564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15489344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma YJ, Wang SM, Cho YH, et al. Taiwan Pediatric Infectious Disease Alliance. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics in children with community-acquired mycoplasma pneumonia in Taiwan: A nationwide surveillance. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2015. Dec;48(6):632–8. doi: 10.1016/j.jmii.2014.08.003. Epub 2014 Oct 11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2014.08.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25311405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng X, Lee S, Selvarangan R, et al. Macrolide-Resistant Mycoplasma pneumoniae, United States. Emerg Infect Dis. 2015. Aug;21(8):1470–2. doi: 10.3201/eid2108.150273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2108.150273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4517703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26196107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz MH, Cross KE, Benitez AJ, et al. Identification of Bacterial and Viral Codetections With Mycoplasma pneumoniae Using the TaqMan Array Card in Patients Hospitalized With Community-Acquired Pneumonia. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2016. Mar 30;3(2):ofw071. doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofw071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofw071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4867659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27191004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Chen Z, Gu W, et al. Viral and bacterial co-infection in hospitalised children with refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia. Epidemiol Infect. 2018. Aug;146(11):1384–1388. doi: 10.1017/S0950268818000778. Epub 2018 Jul 4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268818000778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9133674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29970200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kutty PK, Jain S, Taylor TH, et al. Mycoplasma pneumoniae Among Children Hospitalized With Community-acquired Pneumonia. Clin Infect Dis. 2019. Jan 1;68(1):5–12. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciy419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciy419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6552676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29788037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Wang J, Chen W, et al. Impact of viral coinfection and macrolide-resistant mycoplasma infection in children with refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia. BMC Infect Dis. 2020. Aug 26;20(1):633. doi: 10.1186/s12879-020-05356-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-05356-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7447613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32847534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Q, Li L, Wang C, et al. Comprehensive virome analysis of the viral spectrum in paediatric patients diagnosed with Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia. Virol J. 2022. Nov 9;19(1):181. doi: 10.1186/s12985-022-01914-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-022-01914-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9644017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36352436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haapanen M, Renko M, Artama M, et al. The impact of the lockdown and the re-opening of schools and day cares on the epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 and other respiratory infections in children - A nationwide register study in Finland. EClinicalMedicine. 2021. Apr;34:100807. doi: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100807. Epub 2021 Mar 29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8007090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33817612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi HJ, Kim NY, Eom SA, et al. Effects of Non-Pharmacological Interventions on Respiratory Viruses Other Than SARS-CoV-2: Analysis of Laboratory Surveillance and Literature Review From 2018 to 2021. J Korean Med Sci. 2022. May 30;37(21):e172. doi: 10.3346/jkms.2022.37.e172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3346/jkms.2022.37.e172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9151990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35638198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>