<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37721354</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1521-4028</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>64</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of basic microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Basic Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bioprospecting the potential of metabolites from a Saharan saline soil strain Nocardiopsis dassonvillei GSBS4.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>50</StartPage><EndPage>67</EndPage><MedlinePgn>50-67</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jobm.202300162</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Saharan soil samples collected in El-Oued province have been investigated for actinobacteria as a valuable source for the production of bioactive metabolites. A total of 273 isolates were obtained and subjected to antagonistic activity tests against human pathogenic germs. A strain with a broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity was selected and identified as Nocardiopsis dassonvillei GSBS4, with high sequence similarities to N. dassonvillei subsp. dassonvillei<sup>T</sup> X97886.1 (99%) based on polyphasic taxonomy approach and 16S ribosomal ribonucleic acid gene sequence analysis. The GSBS4 ethyl acetate crude extract showed strong antibacterial activity towards pathogenic bacteria and Candida albicans. It inhibited biofilm formation by Staphylococcus aureus and methicillin-resistant S. aureus with minimum inhibitory concentrations estimated at 0.144 and 1.15 mg·mL<sup>-1</sup> , respectively. A 44% biofilm reduction was obtained for S. aureus and 61% for Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Furthermore, phenols composition of the crude extract showed a significant dose-dependent antioxidant activity by α-diphenyl-β-picrylhydrazyl (57.21%) and 2,2'-azinobis (3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (64.29%) radicals scavenging assays. Although no inhibition was obtained on human coronavirus human coronavirus (HCoV) 229E and on model enterovirus (poliovirus 1) infection, a dose-dependent increase in cell viability of HCoV 229E-infected cells was noticed as the viability increased from 21% to 37%. Bioassay-guided fractionation of the crude extract gave a fraction showing antibacterial activity, which was analyzed by liquid chromatography-electrospray mass spectrometric technique, providing structural features on a major purple metabolite.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Djinni</LastName><ForeName>Ibtissem</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1485-8695</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département de Microbiologie, Laboratoire de Microbiologie Appliquée, Faculté des Sciences de la Nature et de la Vie, Université de Bejaia, Bejaia, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioorganic Chemistry Laboratory, Department of Physics, University of Trento, Povo Trento, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Conroy</LastName><ForeName>Leah</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université de Lorraine, CNRS, Nancy, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>RCSI School of Pharmacy and Biomolecular Sciences (PBS), Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Varbanov</LastName><ForeName>Mihayl</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université de Lorraine, CNRS, Nancy, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie, CHRU de Nancy Brabois, Vandœuvre-lès-Nancy, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Souagui</LastName><ForeName>Samiha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département de Microbiologie, Laboratoire de Microbiologie Appliquée, Faculté des Sciences de la Nature et de la Vie, Université de Bejaia, Bejaia, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yanat</LastName><ForeName>Betitera</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département de Microbiologie, Laboratoire de Biotechnologie Végétale et Ethnobotanique, Faculté des Sciences de la Nature et de la Vie, Université de Bejaia, Bejaia, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Defant</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioorganic Chemistry Laboratory, Department of Physics, University of Trento, Povo Trento, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kecha</LastName><ForeName>Mouloud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Département de Microbiologie, Laboratoire de Microbiologie Appliquée, Faculté des Sciences de la Nature et de la Vie, Université de Bejaia, Bejaia, Algeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mancini</LastName><ForeName>Ines</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bioorganic Chemistry Laboratory, Department of Physics, University of Trento, Povo Trento, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Faculty of Nature Science and Life, University of Bejaia</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>European Commission</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>CNRS and Université de Lorraine</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>University of Trento</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>J Basic Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8503885</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0233-111X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012987">Soil</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Organism" UI="C000645257">Nocardiopsis dassonvillei</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013211" MajorTopicYN="N">Staphylococcus aureus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055624" MajorTopicYN="Y">Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012987" MajorTopicYN="N">Soil</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065132" MajorTopicYN="N">Bioprospecting</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009615" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nocardia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008826" MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial Sensitivity Tests</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086262" MajorTopicYN="N">Nocardiopsis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LC-ESIMS analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nocardiopsis dassonvillei</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibiofilm</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antimicrobials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antioxidants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antivirals</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37721354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jobm.202300162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation (WHO). Antimicrobial resistance. 2020. Accessed February 27, 2022. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genilloud O. Actinomycetes: still a source of novel antibiotics. Nat Prod Rep. 2017;34:1203-1232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djinni I, Defant A, Djoudi W, Chaabane Chaouch F, Souagui S, Kecha M, et al. Modeling improved production of the chemotherapeutic polypeptide actinomycin D by a novel Streptomyces sp. strain from a Saharan soil. Heliyon. 2019;5:e01695.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Simeis D, Serra S. Actinomycetes: a never-ending source of bioactive compounds-an overview on antibiotics production. Antibiotics. 2021;10:483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis DE, Pathak A, Jones CB, Akpovo C, Chauhan A. Metagenomic evaluation of a Utah tar sand microbiota suggests the predominant hydrocarbonoclastic role of actinobacteria. F1000Research. 2018;7:1650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rateb ME, Ebel R, Jaspars M. Natural product diversity of actinobacteria in the Atacama Desert. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek. 2018;111:1467-1477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djinni I, Djoudi W, Harfi N, Stambouli I, Khamtache S, Makhlouf D, et al. Enhanced anti-E. coli ST131 metabolites production by a novel Streptomyces sp. CMB51 strain isolated from a coal mininig soil using statistical optimization. Geomicrobiol J. 2022;39:39-53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djinni I, Defant A, Kecha M, Mancini I. Actinobacteria derived from Algerian ecosystems as a prominent source of antimicrobial molecules. Antibiotics. 2019;8:172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trenozhnikova L, Azizan A. Discovery of actinomycetes from extreme environments with potential to produce novel antibiotics. Cent Asian J Glob Health. 2018;7:337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bérdy J. Thoughts and facts about antibiotics: where we are now and where we are heading. J Antibiot. 2012;65:385-395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennur T, Ravi Kumar A, Zinjarde SS, Javdekar V. Nocardiopsis species: a potential source of bioactive compounds. J Appl Microbiol. 2016;120:1-16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim A, Desoukey S, Fouad M, Kamel M, Gulder T, Abdelmohsen U. Natural product potential of the genus Nocardiopsis. Mar Drugs. 2018;16:147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsujibo H, Sato T, Inui M, Yamamoto H, Inamori Y. Intracellular accumulation of phenazine antibiotics produced by an alkalophilic actinomycete. I. Taxonomy, isolation and identification of the phenazine antibiotics. Agr Biol Chem. 1988;52:301-306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanida S, Takizawa M, Takahashi T, Tsubotani S, Harada S. TAN-999 and TAN-1030A, new indolocarbazole alkaloids with macrophage-activating properties. J Antibiot. 1989;42:1619-1630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsujibo H, Sakamoto T, Miyamoto K, Kusano G, Ogura M, Hasegawa T, et al. Isolation of cytotoxic substance, kalafungin from an alkalophilic actinomycete, Nocardiopsis dassonvillei subsp. Prasina. Chem Pharm Bull. 1990;38:2299-2300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, Xie L, Xia G, Zhang J, Nie Y, Hu J, et al. A new tetrodotoxin-producing actinomycete, Nocardiopsis dassonvillei, isolated from the ovaries of puffer fish Fugu rubripes. Toxicon. 2005;45:851-859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu P, Liu P, Qu H, Wang Y, Chen D, Wang H, et al. α-Pyrones and diketopiperazine derivatives from the marine-derived actinomycete Nocardiopsis dassonvillei HR10-5. J Nat Prod. 2011;74:2219-2223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X, Lu Y, Xing Y, Ma Y, Lu J, Bao W, et al. A novel anticancer and antifungus phenazine derivative from a marine actinomycete BM-17. Microbiol Res. 2012;167:616-622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennur T, Javdekar V, Tomar GB, Zinjarde S. Gold nanoparticles biosynthesized by Nocardiopsis dassonvillei NCIM 5124 enhance osteogenesis in gingival mesenchymal stem cells. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2020;104:4081-4092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhanaraj S, Thirunavukkarasu S, Allen John H, Pandian S, Salmen SH, Chinnathambi A, et al. Novel marine Nocardiopsis dassonvillei-DS013 mediated silver nanoparticles characterization and its bactericidal potential against clinical isolates. Saudi J Biol Sci. 2020;27:991-995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali MI, Ahmad MS, Hozzein WN. WA52-A macrolide antibiotic produced by alkalophile Nocardiopsis dassonvillei WA52. Aust J Basic Appl Sci. 2009;3:607-616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu P, Liu P, Gong Q, Wang Y, Wang P, Zhu W. α-Pyrones from the marine-derived actinomycete Nocardiopsis dassonvillei subsp. dassonvillei XG-8-1. RSC Adv. 2013;3:20726-20731.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miao L, Qian S, Qi S, Jiang W, Dong K. Culture medium optimization and active compounds investigation of an anti-quorum sensing marine actinobacterium Nocardiopsis dassonvillei JS106. Microbiology. 2021;90:11-23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou G, Liao XJ, Peng Q, Chen GD, Wei FY, Xu ZX, et al. A new α-pyrone from the deep-sea actinomycete Nocardiopsis dassonvillei subsp. dassonvillei DSM 43111 (T). J Asian Nat Prod Res. 2017;9:232-238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Tai AM, Ruan JS. Nocardiopsis halophila sp. nov., a new halophilic actinomycete isolated from soil. Int J Syst Bacteriol. 1994;44:474-478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltola JSP, Andersson MA, Kämpfer P, Auling G, Kroppenstedt RM, Busse H, et al. Isolation of toxigenic Nocardiopsis strains from indoor environments and description of two new Nocardiopsis species, N. exhalans sp. nov. and N. umidischolae sp. nov. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2001;67:4293-4304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zitouni A, Boudjella H, Lamari L, Badji B, Mathieu F, Lebrihi A, et al. Nocardiopsis and Saccharothrix genera in Saharan soils in Algeria: isolation, biological activities and partial characterization of antibiotics. Res Microbiol. 2005;156:984-993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirling EB, Gottlieb D. Methods for characterization of Streptomyces species. Int J Syst Bacteriol. 1966;16:313-340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Bharti A, Gusain O, Bisht GS. Scanning electron microscopy of Streptomyces without use of any chemical fixatives. Scanning. 2011;33:446-449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staneck JL, Roberts GD. Simplified approach to identification of aerobic actinomycetes by thin-layer chromatography. Appl Microbiol. 1974;28:226-231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lechevalier MP, Lechevalier H. Chemical composition as a criterion in the classification of aerobic actinomycetes. Int J Syst Bacteriol. 1970;20:435-443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasciak M, Holst O, Lindner B, Mordarska H, Gamian A. Novel bacterial polar lipids containing ether-linked alkyl chains, the structures and biological properties of the four major glycolipids from Propionibacterium propionicum PCM 2431 (ATCC 14157 T). J Biol Chem. 2003;278:3948-3956.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bligh EG, Dyer WJ. A rapid method of total lipid extraction and purification. Can J Biochem Physiol. 1959;37:911-917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djinni I, Defant A, Kecha M, Mancini I. Metabolite profile of marine-derived endophytic Streptomyces sundarbansensis WR1L1S8 by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry and evaluation of culture conditions on antibacterial activity and mycelial growth. J Appl Microbiol. 2014;116:39-50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Athalye M, Goodfellow M, Lacey J, White RP. Numerical classification of Actinomadura and Nocardiopsis. Int J Syst Bacteriol. 1985;35:86-98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon RE, Barnett DA, Handerhan JE, Pang CHN. Nocardia coeliaca, Nocardia autotrophica, and the Nocardin strain. Int J Syst Bacteriol. 1974;24:54-63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson J. The CLUSTAL_X Windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools. Nucleic Acids Res. 1997;25:4876-4882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saitou N, Nei M. The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees. Mol Biol Evol. 1987;4:406-425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura K, Stecher G, Peterson D, Filipski A, Kumar S. MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30:2725-2729.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap. Evolution. 1985;39:783-791.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junaid SKN, RAKESH KNR, Dileep N, Poornima G, Kekuda TRP, Mukunda S. Total phenolic content and antioxidant activity of seed extract of Lagerstroemia speciosa L. Chem Sci Trans. 2012;2:75-80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahorun T, Gressier B, Trotin F, Brunet C, Dine T, Luyckx M, et al. Oxygen species scavenging activity of phenolic extracts from hawthorn fresh plant organs and pharmaceutical preparations. Arzneimittel-Forschung. 1996;46:1086-1089.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sreenivasan S, Ibrahim D, Kassim MJNM. Free radical scavenging activity and total phenolic compounds of Gracilaria changii. Int J Nat Engineer Sci. 2007;1:115-117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Re R, Pellegrini N, Proteggente A, Pannala A, Yang M, Rice-Evans C. Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay. Free Radic Biol Med. 1999;26:1231-1237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur G, Alam MS, Jabbar Z, Javed K, Athar M. Evaluation of antioxidant activity of Cassia siamea flowers. J Ethnopharmacol. 2006;108:340-348.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Toole GA. Microtiter dish biofilm formation assay. J Vis Exp. 2011;30:2437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stiefel P, Rosenberg U, Schneider J, Mauerhofer S, Maniura-Weber K, Ren Q. Is biofilm removal properly assessed? Comparison of different quantification methods in a 96-well plate system. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2016;100:4135-4145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed LJ, Muench H. A simple method of estimating fifty percent endpoints. Am J Epidemiol. 1938;27:493-497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosmann T. Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays. J Immunol Methods. 1983;65:55-63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feoktistova M, Geserick P, Leverkus M. Crystal violet assay for determining viability of cultured cells. Cold Spring Harb Protoc. 2016;2016:pdb.prot087379.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djinni I, Djoudi W, Souagui S, Rabia F, Rahmouni S, Mancini I, et al. Streptomyces thermoviolaceus SRC3 strain as a novel source of the antibiotic adjuvant streptazolin: a statistical approach toward the optimized production. J Microbiol Meth. 2018;148:161-168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meena B, Rajan LA, Vinithkumar NV, Kirubagaran R. Novel marine actinobacteria from emerald Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands: a prospective source for industrial and pharmaceutical byproducts. BMC Microbiol. 2013;13:145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V, Haque S, Singh H, Vetma J., Vibha K., Singh R., et al. Isolation, screening, and identification of novel isolates of actinomycetes from India for antimicrobial applications. Front Microbiol. 2016;7:1921.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sapkota A, Thapa A, Budhathoki A, Sainju M, Shrestha P, Aryal S. Isolation, characterization, and screening of antimicrobial-producing Actinomycetes from soil samples. Int J Microbiol. 2020;2020. Article ID 2716584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selvin J, Shanmughapriya S, Gandhimathi R, Seghal Kiran G, Rajeetha Ravji T, Natarajaseenivasan K, et al. Optimization and production of novel antimicrobial agents from sponge associated marine actinomycetes Nocardiopsis dassonvillei MAD08. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2009;83:435-445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi T, Wang YF, Wang H, Wang B. Genus nocardiopsis: a prolific producer of natural products. Mar Drugs. 2022;20:374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awouafack MD, McGaw LJ, Gottfried S, Mbouangouere R, Tane P, Spiteller M, et al. Antimicrobial activity and cytotoxicity of the ethanol extract, fractions and eight compounds isolated from Eriosema robustum (Fabaceae). BMC Complement Altern Med. 2013;13:289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy R, Tiwari M, Donelli G, Tiwari V. Strategies for combating bacterial biofilms: a focus on anti-biofilm agents and their mechanisms of action. Virulence. 2018;9:522-554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies D. Understanding biofilm resistance to antibacterial agents. Nat Rev Drug Discovery. 2003;2:114-122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Driche EH, Sabaou N, Bijani C, Zitouni A, Pont F, Mathieu F, et al. Streptomyces sp. AT37 isolated from a Saharan soil produces a furanone derivative active against multidrug-resistant Staphylococcus aureus. World J Microbiol Biotechnol. 2017;33:105-119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramanian S, Othman EM, Kampik D, Stopper H, Hentschel U, Ziebuhr W, et al. Marine sponge-derived Streptomyces sp. SBT343 extract inhibits staphylococcal biofilm formation. Front Microbiol. 2017;8:236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajivgandhi G, Vijayan R, Maruthupandy M, Vaseeharan B, Manoharan N. Antibiofilm effect of Nocardiopsis sp. GRG 1 (KT235640) compound against biofilm forming Gram negative bacteria on UTIs. Microb Pathog. 2018;118:190-198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YG, Lee JH, Kim CJ, Lee JC, Ju YJ, Cho MH, et al. Antibiofilm activity of Streptomyces sp. BFI 230 and Kribbella sp. BFI 1562 against Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2012;96:1607-1617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banin E, Brady KM, Greenberg EP. Chelator-induced dispersal and killing of Pseudomonas aeruginosa cells in a bio-film. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2006;72:2064-2069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michel L, González N, Jagdeep S, Nguyen-Ngoc T, Reimmann C. PchR-box recognition by the AraC-type regulator PchR of Pseudomonas aeruginosa requires the siderophore pyochelin as an effector. Mol Microbiol. 2005;58:495-509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visca P, Imperi F, Lamont IL. Pyoverdine siderophores: from biogenesis to biosignificance. TIM. 2007;15:22-30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imperi F, Tiburzi F, Visca P. Molecular basis of pyoverdine siderophore recycling in Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2009;106:20440-20445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox CD. Effect of pyochelin on the virulence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Infect Immun. 1982;36:17-23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabłońska-Wawrzycka A, Rogala P, Czerwonka G, Michałkiewicz S, Hodorowicz M, Gałczyńska K, et al. Tuning anti-biofilm activity of manganese(II) complexes: linking biological effectiveness of heteroaromatic complexes of alcohol, aldehyde, ketone, and carboxylic acid with structural effects and redox activity. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22:4847.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sultana B, Anwar F, Przybylski R. Antioxidant activity of phenolic components present in barks of Azadirachta indica, Terminalia arjuna, Acacia nilotica, and Eugenia jambolana lam. trees. Food Chem. 2007;104:1106-1114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piluzza G, Bullitta S. Correlations between phenolic content and antioxidant properties in twenty-four plant species of traditional ethnoveterinary use in the Mediterranean area. Pharm Biol. 2011;49:240-247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthäus B. Antioxidant activity of extracts obtained from residues of different oilseeds. J Agricult Food Chem. 2002;50:3444-3452.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bharate SB, Sawant SD, Singh PP, Vishwakarma RA. Kinase inhibitors of marine origin. Chem Rev. 2013;113:6761-6815.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kase H, Iwahashi K, MATSUDA Y. K-252a, a potent inhibitor of protein kinase C from microbial origin. J Antibiot. 1986;39:1059-1065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y, Sagara J, Kawai A. Studies on the antiviral activity of protein kinase inhibitors against the replication of vesicular stomatitis virus. Biol Pharm Bull. 1995;18:895-899.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawaz A, Chaudhary R, Shah Z, Dufossé L, Fouillaud M, Mukhtar H, et al. An overview on industrial and medical applications of bio-pigments synthesized by marine bacteria. Microorganisms. 2021;9:11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh Kumar C, Sahu N, Narender Reddy G, Prasad RBN, Nagesh N, Kamal A. Production of melanin pigment from Pseudomonas stutzeri isolated from red seaweed Hypneamusci formis. Lett Appl Microbiol. 2013;57:295-302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamarudheen N, Naushad T, Rao KVB. Biosynthesis characterization and antagonistic applications of extracellular melanin pigment from marine Nocardiopsis sps. Indian J Pharm Educ Res. 2019;53:112-120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasanthabharathi V, Lakshminarayanan R, Jayalakshmi S. Melanin production from marine Streptomyces. Afr J Biotechnol. 2011;10:11224-11234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundar R, Sivaperumal P. Melanin pigments from sediment-associated Nocardiopsis sp. marine actinobacterium and antibacterial potential. J Adv Pharm Technol Res. 2022;13:88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed A, Ahmad A, Li R, AL-Ansi W, Fatima M, Mushtaq BS, et al. Recent advances in synthetic, industrial and biological applications of violacein and its heterologous production. J Microbiol Biotechnol. 2021;31:1465-1480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asencio G, Lavin P, Alegría K, Domínguez M, Bello H, González-Rocha G, et al. Antibacterial activity of the Antarctic bacterium Janthinobacterium sp. SMN 33.6 against multi-resistant Gram-negative bacteria. EJB. 2014;17:1-5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim MC, Hwang E, Kim T, Ham J, Kim SY, Kwon HC. Nocatriones A and B, photoprotective tetracenediones from a marine-derived Nocardiopsis sp. J Nat Prod. 2014;77:2326-2330.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>