<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37725805</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparing the Clinical Courses of Children With Human Rhinovirus/Enterovirus to Children With Other Respiratory Viruses in the Outpatient Setting.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e432</StartPage><EndPage>e439</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e432-e439</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004097</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">While infections caused by rhinoviruses and enteroviruses are common among children, the entirety of their clinical impact remains elusive. We compared the clinical outcomes of children with rhinovirus/enterovirus infections to other common respiratory viruses in outpatient settings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted a retrospective analysis of nasopharyngeal samples singly positive for human rhinovirus/enterovirus (HRV/ENT), influenza A/B (FLU) or respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) from patients ≤17 years submitted for clinical testing via multiplex polymerase chain reaction between 2016 and 2019. We evaluated the following outpatient outcomes: days of respiratory symptoms before testing; visits for respiratory symptoms; receipt of a breathing treatment; receipt of antibiotics and hospital admission. Statistical analyses were conducted controlling for age and comorbid conditions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">There were 1355 positive samples included in this analysis (HRV/ENT: n = 743, FLU: n = 303 and RSV: n = 309). Compared to HRV/ENT, children with FLU had 28% fewer days of respiratory symptoms (β: -0.32; 95% confidence interval: -0.46 to -0.18; P &lt; 0.001), fewer visits for respiratory symptoms, and significantly decreased odds of receiving a breathing treatment or antibiotics, and admission to the hospital. Children with RSV had a similar number of days of respiratory symptoms, outpatient visits and odds of hospital admission, but significantly increased odds of receiving a breathing treatment and antibiotics compared to those with HRV/ENT.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Clinicians should have a high level of vigilance when managing children with positive respiratory viral testing for HRV/ENT given the potential for clinical outcomes similar to and, in some instances, worse than known highly pathogenic viruses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jones</LastName><ForeName>Milissa U</ForeName><Initials>MU</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-1798-2753</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, Bethesda, Maryland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Tripler Army Medical Center, Honolulu, Hawaii.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Montgomery</LastName><ForeName>Agnes S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatrics, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, Bethesda, Maryland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Children's National Hospital, Washington, DC.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Coskun</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer D</ForeName><Initials>JD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Tripler Army Medical Center, Honolulu, Hawaii.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marcelo</LastName><ForeName>Raymundo Z</ForeName><Initials>RZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Tripler Army Medical Center, Honolulu, Hawaii.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sutton</LastName><ForeName>Alyssa B</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Tripler Army Medical Center, Honolulu, Hawaii.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raiciulescu</LastName><ForeName>Sorana</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, Bethesda, Marylan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000956">Antigens, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012229" MajorTopicYN="N">Rhinovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010045" MajorTopicYN="N">Outpatients</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="Y">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018113" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Syncytial Virus, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000956" MajorTopicYN="N">Antigens, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018450" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Progression</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018357" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37725805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202312000-00007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Li S, Leader S. Economic burden and absenteeism from influenza-like illness in healthy households with children (5-17 years) in the US. Respir Med. 2007;101:1244–1250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez A, Lively JY, Curns A, et al.; New Vaccine Surveillance Network Collaborators. Respiratory virus surveillance among children with acute respiratory illnesses - new vaccine surveillance network, United States, 2016-2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:1253–1259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin DA, Spieker AJ, Perez A, et al.; NVSN Network Investigators. Circulation of Rhinoviruses and/or Enteroviruses in pediatric patients with acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2254909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duclos M, Hommel B, Allantaz F, et al. Multiplex PCR detection of respiratory tract infections in SARS-CoV-2-negative patients admitted to the emergency department: an international multicenter study during the COVID-19 pandemic. Microbiol Spectr. 2022;10:e0236822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beal SG, Posa M, Gaffar M, et al. Performance and impact of a CLIA-waived, point-of-care respiratory PCR panel in a pediatric clinic. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2020;39:188–191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrés C, Piñana M, Vila J, et al. The high genetic similarity between rhinoviruses and enteroviruses remains as a pitfall for molecular diagnostic tools: a three-year overview. Infect Genet Evol. 2019;75:103996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royston L, Tapparel C. Rhinoviruses and respiratory enteroviruses: not as simple as ABC. Viruses. 2016;8:16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doss AMA, Stokes JR. Viral infections and wheezing in preschool children. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am. 2022;42:727–741.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jartti T, Korppi M. Rhinovirus-induced bronchiolitis and asthma development. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. 2011;22:350–355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elrick MJ, Pekosz A, Duggal P. Enterovirus D68 molecular and cellular biology and pathogenesis. J Biol Chem. 2021;296:100317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sooksawasdi Na Ayudhya S, Laksono BM, van Riel D. The pathogenesis and virulence of enterovirus-D68 infection. Virulence. 2021;12:2060–2072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez-Garcia MD, Kebe O, Fall AD, et al. Enterovirus A71 genogroups C and E in children with acute flaccid paralysis, West Africa. Emerg Infect Dis. 2016;22:753–755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauinger IL, Bible JM, Halligan EP, et al. Patient characteristics and severity of human rhinovirus infections in children. J Clin Virol. 2013;58:216–220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Robinson CC, Bagdure D, et al. Rhino/enteroviruses in hospitalized children: a comparison to influenza viruses. J Clin Virol. 2013;56:41–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Windsor WJ, Lamb MM, Dominguez SR, et al. Clinical characteristics and illness course based on pathogen among children with respiratory illness presenting to an emergency department. J Med Virol. 2022;94:6103–6110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Precit MR, He K, Mongkolrattanothai K, et al. Impact of filmarray™ respiratory panel testing on the clinical management of pediatric bone marrow transplant patients. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2022;41:395–405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danziger-Isakov L, Steinbach WJ, Paulsen G, et al. A multicenter consortium to define the epidemiology and outcomes of pediatric solid organ transplant recipients with inpatient respiratory virus infection. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2019;8:197–204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asner SA, Petrich A, Hamid JS, et al. Clinical severity of rhinovirus/enterovirus compared to other respiratory viruses in children. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2014;8:436–442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halabi KC, Stockwell MS, Alba L, et al.; Mobile Surveillance for Acute Respiratory Infection/Influenza-like Illness in the Community (MoSAIC) Study Team. Clinical and socioeconomic burden of rhinoviruses/enteroviruses in the community. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2022;16:891–896.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babady NE. The FilmArray® respiratory panel: an automated, broadly multiplexed molecular test for the rapid and accurate detection of respiratory pathogens. Expert Rev Mol Diagn. 2013;13:779–788.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keske S, Ergönül O, Tutucu F, et al. The rapid diagnosis of viral respiratory tract infections and its impact on antimicrobial stewardship programs. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2018;37:779–783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taymaz T, Ergönül O, Kebapci A, et al. Significance of the detection of influenza and other respiratory viruses for antibiotic stewardship: lessons from the post-pandemic period. Int J Infect Dis. 2018;77:53–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattila S, Paalanne N, Honkila M, et al. Effect of point-of-care testing for respiratory pathogens on antibiotic use in children: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:e2216162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanti M, Comito D, Ligon C, et al. Active surveillance documents rates of clinical care seeking due to respiratory illness. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2020;14:499–506.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uyeki TM, Bernstein HH, Bradley JS, et al. Clinical practice guidelines by the infectious diseases society of america: 2018 update on diagnosis, treatment, chemoprophylaxis, and institutional outbreak management of seasonal influenzaa. Clin Infect Dis. 2019;68:895–902.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Bilcke J, van der Velden AW, et al. Direct and indirect costs of influenza-like illness treated with and without oseltamivir in 15 European countries: a descriptive analysis alongside the randomised controlled ALIC(4)E Trial. Clin Drug Investig. 2021;41:685–699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binns E, Tuckerman J, Licciardi PV, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus, recurrent wheeze and asthma: A narrative review of pathophysiology, prevention and future directions. J Paediatr Child Health. 2022;58:1741–1746.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levine DA, Platt SL, Dayan PS, et al.; Multicenter RSV-SBI Study Group of the Pediatric Emergency Medicine Collaborative Research Committee of the American Academy of Pediatrics. Risk of serious bacterial infection in young febrile infants with respiratory syncytial virus infections. Pediatrics. 2004;113:1728–1734.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purcell K, Fergie J. Concurrent serious bacterial infections in 2396 infants and children hospitalized with respiratory syncytial virus lower respiratory tract infections. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2002;156:322–324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chonmaitree T, Alvarez-Fernandez P, Jennings K, et al. Symptomatic and asymptomatic respiratory viral infections in the first year of life: association with acute otitis media development. Clin Infect Dis. 2015;60:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhedin S, Lindstrand A, Rotzén-Östlund M, et al. Clinical utility of PCR for common viruses in acute respiratory illness. Pediatrics. 2014;133:e538–e545.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>