<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37751988</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2052-4439</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMJ open respiratory research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMJ Open Respir Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Aetiological agents of adult community-acquired pneumonia in Japan: systematic review and meta-analysis of published data.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e001800</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1136/bmjresp-2023-001800</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Epidemiological information is essential in providing appropriate empiric antimicrobial therapy for pneumonia. This study aimed to clarify the epidemiology of community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) by conducting a systematic review of published studies in Japan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">Systematic review.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA SOURCE" NlmCategory="METHODS">PubMed and Ichushi web database (January 1970 to October 2022).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA" NlmCategory="METHODS">Clinical studies describing pathogenic micro-organisms in CAP written in English or Japanese, excluding studies on pneumonia other than adult CAP, investigations limited to specific pathogens and case reports.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA EXTRACTION AND SYNTHESIS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Patient setting (inpatient vs outpatient), number of patients, concordance with the CAP guidelines, diagnostic criteria and methods for diagnosing pneumonia pathogens as well as the numbers of each isolate. A meta-analysis of various situations was performed to measure the frequency of each aetiological agent.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Fifty-six studies were included and 17 095 cases of CAP were identified. Pathogens were undetectable in 44.1% (95% CI 39.7% to 48.5%). <i>Streptococcus pneumoniae</i> was the most common cause of CAP requiring hospitalisation or outpatient care (20.0% (95% CI 17.2% to 22.8%)), followed by <i>Haemophilus influenzae</i> (10.8% (95% CI 7.3% to 14.3%)) and <i>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</i> (7.5% (95% CI 4.6% to 10.4%)). However, when limited to CAP requiring hospitalisation, <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> was the third most common at 4.9% (95% CI 3.9% to 5.8%). <i>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</i> was more frequent in hospitalised cases, while atypical pathogens were less common. Methicillin-resistant <i>S. aureus</i> accounted for 40.7% (95% CI 29.0% to 52.4%) of <i>S. aureus</i> cases. In studies that used PCR testing for pan-respiratory viral pathogens, human enterovirus/human rhinovirus (9.4% (95% CI 0% to 20.5%)) and several other respiratory pathogenic viruses were detected. The epidemiology varied depending on the methodology and situation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The epidemiology of CAP varies depending on the situation, such as in the hospital versus outpatient setting. Viruses are more frequently detected by exhaustive genetic searches, resulting in a significant variation in epidemiology.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fujikura</LastName><ForeName>Yuji</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7384-2167</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and Respiratory Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, National Defense Medical College, Tokorozawa, Saitama, Japan fujikura@ndmc.ac.jp.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Risk Management and Infection Control, National Defense Medical College Hospital, Tokorozawa, Saitama, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Somekawa</LastName><ForeName>Kohei</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonology, Yokohama City University Graduate School of Medicine, Yokohama, Kanagawa, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manabe</LastName><ForeName>Toshie</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Medical Science, Nagoya City University, Nagoya, Aichi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>West Medical Center, Nagoya City University, Nagoya, Aichi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Horita</LastName><ForeName>Nobuyuki</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chemotherapy Center, Yokohama City University Hospital, Yokohama, Kanagawa, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takahashi</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Saka General Hospital, Shiogama, Miyagi, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Higa</LastName><ForeName>Futoshi</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Respiratory Medicine, National Hospital Organization Okinawa National Hospital, Ginowan, Okinawa, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yatera</LastName><ForeName>Kazuhiro</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2955-4432</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, University of Occupational and Environmental Health, Japan, Kitakyushu, Fukuoka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miyashita</LastName><ForeName>Naoyuki</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>First Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Respiratory Medicine, Infectious Disease and Allergology, Kansai Medical University, Hirakata, Osaka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Imamura</LastName><ForeName>Yoshifumi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Education Development Center, Nagasaki University Hospital, Nagasaki, Nagasaki, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iwanaga</LastName><ForeName>Naoki</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Nagasaki University Hospital, Nagasaki, Nagasaki, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mukae</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Nagasaki University Graduate School of Biomedical Science, Nagasaki, Nagasaki, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kawana</LastName><ForeName>Akihiko</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and Respiratory Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, National Defense Medical College, Tokorozawa, Saitama, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMJ Open Respir Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101638061</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2052-4439</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacterial infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pneumonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral infection</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interests: YF: Payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, speakers bureaus, manuscript writing or educational events (Kyorin Pharmaceutical). HM: Grants or contracts (Taiho Pharmaceutical, Meiji Seika Pharma, Kyorin Pharmaceutical, Nippon Boehringer Ingelheim, Taisho Pharma, SHIONOGI, OTSUKA Pharmaceutical), Payment or honoraria for lectures, presentations, speakers bureaus, manuscript writing or educational events (Eli Lilly Japan K.K., Taiho Pharmaceutical, Teijin Healthcare, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Chugai Pharmaceutical, Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., Meiji Seika Pharma, Asahi Kasei Pharma, Sumitomo Pharma, Kyorin Pharmaceutical, Taisho Pharma, AstraZeneca K.K., Astellas Pharma, SHIONOGI, Daiichi Sankyo, Pfizer, MSD, Nippon Boehringer Ingelheim, FUJIFILM Toyama Chemical, Miyarisan Pharmaceutical, Novartis Pharma K.K, GlaxoSmithKline K.K., Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare., Insmed Incorporated, Sanofi K.K., Gilead Sciences., Kyokuto Pharmaceutical Industrial, TAUNS Laboratories, Takeda Pharmaceutical, bioMérieux Japan, Merck Biopharma, Tosoh Corporation, Nippon Kayaku), Payment for expert testimony (Kyorin Pharmaceutical, SHIONOGI, MSD, Gilead Sciences, Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., Meiji Seika Pharma, Taiho Pharmaceutical, Insmed Incorporated).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37751988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10533802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2023-001800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10/1/e001800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mandell LA, Wunderink RG, Anzueto A, et al. . Infectious diseases society of America/American Thoracic Society consensus guidelines on the management of community-acquired pneumonia in adults. Clin Infect Dis 2007;44 Suppl 2:S27–72. 10.1086/511159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/511159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7107997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17278083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>File TM. Community-acquired pneumonia. Lancet 2003;362:1991–2001. 10.1016/S0140-6736(03)15021-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)15021-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7119317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14683661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musher DM, Thorner AR. Community-acquired pneumonia. N Engl J Med 2014;371:1619–28. 10.1056/NEJMra1312885</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1312885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25337751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kollef MH, Sherman G, Ward S, et al. . Inadequate antimicrobial treatment of infections: a risk factor for hospital mortality among critically ill patients. Chest 1999;115:462–74. 10.1378/chest.115.2.462</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1378/chest.115.2.462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10027448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arancibia F, Ewig S, Martinez JA, et al. . Antimicrobial treatment failures in patients with community-acquired pneumonia: causes and prognostic implications. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2000;162:154–60. 10.1164/ajrccm.162.1.9907023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.162.1.9907023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10903235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosón B, Carratalà J, Fernández-Sabé N, et al. . Causes and factors associated with early failure in hospitalized patients with community-acquired pneumonia. Arch Intern Med 2004;164:502–8. 10.1001/archinte.164.5.502</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archinte.164.5.502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15006826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metlay JP, Waterer GW, Long AC, et al. . Diagnosis and treatment of adults with community-acquired pneumonia. An official clinical practice guideline of the American Thoracic Society and infectious diseases society of America. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2019;200:e45–67. 10.1164/rccm.201908-1581ST</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.201908-1581ST</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6812437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31573350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haessler S, Guo N, Deshpande A, et al. . Etiology, treatments, and outcomes of patients with severe community-acquired pneumonia in a large U.S. sample. Crit Care Med 2022;50:1063–71. 10.1097/CCM.0000000000005498</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000005498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9233133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35191410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberati A, Altman DG, Tetzlaff J, et al. . The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate healthcare interventions: explanation and elaboration. BMJ 2009;339:b2700. 10.1136/bmj.b2700</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2714672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19622552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroup DF, Berlin JA, Morton SC, et al. . Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology (MOOSE) group. JAMA 2000;283:2008–12. 10.1001/jama.283.15.2008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.283.15.2008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10789670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Thoracic Society, Infectious Diseases Society of America . Guidelines for the management of adults with hospital-acquired, ventilator-associated, and healthcare-associated pneumonia. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2005;171:388–416. 10.1164/rccm.200405-644ST</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.200405-644ST</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15699079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohno S, Imamura Y, Shindo Y, et al. . Clinical practice guidelines for nursing- and Healthcare-associated pneumonia (NHCAP) [complete translation]. Respir Investig 2013;51:103–26. 10.1016/j.resinv.2012.11.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2012.11.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23790739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Committee for The Japanese Respiratory Society guidelines for the management of respiratory infections . Guidelines for the management of community acquired pneumonia in adults. Respirology 2006;11 Suppl 3:S79–133. 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2006.00937_1.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2006.00937_1.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16913899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang GD, Fine M, Orloff J, et al. . New and emerging etiologies for community-acquired pneumonia with implications for therapy. A prospective multicenter study of 359 cases. Medicine (Baltimore) 1990;69:307–16. 10.1097/00005792-199009000-00004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00005792-199009000-00004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2205784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyashita N, Ouchi K, Kawasaki K, et al. . Comparison of serological tests for detection of immunoglobulin M antibodies to chlamydophila pneumoniae. Respirology 2008;13:427–31. 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2007.01230.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2007.01230.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18399867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agresti A, Coull BA. “Approximate is better than "exact" for interval estimation of binomial proportions”. The American Statistician 1998;52:119. 10.2307/2685469</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2685469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tagagi H, Umeno M, Tanaka M, et al. . Clinical evaluation of community-acquired pneumonia in recent 3 years. Rinsyo-to-Kenkyu 1995;72:2791–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishida T, Hashimoto T, Arita M, et al. . Etiology of community-acquired pneumonia in hospitalized patients: a 3-year prospective study in Japan. Chest 1998;114:1588–93. 10.1378/chest.114.6.1588</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1378/chest.114.6.1588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9872193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motomura K, Takasugi M, Furumoto A, et al. . [Clinical features and etiology of community-acquired pneumonia at a general hospital between 1994 and 1997]. Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi 2000;38:267–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10879028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watari M, Ohe M, Kunimoto E, et al. . Mortality and prognostic factors in patients with community-acquired pneumonia: an analysis of 231 cases. Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi 2000;38:509–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11019564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobashi Y, Ohba H, Yoneyama H, et al. . Clinical analysis of patients with community-acquired pneumonia requiring hospitalization classified by age group (in Japanese). Kansenshogakuzasshi 2001;75:193–200. 10.11150/kansenshogakuzasshi1970.75.193</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11150/kansenshogakuzasshi1970.75.193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11321779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato T, Aoshima M, Ohmagari N, et al. . Usefulness of sputum gram staining in community-acquired pneumonia. Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi 2002;40:558–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12382418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okimoto N, Kurihara T, Honda N, et al. . Clinical effect of ampicillin with beta-Lactamase inhibitor (Sulbactam/Ampicillin) on community-acquired pneumonia in the elderly. J Infect Chemother 2003;9:183–6. 10.1007/s10156-003-0233-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-003-0233-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12825120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchiyama N, Aoshima M, Satoh T, et al. . The efficacy of switch therapy in community-acquired pneumonia in Japan. Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi 2003;41:261–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12795180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawai S, Ochi M, Nakagawa T, et al. . Antimicrobial therapy in community-acquired pneumonia among emergency patients in a University hospital in Japan. J Infect Chemother 2004;10:352–8. 10.1007/s10156-004-0350-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-004-0350-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15614461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyashita N, Fukano H, Mouri K, et al. . Community-acquired pneumonia in Japan: a prospective ambulatory and hospitalized patient study. J Med Microbiol 2005;54:395–400. 10.1099/jmm.0.45920-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.45920-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15770027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motomura K, Masaki H, Terada M, et al. . Usefulness of the Japanese respiratory society guidelines for community pneumonia: a retrospective analysis of community-acquired pneumonia between 2000 and 2002 in a general hospital. Respirology 2005;10:208–14. 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2005.00664.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2005.00664.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15823187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshimoto A, Nakamura H, Fujimura M, et al. . Severe community-acquired pneumonia in an intensive care unit: risk factors for mortality. Intern Med 2005;44:710–6. 10.2169/internalmedicine.44.710</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.44.710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16093592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saito A, Kohno S, Matsushima T, et al. . Prospective multicenter study of the causative organisms of community-acquired pneumonia in adults in Japan. J Infect Chemother 2006;12:63–9. 10.1007/s10156-005-0425-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-005-0425-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16648944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanagihara K, Fukuda Y, Seki M, et al. . Clinical comparative study of sulbactam/ampicillin and imipenem/Cilastatin in elderly patients with community-acquired pneumonia. Intern Med 2006;45:995–9. 10.2169/internalmedicine.45.1717</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.45.1717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17015999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiki R, Kawayama T, Ueyama T, et al. . The risk factors for mortality of community-acquired pneumonia in Japan. J Infect Chemother 2007;13:157–65. 10.1007/s10156-007-0512-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-007-0512-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17593502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirakata Y, Yanagihara K, Kurihara S, et al. . Comparison of usefulness of plasma procalcitonin and C-reactive protein measurements for estimation of severity in adults with community-acquired pneumonia. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis 2008;61:170–4. 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2008.01.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2008.01.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18329217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tashiro M, Fukushima K, Hara A, et al. . Evaluation of the severity of community-acquired pneumonia based on the JRS and IDSA/ATS guidelines. Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi 2008;46:981–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19195197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shindo Y, Sato S, Maruyama E, et al. . Health-care-associated pneumonia among hospitalized patients in a Japanese community hospital. Chest 2009;135:633–40. 10.1378/chest.08-1357</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1378/chest.08-1357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19017892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanagihara K, Izumikawa K, Higa F, et al. . Efficacy of azithromycin in the treatment of community-acquired pneumonia, including patients with macrolide-resistant streptococcus pneumoniae infection. Intern Med 2009;48:527–35. 10.2169/internalmedicine.48.1482</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.48.1482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19336954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maruyama T, Gabazza EC, Morser J, et al. . Community-acquired pneumonia and nursing home-acquired pneumonia in the very elderly patients. Respir Med 2010;104:584–92. 10.1016/j.rmed.2009.12.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2009.12.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20060700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohno S, Seki M, Watanabe A, et al. . Evaluation of an assessment system for the JRS 2005: a-DROP for the management of CAP in adults. Intern Med 2011;50:1183–91. 10.2169/internalmedicine.50.4651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.50.4651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21628933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakanishi M, Yoshida Y, Takeda N, et al. . Community-acquired pneumonia distinguished from influenza infection based on clinical signs and symptoms during a novel (swine) influenza A/H1N1 pandemic. Prim Care Respir J 2011;20:421–6. 10.4104/pcrj.2011.00067</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4104/pcrj.2011.00067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6549881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21808939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seki M, Hashiguchi K, Tanaka A, et al. . Characteristics and disease severity of Healthcare-associated pneumonia among patients in a hospital in Kitakyushu, Japan. J Infect Chemother 2011;17:363–9. 10.1007/s10156-010-0127-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-010-0127-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20931256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umeki K, Tokimatsu I, Yasuda C, et al. . Clinical features of healthcare-associated pneumonia (HCAP) in a Japanese community hospital: comparisons among nursing home-acquired pneumonia (NHAP), HCAP other than NHAP, and community-acquired pneumonia. Respirology 2011;16:856–61. 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.01983.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.01983.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21545370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida K, Okimoto N, Kishimoto M, et al. . Efficacy and safety of moxifloxacin for community-acquired bacterial pneumonia based on pharmacokinetic analysis. J Infect Chemother 2011;17:678–85. 10.1007/s10156-011-0282-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-011-0282-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21847518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujii M, Iwakami S, Takagi H, et al. . Factors influencing Weaning from mwechanical ventilation in elderly patients with severe pneumonia. Geriatr Gerontol Int 2012;12:277–83. 10.1111/j.1447-0594.2011.00765.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1447-0594.2011.00765.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22066870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horie M, Ugajin M, Suzuki M, et al. . Diagnostic and prognostic value of Procalcitonin in community-acquired pneumonia. Am J Med Sci 2012;343:30–5. 10.1097/MAJ.0b013e31821d33ef</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MAJ.0b013e31821d33ef</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22207498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasamatsu Y, Yamaguchi T, Kawaguchi T, et al. . Usefulness of a semi-quantitative procalcitonin test and the A-DROP Japanese prognostic scale for predicting mortality among adults hospitalized with community-acquired pneumonia. Respirology 2012;17:330–6. 10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.02101.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.02101.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22059525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyashita N, Kawai Y, Akaike H, et al. . Clinical features and the role of atypical pathogens in nursing and healthcare-associated pneumonia (NHCAP): differences between a teaching University hospital and a community hospital. Intern Med 2012;51:585–94. 10.2169/internalmedicine.51.6475</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.51.6475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22449666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugisaki M, Enomoto T, Shibuya Y, et al. . Clinical characteristics of healthcare-associated pneumonia in a public hospital in a metropolitan area of Japan. J Infect Chemother 2012;18:352–60. 10.1007/s10156-011-0344-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-011-0344-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22116463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishiguro T, Takayanagi N, Yamaguchi S, et al. . Etiology and factors contributing to the severity and mortality of community-acquired pneumonia. Intern Med 2013;52:317–24. 10.2169/internalmedicine.52.8830</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.52.8830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23370738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishikawa G, Nishimura N, Kitamura A, et al. . Impact of blood cultures on the changes of treatment in hospitalized patients with community-acquired pneumonia. Open Respir Med J 2013;7:60–6. 10.2174/1874306401307010060</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1874306401307010060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3735926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23935766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohno S, Seki M, Takehara K, et al. . Prediction of requirement for mechanical ventilation in community-acquired pneumonia with acute respiratory failure: a multicenter prospective study. Respiration 2013;85:27–35. 10.1159/000335466</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000335466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22343936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maruyama T, Fujisawa T, Okuno M, et al. . A new strategy for Healthcare-associated pneumonia: a 2-year prospective multicenter cohort study using risk factors for multidrug-resistant pathogens to select initial empiric therapy. Clin Infect Dis 2013;57:1373–83. 10.1093/cid/cit571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cit571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23999080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshitani Y, Nagai H, Matsui H, et al. . Reevaluation of the Japanese guideline for healthcare-associated pneumonia in a medium-sized community hospital in Japan. J Infect Chemother 2013;19:579–87. 10.1007/s10156-012-0517-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-012-0517-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23179959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shindo Y, Ito R, Kobayashi D, et al. . Risk factors for drug-resistant pathogens in community-acquired and healthcare-associated pneumonia. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2013;188:985–95. 10.1164/rccm.201301-0079OC</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.201301-0079OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23855620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukuyama H, Yamashiro S, Kinjo K, et al. . Validation of Sputum gram stain for treatment of community-acquired pneumonia and healthcare-associated pneumonia: a prospective observational study. BMC Infect Dis 2014;14:534. 10.1186/1471-2334-14-534</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-14-534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4287475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25326650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosai K, Izumikawa K, Imamura Y, et al. . Importance of functional assessment in the management of community-acquired and healthcare-associated pneumonia. Intern Med 2014;53:1613–20. 10.2169/internalmedicine.53.2499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.53.2499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25088872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsunuma R, Asai N, Ohkuni Y, et al. . I-ROAD could be efficient in predicting severity of community-acquired pneumonia or healthcare-associated pneumonia. Singapore Med J 2014;55:318–24. 10.11622/smedj.2014082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11622/smedj.2014082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4294059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25017407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawa N, Saito Y, Sasaki M, et al. . Comparison of clinical profile in elderly patients with nursing and healthcare-associated pneumonia, and those with community-acquired pneumonia. Geriatr Gerontol Int 2014;14:362–71. 10.1111/ggi.12110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ggi.12110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23829585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakoda Y, Ikegame S, Ikeda-Harada C, et al. . Retrospective analysis of nursing and healthcare-associated pneumonia: analysis of adverse prognostic factors and validity of the selection criteria. Respir Investig 2014;52:114–20. 10.1016/j.resinv.2013.08.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2013.08.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24636267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takaki M, Nakama T, Ishida M, et al. . High incidence of community-acquired pneumonia among rapidly aging population in Japan: a prospective hospital-based surveillance. Jpn J Infect Dis 2014;67:269–75. 10.7883/yoken.67.269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7883/yoken.67.269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25056072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura M, Watanabe M, Nakajima A, et al. . Serial Quantification of Procalcitonin (PCT) predicts clinical outcome and prognosis in patients with community-acquired pneumonia (CAP). J Infect Chemother 2014;20:97–103. 10.1016/j.jiac.2013.09.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2013.09.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24462441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ugajin M, Yamaki K, Hirasawa N, et al. . Predictive values of semi-quantitative procalcitonin test and common biomarkers for the clinical outcomes of community-acquired pneumonia. Respir Care 2014;59:564–73. 10.4187/respcare.02807</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4187/respcare.02807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24170911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hifumi T, Jinbo I, Okada I, et al. . The impact of age on outcomes of elderly ED patients ventilated due to community acquired pneumonia. Am J Emerg Med 2015;33:277–81. 10.1016/j.ajem.2014.10.046</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2014.10.046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25541226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamata K, Suzuki H, Kanemoto K, et al. . Clinical evaluation of the need for carbapenems to treat community-acquired and healthcare-associated pneumonia. J Infect Chemother 2015;21:596–603. 10.1016/j.jiac.2015.05.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2015.05.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26070781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohno S, Tateda K, Mikamo H, et al. . Efficacy and safety of intravenous sulbactam/ampicillin 3 G 4 times daily in Japanese adults with moderate to severe community-acquired pneumonia: a multicenter, open-label, uncontrolled study. J Infect Chemother 2015;21:182–8. 10.1016/j.jiac.2014.11.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2014.11.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25533886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haga T, Fukuoka M, Morita M, et al. . Computed tomography for the diagnosis and evaluation of the severity of community-acquired pneumonia in the elderly. Intern Med 2016;55:437–41. 10.2169/internalmedicine.55.5556</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.55.5556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26935360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumagai S, Ishida T, Tachibana H, et al. . Polybacterial aetiology and outcomes in patients with community-acquired pneumonia. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 2016;20:129–35. 10.5588/ijtld.15.0353</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5588/ijtld.15.0353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26688539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurai D, Sasaki Y, Saraya T, et al. . Pathogen profiles and molecular epidemiology of respiratory viruses in Japanese inpatients with community-acquired pneumonia. Respir Investig 2016;54:255–63. 10.1016/j.resinv.2016.01.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2016.01.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27424825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parrott G, Nebeya D, Kinjo T, et al. . Etiological analysis and epidemiological comparison among adult CAP and NHCAP patients in Okinawa, Japan. J Infect Chemother 2017;23:452–8. 10.1016/j.jiac.2017.03.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2017.03.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28431934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asai N, Watanabe H, Shiota A, et al. . Efficacy and accuracy of qSOFA and SOFA scores as prognostic tools for community-acquired and healthcare-associated pneumonia. Int J Infect Dis 2019;84:89–96. 10.1016/j.ijid.2019.04.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2019.04.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31028877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ito A, Ito I, Inoue D, et al. . The utility of serial procalcitonin measurements in addition to pneumonia severity scores in hospitalised community-acquired pneumonia: a multicentre, prospective study. Int J Infect Dis 2020;92:228–33. 10.1016/j.ijid.2020.01.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.01.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31981766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miki M, Mikasa K, Kadota J, et al. . Phase III double-blind comparative study of intravenous lascufloxacin and levofloxacin in patients with community-acquired pneumonia. Jpn J Chemother 2021;69:255–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Hara Y, Horita N, et al. . Is rehabilitation effective in preventing decreased functional status after community-acquired pneumonia in elderly patients? Results from a Multicentre, retrospective observational study. BMJ Open 2022;12:e051307. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-051307</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-051307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9478837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36109034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komiya K, Yamamoto T, Yoshikawa H, et al. . Factors associated with gravity-dependent distribution on chest CT in elderly patients with community-acquired pneumonia: a retrospective observational study. Sci Rep 2022;12:8023. 10.1038/s41598-022-12092-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-12092-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9110711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35577830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carugati M, Aliberti S, Sotgiu G, et al. . Bacterial etiology of community-acquired pneumonia in immunocompetent hospitalized patients and appropriateness of empirical treatment recommendations: an international point-prevalence study. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis 2020;39:1513–25. 10.1007/s10096-020-03870-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-020-03870-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7222990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32242314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis PO. Risk factor evaluation for methicillin-resistant staphylococcus aureus and pseudomonas aeruginosa in community-acquired pneumonia. Ann Pharmacother 2021;55:36–43. 10.1177/1060028020935106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1060028020935106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32545992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadros M, Williams V, Coleman BL, et al. . Epidemiology and outcome of pneumonia caused by methicillin-resistant staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) in Canadian hospitals. PLoS One 2013;8:e75171. 10.1371/journal.pone.0075171</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3775759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24069391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain S, Self WH, Wunderink RG, et al. . Community-acquired pneumonia requiring hospitalization. N Engl J Med 2015;373:415–27. 10.1056/NEJMc1511751</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1511751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9338768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26650159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musher DM, Abers MS, Bartlett JG. Evolving understanding of the causes of pneumonia in adults, with special attention to the role of pneumococcus. Clin Infect Dis 2017;65:1736–44. 10.1093/cid/cix549</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cix549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29028977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naito T, Suzuki M, Fujibayashi K, et al. . The estimated impact of the 5-year national vaccination program on the trend of 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine vaccination rates in the elderly in Japan, 2009-2018. J Infect Chemother 2020;26:407–10. 10.1016/j.jiac.2019.12.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2019.12.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31924523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self WH, Wunderink RG, Williams DJ, et al. . Staphylococcus aureus community-acquired pneumonia: prevalence, clinical characteristics, and outcomes. Clin Infect Dis 2016;63:300–9. 10.1093/cid/ciw300</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciw300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4946021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27161775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanagihara K, Matsumoto T, Tokimatsu I, et al. . Nationwide surveillance of bacterial respiratory pathogens conducted by the surveillance committee of Japanese Society of Chemotherapy, the Japanese Association for Infectious Diseases, and the Japanese Society for Clinical Microbiology in 2016: general view of the pathogens' antibacterial susceptibility. J Infect Chemother 2020;26:873–81. 10.1016/j.jiac.2020.05.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2020.05.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32565151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murakami Y, Hashimoto S, Kawado M, et al. . Estimated number of patients with influenza A(H1)Pdm09, or other viral types, from 2010 to 2014 in Japan. PLoS One 2016;11:e0146520. 10.1371/journal.pone.0146520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4718664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26784031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health . Number of persons receiving routine immunizations. 2023. Available: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/topics/bcg/other/5.html [Accessed 23 Jul 2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobson J, Whitley RJ, Pocock S, et al. . Oseltamivir treatment for influenza in adults: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Lancet 2015;385:1729–37. 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)62449-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)62449-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25640810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson N, Kalin M, Tiveljung-Lindell A, et al. . Etiology of community-acquired pneumonia: increased microbiological yield with new diagnostic methods. Clin Infect Dis 2010;50:202–9. 10.1086/648678</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/648678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7107844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20014950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennings LC, Anderson TP, Beynon KA, et al. . Incidence and characteristics of viral community-acquired pneumonia in adults. Thorax 2008;63:42–8. 10.1136/thx.2006.075077</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thx.2006.075077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17573440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angeles Marcos M, Camps M, Pumarola T, et al. . The role of viruses in the aetiology of community-acquired pneumonia in adults. Antivir Ther 2006;11:351–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16759052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy CN, Fowler R, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. . Multicenter evaluation of the biofire filmarray pneumonia/pneumonia plus panel for detection and quantification of agents of lower respiratory tract infection. J Clin Microbiol 2020;58:e00128-20. 10.1128/JCM.00128-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00128-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7315029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32350043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickson RP, Erb-Downward JR, Huffnagle GB. Towards an Ecology of the lung: new conceptual models of pulmonary microbiology and pneumonia pathogenesis. The Lancet Respiratory Medicine 2014;2:238–46. 10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70028-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70028-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4004084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24621685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faner R, Sibila O, Agustí A, et al. . The microbiome in respiratory medicine: current challenges and future perspectives. Eur Respir J 2017;49:1602086. 10.1183/13993003.02086-2016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/13993003.02086-2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28404649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien KL, Baggett HC, Brooks WA. Causes of severe pneumonia requiring hospital admission in children without HIV infection from Africa and Asia: the PERCH multi-country case-control study. Lancet 2019;394:757–79. 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)30721-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)30721-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6727070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31257127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>