<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37702495</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-660X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>61</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of clinical microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Clin Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of the QIAstat-Dx Meningitis/Encephalitis Panel, a multiplex PCR platform for the detection of community-acquired meningoencephalitis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0042623</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0042623</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00426-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/jcm.00426-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Rapid identification of the causative pathogens of central nervous system infections is essential for providing appropriate management and improving patient outcomes. The performance of QIAstat-Dx Meningitis/Encephalitis (ME) Panel-a multiplex PCR testing platform-in detecting pathogens implicated in meningitis and/or encephalitis was evaluated using BioFire FilmArray ME Panel as a comparator method. This multicenter study analyzed 585 retrospective residual cerebrospinal fluid specimens and 367 contrived specimens. The QIAstat-Dx ME Panel showed positive percent agreement (PPA) values of 100% for <i>Neisseria meningitidis</i>, <i>Streptococcus agalactiae</i>, <i>Escherichia coli</i> K1, <i>Listeria monocytogenes</i>, and <i>Cryptococcus gattii</i>/<i>neoformans</i> on clinical samples compared to the BioFire FilmArray ME Panel. The PPA values observed for <i>Haemophilus influenzae</i> and <i>Streptococcus pneumoniae</i> were 80% and 88.24%, respectively. Negative percent agreement (NPA) values were &gt;99.0% for each of the six bacterial targets and one fungal target tested with clinical samples. One viral target, herpes simplex virus 1, exhibited a PPA value of 100.0%, while the remaining viral targets-human parechovirus, herpes simplex virus 2, human herpes virus 6, and varicella zoster virus-were &gt;90.0%, with the exception of enterovirus, which had a PPA value of 77.8%. The QIAstat-Dx ME Panel detected five true-positive and four true-negative cases compared to BioFire FilmArray ME Panel. The NPA values for all viral pathogens were &gt;99.0%. Overall, the QIAstat-Dx ME Panel showed comparable performance to the BioFire FilmArray ME Panel as a rapid diagnostic tool for community-acquired meningitis and encephalitis.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Sundelin</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Herlev and Gentofte Hospital , Herlev, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Bialas</LastName><ForeName>Johanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Labor Berlin-Charite Vivantes Services GmbH , Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Diego</LastName><ForeName>Juana</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Labor Berlin-Charite Vivantes Services GmbH , Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hermanowski</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Labor Berlin-Charite Vivantes Services GmbH , Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leibhan</LastName><ForeName>Hendrik</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Labor Berlin-Charite Vivantes Services GmbH , Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ponderand</LastName><ForeName>Léa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de bactériologie, CHU Grenoble Alpes , La Tronche, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Grenoble Alpes, CEA, CNRS, IBS , Grenoble, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Juanola-Falgarona</LastName><ForeName>Marti</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4566-7154</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>STAT-Dx Life S.L. (a QIAGEN Company), Carrer de Baldiri Reixac , Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jones</LastName><ForeName>Tara</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QIAGEN Ltd , Manchester, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rey</LastName><ForeName>Melisa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9433-2222</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>STAT-Dx Life S.L. (a QIAGEN Company), Carrer de Baldiri Reixac , Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johnson</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QIAGEN Ltd , Manchester, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pareja</LastName><ForeName>Josep</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>STAT-Dx Life S.L. (a QIAGEN Company), Carrer de Baldiri Reixac , Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Caspar</LastName><ForeName>Yvan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de bactériologie, CHU Grenoble Alpes , La Tronche, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Grenoble Alpes, CEA, CNRS, IBS , Grenoble, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Clin Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7505564</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0095-1137</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060885" MajorTopicYN="N">Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008581" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004660" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008590" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningoencephalitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">QIAstat-Dx</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">encephalitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meningitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular diagnostics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiplex</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">real-time PCR</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>QIAGEN provided support in the form of salaries for M.J.F., M.R., S.J., and J.P. T.J. was contracted by QIAGEN for clinical consulting. S.J. declares QIAGEN stock or stock option ownership. Y.C., L.P., J.B., M.H., J.D.D., H.L., and T.S. declare that their institution received financial support and study materials from QIAGEN to perform the study and that QIAGEN provided clinical writing support. T.S. declares to have received paid travel expenses by QIAGEN for a user meeting.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37702495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10595057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.00426-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zunt JR, Kassebaum NJ, Blake N, Glennie L, Wright C, Nichols E, Abd-Allah F, Abdela J, Abdelalim A, Adamu AA, Adib MG, Ahmadi A, Ahmed MB, Aichour AN, Aichour I, Aichour MTE, Akseer N, Al-Raddadi RM, Alahdab F, Alene KA, Aljunid SM, AlMazroa MA, Altirkawi K, Alvis-Guzman N, Animut MD, Anjomshoa M, Ansha MG, Asghar RJ, Avokpaho E, Awasthi A, Badali H, Barac A, Bärnighausen TW, Bassat Q, Bedi N, Belachew AB, Bhattacharyya K, Bhutta ZA, Bijani A, Butt ZA, Carvalho F, Castañeda-Orjuela CA, Chitheer A, Choi J-Y, Christopher DJ, Dang AK, Daryani A, Demoz GT, Djalalinia S, Do HP, Dubey M, Dubljanin E, Duken EE, El Sayed Zaki M, Elyazar IR, Fakhim H, Fernandes E, Fischer F, Fukumoto T, Ganji M, Gebre AK, Gebremeskel A, Gessner BD, Gopalani SV, Guo Y, Gupta R, Hailu GB, Haj-Mirzaian A, Hamidi S, Hay SI, Henok A, Irvani SSN, Jha RP, Jürisson M, Kahsay A, Karami M, Karch A, Kasaeian A, Kassa GM, Kassa TDD, Kefale AT, Khader YS, Khalil IA, Khan EA, Khang Y-H, Khubchandani J, Kimokoti RW, Kisa A, Lami FH, Levi M, Li S, Loy CT, Majdan M, Majeed A, Mantovani LG, Martins-Melo FR, Mcalinden C, Mehta V, Melese A, Memish ZA, Mengistu DT, Mengistu G, Mestrovic T, Mezgebe HB, Miazgowski B, Milosevic B, Mokdad AH, Monasta L, Moradi G, Moraga P, Mousavi SM, Mueller UO, Murthy S, Mustafa G, Naghavi M, Naheed A, Naik G, Newton CRJ, Nirayo YL, Nixon MR, Ofori-Asenso R, Ogbo FA, Olagunju AT, Olagunju TO, Olusanya BO, Ortiz JR, Owolabi MO, Patel S, Pinilla-Monsalve GD, Postma MJ, Qorbani M, Rafiei A, Rahimi-Movaghar V, Reiner RC, Renzaho AMN, Rezai MS, Roba KT, Ronfani L, Roshandel G, Rostami A, Safari H, Safari S, Safiri S, Sagar R, Samy AM, Santric Milicevic MM, Sartorius B, Sarvi S, Sawhney M, Saxena S, Shafieesabet A, Shaikh MA, Sharif M, Shigematsu M, Si S, Skiadaresi E, Smith M, Somayaji R, Sufiyan MB, Tawye NY, Temsah M-H, Tortajada-Girbés M, Tran BX, Tran KB, Ukwaja KN, Ullah I, Vujcic IS, Wagnew FS, Waheed Y, Weldegwergs KG, Winkler AS, Wiysonge CS, Wiyeh AB, Wyper GMA, Yimer EM, Yonemoto N, Zaidi Z, Zenebe ZM, Feigin VL, Vos T, Murray CJL. 2018. Global, regional, and national burden of meningitis, 1990–2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. Lancet Neurol 17:1061–1082. doi:10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30387-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30387-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6234314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30507391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGill F, Heyderman RS, Michael BD, Defres S, Beeching NJ, Borrow R, Glennie L, Gaillemin O, Wyncoll D, Kaczmarski E, Nadel S, Thwaites G, Cohen J, Davies NWS, Miller A, Rhodes A, Read RC, Solomon T. 2016. The UK joint specialist societies guideline on the diagnosis and management of acute meningitis and meningococcal sepsis in immunocompetent adults. J Infect 72:405–438. doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2016.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2016.01.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26845731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramanan P, Bryson AL, Binnicker MJ, Pritt BS, Patel R. 2018. Syndromic panel-based testing in clinical microbiology. Clin Microbiol Rev 31:e00024-17. doi:10.1128/CMR.00024-17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00024-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5740973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29142077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tunkel AR, Glaser CA, Bloch KC, Sejvar JJ, Marra CM, Roos KL, Hartman BJ, Kaplan SL, Scheld WM, Whitley RJ, Infectious Diseases Society of America . 2008. The management of encephalitis: clinical practice guidelines by the infectious diseases society of America. Clin Infect Dis 47:303–327. doi:10.1086/589747</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/589747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18582201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van de Beek D, Cabellos C, Dzupova O, Esposito S, Klein M, Kloek AT, Leib SL, Mourvillier B, Ostergaard C, Pagliano P, Pfister HW, Read RC, Sipahi OR, Brouwer MC, ESCMID Study Group for Infections of the Brain (ESGIB) . 2016. ESCMID guideline: diagnosis and treatment of acute bacterial meningitis. Clin Microbiol Infect 22:S37–S62. doi:10.1016/j.cmi.2016.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2016.01.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27062097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesan A, Tunkel AR, Bloch KC, Lauring AS, Sejvar J, Bitnun A, Stahl J-P, Mailles A, Drebot M, Rupprecht CE, Yoder J, Cope JR, Wilson MR, Whitley RJ, Sullivan J, Granerod J, Jones C, Eastwood K, Ward KN, Durrheim DN, Solbrig MV, Guo-Dong L, Glaser CA, International Encephalitis Consortium . 2013. Case definitions, diagnostic algorithms, and priorities in encephalitis: consensus statement of the international encephalitis consortium. Clin Infect Dis 57:1114–1128. doi:10.1093/cid/cit458</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cit458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3783060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23861361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van de Beek D, Brouwer M, Hasbun R, Koedel U, Whitney CG, Wijdicks E. 2016. Community-acquired bacterial meningitis. Nat Rev Dis Primers 2:16074. doi:10.1038/nrdp.2016.74</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2016.74</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27808261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer MC, Tunkel AR, van de Beek D. 2010. Epidemiology, diagnosis, and antimicrobial treatment of acute bacterial meningitis. Clin Microbiol Rev 23:467–492. doi:10.1128/CMR.00070-09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00070-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2901656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20610819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leber AL, Everhart K, Balada-Llasat J-M, Cullison J, Daly J, Holt S, Lephart P, Salimnia H, Schreckenberger PC, DesJarlais S, Reed SL, Chapin KC, LeBlanc L, Johnson JK, Soliven NL, Carroll KC, Miller J-A, Dien Bard J, Mestas J, Bankowski M, Enomoto T, Hemmert AC, Bourzac KM. 2016. Multicenter evaluation of biofire filmarray meningitis/encephalitis panel for detection of bacteria, viruses, and yeast in cerebrospinal fluid specimens. J Clin Microbiol 54:2251–2261. doi:10.1128/JCM.00730-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00730-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5005480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27335149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darnell RB. 1993. The polymerase chain reaction: application to nervous system disease. Ann Neurol 34:513–523. doi:10.1002/ana.410340404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ana.410340404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7692807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>QIAGEN GmbH . 2022. Qiastat-DX meningitis/encephalitis (ME) panel instructions for use (Handbook). QIAGEN GmbH, Hilden, Germany.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
BioFire Diagnostics . 2021. Biofire Filmarray ME panel CE IVD instruction booklet. BioFire Diagnostics, LLC, Salt Lake City, UT. https://www.biofiredx.qarad.eifu.online/ITI/US/en/all?keycode=ITI0035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tansarli GS, Chapin KC. 2020. Diagnostic test accuracy of the BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Microbiol Infect 26:281–290. doi:10.1016/j.cmi.2019.11.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2019.11.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31760115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mailles A, Stahl J-P, Steering Committee and Investigators Group . 2009. Infectious encephalitis in France in 2007: a national prospective study. Clin Infect Dis 49:1838–1847. doi:10.1086/648419</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/648419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19929384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindström J, Elfving K, Lindh M, Westin J, Studahl M. 2022. Assessment of the filmarray ME panel in 4199 consecutively tested cerebrospinal fluid samples. Clin Microbiol Infect 28:79–84. doi:10.1016/j.cmi.2021.05.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2021.05.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34015534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Halloran JA, Franklin A, Lainhart W, Burnham C-A, Powderly W, Dubberke E. 2017. Pitfalls associated with the use of molecular diagnostic panels in the diagnosis of cryptococcal meningitis. Open Forum Infect Dis 4:fx242. doi:10.1093/ofid/ofx242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofx242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5726458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29255738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis PO, Lanier CG, Patel PD, Krolikowski WD, Krolikowski MA. 2020. False negative diagnostic errors with polymerase chain reaction for the detection of cryptococcal meningoencephalitis. Med Mycol 58:408–410. doi:10.1093/mmy/myz064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/mmy/myz064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31212317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Panel on Opportunistic Infections in Adults and Adolescents with HIV . n.d.
Guidelines for the prevention and treatment of opportunistic infections in adults and adolescents with HIV:Recommendations from the centers for disease control and prevention, the National Institutes of health, and the HIV medicine Association of the infectious diseases society of America. Available from: http://aidsinfo.nih.gov/contentfiles/lvguidelines/adult_oi.pdf
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouam A, Vincent JJ, Drancourt M, Raoult D, Levy PY. 2021. Preventing contamination of PCR-based multiplex assays including the use of a dedicated biosafety cabinet. Lett Appl Microbiol 72:98–103. doi:10.1111/lam.13375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/lam.13375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33245575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waldrop G, Zucker J, Boubour A, Radmard S, Green DA, Thakur KT. 2022. Clinical significance of positive results of the biofire cerebrospinal fluid filmarray meningitis/encephalitis panel at a tertiary medical center in the United States. Arch Pathol Lab Med 146:194–200. doi:10.5858/arpa.2020-0380-OA</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5858/arpa.2020-0380-OA</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34086848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto Y. 2002. PCR in diagnosis of infection: detection of bacteria in cerebrospinal fluids. Clin Diagn Lab Immunol 9:508–514. doi:10.1128/cdli.9.3.508-514.2002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cdli.9.3.508-514.2002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC119969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11986253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liesman RM, Strasburg AP, Heitman AK, Theel ES, Patel R, Binnicker MJ. 2018. Evaluation of a commercial multiplex molecular panel for diagnosis of infectious meningitis and encephalitis. J Clin Microbiol 56:e01927-17. doi:10.1128/JCM.01927-17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01927-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5869843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29436421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsiodras S, Kelesidis I, Kelesidis T, Stamboulis E, Giamarellou H. 2005. Central nervous system manifestations of Mycoplasma pneumoniae infections. J Infect 51:343–354. doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2005.07.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2005.07.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16181677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plainvert C, Doloy A, Joubrel C, Maataoui N, Dmytruk N, Touak G, Collobert G, Fouet A, Poyart C, Loubinoux J. 2016. Characterization of Streptococcus pyogenes isolates responsible for adult meningitis in France from 2003 to 2013. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis 84:350–352. doi:10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.12.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.12.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26846900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>