<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37736299</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2001-0370</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>21</Volume><PubDate><Year>2023</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Computational and structural biotechnology journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Featured interactome of homocysteine-inducible endoplasmic reticulum protein uncovers novel binding partners in response to ER stress.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>4478</StartPage><EndPage>4487</EndPage><MedlinePgn>4478-4487</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.csbj.2023.09.006</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Homocysteine-inducible endoplasmic reticulum protein (HERP) is an endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-resident protein and important for the adaptation of cellular protein homeostasis by ER-associated degradation (ERAD) system. HERP interactors are critical for cellular viability and the reaction to ER stress. To explore the exact mechanisms by which HERP performed the biological functions, we conducted an interaction analysis of HERP protein in HeLa cells by co-immunoprecipitation (Co-IP) and liquid chromatography-mass spectrometer (LC-MS)/MS coupled with label-free quantification (LFQ). Among the interactome results, 123 proteins significantly interacted with HERP, which leads to numerous biological processes including protein import into nucleus, ubiquitin-dependent ERAD pathway, negative regulation of apoptotic process, and protein transport from ER, along with multiple pathways including several diseases, protein processing in ER, fatty acid metabolism, and steroid biosynthesis. Furthermore, we selected several prey proteins from the interactome data and confirmed that HERP interacted with ancient ubiquitous protein 1 (AUP1), Fas-associated factor family member 2 (FAF2), tripartite motif containing 47 (TRIM47), acyl-CoA synthetase long-chain family member 3 (ACSL3), sequestosome 1 (SQSTM1), and poly(rC) binding protein 2 (PCBP2) by Co-IP and confocal microscopy experiments, respectively. Moreover, the expression and location of several interacted proteins were obviously altered in response to ER stress induced by Thapsigargin stimulation and Enterovirus 71 infection. In conclusion, our findings revealed that the vital proteins interacted with HERP to mediate signaling transduction, thus providing novel clues for the mechanisms of HERP associated with ERAD and metabolism in response to ER stress under physiological and pathological conditions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Su</LastName><ForeName>Rui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Henan Key Laboratory of Immunology and Targeted Drug, Xinxiang Medical University, Xinxiang 453003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Xinxiang Medical University, Xinxiang 453003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yin</LastName><ForeName>Jialing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruan</LastName><ForeName>Xiaolan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yanxi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wan</LastName><ForeName>Pin</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wuhan Institute of Biomedical Sciences, School of Medicine, Jianghan University, Wuhan 430072, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Foshan Institute of Medical Microbiology, Foshan 528315, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Microbiology, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Foshan Institute of Medical Microbiology, Foshan 528315, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Viral Pathogenesis &amp; Infection Prevention and Control (Jinan University), Ministry of Education, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101585369</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2001-0370</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioinformatic analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ER stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HERP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Protein interactome</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>We declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37736299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10510068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2023.09.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2001-0370(23)00318-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Schroder M., Kaufman R.J. ER stress and the unfolded protein response. Mutat Res. 2005;569:29–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15603751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okuda-Shimizu Y., Hendershot L.M. Characterization of an ERAD pathway for nonglycosylated BiP substrates, which require Herp. Mol Cell. 2007;28:544–554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2149893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18042451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid H.O., Yadav R.K., Kim H.R., Chae H.J. ER stress: autophagy induction, inhibition and selection. Autophagy. 2015;11:1956–1977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4824587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26389781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang J., Qi L. Quality control in the endoplasmic reticulum: crosstalk between ERAD and UPR pathways. Trends Biochem Sci. 2018;43:593–605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6327314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30056836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerriero C.J., Brodsky J.L. The delicate balance between secreted protein folding and endoplasmic reticulum-associated degradation in human physiology. Physiol Rev. 2012;92:537–576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4162396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22535891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharya A., Qi L. ER-associated degradation in health and disease - from substrate to organism. J Cell Sci. 2019;132</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6918741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31792042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang J., Peterson B.G., Knupp J., B R.D. The ERAD system is restricted by elevated ceramides. Sci Adv. 2023;9:eadd8579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36638172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kokame K., Agarwala K.L., Kato H., Miyata T. Herp, a new ubiquitin-like membrane protein induced by endoplasmic reticulum stress. J Biol Chem. 2000;275:32846–32853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10922362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slodzinski H., Moran L.B., Michael G.J., Wang B., Novoselov S., Cheetham M.E., Pearce R.K., G M.B. Homocysteine-induced endoplasmic reticulum protein (herp) is up-regulated in parkinsonian substantia nigra and present in the core of Lewy bodies. Clin Neuropathol. 2009;28:333–343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19788048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kny M., Standera S., Hartmann-Petersen R., Kloetzel P.M., Seeger M. Herp regulates Hrd1-mediated ubiquitylation in a ubiquitin-like domain-dependent manner. J Biol Chem. 2011;286:5151–5156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3037627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21149444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge M., Luo Z., Qiao Z., Zhou Y., Cheng X., Geng Q., Cai Y., Wan P., Xiong Y., Liu F., Wu K., Liu Y., Wu J. HERP Binds TBK1 To Activate Innate Immunity and Repress Virus Replication in Response to Endoplasmic Reticulum Stress. J Immunol. 2017;199:3280–3292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28954889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulze A., Standera S., Buerger E., Kikkert M., van Voorden S., Wiertz E., Koning F., Kloetzel P.M., Seeger M. The ubiquitin-domain protein HERP forms a complex with components of the endoplasmic reticulum associated degradation pathway. J Mol Biol. 2005;354:1021–1027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16289116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S., Zheng C., Chen Z.Q., Liu R., Li G.G., Hu W.K., Pei H., Li B. Expression of endoplasmic reticulum stress-related factors in the retinas of diabetic rats. Exp Diabetes Res. 2012;2012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3166715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21904541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chigurupati S., Wei Z., Belal C., Vandermey M., Kyriazis G.A., Arumugam T.V., Chan S.L. The homocysteine-inducible endoplasmic reticulum stress protein counteracts calcium store depletion and induction of CCAAT enhancer-binding protein homologous protein in a neurotoxin model of Parkinson disease. J Biol Chem. 2009;284:18323–18333.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2709401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19447887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong N., Morahan G., Stathopoulos M., Proietto J., Andrikopoulos S. A novel mechanism regulating insulin secretion involving Herpud1 in mice. Diabetologia. 2013;56:1569–1576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23620059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei Z.X., Wang J.J., Li K., Liu P. Herp knockout protects against nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in mice on a high fat diet. Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2021;37:487–496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33464700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie X., Liu D., Zheng M., Li X., Liu O., Guo Q., Zhu L., Lin B. HERPUD1 promotes ovarian cancer cell survival by sustaining autophagy and inhibit apoptosis via PI3K/AKT/mTOR and p38 MAPK signaling pathways. BMC Cancer. 2022;22:1338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9769045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36544104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng Y., Li N., Tang F., Qian C., Jia T., Liu J., Xu Y. Corosolic acid sensitizes ferroptosis by upregulating HERPUD1 in liver cancer cells. Cell Death Discov. 2022;8:376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9424261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36038536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leitman J., Shenkman M., Gofman Y., Shtern N.O., Ben-Tal N., Hendershot L.M., Lederkremer G.Z. Herp coordinates compartmentalization and recruitment of HRD1 and misfolded proteins for ERAD. Mol Biol Cell. 2014;25:1050–1060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3967970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24478453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Americo-Da-Silva L., Diaz J., Bustamante M., Mancilla G., Oyarzun I., Verdejo H.E., Quiroga C. A new role for HERPUD1 and ERAD activation in osteoblast differentiation and mineralization. FASEB J. 2018;32:4681–4695.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29570393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Z., Dong X., Li Y., Zhang Q., Kim C., Song Y., Kang L., Liu Y., Wu K., Wu J. PolyC-binding protein 1 interacts with 5′-untranslated region of enterovirus 71 RNA in membrane-associated complex to facilitate viral replication. PLoS One. 2014;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3906175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24489926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mi H., Muruganujan A., Casagrande J.T., Thomas P.D. Large-scale gene function analysis with the PANTHER classification system. Nat Protoc. 2013;8:1551–1566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6519453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23868073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang da W., Sherman B.T., Lempicki R.A. Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nat Protoc. 2009;4:44–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19131956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szklarczyk D., Franceschini A., Wyder S., Forslund K., Heller D., Huerta-Cepas J., Simonovic M., Roth A., Santos A., Tsafou K.P., Kuhn M., Bork P., Jensen L.J., von Mering C. STRING v10: protein-protein interaction networks, integrated over the tree of life. Nucleic Acids Res. 2015;43:D447–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4383874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25352553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon P., Markiel A., Ozier O., Baliga N.S., Wang J.T., Ramage D., Amin N., Schwikowski B., Ideker T. Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome Res. 2003;13:2498–2504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC403769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14597658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su R., Shereen M.A., Zeng X., Liang Y., Li W., Ruan Z., Li Y., Liu W., Liu Y., Wu K., Luo Z., Wu J. The TLR3/IRF1/Type III IFN axis facilitates antiviral responses against enterovirus infections in the intestine. mBio. 2020;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7683398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33203755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim J., Hao T., Shaw C., Patel A.J., Szabo G., Rual J.F., Fisk C.J., Li N., Smolyar A., Hill D.E., Barabasi A.L., Vidal M., Zoghbi H.Y. A protein-protein interaction network for human inherited ataxias and disorders of Purkinje cell degeneration. Cell. 2006;125:801–814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16713569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C.H., Chu Y.R., Ye Y., Chen X. Role of HERP and a HERP-related protein in HRD1-dependent protein degradation at the endoplasmic reticulum. J Biol Chem. 2014;289:4444–4454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3924306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24366871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ming S.L., Zhang S., Wang Q., Zeng L., Zhou L.Y., Wang M.D., Ma Y.X., Han L.Q., Zhong K., Zhu H.S., Bai Y.L., Yang G.Y., Wang J., Chu B.B. Inhibition of USP14 influences alphaherpesvirus proliferation by degrading viral VP16 protein via ER stress-triggered selective autophagy. Autophagy. 2022;18:1801–1821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9450976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34822318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erzurumlu Y., Doganlar Y., Dogan H.K., Catakli D. HERPUD1, a member of the endoplasmic reticulum protein quality control mechanism, may be a good target for suppressing tumorigenesis in breast cancer cells. Turk J Pharm Sci. 2023;20:157–164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10337018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37417198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klemm E.J., Spooner E., Ploegh H.L. Dual role of ancient ubiquitous protein 1 (AUP1) in lipid droplet accumulation and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) protein quality control. J Biol Chem. 2011;286:37602–37614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3199505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21857022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olzmann J.A., Richter C.M., Kopito R.R. Spatial regulation of UBXD8 and p97/VCP controls ATGL-mediated lipid droplet turnover. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2013;110:1345–1350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3557085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23297223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obata Y., Fukumoto Y., Nakayama Y., Kuga T., Dohmae N., Yamaguchi N. The Lyn kinase C-lobe mediates Golgi export of Lyn through conformation-dependent ACSL3 association. J Cell Sci. 2010;123:2649–2662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20605918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji C.H., Kim H.Y., Heo A.J., Lee S.H., Lee M.J., Kim S.B., Srinivasrao G., Mun S.R., Cha-Molstad H., Ciechanover A., Choi C.Y., Lee H.G., Kim B.Y., Kwon Y.T. The N-Degron Pathway Mediates ER-phagy. Mol Cell. 2019;75:1058–1072. e1059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31375263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian Y., Wang Z., Lin H., Lei T., Zhou Z., Huang W., Wu X., Zuo L., Wu J., Liu Y., Wang L.F., Guan X.H., Deng K.Y., Fu M., Xin H.B. TRIM47 is a novel endothelial activation factor that aggravates lipopolysaccharide-induced acute lung injury in mice via K63-linked ubiquitination of TRAF2. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7:148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9072678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35513381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weidensdorfer D., Stohr N., Baude A., Lederer M., Kohn M., Schierhorn A., Buchmeier S., Wahle E., Huttelmaier S. Control of c-myc mRNA stability by IGF2BP1-associated cytoplasmic RNPs. RNA. 2009;15:104–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2612774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19029303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossi Sebastiano M., Pozzato C., Saliakoura M., Yang Z., Peng R.W., Galiè M., Oberson K., Simon H.U., Karamitopoulou E K.G. ACSL3-PAI-1 signaling axis mediates tumor-stroma cross-talk promoting pancreatic cancer progression. Sci Adv. 2020;6:eabb9200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7608806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33127675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saliakoura M., Reynoso-Moreno I., Pozzato C., Rossi Sebastiano M., Galie M., Gertsch J., Konstantinidou G. The ACSL3-LPIAT1 signaling drives prostaglandin synthesis in non-small cell lung cancer. Oncogene. 2020;39:2948–2960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7118021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32034305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loregger A., Raaben M., Tan J., Scheij S., Moeton M., van den Berg M., Gelberg-Etel H., Stickel E., Roitelman J., Brummelkamp T., Zelcer N. Haploid mammalian genetic screen identifies UBXD8 as a key determinant of HMGCR degradation and cholesterol biosynthesis. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2017;37:2064–2074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5671778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28882874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H., Ye J. Cellular responses to excess fatty acids: focus on ubiquitin regulatory X domain-containing protein 8. Curr Opin Lipido. 2014;25:118–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24378746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Lan Y., Li M.Y., Lamers M.M., Fusade-Boyer M., Klemm E., Thiele C., Ashour J., Sanyal S. Flaviviruses Exploit the Lipid Droplet Protein AUP1 to Trigger Lipophagy and Drive Virus Production. Cell Host Microbe. 2018;23:819–831. e815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L., Wang L., Ketkar H., Ma J., Yang G., Cui S., Geng T., Mordue D.G., Fujimoto T., Cheng G., You F., Lin R., Fikrig E., Wang P. UBXN3B positively regulates STING-mediated antiviral immune responses. Nat Commun. 2018;9:2329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5998066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29899553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L., Kashina A. Post-translational modifications of the protein termini. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8358657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34395449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J.X., Xu D., Cao J.W., Zuo L., Han Z.T., Tian Y.J., Chu C.M., Zhou W., Pan X.W., Cui X.G. TRIM47 promotes malignant progression of renal cell carcinoma by degrading P53 through ubiquitination. Cancer Cell Int. 2021;21:129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7903798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33622324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L., Yu Y., Zhang Z., Guo Y., Yin T., Wu H., Yang M. TRIM47 accelerates aerobic glycolysis and tumor progression through regulating ubiquitination of FBP1 in pancreatic cancer. Pharm Res. 2021;166</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33529753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei H., Ding C., Zhuang H., Hu W. TRIM47 Promotes the Development of Glioma by Ubiquitination and Degradation of FOXO1. Onco Targets Ther. 2020;13:13401–13411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7781021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33408486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Q., Tang C., Tang M., Zhang Q., Gao Y., Ge Z. TRIM47 is up-regulated in colorectal cancer, promoting ubiquitination and degradation of SMAD4. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2019;38:159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6461818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30979374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou S., Li G., Li G., Hou C., Zheng Y., Tang L., Gao Y., Mo R., Li Y., Wang R., Shen B., Zhang J., Han G. Ubiquitination and degradation of NF90 by Tim-3 inhibits antiviral innate immunity. Elife. 2021;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8225388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34110282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blyn L.B., Swiderek K.M., Richards O., Stahl D.C., Semler B.L., E E. Poly(rC) binding protein 2 binds to stem-loop IV of the poliovirus RNA 5′ noncoding region identification by automated liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1996;93:11115–11120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC38293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8855318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>You F., Sun H., Zhou X., Sun W., Liang S., Zhai Z., Jiang Z. PCBP2 mediates degradation of the adaptor MAVS via the HECT ubiquitin ligase AIP4. Nat Immunol. 2009;10:1300–1308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19881509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu H., Yang J., Zhang J., Song Y., Zhang Y., Xu P., Zhu Y., Wang L., Zhang P., Li L., Chen D., Sun Q. PCBP2 maintains antiviral signaling homeostasis by regulating cGAS enzymatic activity via antagonizing its condensation. Nat Commun. 2022;13:1564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8943206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35322803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>