<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37820286</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessment of the Clinical Course of Human Rhinovirus/Enterovirus Infections in Pediatric Intensive Care.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e454</StartPage><EndPage>e460</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e454-e460</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004127</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">This study aims to evaluate the clinical course of human rhinovirus/enterovirus (HRV/EV) infections in the pediatric intensive care unit.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">The study was conducted as a multicenter, prospective observational study from September 2022 to December 2022. Cases with positive polymerase chain reaction testing for HRV/EV of nasopharyngeal swab samples within the first 24 hours of pediatric intensive care unit admission were recorded. There were 2 groups: 1-24 months and &gt;24 months.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">A total of 75 cases (39 male) were included in the study. The median age for all cases was 21 months. The highest polymerase chain reaction positivity rates were observed in October (37.33%). Among the cases, 32 (42.67%) presented with bronchopneumonia/pneumonia, 24 (32%) presented with acute bronchiolitis/bronchitis and 7 (9.33%) presented with sepsis/septic shock. The frequency of pediatric acute respiratory distress syndrome was found to be 6.67%. In the age group of 1-24 months, mean lymphocyte and liver enzyme levels were higher, while in the age group of &gt;24 months, mean hemoglobin and mean kidney function test levels were higher ( P ≤ 0.05). Continuous oxygen therapy was provided to 65.3% of the cases, noninvasive ventilation to 33.3%, high-flow nasal cannula-oxygen therapy to 32% and invasive mechanical ventilation to 16%.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">HRV/EV infections primarily affect the respiratory system and generally exhibit a clinical course with low mortality rates (1, 1.3%). In cases with underlying chronic diseases, more severe clinical conditions such as pediatric acute respiratory distress syndrome and septic shock may occur.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kocoglu Barlas</LastName><ForeName>Ulkem</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7445-5858</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Istanbul Medeniyet University, Goztepe Prof Dr Süleyman Yalcin City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akcay</LastName><ForeName>Nihal</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8273-2226</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Kanuni Sultan Suleyman Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Menentoglu</LastName><ForeName>Mehmet Emin</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3839-4722</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Bakirkoy Dr Sadi Konuk Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sevketoglu</LastName><ForeName>Esra</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8330-2877</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Bakirkoy Dr Sadi Konuk Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duyu</LastName><ForeName>Muhterem</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7892-2927</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Istanbul Medeniyet University, Goztepe Prof Dr Süleyman Yalcin City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Telhan</LastName><ForeName>Leyla</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0037-7636</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Istanbul Medipol University, Bagcilar Mega Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kangin</LastName><ForeName>Murat</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0042-0569</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Istanbul Medipol University, Bagcilar Mega Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tugrul</LastName><ForeName>Hazal Ceren</ForeName><Initials>HC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4990-0408</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Umraniye Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erdogan</LastName><ForeName>Seher</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3393-3363</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Umraniye Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Durak</LastName><ForeName>Cansu</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6309-8859</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Sancaktepe Sehit Prof Dr Ilhan Varank Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guney Sahin</LastName><ForeName>Ebru</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2680-2437</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, University of Health Sciences Turkey, Sancaktepe Sehit Prof Dr Ilhan Varank Training and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Umur</LastName><ForeName>Ozge</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5541-2171</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Acibadem Mehmet Ali Aydinlar University, Atakent Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sik</LastName><ForeName>Sare Guntulu</ForeName><Initials>SG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4526-0485</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Acibadem Mehmet Ali Aydinlar University, Atakent Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Citak</LastName><ForeName>Agop</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5108-3913</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Acibadem Mehmet Ali Aydinlar University, Atakent Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yaman</LastName><ForeName>Ayhan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5651-1286</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Intensive Care Unit, Department of Pediatrics, Istinye University, Bahcesehir Liv Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016448">Multicenter Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>S88TT14065</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010100">Oxygen</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012229" MajorTopicYN="N">Rhinovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012772" MajorTopicYN="Y">Shock, Septic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001988" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bronchiolitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010100" MajorTopicYN="N">Oxygen</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003422" MajorTopicYN="N">Critical Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012128" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Distress Syndrome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018450" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Progression</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37820286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202312000-00010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lukashev AN, Vakulenko YA, Turbabina NA, et al. Molecular epidemiology and phylogenetics of human enteroviruses: is there a forest behind the trees? Rev Med Virol. 2018;28:1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spaeder MC, Custer JW, Miles AH, et al. A multicenter outcomes analysis of children with severe rhino/enteroviral respiratory infection. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2015;16:119–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenmoe S, Sadeuh-Mba SA, Vernet M-A, et al. Molecular epidemiology of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses in patients with acute respiratory infections in Yaounde, Cameroon. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15:641–650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granados A, Goodall EC, Luinstra K, et al. Comparison of asymptomatic and symptomatic rhinovirus infections in university students: incidence, species diversity, and viral load. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2015;82:292–296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudi JM, Molina F, Diaz R, et al. The role of rhinovirus in children hospitalized for acute respiratory disease, Santa Fe, Argentina. J Med Virol. 2015;87:2027–2032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Distributed via the CDC Health Alert Network. Severe respiratory illnesses associated with rhinoviruses and/or enteroviruses including EV-D68 – Multistate, 2022 [CDC web site]. September 9, 2022. Available at: https://emergency.cdc.gov/han/2022/han00474.asp . Accessed July 19, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma KC, Winn A, Moline HL, et al.; New Vaccine Surveillance Network Collaborators. Increase in acute respiratory illnesses among children and adolescents associated with rhinoviruses and enteroviruses, including enterovirus D68-United States, July-September 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:1265–1270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khemani RG, Smith LS, Zimmerman JJ, et al.; Pediatric Acute Lung Injury Consensus Conference Group. Pediatric acute respiratory distress syndrome: definition, incidence, and epidemiology: proceedings from the pediatric acute lung injury consensus conference. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2015;16:S23–S40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giardina FAM, Piralla A, Ferrari G, et al. Molecular epidemiology of rhinovirus/enterovirus and their role on cause severe and prolonged infection in hospitalized patients. Microorganisms. 2022;10:755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith ME, Wilson PT. Human rhinovirus/enterovirus in pediatric acute respiratory distress syndrome. J Pediatr Intensive Care. 2020;9:81–86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaime F-S, Catalina CS, Evelyn O, et al. Characterization of rhinovirus/enterovirus complex infection in children living at high altitudes: a cross sectional study. ResearchSquare. 2021. doi: 10.21203/rs.3.rs-209076/v1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-209076/v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jartti T, Lehtinen P, Vuorinen T, et al. Persistence of rhinovirus and enterovirus RNA after acute respiratory illness in children. J Med Virol. 2004;72:695–699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin DA, Spieker AJ, Perez A, et al.; NVSN Network Investigators. Circulation of rhinoviruses and/or enteroviruses in pediatric patients with acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2254909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asner SA, Petrich A, Hamid JS, et al. Clinical severity of rhinovirus/enterovirus compared to other respiratory viruses in children. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2014;8:436–442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg SB. Respiratory consequences of rhinovirus infection. Arch Intern Med. 2003;163:278–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nokso-Koivisto J, Kinnari TJ, Lindahl P, et al. Human picornavirus and coronavirus RNA in nasopharynx of children without concurrent respiratory symptoms. J Med Virol. 2002;66:417–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakes GP, Arruda E, Ingram JM, et al. Rhinovirus and respiratory syncytial virus in wheezing children requiring emergency care. IgE and eosinophil analyses. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1999;159:785–790.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltola V, Waris M, Osterback R, et al. Rhinovirus transmission within families with children: incidence of symptomatic and asymptomatic infections. J Infect Dis. 2008;197:382–389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss SL, Fitzgerald JC, Pappachan J, et al.; Sepsis Prevalence, Outcomes, and Therapies (SPROUT) Study Investigators and Pediatric Acute Lung Injury and Sepsis Investigators (PALISI) Network. Global epidemiology of pediatric severe sepsis: the sepsis prevalence, outcomes, and therapies study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015;191:1147–1157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makvandi M, Teimoori A, Pirmoradi R, et al. Parechovirus and enteroviruses among young infants with sepsis in Iran. Iran J Microbiol. 2021;13:312–318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan I, Esteva C, Esteban E, et al. Severe enterovirus disease in febrile neonates. Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin. 2009;27:399–402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verboon-Maciolek MA, Groenendaal F, Hahn CD, et al. Human parechovirus causes encephalitis with white matter injury in neonates. Ann Neurol. 2008;64:266–273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo J-H, Yeom JS, Youn H-S, et al. Prevalence of human parechovirus and enterovirus in cerebrospinal fluid samples in children in Jinju, Korea. Korean J Pediatr. 2015;58:102–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterback R, Tevaluoto T, Ylinen T, et al. Simultaneous detection and differentiation of human rhino-and enteroviruses in clinical specimens by real-time PCR with locked nucleic acid probes. J Clin Microbiol. 2013;51:3960–3967.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Fischer M, Dominguez SR, et al. Encephalitis in US children. Infect Dis Clin North Am. 2018;32:145–162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazama K, Shiihara T, Tsukagoshi H, et al. Rhinovirus-associated acute encephalitis/encephalopathy and cerebellitis. Brain Dev. 2019;41:551–554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tosato F, Bucciol G, Pantano G, et al. Lymphocytes subsets reference values in childhood. Cytometry A. 2015;87:81–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh JS, Choi JS, Lee YH, et al. The relationships between respiratory virus infection and aminotransferase in children. Pediatr Gastroenterol Hepatol Nutr. 2016;19:243–250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>England K, Thorne C, Pembrey L, et al. Age-and sex-related reference ranges of alanine aminotransferase levels in children: European paediatric HCV network. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2009;49:71–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang G-T, Tsai I-J, Tsau Y-K. Serum creatinine reference limits in pediatric population- a single center electronic health record-based database in Taiwan. Front Pediatr. 2021;9:793446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garvin JH Jr. Gender-specific aspects of pediatric hematology and oncology. In: Legato MJ, ed. Principles of gender-specific medicine. 2nd ed. London: Elsevier; 2010:51–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horvat CM, Pelletier JH. High-flow nasal cannula use and patient-centered outcomes for pediatric bronchiolitis. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:e2130927.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwane MK, Prill MM, Lu X, et al. Human rhinovirus species associated with hospitalizations for acute respiratory illness in young US children. J Infect Dis. 2011;204:1702–1710.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louie JK, Roy-Burman A, Guardia-Labar L, et al. Rhinovirus associated with severe lower respiratory tract infections in children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009;28:337–339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangil A, Calbo E, Robles A, et al. Aetiology of community-acquired pneumonia among adults in an H1N1 pandemic year: the role of respiratory viruses. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2012;31:2765–2772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chong YM, Chan YF, Jamaluddin MFH, et al. Rhinovirus/enterovirus was the most common respiratory detected in adults with severe acute respiratory infections pre-COVID-19 in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. PLoS One. 2022;17:e0273697.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadopoulos NG, Bates PJ, Bardin PG, et al. Rhinoviruses infect the lower airways. J Infect Dis. 2000;181:1875–1884.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutman JA, Peck AJ, Kuypers J, et al. Rhinovirus as a cause of fatal lower respiratory tract infection in adult stem cell transplantation patients: a report of two cases. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2007;40:809–811.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>