<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37879463</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-1026</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>908</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Science of the total environment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Total Environ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparing the decay of human wastewater-associated markers and enteric viruses in laboratory microcosms simulating estuarine waters in a temperate climatic zone using qPCR/RT-qPCR assays.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>167845</StartPage><MedlinePgn>167845</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167845</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0048-9697(23)06472-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study investigated the decay rates of wastewater-associated markers and enteric viruses in laboratory microcosms mimicking estuarine water environments in temperate Sydney, NSW, Australia using qPCR and RT-qPCR assays. The results demonstrated the reduction in concentrations of Bacteroides HF183, Lachnospiraceae Lachno3, cross-assembly phage (crAssphage), pepper mild mottle virus (PMMoV), human adenovirus (HAdV 40/41), and enterovirus (EV) over a span of 42 days under spring/summer temperatures, presence/absence of microbiota, and different light conditions. The study found that HF183, Lachno3, crAssphage, PMMoV, HAdV 40/41, and EV exhibited varying decay rates depending on the experimental conditions. The average T<sub>90</sub> values ranged from a few days to several months, indicating the rapid decay or prolonged persistence of these markers and enteric viruses in the estuarine environment. Furthermore, the study examined the effects of indigenous microbiota and spring/summer temperatures on wastewater-associated markers and enteric viruses decay rates. It was found that the presence of microbiota and temperature significantly influenced the decay rates of HF183 and PMMoV. Additionally, the study compared the effects of artificial sunlight and spring/summer temperatures on marker decay rates. Bacterial markers decayed faster than viral markers, although among viral markers crAssphage decay rates were relatively faster when compared to PMMoV. The exposure to artificial sunlight significantly accelerated the decay rates of bacterial markers, viral markers, and enteric viruses. Temperature also had an impact on the decay rates of Lachno3, crAssphage, and HAdV 40/41. In conclusion, this study provides valuable insights into the decay rates of wastewater-associated markers and enteric viruses under different experimental conditions that mimicked temperate environmental conditions. The findings contribute to our understanding of the fate and persistence of these markers in the environment which is crucial for assessing and managing risks from contamination by untreated human wastewater.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Warish</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia. Electronic address: Warish.Ahmed@csiro.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korajkic</LastName><ForeName>Asja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Environmental Protection Agency, 26W Martin Luther King Jr. Drive, Cincinnati, OH 45268, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Wendy J</ForeName><Initials>WJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Payyappat</LastName><ForeName>Sudhi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cassidy</LastName><ForeName>Michele</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrison</LastName><ForeName>Nathan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Besley</LastName><ForeName>Colin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>EPA999999</GrantID><Acronym>ImEPA</Acronym><Agency>Intramural EPA</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Total Environ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0330500</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0048-9697</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D015415">Biomarkers</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012722">Sewage</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="Y">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001315" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Australia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015415" MajorTopicYN="N">Biomarkers</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005243" MajorTopicYN="N">Feces</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014871" MajorTopicYN="N">Water Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012722" MajorTopicYN="N">Sewage</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Decay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human health risks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Markers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial source tracking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microcosms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater pollution</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37879463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1987904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11070876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0048-9697(23)06472-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adeyemi OO, Nicol C, Stonehouse NJ, Rowlands DJ, 2017. Increasing type 1 poliovirus capsid stability by thermal selection. J. Virol. 914, e01586.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5286869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27928008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Gyawali P, Sidhu JP, Toze S, 2014. Relative inactivation of faecal indicator bacteria and sewage markers in freshwater and seawater microcosms. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 59, 348–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24834814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, O’Dea C, Masters N, Kuballa A, Marinoni O, Katouli M, 2019a. Marker genes of fecal indicator bacteria and potential pathogens in animal feces in subtropical catchments. Sci. Total Environ. 656, 1427–1435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30625670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Zhang Q, Kozak S, Beale D, Gyawali P, Sadowsky MJ, Simpson S, 2019b. Comparative decay of sewage-associated marker genes in beach water and sediment in a subtropical region. Water Res. 149, 511–521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30500686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Toze S, Veal C, Fisher P, Zhang Q, Zhu Z, Staley C, Sadowsky MJ, 2021. Comparative decay of culturable faecal indicator bacteria, microbial source tracking marker genes, and enteric pathogens in laboratory microcosms that mimic a sub-tropical environment. Sci. Total Environ. 751, 141475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32890804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2023a. Microbial source tracking of untreated human wastewater and animal scats in urbanized estuarine waters. Sci. Total Environ. 877, 162764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36907409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2023b. Reduction of human fecal markers and enteric viruses in Sydney estuarine waters receiving wet weather overflows. Sci. Total Environ. 896, 165008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37348731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An XL, Wang JY, Pu Q, Li H, Pan T, Li HQ, Pan FX, Su JQ, 2020. High-throughput diagnosis of human pathogens and fecal contamination in marine recreational water. Environ. Res. 190, 109982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32745749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae S, Wuertz S, 2012. Survival of host-associated bacteroidales cells and their relationship with Enterococcus spp., campylobacter jejuni, salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium, and adenovirus in freshwater microcosms as measured by propidium monoazide-quantitative PCR. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 78, 922–932.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3272992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22139002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berney C, Romac S, Mahé F, Santini S, Siano R, Bass D, 2013. Vampires in the oceans: predatory cercozoan amoebae in marine habitats. ISME J. 7, 2387–2399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3834849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23864128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Besley CH, Cassidy MC, 2022. The composition of gross pollutants contained in wet weather overflows for different locations, spill frequencies and discharge volumes. J. Environ. Manage. 303, 114256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34902655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin SA, Benes V, Garson JA, Hellemans J, Huggett J, Kubista M, Mueller R, Nolan T, Pfaffl MW, Shipley GL, Vandesompele J, Wittwer CT, 2009. The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments. Clin. Chem. 55 (4), 611–622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19246619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byappanahalli MN, Nevers MB, Whitman RL, Ishii S, 2015. Application of a microfluidic quantitative polymerase chain reaction technique to monitor bacterial pathogens in beach water and complex environmental matrices. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2, 347–351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carratalà A, Bachmann V, Julian TR, Kohn T, 2020. Adaptation of human enterovirus to warm environments leads to resistance against chlorine disinfection. Environ. Sci. Technol. 54, 11292–11300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32875801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cashdollar JL, Brinkman NE, Griffin SM, McMinn BR, Rhodes ER, Varughese EA, Grimm AC, Parshioniker SU, Wymer L, Fout GS, 2013. Development and evaluation of EPA method 1615 for detection of enterovirus and norovirus in water. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 79, 215–223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23087037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chick H, 1908. An investigation of the laws of disinfection. J. Hyg. (Lond). 8, 92–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2167134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20474353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diston D, Robbi R, Baumgartner A, Felleisen R, 2018. Microbial source tracking in highly vulnerable karst drinking water resources. J. Wat. Health. 16 (1), 138–149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29424727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng S, Bootsma M, McLellan SL, 2018. Novel human associated Lachnospiraceae genetic markers improve detection of fecal pollution sources in urban waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 84 e00309–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6029095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29728386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson CM, Coote BG, Ashbolt NJ, Stevenson IM, 1996. Relationship between indicators, pathogens and water quality in an estuarine system. Water Res. 30, 2045–2054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Field KG, Samadpour M, 2007. Fecal source tracking, the indicator paradigm, and managing water quality. Water Res. 41, 3517–3538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17643471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujioka RS, Yoneyama BS, 2002. Sunlight inactivation of human enteric viruses and fecal bacteria. Water Sci. Technol.: a journal of the international association on water. Pollut. Res. 46, 291–295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12523768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girones R, Ferrús MA, Alonso JL, Rodriguez-Manzano J, Calgua B, de Corrêa AA, Hundesa A, Carratala A, Bofill-Mas S, 2010. Molecular detection of pathogens in water–the pros and cons of molecular techniques. Water Res. 44, 4325–4339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20619868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Fernández A, Symonds EM, Gallard-Gongora JF, Mull B, Lukasik JO, Rivera Navarro P, Badilla Aguilar A, Peraud J, Brown ML, Mora Alvarado D, Breitbart M, Cairns MR, Harwood VJ, 2021. Relationships among microbial indicators of fecal pollution, microbial source tracking markers, and pathogens in Costa Rican coastal waters. Water Res. 188, 116507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33126000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green HC, Haugland RA, Varma M, Millen HT, Borchardt MA, Field KG, Walters WA, Knight R, Sivaganesan M, Kelty CA, Shanks OC, 2014. Improved HF183 quantitative real-time PCR assay for characterization of human fecal pollution in ambient surface water samples. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 80, 3086–3094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24610857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gronewold AD, Borsuk ME, Wolpert RL, Reckhow KH, 2008. An assessment of fecal indicator bacteria-based water quality standards. Environ. Sci. Technol. 42, 4676–4682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18677990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagedorn C, Robinson C, Filtz JR, Grubbs SM, Angier TA, Reneau RB Jr., 1999. Determining sources of fecal pollution in a rural Virginia watershed with antibiotic resistance patterns in fecal streptococci. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 65, 5522–5531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC91753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10584013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamza IA, Jurzik L, Überla K, Wilhelm M, 2011. Evaluation of pepper mild mottle virus, human picobirnavirus and torque Teno virus as indicators of fecal contamination in river water. Water Res. 45, 1358–1368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21074236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E, Kitajima M, Kishida N, Konno Y, Katayama H, Asami M, Akiba M, 2013. Occurrence of pepper mild mottle virus in drinking water sources in Japan. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 79, 7413–7418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3837739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24056461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harwood VJ, Staley C, Badgley BD, Borges K, Korajkic A, 2014. Microbial source tracking markers for detection of fecal contamination in environmental waters: relationships between pathogens and human health outcomes. FEMS Microbiology Rev 38, 1–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23815638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haugland RA, Siefring SC, Wymer LJ, Brenner KP, Dufour AP, 2005. Comparison of Enterococcus measurements in freshwater at two recreational beaches by quantitative polymerase chain reaction and membrane filter culture analysis. Water Res. 39 (4), 559–568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15707628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havelaar AH, Furuse K, Hogeboom WM, 1986. Bacteriophages and indicator bacteria in human and animal faeces. The J. Appl. Bacteriol. 60, 255–262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3710943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill WF Jr., Hamblet FE, Benton WH, Akin EW, 1970. Ultraviolet devitalization of eight selected enteric viruses in estuarine water. Appl. Microbiol. 19, 805–812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC376793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4316273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holcomb DA, Stewart JR, 2020. Microbial indicators of fecal pollution: recent progress and challenges in assessing water quality. Curr. Environ. Health Rep. 7, 311–324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7458903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32542574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Zhou N, Zhang S, Yi Y, Han Y, Liu M, Han Y, Shi N, Yang L, Wang Q, Cui T, Jin H, 2022. Norovirus detection in wastewater and its correlation with human gastroenteritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. Int. 29, 22829–22842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8769679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35048346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim EME, El-Liethy MA, Abia ALK, Hemdan BA, Shaheen MN, 2019. Survival of E. Coli O157:H7, salmonella typhimurium, HAdV2 and MNV-1 in river water under dark conditions and varying storage temperatures. Sci. Total Environ. 648, 1297–1304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30340275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imlay JA, 2013. The molecular mechanisms, and physiological consequences of oxidative stress: lessons from a model bacterium. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 11, 443–454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23712352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishii S, Ksoll WB, Hicks RE, Sadowsky MJ, 2006. Presence and growth of naturalized Escherchia coli in temperate soils from Lake Superior watersheds. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 72, 612–621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1352292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16391098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jothikumar N, Lowther JA, Henshilwood K, Lees DN, Hill VR, Vinjé J, 2005. Rapid and sensitive detection of noroviruses by using TaqMan-based one-step reverse transcription-PCR assays and application to naturally contaminated shellfish samples. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 71, 1870–1875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1082570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15812014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King AMQ, et al., 2011. Virus Taxonomy: Ninth Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses. Elsevier, Amsterdam, the Netherlands.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M, Iker BC, Pepper IL, Gerba CP, 2014. Relative abundance and treatment reduction of viruses during wastewater treatment processes – identification of potential viral indicators. Sci. Total Environ. 488–489, 290–296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24836386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M, Sassi HP, Torrey JR, 2018. Pepper mild mottle virus as a water quality indicator. NPJ Clean Water 1, 19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko G, Jothikumar N, Hill VR, Sobsey M, 2005. Rapid detection of infectious adenovirus by mRNA real-time RT-PCR. J. Virol. Methods 127, 148–153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15967237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, McMinn BR, Shanks OC, Sivaganesan M, Fout GS, Ashbolt NJ, 2014. Biotic interactions and sunlight affect persistence of fecal indicator bacteria and microbial source tracking genetic markers in the upper Mississippi river. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 80, 3952–3961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4054226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24747902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, McMinn BR, Harwood VJ, 2018. Relationships between microbial indicators and pathogens in recreational water settings. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 15, 2842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6313479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30551597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, Wanjugi P, Brooks L, Cao Y, Harwood VJ, 2019. Persistence and decay of fecal microbiota in aquatic habitats. Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 83, e00005–e00019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7405076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31578217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, McMinn BR, Harwood VJ, 2023. The effect of protozoa indigenous to lakewater and wastewater on decay of fecal indicator bacteria and coliphage. Pathogens. 12, 378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10053992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36986300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levintov L, Vashisth H, 2021. Role of salt-bridging interactions in recognition of viral RNA by arginine-rich peptides. Biophys. J. 16 (120), 5060–5073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8633718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34710377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Ash KT, Joyner DC, Williams DE, Alamilla I, McKay PJ, Iler C, Green BM, Kara-Murdoch F, Swift CM, Hazen TC, 2023. Decay of enveloped SARS-CoV-2 and non-enveloped PMMoV RNA in raw sewage from university dormitories. Front. Microbiol. 14, 1144026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10175580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37187532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang L, Goh S, Gin KYH, 2017. Decay kinetics of microbial source tracking (MST) markers and human adenovirus under the effects of sunlight and salinity. Sci. Total Environ. 574, 165–175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27631197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maraccini PA, Mattioli MCM, Sassoubre LM, Cao Y, Griffith JF, Ervin JS, Van de Werfhorst LC, Boehm AB, 2016. Solar inactivation of enterococci and Escherichia coli in natural waters: effects of water absorbance and depth. Environ. Sci. Technol. 50, 5068–5076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27119980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattioli MC, Sassoubre LM, Russell TL, Boehm AB, 2017. Decay of sewage-sourced microbial source tracking markers and fecal indicator bacteria in marine waters. Water Res. 108, 106–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27855952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McClary JS, Ramos NA, Boehm AB, 2019. Photoinactivation of uncultured, indigenous enterococci. Environ. Sci: Process Impact. 21, 104–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30525134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson KL, Boehm AB, Davies-Colley RJ, Dodd MC, Kohn T, Linden KG, Liu Y, Maraccini PA, McNeill K, Mitch WA, Nguyen TH, Parker KM, Rodriguez RA, Sassoubre LM, Silverman AI, Wigginton KR, Zepp RG, 2018. Sunlight-mediated inactivation of health-relevant microorganisms in water: a review of mechanisms and modeling approaches. Environ Sci Process Impacts 16, 1089–1122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7064263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30047962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen Y, Jesudhasan PR, Aguilera ER, Pfeiffer JK, 2019. Identification and characterization of a poliovirus capsid mutant with enhanced thermal stability. J. Virol. 936 e01510–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6401428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30567995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olive M, Gan C, Carratalà A, Kohn T, 2020. Control of waterborne human viruses by indigenous bacteria and protists is influenced by temperature, virus type, and microbial species. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 86 (3) e01992–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6974641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31732569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker JK, McIntyre D, Noble RT, 2010. Characterizing fecal contamination in stormwater runoff in coastal North Carolina, USA. Water Res. 44 (14), 4186–4194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20617564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paule-Mercado MA, Ventura JS, Memon SA, Jahng D, Kang J-H, Lee C-H, 2016. Monitoring and predicting the fecal indicator bacteria concentrations from agricultural, mixed land use and urban stormwater runoff. Sci. Total Environ. 550, 1171–1181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26895037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Payment P, Franco E, 1993. Clostridium perfringens and somatic coliphages as indicators of the efficiency of drinking water treatment for viruses and protozoan cysts. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 59, 2418–2424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC182300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8368831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevost B, Goulet M, Lucas FS, Joyeux M, Moulin L, Wurtzer S, 2016. Viral persistence in surface and drinking water: suitability of PCR pre-treatment with intercalating dyes. Water Res. 91, 68–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26773484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rachmadi AT, Kitajima M, Pepper IL, Gerba CP, 2016. Enteric and indicator virus removal by surface flow wetlands. Sci. Total Environ. 542, 976–982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26562344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramírez-Castillo FY, Loera-Muro A, Jacques M, Garneau P, Avelar-González FJ, Harel J, Guerrero-Barrera AL, 2015. Waterborne pathogens: detection methods and challenges. Pathogens. 4, 307–334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4493476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26011827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao VC, Seidel KM, Goyal SM, Metcalf TG, Melnick JL, 1984. Isolation of enteroviruses from water, suspended solids, and sediments from Galveston Bay: survival of poliovirus and rotavirus adsorbed to sediments. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 48, 404–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC241526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6091548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Zaragoza S, 1994. Ecology of free-living amoebae. Crit. Rev. Microbiol. 20, 225–241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7802958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosario K, Symonds EM, Sinigalliano C, Stewart J, Breitbart M, 2009. Pepper mild mottle virus as an indicator of fecal pollution. Appl. Environ. Microbiology 75, 7261–7267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2786529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19767474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sala-Comorera L, Reynolds LJ, Martin NA, O’Sullivan JJ, Meijer WG, Fletcher NF, 2021. Decay of infectious SARS-CoV-2 and surrogates in aquatic environments. Water Res. 201, 117090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34111729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sassi HP, Tuttle KD, Betancourt WQ, Kitajima M, Gerba CP, 2018. Persistence of viruses by qPCR downstream of three effluent-dominated rivers in the Western United States. Food Environ. Virol. 10, 297–304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29679283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiomi H, Urasawa T, Urasawa S, Kobayashi N, Abe S, Taniguchi K, 2004. Isolation and characterisation of poliovirus mutants resistant to heating at 50 °C for 30 min. J. Med. Virol. 74, 484–491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15368512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silverman AI, Boehm AB, 2021. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the persistence of enveloped viruses in environmental waters and wastewater in the absence of disinfectants. Environ. Sci. Technol. 55, 14480–14493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34665598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinigalliano C, Kim K, Gidley M, Yuknavage K, Knee K, Palacios D, Bautista C, Bonacolta A, Lee HW, Maurin L, 2021. Microbial source tracking of fecal indicating bacteria in coral reef waters, recreational waters, and groundwater of Saipan by real-time quantitative PCR. Front. Microbiolo. 11, 596650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33537011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soller J, Bartrand T, Ravenscroft J, Molina M, Whelan G, Schoen M, Ashbolt N, 2015. Estimated human health risks from recreational exposures to stormwater runoff containing animal faecal material. Environ. Model. Software 72, 21–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E, Kelty C, Sivaganesan M, Li X, Bibby K, Shanks OC, 2017. Quantitative CrAssphage PCR assays for human fecal pollution measurement. Environ. Sci. Technol. 51, 9146–9154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28700235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staley C, Gordon KV, Schoen ME, Harwood VJ, 2012. Performance of two quantitative PCR methods for microbial source tracking of human sewage and implications for microbial risk assessment in recreational waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 78, 7317–7326.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3457114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22885746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone NP, Demo G, Agnello E, Kelch BA, 2019. Principles for enhancing virus capsid capacity and stability from a thermophilic virus capsid structure. Nat. Commun. 10, 4471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6775164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31578335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds EM, Verbyla EM, Lukasik JO, Kafle RC, Breitbart M, Mihelcic JR, 2014. A case study of enteric virus removal and insights into the associated risk of water reuse for two wastewater treatment pond systems in Bolivia. Water Res. 65, 257–270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25129566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarus B, Chevalier C, Richard CA, Delmas B, Di Primo C, Slama-Schwok A, 2012. Molecular dynamics studies of the nucleoprotein of influenza a virus: role of the protein flexibility in RNA binding. PloS One 7, e30038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3260217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22272272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari A, Kauppinen A, Räsänen P, Salonen J, Wessels L, Juntunen J, Miettinen IT, Pitkänen T, 2023. Effects of temperature and light exposure on the decay characteristics of fecal indicators, norovirus, and Legionella in mesocosms simulating subarctic river water. Sci. Total Environ. 859, 160340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36423850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA, 2000. Method 1603: Escherichia coli (E. coli) in Water by Membrane Filtration Using Modified Membrane-Thermotolerant Escherichia coli agar (Modified mTEC).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>USEPA, 2002. Method 1600: Enterococci in Water by Membrane Filtration Using Membrane-Enterococcus Indoxyl-β-D-Glucoside Agar (mEI). Washington, DC: US Environmental Protection Agency; 2002. EPA 821-R-02–022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbyla ME, Symonds EM, Kafle RC, Cairns MR, Iriarte M, Mercado Guzman A, Coronado O, Breitbart M, Ledo C, Mihelcic JR, 2016. Managing microbial risks from indirect wastewater reuse for irrigation in urbanizing watersheds. Environ. Sci. Technol. 50, 6803–6813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26992352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walters SP, Yamahara KM, Boehm AB, 2009. Persistence of nucleic acid markers of health-relevant organisms in seawater microcosms: implications for their use in assessing risk in recreational waters. Water Res. 43, 4929–4939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19616273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wanjugi P, Fox GA, Harwood VJ, 2016a. The interplay between predation, competition, and nutrient levels influences the survival of Escherichia coli in aquatic environments. Microbial. Ecol. 72 (3), 526–537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27484343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wanjugi P, Sivaganesan M, Korajkic A, Kelty CA, McMinn B, Ulrich R, Harwood VJ, Shanks OC, 2016b. Differential decomposition of bacterial and viral fecal indicators in common human pollution types. Water Res. 105, 591–601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27693971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, 2011. Guidelines for Drinking-Water Quality, vol. 4. World Health Organization, Geneva.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Long SC, Das D, Dorner SM, 2011. Are microbial indicators and pathogens correlated? A statistical analysis of 40 years of research. J. Water Health 9, 265–278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21942192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan T, Vadde KK, Tonkin JD, Wang J, Lu J, Zhang Z, Zhang Y, McCarthy AJ, Sekar R, 2019. Urbanization impacts the physicochemical characteristics and abundance of fecal markers and bacterial pathogens in surface water. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 16, 1739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6572354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31100947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>