<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37881026</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>First description and phylogenetic analysis of coxsackie virus A non-polio enteroviruses and parechoviruses A in South Sudanese children.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29194</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29194</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29194</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses (EV) and parechoviruses A (PeV-A) are commonly circulating viruses able to cause severe disease. Surveillance studies from sub-Saharan Africa are limited and show high but variable infection rates and a high variation in genotypes. This is the first study to describe EV and PeV-A circulation in children in South Sudan. Of the fecal samples collected, 35% and 10% were positive for EV and PeV-A, respectively. A wide range of genotypes were found, including several rarely described EV and PeV-A types. Coxsackie virus A (CVA) EV-C types, particularly CVA13, were the most dominant EV types. The CVA13 types had a high diversity with the majority belonging to four different previously described clusters. PeV-A1 and -A14 were the most common PeV-A genotypes. A lack of representative data from our and other studies from sub-Saharan Africa demonstrates the need for more systematic surveillance of non-polio EV and PeV-A types in this region.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors. Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Couderé</LastName><ForeName>Karen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6203-8499</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microvida, Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Benschop</LastName><ForeName>Kimberley</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, RIVM, Bilthoven, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Steen</LastName><ForeName>Astrid</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microvida, Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verweij</LastName><ForeName>Jaco J</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microvida, Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pas</LastName><ForeName>Suzan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microvida, Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cremer</LastName><ForeName>Jeroen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, RIVM, Bilthoven, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Edridge</LastName><ForeName>Arthur W D</ForeName><Initials>AWD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, University of Juba, Juba, South Sudan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abd-Elfarag</LastName><ForeName>Gasim O E</ForeName><Initials>GOE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emma Children's Hospital, Department of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Amsterdam University Medical Centers, AMC, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Hensbroek</LastName><ForeName>Michaël B</ForeName><Initials>MB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emma Children's Hospital, Department of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Amsterdam University Medical Centers, AMC, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pajkrt</LastName><ForeName>Dasja</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, OrganoVIR Labs, Emma Children's Hospital, Amsterdam University Medical Centers, University of Amsterdam, AMC, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Murk</LastName><ForeName>Jean-Luc</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microvida, Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wolthers</LastName><ForeName>Katja C</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology, OrganoVIR Labs, Amsterdam UMC, AMC, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030061" MajorTopicYN="Y">Parechovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus A 13</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">parechovirus A</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">south Sudan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sub-Saharan Africa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37881026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Picornaviridae Study Group. Accessed June 22, 2023. https://www.picornastudygroup.com/types/parechovirus/parechovirus_a.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley CM, Watson JT, Nix WA, et al. Severe respiratory illness associated with a nationwide outbreak of enterovirus D68 in the USA (2014): a descriptive epidemiological investigation. Lancet Resp Med. 2015;3(11):879-887.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez-Sanz R, Casas-Alba D, Launes C, et al. Molecular epidemiology of an enterovirus A71 outbreak associated with severe neurological disease, Spain, 2016. Euro Surveill. 2019;24(7):21-29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons-Salort M, Parker EPK, Grassly NC. The epidemiology of non-polio enteroviruses: recent advances and outstanding questions. Curr Opin Infect Dis. 2015;28(5):479-487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson TM, Vuillermin P, Hodge J, et al. An outbreak of severe infections among Australian infants caused by a novel recombinant strain of human parechovirus type 3. Sci Rep. 2017;7:44423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Moreni G, Wolthers KC, Pajkrt D. World-wide prevalence and genotype distribution of enteroviruses. Viruses. 2021;13(3):434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, van der Sanden SMG, Calis JCJ, et al. High frequency of polio-like enterovirus C strains with differential clustering of CVA-13 and EV-C99 subgenotypes in a cohort of Malawian children. Arch Virol. 2018;163(10):2645-2653.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellferscee O, Tempia S, Walaza S, et al. Enterovirus genotypes among patients with severe acute respiratory illness, influenza-like illness, and asymptomatic individuals in South Africa, 2012-2014. J Med Virol. 2017;89(10):1759-1767.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Díaz J, Mira-Pascual L, Collado MC, et al. Presence of human enteric viruses in the stools of healthy Malawian 6-month-old infants. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutrit. 2014;58(4):502-504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Karelehto E, Han AX, et al. High frequency and diversity of parechovirus A in a cohort of Malawian children. Arch Virol. 2019;164(3):799-806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cristanziano VD, Böttcher S, Diedrich S, et al. Detection and characterization of enteroviruses and parechoviruses in healthy people living in the south of Côte d'Ivoire. J Clin Virol. 2015;71:40-43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graul S, Böttcher S, Eibach D, et al. High diversity of human parechovirus including novel types in stool samples from Ghanaian children. J Clin Virol. 2017;96:116-119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osundare FA, Opaleye OO, Akindele AA, et al. Detection and characterization of human enteroviruses, human cosaviruses, and a new human parechovirus type in healthy individuals in osun state, Nigeria, 2016/2017. Viruses. 2019;11(11):1037.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakoto-Andrianarivelo M, Guillot S, Iber J, et al. Co-circulation and evolution of polioviruses and species C enteroviruses in a district of Madagascar. PLoS Pathog. 2007;3(12):e191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Joffret ML, Blondel B, Delpeyroux F. Exchanges of genomic domains between poliovirus and other cocirculating species C enteroviruses reveal a high degree of plasticity. Sci Rep. 2016;6:38831.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang P, Faase JAJ, Toyoda H, Paul A, Wimmer E, Gorbalenya AE. Evidence for emergence of diverse polioviruses from C-cluster coxsackie A viruses and implications for global poliovirus eradication. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2007;104(22):9457-9462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statement of the Thirty-second Polio IHR Emergency Committee. Accessed June 24, 2022. https://www.who.int/news/item/24-06-2022-statement-of-the-thirty-second-polio-ihr-emergency-committee</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarocostas J. WHO keeps polio on the international health emergency list. Lancet. 2018;392(10163):2425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breiman RF, Cosmas L, Njenga MK, et al. Severe acute respiratory infection in children in a densely populated urban slum in Kenya, 2007-2011. BMC Infect Dis. 2015;15:95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böttcher S, Obermeier PE, Diedrich S, et al. Genome sequence of novel human parechovirus type 17. Genome Announc. 2017;5(8). doi:10.1128/genomea.01649-16</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olum S, Scolding P, Hardy C, Obol J, Scolding NJ. Nodding syndrome: a concise review. Brain Commun. 2020;2(1):fcaa037.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-Elfarag GOE, Edridge AWD, Spijker R, Sebit MB, van Hensbroek MB. Nodding syndrome: a scoping review. Trop Med Infect Dis. 2021;6(4):211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nijhuis M, van Maarseveen N, Schuurman R, et al. Rapid and sensitive routine detection of all members of the genus enterovirus in different clinical specimens by real-time PCR. J Clin Microbiol. 2002;40(10):3666-3670.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Maher K, Johansson ES, et al. Detection of all known parechoviruses by real-time PCR. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46(8):2519-2524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44(8):2698-2704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niesters HG, Rossen JW, van der Avoort H, et al. Laboratory-based surveillance in the molecular era: the TYPENED model, a joint data-sharing platform for clinical and public health laboratories. Euro Surveill. 2013;18(4):20387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop KSM, Rahamat-Langendoen JC, van der Avoort HGAM, et al. VIRO-TypeNed, systematic molecular surveillance of enteroviruses in the Netherlands between 2010 and 2014. Euro Surveill. 2016;21(39):18-26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Robertson I, McWilliam Leitch EC, et al. Epidemiology and clinical associations of human parechovirus respiratory infections. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46(10):3446-3453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cremer J, Morley U, Pas S, et al. Highly sensitive parechovirus CODEHOP PCR amplification of the complete VP1 gene for typing directly from clinical specimens and correct typing based on phylogenetic clustering. J Med Microbiol. 2019;68(8):1194-1203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop KSM, Schinkel J, Minnaar RP, et al. Human parechovirus infections in Dutch children and the association between serotype and disease severity. Clin Infect Dis. 2006;42(2):204-210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose TM, Schultz ER, Henikoff JG, Pietrokovski S, McCallum CM, Henikoff S. Consensus-degenerate hybrid oligonucleotide primers for amplification of distantly related sequences. Nucleic Acids Res. 1998;26(7):1628-1635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Tamura K. MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets. Mol Biol Evol. 2016;33(7):1870-1874.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadfield J, Megill C, Bell SM, et al. Nextstrain: real-time tracking of pathogen evolution. Bioinformatics. 2018;34(23):4121-4123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Misawa K, Kuma K, Miyata T. MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform. Nucl Acids Res. 2002;30(14):3059-3066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen LT, Schmidt HA, von Haeseler A, Minh BQ. IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol. 2015;32(1):268-274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sagulenko P, Puller V, Neher RA. TreeTime: maximum-likelihood phylodynamic analysis. Virus Evol. 2018;4(1):vex042.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2020. https://www.R-project.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Joffret ML, Holmblat B, Razafindratsimandresy R, Delpeyroux F. Genetic relationship between cocirculating human enteroviruses species C. PLoS One. 2011;6(9):e24823.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Pillet S, Ibrahim W, et al. Molecular characterization of human enteroviruses in the Central African Republic: uncovering wide diversity and identification of a new human enterovirus A71 genogroup. J Clin Microbiol. 2012;50(5):1650-1658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeuh-Mba SA, Bessaud M, Massenet D, et al. High frequency and diversity of species C enteroviruses in Cameroon and neighboring countries. J Clin Microbiol. 2013;51(3):759-770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edridge AWD, Abd-Elfarag GOE. Parasitic, bacterial, viral, immune-mediated, metabolic, and nutritional factors associated with Nodding syndrome. Braincom. 2023;5:fcad223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakoto-Andrianarivelo M, Rousset D, Razafindratsimandresy R, et al. High frequency of human enterovirus species C circulation in Madagascar. J Clin Microbiol. 2005;43(1):242-249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faleye TOC, Adewumi MO, Coker BA, Nudamajo FY, Adeniji JA. Direct detection and identification of enteroviruses from faeces of healthy Nigerian children using a cell-culture independent RT-seminested PCR assay. Adv Virol. 2016;2016:1-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh S, Forgie S, Robinson J. Non-polio enterovirus detection with acute flaccid paralysis: a systematic review. J Med Virol. 2018;90(1):3-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen BS, Lee HC, Lee KM, Gong YN, Shih SR. Enterovirus and encephalitis. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M, Díaz-Cerio M, Muñoz-Almagro C, et al. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus and parechovirus infections according to patient age over a 4-year period in Spain. J Med Virol. 2017;89(3):435-442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrinelli L, Bubba L, Galli C, et al. Epidemiology and molecular characterization of influenza viruses, human parechoviruses and enteroviruses in children up to 5 years with influenza-like illness in Northern Italy during seven consecutive winter seasons (2010-2017). J Gen Virol. 2017;98(11):2699-2711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop K, Thomas X, Serpenti C, Molenkamp R, Wolthers K. High prevalence of human parechovirus (HPeV) genotypes in the Amsterdam region and identification of specific HPeV variants by direct genotyping of stool samples. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46(12):3965-3970.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>