<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37965045</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2666-4984</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and ecotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Ecotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Data-driven systematic analysis of waterborne viruses and health risks during the wastewater reclamation process.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100328</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100328</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100328</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ese.2023.100328</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Waterborne viral epidemics are a major threat to public health. Increasing interest in wastewater reclamation highlights the importance of understanding the health risks associated with potential microbial hazards, particularly for reused water in direct contact with humans. This study focused on identifying viral epidemic patterns in municipal wastewater reused for recreational applications based on long-term, spatially explicit global literature data during 2000-2021, and modelled human health risks from multiple exposure pathways using a well-established quantitative microbial risk assessment methodology. Global median viral loads in municipal wastewater ranged from 7.92 × 10<sup>4</sup> to 1.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> GC L<sup>-1</sup> in the following ascending order: human adenovirus (HAdV), norovirus (NoV) GII, enterovirus (EV), NoV GI, rotavirus (RV), and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Following secondary or tertiary wastewater treatment, NoV GI, NoV GII, EV, and RV showed a relatively higher and more stable log reduction value with medians all above 0.8 (84%), whereas SARS-CoV-2 and HAdV showed a relatively lower reduction, with medians ranging from 0.33 (53%) to 0.55 (72%). A subsequent disinfection process effectively enhanced viral removal to over 0.89-log (87%). The predicted event probability of virus-related gastrointestinal illness and acute febrile respiratory illnesses in reclaimed recreational water exceeded the World Health Organization recommended recreational risk benchmark (5% and 1.9%, respectively). Overall, our results provided insights on health risks associated with reusing wastewater for recreational purposes and highlighted the need for establishing a regulatory framework ensuring the safety management of reclaimed waters.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Jia-Xin</ForeName><Initials>JX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100085, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Urban Water Resource and Environment, School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100049, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Urban Water Resource and Environment, School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Water Systems, College of Engineering, Mathematics and Physical Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, EX4 4QF, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pan</LastName><ForeName>Yi-Rong</ForeName><Initials>YR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100085, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Urban Water Resource and Environment, School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100049, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zhao-Yue</ForeName><Initials>ZY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Urban Water Resource and Environment, School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Xuesong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100085, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Junxin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100085, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Nan-Qi</ForeName><Initials>NQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Urban Water Resource and Environment, School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, Shenzhen, 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Butler</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Water Systems, College of Engineering, Mathematics and Physical Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, EX4 4QF, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Ecotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918453988906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2666-4984</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Data-driven analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reclaimed water</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Recreational</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Waterborne virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37965045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10641159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ese.2023.100328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2666-4984(23)00093-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tortajada C., van Rensburg P. Drink more recycled wastewater. Nature. 2020;577(7788):26–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31892741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song K., Lu Y., Dao G., Chen Z., Wu Y., Wang S., Liu J., Hu H.-Y. Reclaimed water for landscape water replenishment: threshold nitrogen and phosphorus concentrations values for bloom control. Algal Research-Biomass Biofuels and Bioproducts. 2022;62</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray C.J.L., Aravkin A.Y., Zheng P., Abbafati C., Abbas K.M., Abbasi-Kangevari M., Abd-Allah F., Abdelalim A., Abdollahi M., Abdollahpour I., Abegaz K.H., Abolhassani H., Aboyans V., Abreu L.G., Abrigo M.R.M., Abualhasan A., Abu-Raddad L.J., Abushouk A.I., Adabi M., Adekanmbi V., Adeoye A.M., Adetokunboh O.O., Adham D., Advani S.M., Agarwal G., Aghamir S.M.K., Agrawal A., Ahmad T., Ahmadi K., Ahmadi M., Ahmadieh H., Ahmed M.B., Akalu T.Y., Akinyemi R.O., Akinyemiju T., Akombi B., Akunna C.J., Alahdab F., Al-Aly Z., Alam K., Alam S., Alam T., Alanezi F.M., Alanzi T.M., Alemu B.W., Alhabib K.F., Ali M., Ali S., Alicandro G., Alinia C., Alipour V., Alizade H., Aljunid S.M., Alla F., Allebeck P., Almasi-Hashiani A., Al-Mekhlafi H.M., Alonso J., Altirkawi K.A., Amini-Rarani M., Amiri F., Amugsi D.A., Ancuceanu R., Anderlini D., Anderson J.A., Andrei C.L., Andrei T., Angus C., Anjomshoa M., Ansari F., Ansari-Moghaddam A., Antonazzo I.C., Antonio C.A.T., Antony C.M., Antriyandarti E., Anvari D., Anwer R., Appiah S.C.Y., Arabloo J., Arab-Zozani M., Ariani F., Armoon B., Arnlov J., Arzani A., Asadi-Aliabadi M., Asadi-Pooya A.A., Ashbaugh C., Assmus M., Atafar Z., Atnafu D.D., Atout M.M.d.W., Ausloos F., Ausloos M., Quintanilla B.P.A., Ayano G., Ayanore M.A., Azari S., Azarian G., Azene Z.N., Badawi A., Badiye A.D., Bahrami M.A., Bakhshaei M.H., Bakhtiari A., Bakkannavar S.M., Baldasseroni A., Ball K., Ballew S.H., Balzi D., Banach M., Banerjee S.K., Bante A.B., Baraki A.G., Barker-Collo S.L., Barnighausen T.W., Barrero L.H., Barthelemy C.M., Barua L., Basu S., Baune B.T., Bayati M., Becker J.S., Bedi N., Beghi E., Bejot Y., Bell M.L., Bennitt F.B., Bensenor I.M., Berhe K., Berman A.E., Bhagavathula A.S., Bhageerathy R., Bhala N., Bhandari D., Bhattacharyya K., Bhutta Z.A., Bijani A., Bikbov B., Bin Sayeed M.S., Biondi A., Birihane B.M., Bisignano C., Biswas R.K., Bitew H., Bohlouli S., Bohluli M., Boon-Dooley A.S., Borges G., Borzi A.M., Borzouei S., Bosetti C., Boufous S., Braithwaite D., Breitborde N.J.K., Breitner S., Brenner H., Briant P.S., Briko A.N., Briko N.I., Britton G.B., Bryazka D., Bumgarner B.R., Burkart K., Burnett R.T., Nagaraja S.B., Butt Z.A., Caetano dos Santos F.L., Cahill L.E., Camera L.A., Campos-Nonato I.R., Cardenas R., Carreras G., Carrero J.J., Carvalho F., Castaldelli-Maia J.M., Castaneda-Orjuela C.A., Castelpietra G., Castro F., Causey K., Cederroth C.R., Cercy K.M., Cerin E., Chandan J.S., Chang K.-L., Charlson F.J., Chattu V.K., Chaturvedi S., Cherbuin N., Chimed-Ochir O., Cho D.Y., Choi J.-Y.J., Christensen H., Chu D.-T., Chung M.T., Chung S.-C., Cicuttini F.M., Ciobanu L.G., Cirillo M., Classen T.K.D., Cohen A.J., Compton K., Cooper O.R., Costa V.M., Cousin E., Cowden R.G., Cross D.H., Cruz J.A., Dahlawi S.M.A., Damasceno A.A.M., Damiani G., Dandona L., Dandona R., Dangel W.J., Danielsson A.-K., Dargan P.I., Darwesh A.M., Daryani A., Das J.K., Das Gupta R., Das Neves J., Davila-Cervantes C.A., Davitoiu D.V., De Leo D., Degenhardt L., DeLang M., Dellavalle R.P., Demeke F.M., Demoz G.T., Demsie D.G., Denova-Gutierrez E., Dervenis N., Dhungana G.P., Dianatinasab M., da Silva D.D., Diaz D., Forooshani Z.S.D., Djalalinia S., Do H.T., Dokova K., Dorostkar F., Doshmangir L., Driscoll T.R., Duncan B.B., Duraes A.R., Eagan A.W., Edvardsson D., El Nahas N., El Sayed I., El Tantawi M., Elbarazi I., Elgendy I.Y., El-Jaafary S.I., Elyazar I.R.F., Emmons-Bell S., Erskine H.E., Eskandarieh S., Esmaeilnejad S., Esteghamati A., Estep K., Etemadi A., Etisso A.E., Fanzo J., Farahmand M., Fareed M., Faridnia R., Farioli A., Faro A., Faruque M., Farzadfar F., Fattahi N., Fazlzadeh M., Feigin V.L., Feldman R., Fereshtehnejad S.-M., Fernandes E., Ferrara G., Ferrari A.J., Ferreira M.L., Filip I., Fischer F., Fisher J.L., Flor L.S., Foigt N.A., Folayan M.O., Fomenkov A.A., Force L.M., Foroutan M., Franklin R.C., Freitas M., Fu W., Fukumoto T., Furtado J.M., Gad M.M., Gakidou E., Gallus S., Garcia-Basteiro A.L., Gardner W.M., Geberemariyam B.S., Gebreslassie A.A.A.A., Geremew A., Hayoon A.G., Gething P.W., Ghadimi M., Ghadiri K., Ghaffarifar F., Ghafourifard M., Ghamari F., Ghashghaee A., Ghiasvand H., Ghith N., Gholamian A., Ghosh R., Gill P.S., Ginindza T.G., Giussani G., Gnedovskaya E.V., Goharinezhad S., Gopalani S.V., Gorini G., Goudarzi H., Goulart A.C., Greaves F., Grivna M., Grosso G., Gubari M.I.M., Gugnani H.C., Guimaraes R.A., Guled R.A., Guo G., Guo Y., Gupta R., Gupta T., Haddock B., Hafezi-Nejad N., Hafiz A., Haj-Mirzaian A., Haj-Mirzaian A., Hall B.J., Halvaei I., Hamadeh R.R., Hamidi S., Hammer M.S., Hankey G.J., Haririan H., Haro J.M., Hasaballah A.I., Hasan M.M., Hasanpoor E., Hashi A., Hassanipour S., Hassankhani H., Havmoeller R.J., Hay S.I., Hayat K., Heidari G., Heidari-Soureshjani R., Henrikson H.J., Herbert M.E., Herteliu C., Heydarpour F., Hird T.R., Hoek H.W., Holla R., Hoogar P., Hosgood H.D., Hossain N., Hosseini M., Hosseinzadeh M., Hostiuc M., Hostiuc S., Househ M., Hsairi M., Hsieh V.C.-R., Hu G., Hu K., Huda T.M., Humayun A., Huynh C.K., Hwang B.-F., Iannucci V.C., Ibitoye S.E., Ikeda N., Ikuta K.S., Ilesanmi O.S., Ilic I.M., Ilic M.D., Inbaraj L.R., Ippolito H., Iqbal U., Irvani S.S.N., Irvine C.M.S., Islam M.M., Islam S.M.S., Iso H., Ivers R.Q., Iwu C.C.D., Iwu C.J., Iyamu I.O., Jaafari J., Jacobsen K.H., Jafari H., Jafarinia M., Jahani M.A., Jakovljevic M., Jalilian F., James S.L., Janjani H., Javaheri T., Javidnia J., Jeemon P., Jenabi E., Jha R.P., Jha V., Ji J.S., Johansson L., John O., John-Akinola Y.O., Johnson C.O., Jonas J.B., Joukar F., Jozwiak J.J., Jurisson M., Kabir A., Kabir Z., Kalani H., Kalani R., Kalankesh L.R., Kalhor R., Kanchan T., Kapoor N., Matin B.K., Karch A., Karim M.A., Kassa G.M., Katikireddi S.V., Kayode G.A., Karyani A.K., Keiyoro P.N., Keller C., Kemmer L., Kendrick P.J., Khalid N., Khammarnia M., Khan E.A., Khan M., Khatab K., Khater M.M., Khatib M.N., Khayamzadeh M., Khazaei S., Kieling C., Kim Y.J., Kimokoti R.W., Kisa A., Kisa S., Kivimaki M., Knibbs L.D., Knudsen A.K.S., Kocarnik J.M., Kochhar S., Kopec J.A., Korshunov V.A., Koul P.A., Koyanagi A., Kraemer M.U.G., Krishan K., Krohn K.J., Kromhout H., Defo B.K., Kumar G.A., Kumar V., Kurmi O.P., Kusuma D., La Vecchia C., Ben L., Lal D.K., Lalloo R., Lallukka T., Lami F.H., Landires I., Lang J.J., Langan S.M., Larsson A.O., Lasrado S., Lauriola P., Lazarus J.V., Lee P.H., Lee S.W.H., LeGrand K.E., Leigh J., Leonardi M., Lescinsky H., Leung J., Levi M., Li S., Lim L.-L., Linn S., Liu S., Liu S., Liu Y., Lo J., Lopez A.D., Lopez J.C.F., Lopukhov P.D., Lorkowski S., Lotufo P.A., Lu A., Lugo A., Maddison E.R., Mahasha P.W., Mahdavi M.M., Mahmoudi M., Majeed A., Maleki A., Maleki S., Malekzadeh R., Malta D.C., Mamun A.A., Manda A.L., Manguerra H., Mansour-Ghanaei F., Mansouri B., Mansournia M.A., Herrera A.M.M., Maravilla J.C., Marks A., Martin R.V., Martini S., Martins-Melo F.R., Masaka A., Masoumi S.Z., Mathur M.R., Matsushita K., Maulik P.K., McAlinden C., McGrath J.J., McKee M., Mehndiratta M.M., Mehri F., Mehta K.M., Memish Z.A., Mendoza W., Menezes R.G., Mengesha E.W., Mereke A., Mereta S.T., Meretoja A., Meretoja T.J., Mestrovic T., Miazgowski B., Miazgowski T., Michalek I.M., Miller T.R., Mills E.J., Mini G.K., Miri M., Mirica A., Mirrakhimov E.M., Mirzaei H., Mirzaei M., Mirzaei R., Mirzaei-Alavijeh M., Misganaw A.T., Mithra P., Moazen B., Mohammad D.K., Mohammad Y., Mezerji N.M.G., Mohammadian-Hafshejani A., Mohammadifard N., Mohammadpourhodki R., Mohammed A.S., Mohammed H., Mohammed J.A., Mohammed S., Mokdad A.H., Molokhia M., Monasta L., Mooney M.D., Moradi G., Moradi M., Moradi-Lakeh M., Moradzadeh R., Moraga P., Morawska L., Morgado-da-Costa J., Morrison S.D., Mosapour A., Mosser J.F., Mouodi S., Mousavi S.M., Khaneghah A.M., Mueller U.O., Mukhopadhyay S., Mullany E.C., Musa K.I., Muthupandian S., Nabhan A.F., Naderi M., Nagarajan A.J., Nagel G., Naghavi M., Naghshtabrizi B., Naimzada M.D., Najafi F., Nangia V., Nansseu J.R., Naserbakht M., Nayak V.C., Negoi I., Ngunjiri J.W., Nguyen C.T., Nguyen H.L.T., Nguyen M., Nigatu Y.T., Nikbakhsh R., Nixon M.R., Nnaji C.A., Nomura S., Norrving B., Noubiap J.J., Nowak C., Nunez-Samudio V., Oiu A.O., Oancea B., Odell C.M., Ogbo F.A., Oh I.-H., Okunga E.W., Oladnabi M., Olagunju A.T., Olusanya B.O., Olusanya J.O., Omer M.O., Ong K.L., Onwujekwe O.E., Orpana H.M., Ortiz A., Osarenotor O., Osei F.B., Ostroff S.M., Otstavnov N., Otstavnov S.S., Overland S., Owolabi M.O., Section M.P.A., Padubidri J.R., Palladino R., Panda-Jonas S., Pandey A., Parry C.D.H., Pasovic M., Pasupula D.K., Patel S.K., Pathak M., Patten S.B., Patton G.C., Toroudi H.P., Peden A.E., Pennini A., Pepito V.C.F., Peprah E.K., Pereira D.M., Pesudovs K., Pham H.Q., Phillips M.R., Piccinelli C., Pilz T.M., Piradov M.A., Pirsaheb M., Plass D., Polinder S., Polkinghorne K.R., Pond C.D., Postma M.J., Pourjafar H., Pourmalek F., Poznanska A., Prada S.I., Prakash V., Pribadi D.R.A., Pupillo E., Quazi Syed Z., Rabiee M., Rabiee N., Radfar A., Rafiee A., Raggi A., Rahman M.A., Rajabpour-Sanati A., Rajati F., Rakovac I., Ram P., Ramezanzadeh K., Ranabhat C.L., Rao P.C., Rao S.J., Rashedi V., Rathi P., Rawaf D.L., Rawaf S., Rawal L., Rawassizadeh R., Rawat R., Razo C., Boston S., Reiner R.C., Jr., Reitsma M.B., Remuzzi G., Renjith V., Renzaho A.M.N., Resnikoff S., Rezaei N., Rezaei N., Rezapour A., Rhinehart P.-A., Riahi S.M., Ribeiro D.C., Ribeiro D., Rickard J., Rivera J.A., Roberts N.L.S., Rodriguez-Ramirez S., Roever L., Ronfani L., Room R., Roshandel G., Roth G.A., Rothenbacher D., Rubagotti E., Rwegerera G.M., Sabour S., Sachdev P.S., Saddik B., Sadeghi E., Sadeghi M., Saeedi R., Moghaddam S.S., Safari Y., Safi S., Safiri S., Sagar R., Sahebkar A., Sajadi S.M., Salam N., Salamati P., Salem H., Salem M.R., Salimzadeh H., Salman O.M., Salomon J.A., Samad Z., Kafil H.S., Sambala E.Z., Samy A.M., Sanabria J., Sanchez-Pimienta T.G., Santomauro D.F., Santos I.S., Santos J.V., Santric-Milicevic M.M., Saraswathy S.Y.I., Sarmiento-Suarez R., Sarrafzadegan N., Sartorius B., Sarveazad A., Sathian B., Sathish T., Sattin D., Saxena S., Schaeffer L.E., Schiavolin S., Schlaich M.P., Schmidt M.I., Schutte A.E., Schwebel D.C., Schwendicke F., Senbeta A.M., Senthilkumaran S., Sepanlou S.G., Serdar B., Serre M.L., Shadid J., Shafaat O., Shahabi S., Shaheen A.A., Shaikh M.A., Shalash A.S., Shams-Beyranvand M., Shamsizadeh M., Sharafi K., Sheikh A., Sheikhtaheri A., Shibuya K., Shield K.D., Shigematsu M., Shin J.I., Shin M.-J., Shiri R., Shirkoohi R., Shuval K., Siabani S., Sierpinski R., Sigfusdottir I.D., Sigurvinsdottir R., Silva J.P., Simpson K.E., Singh J.A., Singh P., Skiadaresi E., Skou S.T., Skryabin V.Y., Smith E.U.R., Soheili A., Soltani S., Soofi M., Sorensen R.J.D., Soriano J.B., Sorrie M.B., Soshnikov S., Soyiri I.N., Spencer C.N., Spotin A., Sreeramareddy C.T., Srinivasan V., Stanaway J.D., Stein C., Stein D.J., Steiner C., Stockfelt L., Stokes M.A., Straif K., Stubbs J.L., Sufiyan M.a.B., Suleria H.A.R., Abdulkader R.S., Sulo G., Sultan I., Szumowski L., Tabares-Seisdedos R., Tabb K.M., Tabuchi T., Taherkhani A., Tajdini M., Takahashi K., Takala J.S., Tamiru A.T., Taveira N., Tehrani-Banihashemi A., Temsah M.-H., Tesema G.A., Tessema Z.T., Thurston G.D., Titova M.V., Tohidinik H.R., Tonelli M., Topor-Madry R., Topouzis F., Torre A.E., Touvier M., Tovani-Palone M.R., Tran B.X., Travillian R., Tsatsakis A., Car L.T., Tyrovolas S., Uddin R., Umeokonkwo C.D., Unnikrishnan B., Upadhyay E., Vacante M., Valdez P.R., Van Donkelaar A., Vasankari T.J., Vasseghian Y., Veisani Y., Venketasubramanian N., Violante F.S., Vlassov V., Vollset S.E., Vos T., Vukovic R., Waheed Y., Wallin M.T., Wang Y., Wang Y.-P., Watson A., Wei J., Wei M.Y.W., Weintraub R.G., Weiss J., Werdecker A., Westerman R., Whisnant J.L., Whiteford H.A., Wiens K.E., Wolfe C.D.A., Wozniak S.S., Wu A.-M., Wu J., Hanson S.W., Xu G., Xu R., Yadgir S., Jabbari S.H.Y., Yamagishi K., Yaminfirooz M., Yano Y., Yaya S., Yazdi-Feyzabadi V., Yeheyis T.Y., Yilgwan C.S., Yilma M.T., Yip P., Yonemoto N., Younis M.Z., Younker T.P., Yousefi B., Yousefi Z., Yousefinezhadi T., Yousuf A.Y., Yu C., Yusefzadeh H., Moghadam T.Z., Zamani M., Zamanian M., Zandian H., Zastrozhin M.S., Zhang Y., Zhang Z.-J., Zhao J.T., Zhao X.-J.G., Zhao Y., Zhou M., Ziapour A., Zimsen S.R.M., Brauer M., Afshin A., Lim S.S., Factors G.B.D.R. Global burden of 87 risk factors in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396(10258):1223–1249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7566194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair R.G., Jones E.L., Gerba C.P. Viruses in recreational water-borne disease outbreaks: a review. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2009;107(6):1769–1780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19486213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsamadony M., Fujii M., Miura T., Watanabe T. Possible transmission of viruses from contaminated human feces and sewage: implications for SARS-CoV-2. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7522648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melvin R.G., Hendrickson E.N., Chaudhry N., Georgewill O., Freese R., Schacker T.W., Simmons G.E., Jr. A novel wastewater-based epidemiology indexing method predicts SARS-CoV-2 disease prevalence across treatment facilities in metropolitan and regional populations. Sci. Rep. 2021;11(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8560786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34725394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva A.K., Le Saux J.-C., Parnaudeau S., Pommepuy M., Elimelech M., Le Guyader F.S. Evaluation of removal of noroviruses during wastewater treatment, using real-time reverse transcription-PCR: different behaviors of genogroups I and II. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2007;73(24):7891–7897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2168159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17933913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carducci A., Morici P., Pizzi F., Battistini R., Rovini E., Verani M. Study of the viral removal efficiency in a urban wastewater treatment plant. Water Sci. Technol. 2008;58(4):893–897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18776627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miura T., Okabe S., Nakahara Y., Sano D. Removal properties of human enteric viruses in a pilot-scale membrane bioreactor (MBR) process. Water Res. 2015;75:282–291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25770448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassine-Zaafrane M., Kaplon J., Ben Salem I., Sdiri-Loulizi K., Sakly N., Pothier P., Aouni M., Ambert-Balay K. Detection and genotyping of group A rotaviruses isolated from sewage samples in Monastir, Tunisia between April 2007 and April 2010. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2015;119(5):1443–1453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26248601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M., Yang Y., Lu Y., Zhang D., Liu Y., Cui X., Yang L., Liu R., Liu J., Li G., Qu J. Natural host-environmental media-human: a new potential pathway of COVID-19 outbreak. Engineering. 2020;6(10):1085–1098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33520330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira L.C., Torres-Franco A.F., Lopes B.C., Santos B.S. A.d.S., Costa E.A., Costa M.S., Reis M.T.P., Melo M.C., Polizzi R.B., Teixeira M.M., Mota C.R. Viability of SARS-CoV-2 in river water and wastewater at different temperatures and solids content. Water Res. 2021;195</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7927590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S., Dong Q., Li S., Cheng Z., Kang X., Ren D., Xu C., Zhou X., Liang P., Sun L., Zhao J., Jiao Y., Han T., Liu Y., Qian Y., Liu Y., Huang X., Qu J. Persistence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater after the end of the COVID-19 epidemics. J. Hazard Mater. 2022;429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8800135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35123131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M., Alamin M., Kuroda K., Dhangar K., Hata A., Yamaguchi H., Honda R. Potential discharge, attenuation and exposure risk of SARS-CoV-2 in natural water bodies receiving treated wastewater. Npj Clean Water. 2021;4(1):8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons F.J., Xagoraraki I. Release of infectious human enteric viruses by full-scale wastewater utilities. Water Res. 2011;45(12):3590–3598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21570703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J., Liu J., Yu H., Zhao W., Xia X., You S., Zhang J., Tong H., Wei L. Sources, fates and treatment strategies of typical viruses in urban sewage collection/treatment systems: a review. Desalination. 2022;534</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9033450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35498908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wigginton K.R., Kohn T. Virus disinfection mechanisms: the role of virus composition, structure, and function. Current Opinion in Virology. 2012;2(1):84–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22440970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wigginton K.R., Pecson B.M., Sigstam T., Bosshard F., Kohn T. Virus inactivation mechanisms: impact of disinfectants on virus function and structural integrity. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2012;46(21):12069–12078.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23098102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogler A., Packman A., Furman A., Gross A., Kushmaro A., Ronen A., Dagot C., Hill C., Vaizel-Ohayon D., Morgenroth E., Bertuzzo E., Wells G., Kiperwas H.R., Horn H., Negev I., Zucker I., Bar-Or I., Moran-Gilad J., Balcazar J.L., Bibby K., Elimelech M., Weisbrod N., Nir O., Sued O., Gillor O., Alvarez P.J., Crameri S., Arnon S., Walker S., Yaron S., Nguyen T.H., Berchenko Y., Hu Y.X., Ronen Z., Bar-Zeev E. Rethinking wastewater risks and monitoring in light of the COVID-19 pandemic. Nat. Sustain. 2020;3(12):981–990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purnell S., Halliday A., Newman F., Sinclair C., Ebdon J. Pathogen infection risk to recreational water users, associated with surface waters impacted by de facto and indirect potable reuse activities. Sci. Total Environ. 2020;722</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32197157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sales-Ortells H., Medema G. Screening-level microbial risk assessment of urban water locations: a tool for prioritization. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2014;48(16):9780–9789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25061968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seto E., Olivieri A.W., Danielson R.E. Quantitative microbial risk assessment used to evaluate seasonal wastewater treatment limits: case study in Vacaville, CA. Water Sci. Technol. Water Supply. 2018;18(3):910–925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S., Persson K.M. Estimating microbial risk in treated wastewater for reuse: a case study in Lund, Sweden. Journal of Water Reuse and Desalination. 2014;4(4):263–275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray C.J.L., Lopez A.D., Organization W.H., Bank W., Harvard H. In: Harvard School of Public Health on Behalf of the World Health Organization and the World Bank. Murray Christopher J.L., Lopez Alan D., editors. 1996. School of Public, the Global burden of disease : a comprehensive assessment of mortality and disability from diseases, injuries, and risk factors in 1990 and projected to 2020. Boston.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burda B.U., O'Connor E.A., Webber E.M., Redmond N., Perdue L.A. Estimating data from figures with a Web-based program: considerations for a systematic review. Res. Synth. Methods. 2017;8(3):258–262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28268241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher D., Liberati A., Tetzlaff J., Altman D.G., Grp P. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. BMJ Br. Med. J. (Clin. Res. Ed.) 2009;339:b2535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2714657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19622551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganser G.H., Hewett P. An accurate substitution method for analyzing censored data. J. Occup. Environ. Hyg. 2010;7(4):233–244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20169489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Y., Hein M.J., Deddens J.A., Hines C.J. Analysis of lognormally distributed exposure data with repeated measures and values below the limit of detection using SAS. Ann. Occup. Hyg. 2011;55(1):97–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21177260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canales R.A., Wilson A.M., Pearce-Walker J.I., Verhougstraete M.P., Reynolds K.A. Methods for handling left-censored data in quantitative microbial risk assessment. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2018;84(20)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6182903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30120116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park J.-H., Choi S., Koh D.-H., Park D.-U., yeji S. A comparison of analysis methods for work environment measurement databases including left-censored data. Journal of Korean Society of Occupational and Environmental Hygiene. 2022;32(1):21–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramiro Poma H., Kundu A., Wuertz S., Beatriz Rajal V. Data fitting approach more critical than exposure scenarios and treatment of censored data for quantitative microbial risk assessment. Water Res. 2019;154:45–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30771706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhiteneva V., Hubner U., Medema G.J., Drewes J.E. Trends in conducting quantitative microbial risk assessments for water reuse systems: a review. Microbial Risk Analysis. 2020;16</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng S., Yan X., Zhu Q., Liao C. The utilization of reclaimed water: possible risks arising from waterborne contaminants. Environ. Pollut. 2019;254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31421574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maal-Bared R., Brisolara K., Munakata N., Bibby K., Gerba C., Sobsey M., Schaefer S., Swift J., Gary L., Sherchan S., Babatola A., Bastian R., Olabode L., Reimers R., Rubin A. Implications of SARS-CoV-2 on current and future operation and management of wastewater systems. Water Environ. Res. 2021;93(4):502–515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32866312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dada A.C., Gyawali P. Quantitative microbial risk assessment (QMRA) of occupational exposure to SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater treatment plants. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;763</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7560119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33498115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gottschalk F., Sonderer T., Scholz R.W., Nowack B. Possibilities and limitations of modeling environmental exposure to engineered nanomaterials by probabilistic material flow analysis. Environ. Toxicol. Chem. 2010;29(5):1036–1048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20821538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R J.B., P G., Haas Charles N. second ed. 2014. Quantitative Microbial Risk Assessment.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Abel N., Mans J., Taylor M.B. Quantitative microbial risk assessment to estimate the health risk from exposure to noroviruses in polluted surface water in South Africa. J. Water Health. 2017;15(6):908–922.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29215355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks J.R., McLaughlin M.R., Gerba C.P., Pepper I.L. Land application of manure and class B biosolids: an occupational and public quantitative microbial risk assessment. J. Environ. Qual. 2012;41(6):2009–2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23128758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teunis P.F.M., Moe C.L., Liu P., Miller S.E., Lindesmith L., Baric R.S., Le Pendu J., Calderon R.L. Norwalk virus: how infectious is it? J. Med. Virol. 2008;80(8):1468–1476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18551613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasalari H., Akbari H., Ataei-Pirkooh A., Adibzadeh A., Akbari H. Assessment of rotavirus and norovirus emitted from water spray park: QMRA, diseases burden and sensitivity analysis. Heliyon. 2022;8(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9568861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36254289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao P., Ma M., Hu Y., Wu W., Xiao J. Comparison of international standards for irrigation with reclaimed water. Agric. Water Manag. 2022;274</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhipi-Shrestha G., Hewage K., Sadiq R. Microbial quality of reclaimed water for urban reuses: probabilistic risk-based investigation and recommendations. Sci. Total Environ. 2017;576:738–751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27810759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization W.H. In: Organization W.H., editor. ume 1. World Health Organization; Geneva: 2021. Guidelines on recreational water quality; p. 164. (Coastal and Fresh Waters).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y.-h., Yan C., Yang Y.-f., Ma J.-x. Quantitative microbial risk assessment and sensitivity analysis for workers exposed to pathogenic bacterial bioaerosols under various aeration modes in two wastewater treatment plants. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;755(2) 142615 142615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7527313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33038813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capodaglio A.G. Fit-for-purpose urban wastewater reuse: analysis of issues and available technologies for sustainable multiple barrier approaches. Crit. Rev. Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021;51(15):1619–1666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>o. Q. E. P. Agency T.S. In: Queensland Water Recycling Guidelines. Agency E.P., editor. 2005. p. 82. Queensland.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C.-M., Wang X.-C. Distribution of enteric pathogens in wastewater secondary effluent and safety analysis for urban water reuse. Human and Ecological Risk Assessment. 2014;20(3):797–806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayi B. Infections acquired via fresh water: from lakes to hot tubs. Microbiol. Spectr. 2015;3(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27337285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>