<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37909741</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Molecular characterization of a novel clade echovirus 3 isolated from patients with hand-foot-and-mouth disease in southwest China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29202</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29202</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29202</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Echovirus 3 (E3) belongs to the species Enterovirus B. Currently, three nearly whole-genome sequences of E3 are available in GenBank in China. In this study, we determined the whole genomic sequences of six E3 strains isolated from the stools of patients with hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Southwest China in 2022. Their nucleotide and amino acid sequences shared 82.1%-86.4% and 96.6%-97.2% identity with the prototype Morrisey strain, respectively, and showed 87.1% and 97.2% mutual identity. The six E3 strains are not clustered with other Chinese strains and formed a novel subgenotype (C6) with the recent American and British strains. Recombination analyses revealed that intertype recombination had occurred in the 2 C and 3D regions of the six E3 strains with coxsackieviruses B5 and B4, respectively. This study augments the nearly whole-genome sequences of E3 in the GenBank database and extends the molecular characterization of this virus in China.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Junwei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Yunnan University, Kunming, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chu</LastName><ForeName>Zhaoyang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Ming</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yuhan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Changzeng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory Kunming Maternal and Child Health hospital, Kunming, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Zhaoqing</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Shaohui</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8992-1177</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, and Peking Union Medical College, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Vaccine Research Development on Severe Infectious Disease, Kunming, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005536" MajorTopicYN="Y">Foot-and-Mouth Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D023281" MajorTopicYN="N">Genomics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000595" MajorTopicYN="N">Amino Acid Sequence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016679" MajorTopicYN="N">Genome, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">echovirus 3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nearly whole-genome sequence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">phylogenetic analysis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37909741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Racaniello VR. Picornaviridae: the viruses and their replication. In: Knipe DM, Howley PM, eds. Fields Virology. fifth ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2007:795-838.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan J, Shen L, Wu J, et al. Enterovirus A71 proteins: structure and function. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:286. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2018.00286</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang SW, Cheng D, Wang JR. Enterovirus A71: virulence, antigenicity, and genetic evolution over the years. J Biomed Sci. 2019;26(1):81. doi:10.1186/s12929-019-0574-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekiguchi J, Kubo H, Kaida A, et al. High incidence of human echovirus type 3 among children in Osaka, Japan during the summer of 2010. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2011;64(6):533-535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pouremamali A, Makavndi M, Samarbafzadeh A, et al. Human rhinoviruses A9, A49, B14 and echovirus 3, 9 among the patients with acute respiratory infection. Epidemiol Mikrobiol Imunol. 2018;67(1):18-23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh S, Forgie S, Robinson J. Non-polio enterovirus detection with acute flaccid paralysis: a systematic review. J Med Virol. 2018;90(1):3-7. doi:10.1002/jmv.24933</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramalho E, Sousa Jr. I, Burlandy F, et al. Identification and phylogenetic characterization of human enteroviruses isolated from cases of aseptic meningitis in Brazil, 2013-2017. Viruses. 2019;11(8):690. doi:10.3390/v11080690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyata I, Hanaoka N, Okabe N, et al. Echovirus 3 as another enterovirus causing life-threatening neonatal fulminant hepatitis. J Clin Virol. 2014;59(2):132-134. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2013.11.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Kutateladze T, Zangaladze E, et al. High degree of genetic diversity of non-polio enteroviruses identified in Georgia by environmental and clinical surveillance, 2002-2005. J Med Microbiol. 2010;59(Pt 11):1340-1347. doi:10.1099/jmm.0.023028-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeats J, Smuts H, Serfontein CJ, Kannemeyer J. Investigation into a school enterovirus outbreak using PCR detection and serotype identification based on the 5' non-coding region. Epidemiol Infect. 2005;133(6):1123-1130. doi:10.1017/S0950268805004462</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>do Socorro Fôro Ramos E, Rosa UA, de Oliveira Ribeiro G, et al. High heterogeneity of echoviruses in Brazilian children with acute gastroenteritis. Viruses. 2021;13(4):595. doi:10.3390/v13040595</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prim N, Rodríguez G, Margall N, Del Cuerpo M, Trallero G, Rabella N. Combining cell lines to optimize isolation of human enterovirus from clinical specimens: report of 25 years of experience. J Med Virol. 2013;85(1):116-120. doi:10.1002/jmv.23426</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Guo W, Xu D, et al. Molecular characterization of echovirus 9 strains isolated from hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Kunming, Yunnan province, China. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):2293. doi:10.1038/s41598-022-06309-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroneman A, Vennema H, Deforche K, et al. An automated genotyping tool for enteroviruses and noroviruses. J Clin Virol. 2011;51(2):121-125. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2011.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Tamura K. MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets. Mol Biol Evol. 2016;33(7):1870-1874. doi:10.1093/molbev/msw054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lole KS, Bollinger RC, Paranjape RS, et al. Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype c-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination. J Virol. 1999;73(1):152-160. doi:10.1128/JVI.73.1.152-160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Maher K, Pallansch MA. Evidence for frequent recombination within species human enterovirus B based on complete genomic sequences of all thirty-seven serotypes. J Virol. 2004;78(2):855-867. doi:10.1128/jvi.78.2.855-867.2004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan YF, Sam IC, AbuBakar S. Phylogenetic designation of enterovirus 71 genotypes and subgenotypes using complete genome sequences. Infect Genet Evol. 2010;10(3):404-412. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2009.05.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Z, Zhao Y, Luo Y, et al. Ongoing change of severe hand, foot, and mouth disease pathogens in Yunnan, China, 2012 to 2016. J Med Virol. 2019;91(5):881-885. doi:10.1002/jmv.25393</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ai Y, Zhang W, Wu J, et al. Molecular epidemiology and clinical features of enteroviruses-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease and Herpangina outbreak in Zunyi, China, 2019. Front Med. 2021;8:656699. doi:10.3389/fmed.2021.656699</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian L, Wang Y, Yao X, Mao Q, Xu M, Liang Z. Coxsackievirus A6: a new emerging pathogen causing hand, foot and mouth disease outbreaks worldwide. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2015;13(9):1061-1071. doi:10.1586/14787210.2015.1058156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li JF, Zhang CJ, Li YW, et al. Coxsackievirus A6 was the most common enterovirus serotype causing hand, foot, and mouth disease in Shiyan city, central China. World J Clin Cases. 2022;10(31):11358-11370. doi:10.12998/wjcc.v10.i31.11358</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao J, Wang J, Zhang Y, et al. Coxsackievirus B4: an underestimated pathogen associated with a hand, foot, and mouth disease outbreak. Arch Virol. 2021;166(8):2225-2234. doi:10.1007/s00705-021-05128-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu YF, Yang F, Du J, Zhang T, Xue Y, Jin Q. Coxsackievirus B5, associated with neurological hand, foot and mouth disease, China. J Infect. 2012;65(2):189-191. doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2012.03.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Xu D, Cong S, et al. Co-infection and enterovirus B: post EV-A71 mass vaccination scenario in China. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):671. doi:10.1186/s12879-022-07661-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Chen J, Zhang M, et al. Coxsackievirus B: the important agent of hand, foot, and mouth disease. J Med Virol. 2023;95(3):e28669. doi:10.1002/jmv.28669</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyriakopoulou Z, Bletsa M, Tsakogiannis D, et al. Molecular epidemiology and evolutionary dynamics of echovirus 3 serotype. Infect Genet Evol. 2015;32:305-312. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2015.03.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savolainen-Kopra C, Blomqvist S. Mechanisms of genetic variation in polioviruses. Rev Med Virol. 2010;20(6):358-371. doi:10.1002/rmv.663</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Zhang H, Zhao Y, Guo C, Yang Z, Ma S. Molecular characterization of a new human coxsackievirus B2 associated with severe hand-foot-mouth disease in Yunnan province of China in 2012. Arch Virol. 2017;162(1):307-311. doi:10.1007/s00705-016-3075-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng H, Zhang Y, Liu L, et al. Isolation and characterization of a highly mutated Chinese isolate of enterovirus B84 from a patient with acute flaccid paralysis. Sci Rep. 2016;6:31059. doi:10.1038/srep31059</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukashev AN, Lashkevich VA, Ivanova OE, Koroleva GA, Hinkkanen AE, Ilonen J. Recombination in circulating human enterovirus B: independent evolution of structural and non-structural genome regions. J Gen Virol. 2005;86(Pt 12):3281-3290. doi:10.1099/vir.0.81264-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q, Wang Y, Yao X, et al. Coxsackievirus A16: epidemiology, diagnosis, and vaccine. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2014;10(2):360-367. doi:10.4161/hv.27087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyoshi M, Goto A, Komagome R, et al. Genetic characterization of a novel recombinant echovirus 30 strain causing a regional epidemic of aseptic meningitis in Hokkaido, Japan, 2017. Arch Virol. 2020;165(2):433-438. doi:10.1007/s00705-019-04484-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Z, Zhang Y, Huang K, et al. Genetic characterization and molecular epidemiological analysis of novel enterovirus EV-B80 in China. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2018;7(1):1-12. doi:10.1038/s41426-018-0196-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Zhang H, Liu H, et al. Molecular characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease for hospitalized pediatric patients in Yunnan, China. Medicine. 2018;97(31):e11610. doi:10.1097/MD.0000000000011610</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Han Z, Wu H, Xu W, Yu D, Zhang Y. A large-scale outbreak of echovirus 30 in Gansu province of China in 2015 and its phylodynamic characterization. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:1137. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2020.01137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farshadpour F, Taherkhani R. Molecular epidemiology of enteroviruses and predominance of echovirus 30 in an Iranian population with aseptic meningitis. J Neurovirol. 2021;27(3):444-451. doi:10.1007/s13365-021-00973-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maruo Y, Nakanishi M, Suzuki Y, et al. Outbreak of aseptic meningitis caused by echovirus 30 in Kushiro, Japan in 2017. J Clin Virol. 2019;116:34-38. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2019.05.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Zheng Y, Shi W, et al. Pathogenic characteristics of hand, foot and mouth disease in Shaanxi province, China, 2010-2016. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):989. doi:10.1038/s41598-020-57807-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao X, Bian LL, Lu WW, et al. Epidemiological and etiological characteristics of herpangina and hand foot mouth diseases in Jiangsu, China, 2013-2014. Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2017;13(4):823-830. doi:10.1080/21645515.2016.1236879</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>