<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38025911</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2287-3651</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical and experimental vaccine research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Exp Vaccine Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Experimental animal models for development of human enterovirus vaccine.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>291</StartPage><EndPage>297</EndPage><MedlinePgn>291-297</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7774/cevr.2023.12.4.291</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus infections induce infectious diseases in young children, such as hand, foot, and mouth disease which is characterized by highly contagious rashes or blisters around the hands, feet, buttocks, and mouth. This predominantly arises from enterovirus A71 or coxsackievirus A16 infections and in severe cases, they can lead to encephalitis, paralysis, pulmonary edema, or even fatality, representing a global health threat. Due to the absence of effective therapeutic strategies for these infections, various experimental animal models are being investigated for the development of vaccines. During the early stages of research on enterovirus infections, non-human primate infections exhibited symptoms like those in humans, leading to their utilization as model animals. However, due to economic and ethical considerations, their current usage is limited. While enterovirus infections do not readily occur in mice, an infection model with mouse-adapted strain in neonatal mice has been employed. Cellular receptors have been identified in human cells, and genetically modified mice expressing these receptors have been used. Most recently, the utilization of Mongolian gerbil model is actively being considered and should be pursued for further animal model development. So, herein, we provide a summarized overview of the current portfolio of available enterovirus infection models, emphasizing their respective advantages and limitations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Korean Vaccine Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Jae Min</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0460-1113</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biopharmaceutical and Medical Sciences, Sungshin Women's University, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Exp Vaccine Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101592344</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2287-3651</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disease models</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccines</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38025911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10655152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7774/cevr.2023.12.4.291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Peng W, Ren J, et al. A sensor-adaptor mechanism for enterovirus uncoating from structures of EV71. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2012;19:424–429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3378640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22388738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu H, Liu X, Wu Y, et al. Identification of a neutralizing linear epitope within the VP1 protein of coxsackievirus A10. Virol J. 2022;19:203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9714398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36457099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamayoshi S, Yamashita Y, Li J, et al. Scavenger receptor B2 is a cellular receptor for enterovirus 71. Nat Med. 2009;15:798–801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19543282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan CW, Poh CL, Sam IC, Chan YF. Enterovirus 71 uses cell surface heparan sulfate glycosaminoglycan as an attachment receptor. J Virol. 2013;87:611–620.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23097443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishimura Y, Shimojima M, Tano Y, Miyamura T, Wakita T, Shimizu H. Human P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 is a functional receptor for enterovirus 71. Nat Med. 2009;15:794–797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19543284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Chuang H, Yang KD. Sialylated glycans as receptor and inhibitor of enterovirus 71 infection to DLD-1 intestinal cells. Virol J. 2009;6:141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2751754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19751532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrero LJ, Lee CS, Hurrelbrink RJ, Chua BH, Chua KB, McMinn PC. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus 71 in peninsular Malaysia, 1997-2000. Arch Virol. 2003;148:1369–1385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12827466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan LG, Parashar UD, Lye MS, et al. Deaths of children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Sarawak, Malaysia: clinical and pathological characteristics of the disease: for the Outbreak Study Group. Clin Infect Dis. 2000;31:678–683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11017815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanh TH, Sabanathan S, Thanh TT, et al. Enterovirus 71-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease, Southern Vietnam, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18:2002–2005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3557876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23194699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duong V, Mey C, Eloit M, et al. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus 71 at the origin of an epidemic of fatal hand, foot and mouth disease cases in Cambodia. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2016;5:e104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5113052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27651091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Sanden S, Koopmans M, Uslu G, van der Avoort H Dutch Working Group for Clinical Virology. Epidemiology of enterovirus 71 in the Netherlands, 1963 to 2008. J Clin Microbiol. 2009;47:2826–2833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2738086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19625480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kung YA, Hung CT, Liu YC, Shih SR. Update on the development of enterovirus 71 vaccines. Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2014;14:1455–1464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24989170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Liu G, Liu X, et al. Optimization and characterization of candidate strain for coxsackievirus A16 inactivated vaccine. Viruses. 2015;7:3891–3909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4517132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26193302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hober D, Sane F, Jaidane H, Riedweg K, Goffard A, Desailloud R. Immunology in the clinic review series; focus on type 1 diabetes and viruses: role of antibodies enhancing the infection with coxsackievirus-B in the pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. Clin Exp Immunol. 2012;168:47–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3390492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22385236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoang MT, Nguyen TA, Tran TT, et al. Clinical and aetiological study of hand, foot and mouth disease in southern Vietnam, 2013-2015: inpatients and outpatients. Int J Infect Dis. 2019;80:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6403263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30550944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu S, Liao Q, Zhou Y, et al. Population based hospitalization burden of laboratory-confirmed hand, foot and mouth disease caused by multiple enterovirus serotypes in Southern China. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0203792.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6292616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30543631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Teng Z, Cui X, et al. Epidemiological and serological surveillance of hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Shanghai, China, 2012-2016. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2018;7:8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5837173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29362406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi L, Lu J, Kung HF, He ML. The virology and developments toward control of human enterovirus 71. Crit Rev Microbiol. 2011;37:313–327.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21651436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velandia-Romero ML, Acosta-Losada O, Castellanos JE. In vivo infection by a neuroinvasive neurovirulent dengue virus. J Neurovirol. 2012;18:374–387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22825914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vermillion MS, Lei J, Shabi Y, et al. Intrauterine Zika virus infection of pregnant immunocompetent mice models transplacental transmission and adverse perinatal outcomes. Nat Commun. 2017;8:14575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5321801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28220786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couderc T, Chretien F, Schilte C, et al. A mouse model for Chikungunya: young age and inefficient type-I interferon signaling are risk factors for severe disease. PLoS Pathog. 2008;4:e29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2242832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18282093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathur A, Arora KL, Chaturvedi UC. Congenital infection of mice with Japanese encephalitis virus. Infect Immun. 1981;34:26–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC350815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6271682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J, Wu J, Cao Y, et al. A mouse model for infection with enterovirus A71 in small extracellular vesicles. mSphere. 2020;5:e00377–e00320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7333570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32611697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q, Hao X, Hu Y, et al. A neonatal mouse model of central nervous system infections caused by Coxsackievirus B5. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2018;7:185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6246558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30459302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Q, Li N, Yu X, et al. Antigenicity, animal protective effect and genetic characteristics of candidate vaccine strains of enterovirus 71. Arch Virol. 2012;157:37–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21984267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sickles GM, Mutterer M, Feorino P, Plager H. Recently classified types of Coxsackie virus, group A; behavior in tissue culture. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med. 1955;90:529–531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13273503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua BH, Phuektes P, Sanders SA, Nicholls PK, McMinn PC. The molecular basis of mouse adaptation by human enterovirus 71. J Gen Virol. 2008;89(Pt 7):1622–1632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18559932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn P, Lindsay K, Perera D, Chan HM, Chan KP, Cardosa MJ. Phylogenetic analysis of enterovirus 71 strains isolated during linked epidemics in Malaysia, Singapore, and Western Australia. J Virol. 2001;75:7732–7738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC115010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11462047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn P, Stratov I, Nagarajan L, Davis S. Neurological manifestations of enterovirus 71 infection in children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Western Australia. Clin Infect Dis. 2001;32:236–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11170913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang YF, Chou CT, Lei HY, et al. A mouse-adapted enterovirus 71 strain causes neurological disease in mice after oral infection. J Virol. 2004;78:7916–7924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC446098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15254164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen YC, Yu CK, Wang YF, Liu CC, Su IJ, Lei HY. A murine oral enterovirus 71 infection model with central nervous system involvement. J Gen Virol. 2004;85(Pt 1):69–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14718621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang SW, Wang YF, Yu CK, Su IJ, Wang JR. Mutations in VP2 and VP1 capsid proteins increase infectivity and mouse lethality of enterovirus 71 by virus binding and RNA accumulation enhancement. Virology. 2012;422:132–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22078110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YI, Song JH, Kwon BE, et al. Pros and cons of VP1-specific maternal IgG for the protection of enterovirus 71 infection. Vaccine. 2015;33:6604–6610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26529069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osorio JE, Schoepp RJ, Yuill TM. Effects of La Crosse virus infection on pregnant domestic rabbits and mongolian gerbils. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1996;55:384–390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8916793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong Y, He ZJ, Tao W, Fu T, Wang YK, Chen Y. Experimental infection of Z:ZCLA Mongolian gerbils with human hepatitis E virus. World J Gastroenterol. 2015;21:862–867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4299338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25624719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao PP, Qian L, Xia Y, et al. Enterovirus 71-induced neurological disorders in young gerbils, Meriones unguiculatus: development and application of a neurological disease model. PLoS One. 2012;7:e51996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3528719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23284845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu F, Yao PP, Xia Y, et al. Enterovirus 71 infection causes severe pulmonary lesions in gerbils, meriones unguiculatus, which can be prevented by passive immunization with specific antisera. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0119173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4359154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25767882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun YS, Xia Y, Xu F, et al. Development and evaluation of an inactivated coxsackievirus A16 vaccine in gerbils. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2022;11:1994–2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9377242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35787233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi EJ, Kim YI, Kim SY, et al. A bivalent inactivated vaccine prevents enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A16 infections in the Mongolian gerbil. Biomol Ther (Seoul) 2023;31:350–358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10129857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37041034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Li J, Li Q. Immune evasion of enteroviruses under innate immune monitoring. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:1866.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6102382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30154774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Ennis J, Turner JD, Chu JJ. Single dose of an adenovirus vectored mouse interferon-α protects mice from lethal EV71 challenge. Antiviral Res. 2016;134:207–215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7113890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27623347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin H, Huang L, Zhou J, et al. Efficacy and safety of inter-feron-α2b spray in the treatment of hand, foot, and mouth disease: a multicenter, randomized, double-blind trial. Arch Virol. 2016;161:3073–3080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27518403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khong WX, Yan B, Yeo H, et al. A non-mouse-adapted enterovirus 71 (EV71) strain exhibits neurotropism, causing neurological manifestations in a novel mouse model of EV71 infection. J Virol. 2012;86:2121–2131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3302383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22130542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caine EA, Moncla LH, Ronderos MD, Friedrich TC, Osorio JE. A single mutation in the VP1 of enterovirus 71 is responsible for increased virulence and neurotropism in adult interferon-deficient mice. J Virol. 2016;90:8592–8604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5021399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27440896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao CC, Liou AT, Chang YS, et al. Immunodeficient mouse models with different disease profiles by in vivo infection with the same clinical isolate of enterovirus 71. J Virol. 2014;88:12485–12499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4248922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25142603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liou AT, Wu SY, Liao CC, Chang YS, Chang CS, Shih C. A new animal model containing human SCARB2 and lacking stat-1 is highly susceptible to EV71. Sci Rep. 2016;6:31151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4976353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27499235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SM, Lei HY, Yu CK, Wang JR, Su IJ, Liu CC. Acute chemokine response in the blood and cerebrospinal fluid of children with enterovirus 71-associated brainstem encephalitis. J Infect Dis. 2008;198:1002–1006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18710325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen FH, Tsai CC, Wang LC, et al. Enterovirus 71 infection increases expression of interferon-gamma-inducible protein 10 which protects mice by reducing viral burden in multiple tissues. J Gen Virol. 2013;94(Pt 5):1019–1027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23288420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang SL, Chou YT, Wu CN, Ho MS. Annexin II binds to capsid protein VP1 of enterovirus 71 and enhances viral infectivity. J Virol. 2011;85:11809–11820.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3209289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21900167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Dong W, Quan X, Ma C, Qin C, Zhang L. Transgenic expression of human P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 is not sufficient for enterovirus 71 infection in mice. Arch Virol. 2012;157:539–543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22187102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin YW, Yu SL, Shao HY, et al. Human SCARB2 transgenic mice as an infectious animal model for enterovirus 71. PLoS One. 2013;8:e57591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3581494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23451246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujii K, Nagata N, Sato Y, et al. Transgenic mouse model for the study of enterovirus 71 neuropathogenesis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110:14753–14758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3767555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23959904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chumakov M, Voroshilova M, Shindarov L, et al. Enterovirus 71 isolated from cases of epidemic poliomyelitis-like disease in Bulgaria. Arch Virol. 1979;60:329–340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">228639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto I, Hagiwara A, Kodama H. Neurovirulence in cynomolgus monkeys of enterovirus 71 isolated from a patient with hand, foot and mouth disease. Arch Virol. 1978;56:257–261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">205198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto I, Hagiwara A. Pathogenicity of a poliomyelitis-like disease in monkeys infected orally with enterovirus 71: a model for human infection. Neuropathol Appl Neurobiol. 1982;8:149–156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7048123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagata N, Shimizu H, Ami Y, et al. Pyramidal and extrapyramidal involvement in experimental infection of cynomolgus monkeys with enterovirus 71. J Med Virol. 2002;67:207–216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11992581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Cui W, Liu L, et al. Pathogenesis study of enterovirus 71 infection in rhesus monkeys. Lab Invest. 2011;91:1337–1350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21555996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Zhao H, Zhang Y, et al. Neonatal rhesus monkey is a potential animal model for studying pathogenesis of EV71 infection. Virology. 2011;412:91–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21262515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Nagata N, Iwata N, et al. An attenuated strain of enterovirus 71 belonging to genotype a showed a broad spectrum of antigenicity with attenuated neurovirulence in cynomolgus monkeys. J Virol. 2007;81:9386–9395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1951441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17567701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Shimizu H, Nagata N, et al. Temperature-sensitive mutants of enterovirus 71 show attenuation in cynomolgus monkeys. J Gen Virol. 2005;86(Pt 5):1391–1401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15831951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagata N, Iwasaki T, Ami Y, et al. Differential localization of neurons susceptible to enterovirus 71 and poliovirus type 1 in the central nervous system of cynomolgus monkeys after intravenous inoculation. J Gen Virol. 2004;85(Pt 10):2981–2989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15448361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>