<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38024246</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>101</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Polio outbreak response, Yemen.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>808</StartPage><EndPage>812</EndPage><MedlinePgn>808-812</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.23.290122</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PROBLEM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A decrease in vaccine coverage in conflict-affected areas has placed Yemen at higher risk of polio outbreaks caused by vaccine-derived poliovirus strains.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROACH" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In response to polio outbreaks, the Yemeni health ministry and partners initiated multiple vaccination campaigns to deliver vaccines to children. We also implemented several measures to enhance communication, education, health promotion and hygiene, especially in camps for internally displaced people.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LOCAL SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In 2009, Yemen achieved polio-free status and maintained it until 2019. However, the ongoing political conflict since 2015, coupled with challenges in delivering the polio vaccine to conflict-affected areas, resulted in two polio outbreaks: 35 cases caused by vaccine-derived poliovirus strain 1 between 2019 and 2021, and 230 cases due to vaccine-derived poliovirus strain 2 between November 2021 and December 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANT CHANGES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In response to the first outbreak, by the end of 2020, we vaccinated 7.2 million children through nationwide vaccination campaigns, except in Sa'ada governorate due to a ban by the authorities. By the end of 2021, 3 800 313 children younger than 5 years had received polio vaccines. For the second outbreak, by the end of 2022, 4 463 389 vaccines had been given to children younger than 10 years, and 1 217 423 to those younger than 5 years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LESSONS LEARNT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Vaccination campaigns in conflict-affected areas with low vaccine coverage remain crucial in eradicating polio. Efforts are needed to reach vulnerable groups such as displaced populations. Advocacy, communication and social mobilization actions help ensure broader public inclusion and participation in vaccination efforts to prevent polio outbreaks.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beshr</LastName><ForeName>Ibrahem Abduallah</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Sana'a University, Wadi Dhaher Road, PO Box 13078, Sana'a, Yemen.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beshr</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed Sadeq</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Sana'a University, Wadi Dhaher Road, PO Box 13078, Sana'a, Yemen.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Qubati</LastName><ForeName>Hibah Abdulqader</ForeName><Initials>HA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Sana'a University, Wadi Dhaher Road, PO Box 13078, Sana'a, Yemen.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D023321">Poliovirus Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015006" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Yemen</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D023321" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus Vaccines</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText Label="PROBLÈME" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Avec le déclin de la couverture vaccinale dans les régions en conflit, le Yémen encourt un risque accru d'épidémies de poliomyélite dues à un poliovirus dérivé d'une souche vaccinale.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROCHE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Face aux épidémies de poliomyélite, le Ministère de la Santé yéménite et ses partenaires ont lancé plusieurs campagnes de vaccination des enfants. Nous avons également déployé de nombreuses mesures visant à améliorer la communication, l'éducation, la promotion de la santé et l'hygiène, en particulier dans les camps abritant des personnes déplacées à l’intérieur du pays.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENVIRONNEMENT LOCAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En 2009, le Yémen avait été déclaré exempt de poliomyélite et a conservé ce statut jusqu'en 2019. Toutefois, les luttes politiques qui font rage depuis 2015, associées aux difficultés rencontrées dans la fourniture du vaccin antipoliomyélitique dans les régions en conflit, ont entraîné deux épidémies: 35 cas ont été causés par un poliovirus dérivé d'une souche vaccinale de type 1 entre 2019 et 2021, et 230 cas par un poliovirus dérivé d'une souche vaccinale de type 2 entre novembre 2021 et décembre 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CHANGEMENTS SIGNIFICATIFS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Pour lutter contre la première épidémie, fin 2020, nous avons vacciné 7,2 millions d'enfants dans le cadre de campagnes de vaccination à l'échelle nationale, à l'exception du gouvernorat de Saada, en raison de l'interdiction imposée par les autorités. Fin 2021, 3 800 313 enfants de moins de cinq ans avaient reçu leur vaccin antipoliomyélitique. Lors de la seconde épidémie, fin 2022, 4 463 389 vaccins avaient été administrés aux enfants de moins de 10 ans et 1 217 423 aux enfants de moins de 5 ans.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LEÇONS TIRÉES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Les campagnes de vaccination dans les régions en conflit où la couverture vaccinale est faible demeurent cruciales pour l'éradication de la poliomyélite. Des efforts sont nécessaires pour atteindre les groupes vulnérables tels que les populations déplacées. Les actions de sensibilisation, de communication et de mobilisation sociale permettent de toucher un plus large public et d'encourager la participation aux efforts de vaccination, essentiels dans la prévention des épidémies de poliomyélite.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="SITUACIÓN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">La disminución de la cobertura de vacunación en las regiones afectadas como consecuencia del conflicto ha hecho que Yemen corra un mayor riesgo de brotes de poliomielitis causados por cepas de poliovirus derivadas de la vacuna.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENFOQUE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En respuesta a los brotes de poliomielitis, el Ministerio de Salud de Yemen y sus asociados emprendieron múltiples campañas de vacunación para suministrar vacunas a los niños. También aplicamos varias medidas para mejorar la comunicación, la educación, la promoción de la salud y la higiene, especialmente en los campamentos para desplazados internos.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MARCO REGIONAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En 2009, Yemen logró la condición de país libre de poliomielitis y la mantuvo hasta 2019. Sin embargo, el conflicto político en curso desde 2015, junto con las dificultades para suministrar la vacuna antipoliomielítica a las regiones afectadas por el conflicto, dieron lugar a dos brotes de poliomielitis: 35 casos causados por la cepa 1 del poliovirus derivado de la vacuna entre 2019 y 2021, y 230 casos debidos a la cepa 2 del poliovirus derivado de la vacuna entre noviembre de 2021 y diciembre de 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CAMBIOS IMPORTANTES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En respuesta al primer brote, a finales de 2020 habíamos vacunado a 7,2 millones de niños a través de campañas de vacunación en todo el país, excepto en la gobernación de Saada debido a una prohibición de las autoridades. A finales de 2021, 3 800 313 niños menores de 5 años habían sido vacunados contra la poliomielitis. Para el segundo brote, a finales de 2022 se habían administrado 4 463 389 vacunas a niños menores de 10 años y 1 217 423 a menores de 5 años.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LECCIONES APRENDIDAS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Las campañas de vacunación en regiones afectadas por conflictos con baja cobertura de vacunación siguen siendo esenciales para erradicar la poliomielitis. Se necesitan esfuerzos para llegar a los grupos vulnerables, como las poblaciones desplazadas. Las acciones de promoción, comunicación y movilización social ayudan a garantizar una mayor inclusión y participación del público en los esfuerzos de vacunación para prevenir los brotes de poliomielitis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText Label="المشكلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">إن الانخفاض في تغطية اللقاحات للمناطق المتضررة من النزاع، أدى لوضع اليمن في موقع أكثر خطورة لتفشي مرض شلل الأطفال الناتج عن سلالات فيروس شلل الأطفال المشتقة من اللقاح.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الأسلوب" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">استجابةً لحالات تفشي مرض شلل الأطفال، أطلقت وزارة الصحة اليمنية وشركاؤها حملات تطعيم متعددة لتوصيل اللقاحات للأطفال. كما قمنا بتنفيذ العديد من التدابير لتعزيز التواصل، والتعليم، والارتقاء بالصحة والنظافة، وخاصة في مخيمات النازحين بالداخل.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="المواقع المحلية" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">في عام 2009، حقق اليمن حالة الخلو من مرض شلل الأطفال، وحافظ عليها حتى عام 2019. ومع ذلك، أدى الصراع السياسي الدائر منذ عام 2015، مقترنًا بالتحديات في توصيل لقاح شلل الأطفال إلى المناطق المتضررة من النزاع، إلى حالتين من تفشي مرض شلل الأطفال: 35 حالة ناجمة عن سلالة فيروس شلل الأطفال المشتقة من اللقاح 1 بين عامي 2019 و2021، و230 حالة بسبب سلالة فيروس شلل الأطفال المشتقة من اللقاح 2 بين نوفمبر/تشرين ثاني 2021 وديسمبر/كانون أول 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="التغيّرات ذات الصلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">استجابةً لحالة التفشي الأولى، بنهاية عام 2020، قمنا بتطعيم 7.2 مليون طفل من خلال حملات التطعيم المنتشرة على مستوى الدولة، باستثناء محافظة صعدة بسبب الحظر الذي فرضته السلطات. وبنهاية عام 2021، تلقى عدد 3800313 طفلاً تقل أعمارهم عن 5 سنوات لقاحات شلل الأطفال. وبالنسبة لحالة التفشي الثانية، بنهاية عام 2022، تم إعطاء 4463389 لقاحًا للأطفال الذين تقل أعمارهم عن 10 سنوات، و1217423 لقاحًا للأطفال الذين تقل أعمارهم عن 5 سنوات.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الدروس المستفادة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">إن حملات التطعيم في المناطق المتضررة من النزاع، والتي تعاني من تغطية منخفضة من اللقاحات، تظل ذات أهمية بالغة في استئصال مرض شلل الأطفال. هناك حاجة إلى بذل جهود للوصول إلى المجموعات المهمشة مثل السكان النازحين. وتساعد إجراءات الدعم، والاتصال، والتعبئة الاجتماعية على ضمان الإدماج والمشاركة العامة على نطاق أوسع في جهود التطعيم لمنع حالات تفشي مرض شلل الأطفال.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText Label="问题" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">受冲突影响地区的疫苗覆盖率下降，使也门面临较高的脊髓灰质炎爆发风险。该脊髓灰质炎是由疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒株引起的。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="方法" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">为了应对脊髓灰质炎爆发，也门卫生部及其合作伙伴发起了多项为儿童接种疫苗的疫苗接种运动。我们还实施了若干措施，以加强沟通、宣传教育、促进健康和卫生条件，尤其针对境内流离失所者所居的营地。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="当地状况" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">2009 年，也门实现了“无脊髓灰质炎状态”，并一直维持此状态到 2019 年。然而，自 2015 年以来，持续的政治冲突，加上在向受冲突影响地区提供脊髓灰质炎疫苗方面面临的挑战，导致了两次脊髓灰质炎的爆发：2019 年至 2021 年期间，疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒株 1 型引起了 35 例脊髓灰质炎， 2021 年 11 月至 2022 年 12 月期间，疫苗衍生脊髓灰质炎病毒株 2 型引起了 230 例脊髓灰质炎。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="相关变化" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">为应对第一次脊髓灰质炎爆发，截至 2020 年底，除受当局禁令影响的萨达省外，我们通过全国范围内的疫苗接种运动为 720 万名儿童接种了疫苗。截至 2021 年底，已有 3,800,313 名 5 岁以下的儿童接种了脊髓灰质炎疫苗。为应对第二次爆发，截至 2022 年底，我们已为 10 岁以下儿童接种了 4,463,389 支疫苗，为 5 岁以下儿童接种了 1,217,423 支疫苗。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="经验教训" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">在受冲突影响、疫苗覆盖率低的地区开展疫苗接种运动对于根除脊髓灰质炎仍然至关重要。需要采取行动来帮助流离失所者等弱势群体。进行宣传、沟通和社会动员活动有助于确保更多的公众加入和参与预防脊髓灰质炎爆发的疫苗接种工作。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText Label="ПРОБЛЕМА" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Снижение уровня охвата вакцинацией в зонах конфликта привело к тому, что в Йемене повысился риск возникновения вспышек полиомиелита, вызванных штаммами вакцинного полиовируса.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ПОДХОД" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В ответ на вспышки полиомиелита Министерство здравоохранения Йемена и партнеры провели многочисленные кампании по вакцинации детей. Также был реализован ряд мер по улучшению коммуникации, образования, укреплению здоровья и соблюдению гигиены, особенно в лагерях для перемещенных лиц.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="МЕСТНЫЕ УСЛОВИЯ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В 2009 году Йемен получил статус страны, свободной от полиомиелита, и сохранял его до 2019 года. Однако продолжающийся с 2015 года политический конфликт в совокупности со сложностями при доставке вакцины против полиомиелита в охваченные конфликтом районы привел к двум вспышкам полиомиелита: 35 случаев, вызванных штаммом 1 вакцинного полиовируса в период с 2019 по 2021 год, и 230 случаев, вызванных штаммом 2 вакцинного полиовируса в период с ноября 2021 года по декабрь 2022 года.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ОСУЩЕСТВЛЕННЫЕ ПЕРЕМЕНЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В ответ на первую вспышку к концу 2020 года была проведена вакцинация 7,2 млн детей в рамках общенациональных кампаний по вакцинации, за исключением провинции Саада из-за запрета властей. К концу 2021 года вакцины против полиомиелита получили 3 800 313 детей в возрасте до 5 лет. Что касается второй вспышки, к концу 2022 года детям в возрасте до 10 лет было введено 4 463 389 вакцин, а детям в возрасте до 5 лет – 1 217 423.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ВЫВОДЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Кампании по вакцинации в зонах конфликта с низким уровнем охвата вакцинацией по-прежнему имеют решающее значение для ликвидации полиомиелита. Необходимы усилия по охвату уязвимых групп населения, таких как перемещенные лица. Мероприятия по информационно-просветительской деятельности, коммуникации и социальной мобилизации способствуют более широкому вовлечению и участию населения в вакцинации с целью предотвращения вспышек полиомиелита.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2023 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38024246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10680107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.23.290122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.23.290122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Al-Dubaiee R, Al Qassimi M, Al-Dar A, Al Serouri A, Khader Y. Impact of the protracted war in Yemen on the acute flaccid paralysis surveillance system: retrospective descriptive analysis. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2021. May 19;7(5):e27638. 10.2196/27638</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/27638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8173393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34009132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estivariz CF, Link-Gelles R, Shimabukuro T, editors. Poliomyelitis. Atlanta: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; 2021. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/pubs/pinkbook/polio.html [cited 2023 Jul 9].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine-derived polioviruses [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; c2023. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-prevention/the-virus/vaccine-derived-polio-viruses/ [cited 2023 Apr 15].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine-derived poliovirus. Fact sheet [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2018. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/Global Polio Eradication Initiative-cVDPV-Fact-Sheet-20191115.pdf [cited 2023 Apr 15]. </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yemen’s top AFP surveillance officer on what the indicators tell us [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2022. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/news-post/yemens-top-afp-surveillance-officer-on-what-the-indicators-tell-us/ [cited 2023 Aug 9].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yemen humanitarian situation report, mid-year. Geneva: United Nations Children’s Fund; 2023. Available from: https://www.unicef.org/documents/yemen-humanitarian-situation-report-mid-year-2023 [cited 2023 Aug 9].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torbosh A, Al Amad MA, Al Serouri A, Khader Y. The impact of war in Yemen on immunization coverage of children under one year of age: descriptive study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2019. Oct 23;5(4):e14461. 10.2196/14461</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/14461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6913770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31647465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gayer M, Legros D, Formenty P, Connolly MA. Conflict and emerging infectious diseases. Emerg Infect Dis. 2007. Nov;13(11):1625–31. 10.3201/eid1311.061093</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1311.061093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3375795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18217543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yemen [internet]. Cairo: World Health Organization Regional Office for the Eastern Mediterranean; 2023. Available from: https://www.emro.who.int/polio-eradication/priority-countries/yemen.html [cited 2023 Apr 16].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Country: Yemen [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative World Health Organization; 2023. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/countries/yemen/ [cited 2023 Apr 15].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polio global update, 22 March 2023 [internet]. Geneva: Global Polio Eradication Initiative; 2023. Available from: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/weekly-polio-analyses-cVDPV-20230321.pdf [cited 2023 Oct 11].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yemen humanitarian situation report, end of year. Geneva: United Nations Children’s Fund; 2020. Available from: https://www.unicef.org/media/93126/file/Yemen_Humanitarian_Situation_Report%2C_End_of_Year_2020.pdf [cited 2023 Aug 9].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yemen humanitarian situation report, end of year. Geneva: United Nations Children’s Fund; 2022. Available from: https://www.unicef.org/documents/yemen-humanitarian-situation-report-end-year-31-december-2022 [cited 2023 Aug 9].</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>