<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38010589</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>14</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1522-2683</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>45</Volume><Issue>3-4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Electrophoresis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Electrophoresis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analysis of full and empty ratio of EV71 virus by using capillary zone electrophoresis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>327</StartPage><EndPage>332</EndPage><MedlinePgn>327-332</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/elps.202300150</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Hand, foot, and mouth disease is a serious public health problem, and the main pathogen is enterovirus 71 (EV71). Its capsid assembly mechanism including capsid protein processing has been widely studied. Full and empty capsids have different immunological efficacy. Therefore, tracking full/empty capsid ratio throughout the EV71 production process is important to ensure consistent product quality and proper dosing response. The analysis of full/empty capsid ratio of intact virus has been widely reported as well. A variety of techniques have been employed to evaluate the full/empty capsid ratios. However, there has not been a rapid, reproducible, and robust assay to determine the full/empty capsid ratios of final and in-process products. In this study, a novel assay based on capillary zone electrophoresis was established. The separation of full and empty species could be achieved within 10 min and the ratio of peak areas was used to calculate the full/empty capsid ratio directly. The results showed good reproducibility and linearity for the determination of full/empty capsid ratios.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jie-Ru</ForeName><Initials>JR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech Ltd., Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Hong-Xu</ForeName><Initials>HX</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4537-0382</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sciex China, Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Hua-Qing</ForeName><Initials>HQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech Ltd., Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Run</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4101-3601</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech Ltd., Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jia</LastName><ForeName>Zeng</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing BioCEart Technology Institute, Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech Ltd., Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sinovac Biotech Ltd., Beijing, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Electrophoresis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8204476</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0173-0835</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D036022">Capsid Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036022" MajorTopicYN="N">Capsid Proteins</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002213" MajorTopicYN="N">Capsid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011499" MajorTopicYN="N">Protein Processing, Post-Translational</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EV71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">capillary zone electrophoresis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dynamic coating</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">full/empty capsid ratio</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38010589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/elps.202300150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Gou E, Li Q, Li X, Gu S, Han Y, Tang Z, et al. Analysis on the sequence of the whole genome of an isolated enterovirus 71 strain. Int J Clin Exp Med. 2015;8(11):20652-20657.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Wang C, Mueller S, Paul AV, Wimmer E, Jiang P. Direct interaction between two viral proteins, the nonstructural protein 2C and the capsid protein VP3, is required for enterovirus morphogenesis. PLoS Pathog. 2010;6(8):e1001066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basavappa R, Syed R, Flore O, Icenogle JP, Filman DJ, Hogle JM. Role and mechanism of the maturation cleavage of VP0 in poliovirus assembly: structure of the empty capsid assembly intermediate at 2.9 A resolution. Protein Sci. 1994;3(10):1651-1669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curry S, Fry E, Blakemore W, Abu-Ghazaleh R, Jackson T, King A, et al. Dissecting the roles of VP0 cleavage and RNA packaging in picornavirus capsid stabilization: the structure of empty capsids of foot-and-mouth disease virus. J Virol. 1997;71(12):9743-9752.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plevka P, Perera R, Cardosa J, Kuhn RJ, Rossmann MG. Crystal structure of human enterovirus 71. Science. 2012;336(6086):1274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Peng W, Ren J, Hu Z, Xu J, Lou Z, et al. A sensor-adaptor mechanism for enterovirus uncoating from structures of EV71. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2012;19(4):424-429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, Liu H, Qu M, Hou A, Zhou Y, Sun B, et al. Determination of the cleavage site of enterovirus 71 VP0 and the effect of this cleavage on viral infectivity and assembly. Microb Pathog. 2019;134:103568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng C, Feng M, Yang EX, Pu J, Cui PF, Zhang Y, et al. Immune characteristics of two enterovirus 71 virion fractions. Chin J Biol. 2014;27(11):1388-1393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kronenberg S, Kleinschmidt JA, Böttcher B. Electron cryo-microscopy and image reconstruction of adeno-associated virus type 2 empty capsids. EMBO Rep. 2001;2(11):997-1002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allay JA, Sleep S, Long S, Tillman DM, Clark R, Carney G, et al. Good manufacturing practice production of self-complementary serotype 8 adeno-associated viral vector for a hemophilia B clinical trial. Hum Gene Ther. 2011;22(5):595-604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm D, Kern A, Pawlita M, Ferrari F, Samulski R, Kleinschmidt J. Titration of AAV-2 particles via a novel capsid ELISA: packaging of genomes can limit production of recombinant AAV-2. Gene Ther. 1999;6(7):1322-1330.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sommer JM, Smith PH, Parthasarathy S, Isaacs J, Vijay S, Kieran J, et al. Quantification of adeno-associated virus particles and empty capsids by optical density measurement. Mol Ther. 2003;7(1):122-128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Mulagapati SHR, Chen Z, Du J, Zhao X, Xi G, et al. Developing an anion exchange chromatography assay for determining empty and full capsid contents in AAV6.2. Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev. 2019;15:257-263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han M, Phan D, Nightlinger N, Taylor L, Jankhah S, Woodruff B, et al. Optimization of CE-SDS method for antibody separation based on multi-users experimental practices. Chromatographia. 2006;64(5-6):1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunnally B, Park SS, Patel K, Hong M, Zhang X, Wang S-X, et al. A series of collaborations between various pharmaceutical companies and regulatory authorities concerning the analysis of biomolecules using capillary electrophoresis. Chromatographia. 2006;64(5):359-368.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bristow AF, Charton E. Assessment of the suitability of a capillary zone electrophoresis method for determining isoform distribution of erythropoietin. Pharmeuropa. 1999;11(2):290-300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kremser L, Petsch M, Blaas D, Kenndler E. Capillary electrophoresis of affinity complexes between subviral 80S particles of human rhinovirus and monoclonal antibody 2G2. Electrophoresis. 2006;27(13):2630-2637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okun VM, Moser R, Ronacher B, Kenndler E, Blaas D. VLDL receptor fragments of different lengths bind to human rhinovirus HRV2 with different stoichiometry. An analysis of virus-receptor complexes by capillary electrophoresis. J Biol Chem. 2001;276(2):1057-1062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Pawliszyn J. Behaviors of the MS2 virus and related antibodies in capillary isoelectric focusing with whole-column imaging detection. Electrophoresis. 2005;26(3):556-562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li T, Gao T, Chen H, Pekker P, Menyhart A, Guttman A. Rapid determination of full and empty adeno-associated virus capsid ratio by capillary isoelectric focusing. Curr Mol Med. 2020;20(10):814-820.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang M, Wang X, Wang Q, Wang Y, Lin J, Sun Y, et al. Molecular mechanism of SCARB2-mediated attachment and uncoating of EV71. Protein Cell. 2014;5(9):692-703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamayoshi S, Ohka S, Fujii K, Koike S. Functional comparison of SCARB2 and PSGL1 as receptors for enterovirus 71. J Virol. 2013;87(6):3335-3347.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>