<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38009321</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>20</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1600-065X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>322</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Immunological reviews</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Immunol Rev</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Rubella virus chronic inflammatory disease and other unusual viral phenotypes in inborn errors of immunity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>113</StartPage><EndPage>137</EndPage><MedlinePgn>113-137</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/imr.13290</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Infectious susceptibility is a component of many inborn errors of immunity. Nevertheless, antibiotic use is often used as a surrogate in history taking for infectious susceptibility, thereby disadvantaging patients who present with viral infections as their phenotype. Further complicating clinical evaluations are unusual manifestations of viral infections which may be less familiar that the typical respiratory viral infections. This review covers several unusual viral phenotypes arising in patients with inborn errors of immunity and other settings of immune compromise. In some cases, chronic infections lead to oncogenesis or tumor-like growths and the conditions and mechanisms of viral-induced oncogenesis will be described. This review covers enterovirus, rubella, measles, papillomavirus, and parvovirus B19. It does not cover EBV and hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis nor lymphomagenesis related to EBV. EBV susceptibility has been recently reviewed. Our goal is to increase awareness of the unusual manifestations of viral infections in patients with IEI and to describe treatment modalities utilized in this setting. Coincidentally, each of the discussed viral infections can have a cutaneous component and figures will serve as a reminder of the physical features of these viruses. Given the high morbidity and mortality, early recognition can only improve outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 John Wiley &amp; Sons A/S. Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kilich</LastName><ForeName>Gonench</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-5043-6066</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perelygina</LastName><ForeName>Ludmila</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Viral Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sullivan</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen E</ForeName><Initials>KE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4018-1646</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Immunol Rev</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7702118</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0105-2896</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012412" MajorTopicYN="N">Rubella virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012409" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rubella</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008457" MajorTopicYN="Y">Measles</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002908" MajorTopicYN="N">Chronic Disease</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010641" MajorTopicYN="N">Phenotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D063646" MajorTopicYN="N">Carcinogenesis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CEMA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunodeficiencies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inborn errors of immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">measles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rubella</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38009321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/imr.13290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Tangye SG, Al-Herz W, Bousfiha A, et al. Human inborn errors of immunity: 2022 update on the classification from the International Union of Immunological Societies Expert Committee. J Clin Immunol. 2022;42(7):1473-1507.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duncan CJA, Randall RE, Hambleton S. Genetic lesions of type I interferon signalling in human antiviral immunity. Trends Genet. 2021;37(1):46-58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abolhassani H, Delavari S, Landegren N, et al. Genetic and immunologic evaluation of children with inborn errors of immunity and severe or critical COVID-19. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2022;150(5):1059-1073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matuozzo D, Talouarn E, Marchal A, et al. Rare predicted loss-of-function variants of type I IFN immunity genes are associated with life-threatening COVID-19. medRxiv. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Matuozzo D, Le Pen J, et al. Recessive inborn errors of type I IFN immunity in children with COVID-19 pneumonia. J Exp Med. 2022;219(8):e20220131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otto WR, Behrens EM, Teachey DT, et al. Human adenovirus 7-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis-like illness: clinical and virological characteristics in a cluster of five pediatric cases. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73(7):e1532-e1538.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si SJ, Tasian SK, Bassiri H, et al. Diagnostic challenges in pediatric hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. J Clin Immunol. 2021;41(6):1213-1218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bode SF, Ammann S, Al-Herz W, et al. The syndrome of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in primary immunodeficiencies: implications for differential diagnosis and pathogenesis. Haematologica. 2015;100(7):978-988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinn IK, Eckstein OS, Peckham-Gregory EC, et al. Genetic and mechanistic diversity in pediatric hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Blood. 2018;132(1):89-100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birndt S, Schenk T, Heinevetter B, et al. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in adults: collaborative analysis of 137 cases of a nationwide German registry. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2020;146(4):1065-1077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meeths M, Bryceson YT. Genetics and pathophysiology of haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Acta Paediatr. 2021;110(11):2903-2911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tangye SG, Palendira U, Edwards ES. Human immunity against EBV-lessons from the clinic. J Exp Med. 2017;214(2):269-283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan KE, Puck JM, Notarangelo LD, et al. USIDNET: a strategy to build a community of clinical immunologists. J Clin Immunol. 2014;34(4):428-435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams MJ, Carstens EB. Ratification vote on taxonomic proposals to the international committee on taxonomy of viruses (2012). Arch Virol. 2012;157(7):1411-1422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(3):793-797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Non-polio enterovirus. 2015 http://www.cdc.gov/non-polio-enterovirus/about/overview.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Lamonte A, Oberste MS, Pallansch M. Neonatal enterovirus infections reported to the national enterovirus surveillance system in the United States, 1983-2003. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2006;25(10):889-893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermaszewski RA, Webster AD. Primary hypogammaglobulinaemia: a survey of clinical manifestations and complications. Q J Med. 1993;86(1):31-42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halliday E, Winkelstein J, Webster A. Enteroviral infections in primary immunodeficiency (PID): a survey of morbidity and mortality. J Infect. 2003;46(1):1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilfert CM, Buckley RH, Mohanakumar T, et al. Persistent and fatal central-nervous-system ECHOvirus infections in patients with agammaglobulinemia. N Engl J Med. 1977;296(26):1485-1489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardelas JA, Winkelstein JA, Seto DS, Tsai T, Rogol AD. Fatal ECHO 24 infection in a patient with hypogammaglobulinemia: relationship to dermatomyositis-like syndrome. J Pediatr. 1977;90(3):396-399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scaravilli F, Coutinho P. Lymphocytic encephalitis in a case of agammaglobulinaemia. Acta Neuropathol. 1973;25(3):188-195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Toole D, Groth D, Wright H, et al. X-linked agammaglobulinemia: infection frequency and infection-related mortality in the USIDNET registry. J Clin Immunol. 2022;42(4):827-836.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez-Trujillo V, Zhou C, Scalchunes C, et al. A registry study of 240 patients with X-linked agammaglobulinemia living in the USA. J Clin Immunol. 2023;43(6):1468-1477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quartier P, Debre M, De Blic J, et al. Early and prolonged intravenous immunoglobulin replacement therapy in childhood agammaglobulinemia: a retrospective survey of 31 patients. J Pediatr. 1999;134(5):589-596.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKinney RJ, Katz S, Wilfert C. Chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis in agammaglobulinemic patients. Rev Infect Dis. 1987;9(2):334-356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudge P, Webster A, Revesz T, et al. Encephalomyelitis in primary hypogammaglobulinaemia. Brain. 1996;119(Pt 1):1-15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ito N, Kokubo Y, Narita Y, Naito Y, Kuzuhara S. A case of agammaglobulinemia with chronic enteroviral meningomyelitis. Rinsho Shinkeigaku. 1996;36(2):306-311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bearden D, Collett M, Quan PL, Costa-Carvalho BT, Sullivan KE. Enteroviruses in X-linked agammaglobulinemia: update on epidemiology and therapy. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract. 2016;4(6):1059-1065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozdoba C, Ramelli G, Schroth G. MRI in a patient with congenital agammaglobulinaemia. Neuroradiology. 1998;40(8):516-518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sole D, Radvani J, Leser P, Naspitz C. Magnetic resonance imaging in a patient with X-linked agammaglobulinemia and chronic meningoencephalitis. J Investig Allergol Clin Immunol. 1992;2(1):43-45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerner E, Bilaniuk L. Bruton-type (congenital X-linked) agammaglobulinemia: MR imaging of unusual intracranial complications. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 1992;13(3):976-980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozawa T, Onodera O, Iizuka O, et al. A case of chronic enteroviral meningitis and hydrocephalus associated with Bruton type agammaglobulinemia. No to Shinkei. 1998;50(2):191-196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaker O, Abdelhamid N. Detection of enteroviruses in pediatric patients with aseptic meningitis. Clin Neurol Neurosurg. 2015;129:67-71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyeon J, Hwang S, Kim H, et al. Accuracy of diagnostic methods and surveillance sensitivity for human enterovirus, South Korea, 1999-2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2013;19(8):1268-1275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilfert CM, Lehrman SN, Katz SL. Enteroviruses and meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis. 1983;2(4):333-341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quan PL, Wagner TA, Briese T, et al. Astrovirus encephalitis in boy with X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Emerg Infect Dis. 2010;16(6):918-925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegner UH, Kobayashi RH, Cunningham-Rundles C, et al. Progressive neurodegeneration in patients with primary immunodeficiency disease on IVIG treatment. Clin Immunol. 2002;102(1):19-24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jyonouchi S, Jongco AM, Puck J, Sullivan KE. Immunodeficiencies associated with abnormal newborn screening for T cell and B cell lymphopenia. J Clin Immunol. 2017;37(4):363-374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyarchuk O, Yarema N, Kravets V, et al. Newborn screening for severe combined immunodeficiency: the results of the first pilot TREC and KREC study in Ukraine with involving of 10,350 neonates. Front Immunol. 2022;13:999664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed R, Buckland M, Davies L, et al. Enterovirus 71 meningoencephalitis complicating rituximab therapy. J Neurol Sci. 2011;305(1-2):149-151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson SM, Gold D, Olson G, Pisano J. Chronic aseptic meningitis caused by enterovirus in a humorally immunosuppressed adult patient presenting with sensorineural hearing loss: a case report. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Archimbaud C, Bailly JL, Chambon M, Tournilhac O, Travade P, Peigue-Lafeuille H. Molecular evidence of persistent echovirus 13 meningoencephalitis in a patient with relapsed lymphoma after an outbreak of meningitis in 2000. J Clin Microbiol. 2003;41(10):4605-4610.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron Smail R, O'Neill JH, Andresen D. Brainstem encephalitis caused by Coxsackie A16 virus in a rituximab-immunosuppressed patient. BMJ Case Rep. 2019;12(8):e230177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheema S, Bunting E, Good C, Hajela V, Ridha BH, Saha RA. Balancing immunosuppression and infection: recurrent enterovirus encephalitis in SLE. Pract Neurol. 2019;19(6):508-510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook SG, Ford AW, Lindholm DA, Scott J. Enteroviral meningoencephalitis as a complication of rituximab therapy for rheumatoid arthritis. Cureus. 2021;13(9):e18189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epstein S, Thakkar R, Fong KT, et al. Compassionate-use pocapavir and immunoglobulin therapy for treatment of rituximab-associated enterovirus meningoencephalitis. J Neurovirol. 2022;28(2):329-334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heger JM, Eichenauer DA, Kasper P, Boll B, Shimabukuro-Vornhagen A, Kochanek M. Fatal disseminated enterovirus infection in a patient with follicular lymphoma undergoing obinutuzumab maintenance therapy. Eur J Haematol. 2019;103(3):268-271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapadia RK, Gill CM, Baca C, et al. Enterovirus A71 causing meningoencephalitis and acute flaccid myelitis in a patient receiving rituximab. J Neuroimmunol. 2021;358:577639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luciani L, Ninove L, Zandotti C, et al. Fatal underhanded chronic enterovirus infection associated with anti-CD20 monotherapy for central nervous system demyelinating disease. Mult Scler. 2021;27(2):320-323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sellier-Leclerc AL, Belli E, Guerin V, Dorfmuller P, Deschenes G. Fulminant viral myocarditis after rituximab therapy in pediatric nephrotic syndrome. Pediatr Nephrol. 2013;28(9):1875-1879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaheen N, Mussai F. Enteroviral encephalitis in a child with CNS relapse of Burkitt leukemia treated with rituximab. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2019;41(1):e27-e29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tekin B, Boire N, Shah K, Hanson J, Bridges AG. Viral panniculitis in a patient with disseminated opportunistic enterovirus infection. J Cutan Pathol. 2021;48(3):434-438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vermeersch G, Laenen L, Lens G, et al. Antiviral treatment with fluoxetine for rituximab-associated chronic echovirus 13 meningoencephalitis and myofasciitis. Eur J Neurol. 2022;29(10):3117-3123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higer M, Cana D, Podlech J, et al. Life-threatening disseminated enterovirus infection during combined rituximab and ibrutinib maintenance treatment for mantle cell lymphoma: a case report. J Med Case Reports. 2020;14(1):135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grisariu S, Vaxman I, Gatt M, et al. Enteroviral infection in patients treated with rituximab for non-Hodgkin lymphoma: a case series and review of the literature. Hematol Oncol. 2017;35(4):591-598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Sayed ZA, Abramova I, Aldave JC, et al. X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA): phenotype, diagnosis, and therapeutic challenges around the world. World Allergy Organ J. 2019;12(3):100018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misbah S, Spickett G, Ryba P, et al. Chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis in agammaglobulinemia: case report and literature review. J Clin Immunol. 1992;12(4):266-270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiroma N, Omi T, Hasegawa H, Nagashima K, Ohta T. A case of X-linked agammaglobulinemia with progressive encephalitis. Pediatr Neurol. 2004;31(5):371-373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von der Wense A, Herrmann B, Deppermann R, Harms F, Wehinger H. Intrathecal interferon therapy in chronic echovirus meningoencephalitis in Bruton type agammaglobulinemia. Klin Padiatr. 1998;210(2):51-55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwyer J, Erlendsson K. Intraventricular gamma-globulin for the management of enterovirus encephalitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 1988;7(5 Suppl):S30-S33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibaut H, Leyssen P, Puerstinger G, Muigg A, Neyts J, De Palma A. Towards the design of combination therapy for the treatment of enterovirus infections. Antiviral Res. 2011;90(3):213-217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang G, Zhou F, Gu B, et al. In vitro and in vivo evaluation of ribavirin and pleconaril antiviral activity against enterovirus 71 infection. Arch Virol. 2012;157(4):669-679.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotbart H, Webster A. Treatment of potentially life-threatening enterovirus infections with pleconaril. Clin Infect Dis. 2001;32(2):228-235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webster A. Pleconaril-an advance in the treatment of enteroviral infection in immuno-compromised patients. J Clin Virol. 2005;32(1):1-6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildenbeest J, van den Broek P, Benschop K, et al. Pleconaril revisited: clinical course of chronic enteroviral meningoencephalitis after treatment correlates with in vitro susceptibility. Antivir Ther. 2012;17(3):459-466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibaut H, De Palma A, Neyts J. Combating enterovirus replication: state-of-the-art on antiviral research. Biochem Pharmacol. 2012;83(2):185-192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collett MS, Neyts J, Modlin JF. A case for developing antiviral drugs against polio. Antiviral Res. 2008;79(3):179-187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Moore D, Anderson B, Pallansch MA, Pevear DC, Collett MS. In vitro antiviral activity of V-073 against polioviruses. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2009;53(10):4501-4503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Model M, Collett S, Hinscks J, Oberste S. Anti-poliovirus activity of Pocapavir in a human mOPV1 challenge. Paper presented at: 15. Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy 53rd Annual Meeting 2013; Denver, Colorado.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulferts R, van der Linden L, Thibaut H, et al. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor fluoxetine inhibits replication of human enteroviruses B and D by targeting viral protein 2C. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2013;57(4):1952-1956.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuo J, Quinn K, Kye S, Cooper P, Damoiseaux R, Krogstad P. Fluoxetine is a potent inhibitor of coxsackievirus replication. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2012;56(9):4838-4844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishimura A, Uppuluri R, Raj R, et al. An international survey of allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation for X-linked Agammaglobulinemia. J Clin Immunol. 2023;in press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun D, Heimall JR, Greenhawt MJ, Bunin NJ, Shaker MS, Romberg N. Cost utility of lifelong immunoglobulin replacement therapy vs hematopoietic stem cell transplant to treat agammaglobulinemia. JAMA Pediatr. 2022;176(2):176-184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cong H, Jiang Y, Tien P. Identification of the myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein as a cellular receptor for rubella virus. J Virol. 2011;85(21):11038-11047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winter AK, Moss WJ. Rubella. Lancet. 2022;399(10332):1336-1346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tingle AJ, Allen M, Petty RE, Kettyls GD, Chantler JK. Rubella-associated arthritis. I. Comparative study of joint manifestations associated with natural rubella infection and RA 27/3 rubella immunisation. Ann Rheum Dis. 1986;45(2):110-114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plotkin SA. Rubella eradication: not yet accomplished, but entirely feasible. J Infect Dis. 2021;224(12 Suppl 2):S360-S366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabinowe SL, George KL, Loughlin R, Soeldner JS, Eisenbarth GS. Congenital rubella. Monoclonal antibody-defined T cell abnormalities in young adults. Am J Med. 1986;81(5):779-782.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry CL, Thompson EN. Clinico-pathological study of thymic dysplasia. Arch Dis Child. 1968;43(231):579-584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verder H, Dickmeiss E, Haahr S, et al. Late-onset rubella syndrome: coexistence of immune complex disease and defective cytotoxic effector cell function. Clin Exp Immunol. 1986;63(2):367-375.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frey TK. Neurological aspects of rubella virus infection. Intervirology. 1997;40(2-3):167-175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Townsend JJ, Baringer JR, Wolinsky JS, et al. Progressive rubella panencephalitis. Late onset after congenital rubella. N Engl J Med. 1975;292(19):990-993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Hey E, Baarsma GS, De Vries J, Kijlstra A. Clinical analysis of Fuchs' heterochromic cyclitis. Doc Ophthalmol. 1991;78(3-4):225-235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quentin CD, Reiber H. Fuchs heterochromic cyclitis: rubella virus antibodies and genome in aqueous humor. Am J Ophthalmol. 2004;138(1):46-54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruokonen PC, Metzner S, Ucer A, Torun N, Hofmann J, Pleyer U. Intraocular antibody synthesis against rubella virus and other microorganisms in Fuchs' heterochromic cyclitis. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2010;248(4):565-571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knoll AB, Postole AS, Auffarth GU, Mackensen F. Frequency of dendritiform inflammatory cells in the cornea in herpetic anterior uveitis without clinical keratitis and Fuchs uveitis. J Ophthalmic Inflamm Infect. 2014;4:31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodemer C, Sauvage V, Mahlaoui N, et al. Live rubella virus vaccine long-term persistence as an antigenic trigger of cutaneous granulomas in patients with primary immunodeficiency. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2014;20(10):O656-O663.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D, Wanat KA, Perelygina L, et al. Cutaneous granulomas associated with rubella virus: a clinical review. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2023;in press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchbinder D, Hauck F, Albert MH, et al. Rubella virus-associated cutaneous granulomatous disease: a unique complication in immune-deficient patients, not limited to DNA repair disorders. J Clin Immunol. 2019;39(1):81-89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Plotkin S, Russo P, et al. Rubella persistence in epidermal keratinocytes and granuloma M2 macrophages in patients with primary immunodeficiencies. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2016;138(5):1436-1439 e1411.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Faisthalab R, Abernathy E, et al. Rubella virus infected macrophages and neutrophils define patterns of granulomatous inflammation in inborn and acquired errors of immunity. Front Immunol. 2021;12:796065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Chen MH, Suppiah S, et al. Infectious vaccine-derived rubella viruses emerge, persist, and evolve in cutaneous granulomas of children with primary immunodeficiencies. PLoS Pathog. 2019;15(10):e1008080.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wanat KA, Perelygina L, Chen MH, et al. Association of persistent rubella virus with idiopathic skin granulomas in clinically immunocompetent adults. JAMA Dermatol. 2022;158:626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shields BE, Perelygina L, Samimi S, et al. Granulomatous dermatitis associated with rubella virus infection in an adult with immunodeficiency. JAMA Dermatol. 2021;157(7):842-847.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanella MC, Cordey S, Laubscher F, et al. Unmasking viral sequences by metagenomic next-generation sequencing in adult human blood samples during steroid-refractory/dependent graft-versus-host disease. Microbiome. 2021;9(1):28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Buchbinder D, Dorsey MJ, et al. Outcomes for Nitazoxanide treatment in a case series of patients with primary immunodeficiencies and rubella virus-associated granuloma. J Clin Immunol. 2019;39(1):112-117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Hautala T, Seppanen M, Adebayo A, Sullivan KE, Icenogle J. Inhibition of rubella virus replication by the broad-spectrum drug nitazoxanide in cell culture and in a patient with a primary immune deficiency. Antiviral Res. 2017;147:58-66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faisthalab R, Suppiah S, Dorsey M, Sullivan KE, Icenogle J, Perelygina L. Drug sensitivity of vaccine-derived rubella viruses and quasispecies evolution in granulomatous lesions of two ataxia-telangiectasia patients treated with Nitazoxanide. Pathogens. 2022;11(3):33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takeuchi K, Miyajima N, Nagata N, Takeda M, Tashiro M. Wild-type measles virus induces large syncytium formation in primary human small airway epithelial cells by a SLAM (CD150)-independent mechanism. Virus Res. 2003;94(1):11-16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto K, Ono N, Tatsuo H, et al. SLAM (CD150)-independent measles virus entry as revealed by recombinant virus expressing green fluorescent protein. J Virol. 2002;76(13):6743-6749.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohno S, Ono N, Seki F, et al. Measles virus infection of SLAM (CD150) knockin mice reproduces tropism and immunosuppression in human infection. J Virol. 2007;81(4):1650-1659.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin DE. Measles immunity and immunosuppression. Curr Opin Virol. 2021;46:9-14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perry RT, Halsey NA. The clinical significance of measles: a review. J Infect Dis. 2004;189(Suppl 1):S4-S16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patterson MC. Neurological complications of measles (Rubeola). Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep. 2020;20(2):2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diwan MN, Samad S, Mushtaq R, et al. Measles induced encephalitis: recent interventions to overcome the obstacles encountered in the management amidst the COVID-19 pandemic. Diseases. 2022;10(4):104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin DE, Ward BJ, Esolen LM. Pathogenesis of measles virus infection: an hypothesis for altered immune responses. J Infect Dis. 1994;170(Suppl 1):S24-S31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher DL, Defres S, Solomon T. Measles-induced encephalitis. QJM. 2015;108(3):177-182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson RT, Griffin DE, Hirsch RL, et al. Measles encephalomyelitis-clinical and immunologic studies. N Engl J Med. 1984;310(3):137-141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez N, Bucciol G, Moens L, et al. Inherited IFNAR1 deficiency in otherwise healthy patients with adverse reaction to measles and yellow fever live vaccines. J Exp Med. 2019;216(9):2057-2070.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duncan CJ, Mohamad SM, Young DF, et al. Human IFNAR2 deficiency: lessons for antiviral immunity. Sci Transl Med. 2015;7(307):307ra154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mawhinney H, Allen IV, Beare JM, et al. Dysgammaglobulinaemia complicated by disseminated measles. Br Med J. 1971;2(5758):380-381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence DM, Vaughn MM, Belman AR, Cole JS, Rall GF. Immune response-mediated protection of adult but not neonatal mice from neuron-restricted measles virus infection and central nervous system disease. J Virol. 1999;73(3):1795-1801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardie DR, Albertyn C, Heckmann JM, Smuts HE. Molecular characterisation of virus in the brains of patients with measles inclusion body encephalitis (MIBE). Virol J. 2013;10:283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albertyn C, van der Plas H, Hardie D, et al. Silent casualties from the measles outbreak in South Africa. S Afr Med J. 2011;101(5):313-314, 316-317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe S, Ohno S, Shirogane Y, Suzuki SO, Koga R, Yanagi Y. Measles virus mutants possessing the fusion protein with enhanced fusion activity spread effectively in neuronal cells, but not in other cells, without causing strong cytopathology. J Virol. 2015;89(5):2710-2717.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo R, Rebmann G, Baczko K, ter Meulen V, Billeter MA. Altered ratios of measles virus transcripts in diseased human brains. Virology. 1987;160(2):523-526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo R, Rebmann G, Schmid A, Baczko K, ter Meulen V, Billeter MA. Altered transcription of a defective measles virus genome derived from a diseased human brain. EMBO J. 1987;6(3):681-688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samia P, Oyieke K, Tunje D, et al. Options in the treatment of subacute sclerosing panencephalitis: implications for low resource areas. Curr Treat Options Neurol. 2022;24(3):99-110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekki M, Eley B, Hardie D, Wilmshurst JM. Subacute sclerosing panencephalitis: clinical phenotype, epidemiology, and preventive interventions. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2019;61(10):1139-1144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafri SK, Kumar R, Ibrahim SH. Subacute sclerosing panencephalitis-current perspectives. Pediatric Health Med Ther. 2018;9:67-71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manesh A, Moorthy M, Bandopadhyay R, Rupali P. HIV-associated sub-acute sclerosing panencephalitis-an emerging threat? Int J STD AIDS. 2017;28(9):937-939.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kija E, Ndondo A, Spittal G, Hardie DR, Eley B, Wilmshurst JM. Subacute sclerosing panencephalitis in south African children following the measles outbreak between 2009 and 2011. S Afr Med J. 2015;105(9):713-718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyken PR. Subacute sclerosing panencephalitis. Current status. Neurol Clin. 1985;3(1):179-196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diana NE, Feldman C. Measles in adults: a comparison of hospitalised HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected patients. South Afr J HIV Med. 2019;20(1):a877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain R, Aulakh R. Measles-associated CNS complications: a review. Journal of Child Science. 2022;12:e172-e181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafa MM, Weitman SD, Winick NJ, Bellini WJ, Timmons CF, Siegel JD. Subacute measles encephalitis in the young immunocompromised host: report of two cases diagnosed by polymerase chain reaction and treated with ribavirin and review of the literature. Clin Infect Dis. 1993;16(5):654-660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lievano F, Galea SA, Thornton M, et al. Measles, mumps, and rubella virus vaccine (M-M-RII): a review of 32 years of clinical and postmarketing experience. Vaccine. 2012;30(48):6918-6926.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman AF, Jacobsohn DA, Shulman ST, et al. A new complication of stem cell transplantation: measles inclusion body encephalitis. Pediatrics. 2004;114(5):e657-e660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bitnun A, Shannon P, Durward A, et al. Measles inclusion-body encephalitis caused by the vaccine strain of measles virus. Clin Infect Dis. 1999;29(4):855-861.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monafo WJ, Haslam DB, Roberts RL, Zaki SR, Bellini WJ, Coffin CM. Disseminated measles infection after vaccination in a child with a congenital immunodeficiency. J Pediatr. 1994;124(2):273-276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns C, Cheung A, Stark Z, et al. A novel presentation of homozygous loss-of-function STAT-1 mutation in an infant with hyperinflammation-a case report and review of the literature. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract. 2016;4(4):777-779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hambleton S, Goodbourn S, Young DF, et al. STAT2 deficiency and susceptibility to viral illness in humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2013;110(8):3053-3058.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moens L, Van Eyck L, Jochmans D, et al. A novel kindred with inherited STAT2 deficiency and severe viral illness. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2017;139(6):1995-1997 e1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama Y, Hotta H, Nishimura A, Tatsuno Y, Homma M. Detection of measles virus nucleoprotein mRNA in autopsied brain tissues. J Gen Virol. 1995;76(Pt 12):3201-3204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigeta S, Mori S, Baba M, et al. Antiviral activities of ribavirin, 5-ethynyl-1-beta-D-ribofuranosylimidazole-4-carboxamide, and 6′-(R)-6'-C-methylneplanocin A against several ortho- and paramyxoviruses. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1992;36(2):435-439.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uylangco CV, Beroy GJ, Santiago LT, Mercoleza VD, Mendoza SL. A double-blind, placebo-controlled evaluation of ribavirin in the treatment of acute measles. Clin Ther. 1981;3(5):389-396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olding-Stenkvist E, Forsgren M, Henley D, et al. Measles encephalopathy during immunosuppression: failure of interferon treatment. Scand J Infect Dis. 1982;14(1):1-4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson R, Eden OB. Possible interferon response in a child with measles encephalitis during immunosuppression. Scand J Infect Dis. 1984;16(3):315-319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pritha A, Medha T, Garg R. A comprehensive investigation of the current subacute sclerosing panencephalitis (SSPE) treatment options to improve patient quality of life. Cureus. 2022;14:e228389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydin OF, Senbil N, Kuyucu N, Gurer YK. Combined treatment with subcutaneous interferon-alpha, oral isoprinosine, and lamivudine for subacute sclerosing panencephalitis. J Child Neurol. 2003;18(2):104-108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonsson A, Forslund O, Ekberg H, Sterner G, Hansson BG. The ubiquity and impressive genomic diversity of human skin papillomaviruses suggest a commensalic nature of these viruses. J Virol. 2000;74(24):11636-11641.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouvard V, Baan R, Straif K, et al. A review of human carcinogens-part B: biological agents. Lancet Oncol. 2009;10(4):321-322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halec G, Schmitt M, Dondog B, et al. Biological activity of probable/possible high-risk human papillomavirus types in cervical cancer. Int J Cancer. 2013;132(1):63-71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derkay CS, Wiatrak B. Recurrent respiratory papillomatosis: a review. Laryngoscope. 2008;118(7):1236-1247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ball SL, Winder DM, Vaughan K, et al. Analyses of human papillomavirus genotypes and viral loads in anogenital warts. J Med Virol. 2011;83(8):1345-1350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egawa N, Egawa K, Griffin H, Doorbar J. Human papillomaviruses; epithelial tropisms, and the development of neoplasia. Viruses. 2015;7(7):3863-3890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shamanin V, zur Hausen H, Lavergne D, et al. Human papillomavirus infections in nonmelanoma skin cancers from renal transplant recipients and nonimmunosuppressed patients. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1996;88(12):802-811.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evander M, Edlund K, Gustafsson A, et al. Human papillomavirus infection is transient in young women: a population-based cohort study. J Infect Dis. 1995;171(4):1026-1030.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brickman C, Palefsky JM. Human papillomavirus in the HIV-infected host: epidemiology and pathogenesis in the antiretroviral era. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2015;12(1):6-15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morsheimer MM, Rychik J, Forbes L, et al. Risk factors and clinical significance of lymphopenia in survivors of the Fontan procedure for single-ventricle congenital cardiac disease. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract. 2016;4(3):491-496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leiding JW, Holland SM. Warts and all: human papillomavirus in primary immunodeficiencies. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2012;130(5):1030-1048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beziat V. Human genetic dissection of papillomavirus-driven diseases: new insight into their pathogenesis. Hum Genet. 2020;139(6-7):919-939.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruffner MA, Sullivan KE, Henrickson SE. Recurrent and sustained viral infections in primary immunodeficiencies. Front Immunol. 2017;8:665.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewavisenti RV, Arena J, Ahlenstiel CL, Sasson SC. Human papillomavirus in the setting of immunodeficiency: pathogenesis and the emergence of next-generation therapies to reduce the high associated cancer risk. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1112513.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutzner MA, Blanchet-Bardon C, Orth G. Clinical observations, virologic studies, and treatment trials in patients with epidermodysplasia verruciformis, a disease induced by specific human papillomaviruses. J Invest Dermatol. 1984;83(1 Suppl):18s-25s.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Androphy EJ, Dvoretzky I, Lowy DR. X-linked inheritance of epidermodysplasia verruciformis. Genetic and virologic studies of a kindred. Arch Dermatol. 1985;121(7):864-868.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uitto J, Saeidian AH, Youssefian L, et al. Recalcitrant warts, epidermodysplasia verruciformis, and the tree-man syndrome: phenotypic spectrum of cutaneous human papillomavirus infections at the intersection of genetic variability of viral and human genomes. J Invest Dermatol. 2022;142(5):1265-1269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira WR, Festa Neto C, Rady PL, Tyring SK. Clinical aspects of epidermodysplasia verruciformis. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2003;17(4):394-398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuovo GJ, Ishag M. The histologic spectrum of epidermodysplasia verruciformis. Am J Surg Pathol. 2000;24(10):1400-1406.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gul U, Kilic A, Gonul M, Cakmak SK, Bayis SS. Clinical aspects of epidermodysplasia verruciformis and review of the literature. Int J Dermatol. 2007;46(10):1069-1072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saeidian AH, Youssefian L, Naji M, et al. Whole transcriptome-based skin virome profiling in typical epidermodysplasia verruciformis reveals alpha-, beta-, and gamma-HPV infections. JCI Insight. 2023;8(5):e162558.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin KMF, Amin R, Majumder SN, et al. An ANKRD26 nonsense somatic mutation in a female with epidermodysplasia verruciformis (tree man syndrome). Clin Case Rep. 2018;6(8):1426-1430.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak K, Linzner D, Thrasher AJ, Lambert PF, Di WL, Burns SO. Absence of gamma-chain in keratinocytes alters chemokine secretion, resulting in reduced immune cell recruitment. J Invest Dermatol. 2017;137(10):2120-2130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mace EM. Human natural killer cells: form, function, and development. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2023;151(2):371-385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong SJ, Crequer A, Matos I, et al. The human CIB1-EVER1-EVER2 complex governs keratinocyte-intrinsic immunity to beta-papillomaviruses. J Exp Med. 2018;215(9):2289-2310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Z, Wu Y, Zhou Z, et al. ALA-PDT successfully treated multiple cSCC in situ and AK in a patient with epidermodysplasia verruciformis. Photodiagnosis Photodyn Ther. 2021;35:102395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gubinelli E, Posteraro P, Cocuroccia B, Girolomoni G. Epidermodysplasia verruciformis with multiple mucosal carcinomas treated with pegylated interferon alfa and acitretin. J Dermatolog Treat. 2003;14(3):184-188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anadolu R, Oskay T, Erdem C, Boyvat A, Terzi E, Gurgey E. Treatment of epidermodysplasia verruciformis with a combination of acitretin and interferon alfa-2a. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2001;45(2):296-299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDermott DH, Pastrana DV, Calvo KR, et al. Plerixafor for the treatment of WHIM syndrome. N Engl J Med. 2019;380(2):163-170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henrickson SE, Treat JR. Topical Cidofovir for recalcitrant verrucae in individuals with severe combined immunodeficiency after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Pediatr Dermatol. 2017;34(1):e24-e25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moffatt S, Yaegashi N, Tada K, Tanaka N, Sugamura K. Human parvovirus B19 nonstructural (NS1) protein induces apoptosis in erythroid lineage cells. J Virol. 1998;72(4):3018-3028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broliden K, Tolfvenstam T, Norbeck O. Clinical aspects of parvovirus B19 infection. J Intern Med. 2006;260(4):285-304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayakawa H, Tara M, Niina K, Osame M. A clinical study of adult human parvovirus B19 infection. Intern Med. 2002;41(4):295-299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons R, Sharp C, McClure CP, et al. Parvovirus 4 infection and clinical outcome in high-risk populations. J Infect Dis. 2012;205(12):1816-1820.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benjamin LA, Lewthwaite P, Vasanthapuram R, et al. Human parvovirus 4 as potential cause of encephalitis in children, India. Emerg Infect Dis. 2011;17(8):1484-1487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heegaard ED, Petersen BL, Heilmann CJ, Hornsleth A. Prevalence of parvovirus B19 and parvovirus V9 DNA and antibodies in paired bone marrow and serum samples from healthy individuals. J Clin Microbiol. 2002;40(3):933-936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seyama K, Kobayashi R, Hasle H, et al. Parvovirus B19-induced anemia as the presenting manifestation of X-linked hyper-IgM syndrome. J Infect Dis. 1998;178(2):318-324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grammatikos A, Donati M, Johnston SL, Gompels MM. Peripheral B cell deficiency and predisposition to viral infections: the paradigm of immune deficiencies. Front Immunol. 2021;12:731643.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanelli M, Ruggeri L, Sanguedolce F, et al. Parvovirus B19 infection in a patient with common variable immunodeficiency. Mediterr J Hematol Infect Dis. 2021;13(1):e2021026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurtzman GJ, Ozawa K, Cohen B, Hanson G, Oseas R, Young NS. Chronic bone marrow failure due to persistent B19 parvovirus infection. N Engl J Med. 1987;317(5):287-294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naides SJ, Scharosch LL, Foto F, Howard EJ. Rheumatologic manifestations of human parvovirus B19 infection in adults. Initial two-year clinical experience. Arthritis Rheum. 1990;33(9):1297-1309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassinotti P, Siegl G, Michel BA, Bruhlmann P. Presence and significance of human parvovirus B19 DNA in synovial membranes and bone marrow from patients with arthritis of unknown origin. J Med Virol. 1998;56(3):199-204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams ST, Schmidt KM, Cost KM, Marshall GS. Common variable immunodeficiency presenting with persistent parvovirus B19 infection. Pediatrics. 2012;130(6):e1711-e1715.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe T, Kawashima H. Acute encephalitis and encephalopathy associated with human parvovirus B19 infection in children. World J Clin Pediatr. 2015;4(4):126-134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolan RC, Chidlow G, French MA. Parvovirus B19 encephalitis presenting as immune restoration disease after highly active antiretroviral therapy for human immunodeficiency virus infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2003;36(9):1191-1194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen LS, Hoiby N. Parvovirus B19-a cause of hepatitis in patients with liver transplantation, anemia in HIV positive individuals and encephalopathies in children. Ugeskr Laeger. 1998;160(11):1653.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strenger V, Merth G, Lackner H, et al. Malignancy and chemotherapy induced haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in children and adolescents-a single Centre experience of 20 years. Ann Hematol. 2018;97(6):989-998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moritake H, Kamimura S, Nunoi H, et al. Clinical characteristics and genetic analysis of childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: a Japanese retrospective study by the Kyushu-Yamaguchi Children's cancer study group. Int J Hematol. 2014;100(1):70-78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drago E, Garbarino F, Signa S, et al. Case report: susceptibility to viral infections and secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis responsive to intravenous immunoglobulin as primary manifestations of adenosine deaminase 2 deficiency. Front Immunol. 2022;13:937108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bird JA, McClain KL, Rosenblatt HM, Abramson SL, Hanson IC. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with x-linked lymphoproliferative disease. Allergy Asthma Proc. 2009;30(4):458-462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong Q, Zeng J, Lin T, Song T. The detection, treatment of parvovirus B19 infection induced anemia in solid organ transplants: a case series and literature review of 194 patients. Transfus Clin Biol. 2022;29(2):168-174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holterhus M, Hennies M, Hillmann H, et al. Parvovirus B19 infection in pediatric allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation-single-center experience and review. Transpl Infect Dis. 2023;25(2):e14028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thibile S, Barrett C, Potgieter S, Joubert G, Malherbe J. Adult pure red cell aplasia at Universitas academic hospital, Bloemfontein, South Africa: a 9-year review. S Afr Med J. 2022;112(9):753-759.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keramari S, Poutoglidis A, Chatzis S, Keramaris M, Savopoulos C, Kaiafa G. Parvovirus B19-associated myocarditis: A literature review of pediatric cases. Cureus. 2022;14(1):e21726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Espinosa D, Esforzado N, Hermida E, et al. A case of recurrent anemia due to chronic parvovirus B19 infection in a kidney transplant recipient. Can everolimus make a difference? CEN Case Rep. 2021;10(3):388-392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang SY. Herpes simplex virus encephalitis of childhood: inborn errors of central nervous system cell-intrinsic immunity. Hum Genet. 2020;139(6-7):911-918.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogunjimi B, Zhang SY, Sorensen KB, et al. Inborn errors in RNA polymerase III underlie severe varicella zoster virus infections. J Clin Invest. 2017;127(9):3543-3556.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyts I, Bucciol G, Jansen K, Wollants E, Breuer J. Aichivirus: an emerging pathogen in patients with primary and secondary B-cell deficiency. J Clin Immunol. 2023;43(3):532-535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayor PC, Eng KH, Singel KL, et al. Cancer in primary immunodeficiency diseases: cancer incidence in the United States immune deficiency network registry. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2018;141(3):1028-1035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLaughlin-Drubin ME, Munger K. Viruses associated with human cancer. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2008;1782(3):127-150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen ML, Wang SH, Wei JC, Yip HT, Hung YM, Chang R. The impact of human papillomavirus infection on skin cancer: a population-based cohort study. Oncologist. 2021;26(3):e473-e483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hauck F, Voss R, Urban C, Seidel MG. Intrinsic and extrinsic causes of malignancies in patients with primary immunodeficiency disorders. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2018;141(1):59-68 e54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harwood CA, Surentheran T, Sasieni P, et al. Increased risk of skin cancer associated with the presence of epidermodysplasia verruciformis human papillomavirus types in normal skin. Br J Dermatol. 2004;150(5):949-957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarczyk M, Cassonnet P, Pons C, Jacob Y, Favre M. The EVER proteins as a natural barrier against papillomaviruses: a new insight into the pathogenesis of human papillomavirus infections. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev. 2009;73(2):348-370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong SJ, Imahorn E, Itin P, et al. Epidermodysplasia verruciformis: inborn errors of immunity to human beta-papillomaviruses. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:1222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Partridge ME, Pariser RJ. Ocular and cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma in an African American man with epidermodysplasia verruciformis resulting in blindness and death. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2003;49(5 Suppl):S262-S264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarczyk M, Dalard C, Hayder M, et al. EVER proteins, key elements of the natural anti-human papillomavirus barrier, are regulated upon T-cell activation. PloS One. 2012;7(6):e39995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orth G. Genetics of epidermodysplasia verruciformis: insights into host defense against papillomaviruses. Semin Immunol. 2006;18(6):362-374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarczyk M, Pons C, Mendoza JA, Cassonnet P, Jacob Y, Favre M. Regulation of cellular zinc balance as a potential mechanism of EVER-mediated protection against pathogenesis by cutaneous oncogenic human papillomaviruses. J Exp Med. 2008;205(1):35-42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howley PM, Pfister HJ. Beta genus papillomaviruses and skin cancer. Virology. 2015;479-480:290-296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hufbauer M, Lazic D, Akgul B, Brandsma JL, Pfister H, Weissenborn SJ. Enhanced human papillomavirus type 8 oncogene expression levels are crucial for skin tumorigenesis in transgenic mice. Virology. 2010;403(2):128-136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heusinkveld LE, Majumdar S, Gao JL, McDermott DH, Murphy PM. WHIM syndrome: from pathogenesis towards personalized medicine and cure. J Clin Immunol. 2019;39(6):532-556.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastrana DV, Peretti A, Welch NL, et al. Metagenomic discovery of 83 new human papillomavirus types in patients with immunodeficiency. mSphere. 2018;3(6):e00645-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulino AV. WHIM syndrome: a genetic disorder of leukocyte trafficking. Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol. 2003;3(6):443-450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meuris F, Carthagena L, Jaracz-Ros A, et al. The CXCL12/CXCR4 signaling pathway: a new susceptibility factor in human papillomavirus pathogenesis. PLoS Pathog. 2016;12(12):e1006039.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotta L, Notarangelo LD, Moratto D, et al. Long-term outcome of WHIM syndrome in 18 patients: high risk of lung disease and HPV-related malignancies. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract. 2019;7(5):1568-1577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaussant Cohen S, Fenneteau O, Plouvier E, et al. Description and outcome of a cohort of 8 patients with WHIM syndrome from the French severe chronic Neutropenia registry. Orphanet J Rare Dis. 2012;7:71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su HC. Dedicator of cytokinesis 8 (DOCK8) deficiency. Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol. 2010;10(6):515-520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Davis JC, Lamborn IT, et al. Combined immunodeficiency associated with DOCK8 mutations. N Engl J Med. 2009;361(21):2046-2055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydin SE, Kilic SS, Aytekin C, et al. DOCK8 deficiency: clinical and immunological phenotype and treatment options-a review of 136 patients. J Clin Immunol. 2015;35(2):189-198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cekic S, Metin A, Aytekin C, et al. The evaluation of malignancies in Turkish primary immunodeficiency patients; a multicenter study. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. 2020;31(5):528-536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasihuseyinoglu AS, Yilmaz M, Altintas DU, et al. Squamous cell carcinoma with hyper-IgE syndrome: A case report. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2018;40(6):e380-e382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu EY, Freeman AF, Jing H, et al. Cutaneous manifestations of DOCK8 deficiency syndrome. Arch Dermatol. 2012;148(1):79-84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papa R, Penco F, Volpi S, Gattorno M. Actin remodeling defects leading to autoinflammation and immune dysregulation. Front Immunol. 2020;11:604206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu AP, Sampaio EP, Khan J, et al. Mutations in GATA2 are associated with the autosomal dominant and sporadic monocytopenia and mycobacterial infection (MonoMAC) syndrome. Blood. 2011;118(10):2653-2655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spinner MA, Sanchez LA, Hsu AP, et al. GATA2 deficiency: a protean disorder of hematopoiesis, lymphatics, and immunity. Blood. 2014;123(6):809-821.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickinson RE, Griffin H, Bigley V, et al. Exome sequencing identifies GATA-2 mutation as the cause of dendritic cell, monocyte, B and NK lymphoid deficiency. Blood. 2011;118(10):2656-2658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu AP, Johnson KD, Falcone EL, et al. GATA2 haploinsufficiency caused by mutations in a conserved intronic element leads to MonoMAC syndrome. Blood. 2013;121(19):3830-3837, S3831-3837.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wlodarski MW, Hirabayashi S, Pastor V, et al. Prevalence, clinical characteristics, and prognosis of GATA2-related myelodysplastic syndromes in children and adolescents. Blood. 2016;127(11):1387-1397; quiz 1518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parta M, Cole K, Avila D, et al. Hematopoietic cell transplantation and outcomes related to human papillomavirus disease in GATA2 deficiency. Transplant Cell Ther. 2021;27(5):435.e1-435.e11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdollahpour H, Appaswamy G, Kotlarz D, et al. The phenotype of human STK4 deficiency. Blood. 2012;119(15):3450-3457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saglam A, Cagdas D, Aydin B, et al. STK4 deficiency and EBV-associated lymphoproliferative disorders, emphasis on histomorphology, and review of literature. Virchows Arch. 2022;480(2):393-401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schipp C, Schlutermann D, Honscheid A, et al. EBV negative lymphoma and autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome like phenotype extend the clinical spectrum of primary immunodeficiency caused by STK4 deficiency. Front Immunol. 2018;9:2400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherkat R, Sabri MR, Dehghan B, et al. EBV lymphoproliferative-associated disease and primary cardiac T-cell lymphoma in a STK4 deficient patient: a case report. Medicine (Baltimore). 2017;96(48):e8852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morgan EL, Patterson MR, Ryder EL, et al. MicroRNA-18a targeting of the STK4/MST1 tumour suppressor is necessary for transformation in HPV positive cervical cancer. PLoS Pathog. 2020;16(6):e1008624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard A, Bojko J, Flynn B, Bowen S, Jungwirth U, Walko G. Targeting the hippo/YAP/TAZ signalling pathway: novel opportunities for therapeutic interventions into skin cancers. Exp Dermatol. 2022;31(10):1477-1499.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour S, Josephs KS, Ostergaard P, et al. Redefining WILD syndrome: a primary lymphatic dysplasia with congenital multisegmental lymphoedema, cutaneous lymphovascular malformation, CD4 lymphopaenia and warts. J Med Genet. 2023;60(1):84-90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Kettani A, Ailal F, El Bakkouri J, et al. HPV-related skin phenotypes in patients with inborn errors of immunity. Pathogens. 2022;11(8):857.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira WR, da Cruz Silva LL, Neto CF, Tyring S. Deleterious effect of radiation therapy on epidermodysplasia verruciformis patients. J Cutan Med Surg. 2015;19(4):416-421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajabi MT, Ghasemi H, Safizadeh M, et al. Conjunctival squamous cell carcinoma with intraocular invasion after radiotherapy in epidermodysplasia verruciformis. Can J Ophthalmol. 2014;49(2):e43-e46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spurgeon ME, Lambert PF. Merkel cell polyomavirus: a newly discovered human virus with oncogenic potential. Virology. 2013;435(1):118-130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolstov YL, Pastrana DV, Feng H, et al. Human Merkel cell polyomavirus infection II. MCV is a common human infection that can be detected by conformational capsid epitope immunoassays. Int J Cancer. 2009;125(6):1250-1256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heath M, Jaimes N, Lemos B, et al. Clinical characteristics of Merkel cell carcinoma at diagnosis in 195 patients: the AEIOU features. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2008;58(3):375-381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harms KL, Healy MA, Nghiem P, et al. Analysis of prognostic factors from 9387 Merkel cell carcinoma cases forms the basis for the new 8th edition AJCC staging system. Ann Surg Oncol. 2016;23(11):3564-3571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker JC. Merkel cell carcinoma. Ann Oncol. 2010;21 Suppl 7:vii81-vii85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kouzmina M, Koljonen V, Leikola J, Bohling T, Lantto E. Frequency and locations of systemic metastases in Merkel cell carcinoma by imaging. Acta Radiol Open. 2017;6(3):2058460117700449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agelli M, Clegg LX. Epidemiology of primary Merkel cell carcinoma in the United States. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2003;49(5):832-841.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garneski KM, Warcola AH, Feng Q, Kiviat NB, Leonard JH, Nghiem P. Merkel cell polyomavirus is more frequently present in north American than Australian Merkel cell carcinoma tumors. J Invest Dermatol. 2009;129(1):246-248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma JE, Brewer JD. Merkel cell carcinoma in immunosuppressed patients. Cancers (Basel). 2014;6(3):1328-1350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Starrett GJ, Marcelus C, Cantalupo PG, et al. Merkel cell polyomavirus exhibits dominant control of the tumor genome and transcriptome in virus-associated Merkel cell carcinoma. MBio. 2017;8(1):e02079-16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hesbacher S, Pfitzer L, Wiedorfer K, et al. RB1 is the crucial target of the Merkel cell polyomavirus large T antigen in Merkel cell carcinoma cells. Oncotarget. 2016;7(22):32956-32968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goessling W, McKee PH, Mayer RJ. Merkel cell carcinoma. J Clin Oncol. 2002;20(2):588-598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crall C, Morley KW, Rabinowits G, Schmidt B, Dioun Broyles A, Huang JT. Merkel cell carcinoma in a patient with GATA2 deficiency: a novel association with primary immunodeficiency. Br J Dermatol. 2016;174(1):169-171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recher M, Karjalainen-Lindsberg ML, Lindlof M, et al. Genetic variation in schlafen genes in a patient with a recapitulation of the murine Elektra phenotype. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2014;133(5):1462-1465, 1465 e1461-1465.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira WR, Sotto MN, Festa C, Rady P, Tyring SK. Merkel cell polyomavirus in Merkel cell carcinoma from a Brazilian epidermodysplasia verruciformis patient. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2010;62(5):889-890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mizuno Y, Kato G, Shu E, et al. Merkel cell polyomavirus-positive Merkel cell carcinoma in a patient with epidermodysplasia verruciformis. Acta Derm Venereol. 2015;95(1):98-99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mertz KD, Schmid M, Burger B, et al. Detection of Merkel cell polyomavirus in epidermodysplasia-verruciformis-associated skin neoplasms. Dermatology. 2011;222(1):87-92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott MP, Helm KF. Cytokeratin 20: a marker for diagnosing Merkel cell carcinoma. Am J Dermatopathol. 1999;21(1):16-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siqueira SOM, Campos-do-Carmo G, Dos Santos ALS, Martins C, de Melo AC. Merkel cell carcinoma: epidemiology, clinical features, diagnosis and treatment of a rare disease. An Bras Dermatol. 2023;98(3):277-286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis DJ, Sobanko JF, Etzkorn JR, et al. Merkel cell carcinoma. Dermatol Clin. 2023;41(1):101-115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SY, Doolittle-Amieva C, Moshiri Y, et al. How we treat Merkel cell carcinoma: within and beyond current guidelines. Future Oncol. 2021;17(11):1363-1377.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitley R, Baines J. Clinical management of herpes simplex virus infections: past, present, and future. F1000Res. 2018;7:1726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Looker KJ, Johnston C, Welton NJ, et al. The global and regional burden of genital ulcer disease due to herpes simplex virus: a natural history modelling study. BMJ Glob Health. 2020;5(3):e001875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradshaw MJ, Venkatesan A. Herpes simplex virus-1 encephalitis in adults: pathophysiology, diagnosis, and management. Neurotherapeutics. 2016;13(3):493-508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steiner I, Benninger F. Update on herpes virus infections of the nervous system. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep. 2013;13(12):414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Wang R, Xu C, Zhou H. Pathogenesis of herpes stromal keratitis: immune inflammatory response mediated by inflammatory regulators. Front Immunol. 2020;11:766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beasley KL, Cooley GE, Kao GF, Lowitt MH, Burnett JW, Aurelian L. Herpes simplex vegetans: atypical genital herpes infection in a patient with common variable immunodeficiency. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1997;37(5 Pt 2):860-863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado-Marquez AM, Zarco C, Ruiz R, Simarro A, Vanaclocha F. Severe disseminated primary herpes simplex infection as skin manifestation of GATA2 deficiency. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2016;30(7):1248-1250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parsons K, Cipriano SD, Rosen LB, et al. Severe facial herpes vegetans and viremia in NFKB2-deficient common variable immunodeficiency. Front Pediatr. 2019;7:61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spinner MA, Ker JP, Stoudenmire CJ, et al. GATA2 deficiency underlying severe blastomycosis and fatal herpes simplex virus-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2016;137(2):638-640.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jasim A, Proietto A, Scurry J. Herpes simplex virus infection of vulvar squamous cell carcinoma. Pathology. 2016;48(1):80-81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alibek K, Baiken Y, Kakpenova A, et al. Implication of human herpesviruses in oncogenesis through immune evasion and supression. Infect Agent Cancer. 2014;9(1):3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strehl JD, Mehlhorn G, Koch MC, et al. HIV-associated hypertrophic herpes simplex genitalis with concomitant early invasive squamous cell carcinoma mimicking advanced genital cancer: case report and literature review. Int J Gynecol Pathol. 2012;31(3):286-293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronkainen SD, Rothenberger M. Herpes vegetans: an unusual and acyclovir-resistant form of HSV. J Gen Intern Med. 2018;33(3):393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akbari M, Elmi R. Herpes simplex virus and human papillomavirus coinfections in hyperimmunoglobulin E syndrome presenting as a conjunctival mass lesion. Case Rep Med. 2017;2017:1650841.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blieden LS, Chevez-Barrios P, Yen MT. Herpes simplex vegetans presenting as an eyelid mass. Ophthalmic Plast Reconstr Surg. 2011;27(3):e58-e59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magg T, Schober T, Walz C, et al. Epstein-Barr virus(+) smooth muscle tumors as manifestation of primary immunodeficiency disorders. Front Immunol. 2018;9:368.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beziat V, Jouanguy E. Human inborn errors of immunity to oncogenic viruses. Curr Opin Immunol. 2021;72:277-285.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>