<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38045212</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemiology and clinical characteristics of severe acute respiratory infections among hospitalized children under 5 years of age in a tertiary care center in Bangkok, Thailand, 2019-2020.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e22300</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e22300</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e22300</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22300</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Acute respiratory infections (ARIs) are common in children and can range in severity from mild self-limiting illnesses to more severe conditions such as pneumonia and respiratory failure. Data on the epidemiology of viral and bacterial pathogens causing ARIs in children are scarce in this region. This study aimed to investigate the epidemiology and clinical manifestations of pathogens in children aged ≤5 years presenting with severe acute respiratory infection (SARI) in Bangkok, Thailand. The impact of rapid multiplex PCR-based testing on clinical management is also explored.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This cross-sectional study enrolled consecutive children aged ≤5 years presenting with SARI at a tertiary care centre in Bangkok, Thailand, between 2019 and 2020. Nasopharyngeal swabs were collected once at admission, and viral and bacterial pathogens were tested using the QIAstat-Dx respiratory panel.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 169 children were enrolled in this study. At least one pathogenic virus was detected in 91.7 % of participants. Based on the final diagnoses made upon discharge, 30.2 % had upper respiratory tract infection, whereas 66.3 % had lower respiratory tract infection. Pneumonia was the most common diagnosis (59.2 %). The most common pathogen identified was rhino/enterovirus (45.2 %), followed by respiratory syncytial virus (31.6 %) and parainfluenza virus (14.2 %). Co-infection was found in 15.4 % and was not associated with increased disease severity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study provides additional insights into the pathogen profiles, clinical diagnosis, and co-infection combinations of ARIs in hospitalized children. This information is useful for diagnosis and treatment of ARIs, as well as implementation of appropriate infection control measures and guidance for future vaccine policy development.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wanlapakorn</LastName><ForeName>Nasamon</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thongpan</LastName><ForeName>Ilada</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Abigail Wexner Research Institute at Nationwide Children's Hospital, Center for Vaccines and Immunity, Columbus, OH 43205, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarawanangkoor</LastName><ForeName>Nasiri</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vichaiwattana</LastName><ForeName>Preeyaporn</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Auphimai</LastName><ForeName>Chompoonut</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srimuan</LastName><ForeName>Donchida</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thatsanathorn</LastName><ForeName>Thaksaporn</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kongkiattikul</LastName><ForeName>Lalida</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of pulmonology and critical care, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kerr</LastName><ForeName>Stephen J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biostatistics Excellence Center, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poovorawan</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>FRS(T), the Royal Society of Thailand, Sanam Sueapa, Dusit, Bangkok, 10300, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacterial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical manifestations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Respiratory pathogens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Severe acute respiratory infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Yong Poovorawan reports financial support was provided by 10.13039/501100002873Chulalongkorn University. Yong Poovorawan reports equipment, drugs, or supplies was provided by QIAGEN GmbH.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38045212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10692904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(23)09508-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Perin J., Mulick A., Yeung D., et al. Global, regional, and national causes of under-5 mortality in 2000-19: an updated systematic analysis with implications for the Sustainable Development Goals. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2022;6:106–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8786667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34800370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y., Li W., Yang B., et al. Epidemiological and virological characteristics of respiratory tract infections in children during COVID-19 outbreak. BMC Pediatr. 2021;21:195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8060686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33888063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chieochansin T., Samransamruajkit R., Chutinimitkul S., et al. Human bocavirus (HBoV) in Thailand: clinical manifestations in a hospitalized pediatric patient and molecular virus characterization. J. Infect. 2008;56:137–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18164764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soonnarong R., Thongpan I., Payungporn S., et al. Molecular epidemiology and characterization of human coronavirus in Thailand, 2012-2013. SpringerPlus. 2016;5:1420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4999384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27625974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pratheepamornkull T., Ratanakorn W., Samransamruajkit R., et al. Causative agents of severe community aquired viral pneumonia among children in Eastern Thailand. Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health. 2015;46:650–656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26867384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinthanate S., Wanlapakorn N., Puenpa J., et al. Pertussis in Thai adult and pediatric patients presenting with prolonged acute cough. Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health. 2018;49:447–455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izu A., Nunes M.C., Solomon F., et al. All-cause and pathogen-specific lower respiratory tract infection hospital admissions in children younger than 5 years during the COVID-19 pandemic (2020-22) compared with the pre-pandemic period (2015-19) in South Africa: an observational study. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2023;S1473–3099(23) 00200-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10151031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37141913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling Y., Zhang T., Guo W., et al. Identify clinical factors related to Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia with hypoxia in children. BMC Infect. Dis. 2020;20:534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7374650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32698769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lochindarat S., Suwanjutha S., Prapphal N., et al. Mycoplasma pneumoniae and Chlamydophila pneumoniae in children with community-acquired pneumonia in Thailand. Int. J. Tubercul. Lung Dis. 2007;11:814–819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17609060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouafi M., Dubos F., Engelman I., et al. Rapid syndromic testing for respiratory viral infections in children attending the emergency department during COVID-19 pandemic in Lille, France, 2021-2022. J. Clin. Virol. 2022;153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9233550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35777223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parčina M., Schneider U.V., Visseaux B., et al. Multicenter evaluation of the QIAstat Respiratory Panel-A new rapid highly multiplexed PCR based assay for diagnosis of acute respiratory tract infections. PLoS One. 2020;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7067435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32163484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brendish N.J., Malachira A.K., Clark T.W. Molecular point-of-care testing for respiratory viruses versus routine clinical care in adults with acute respiratory illness presenting to secondary care: a pragmatic randomised controlled trial protocol (ResPOC) BMC Infect. Dis. 2017;17:128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5294894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28166743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brendish N.J., Malachira A.K., Armstrong L., et al. Routine molecular point-of-care testing for respiratory viruses in adults presenting to hospital with acute respiratory illness (ResPOC): a pragmatic, open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Respir. Med. 2017;5:401–411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28392237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almannaei L., Alsaadoon E., AlbinAli S., et al. A retrospective study examining the clinical significance of testing respiratory panels in children who presented to a tertiary hospital in 2019. Access Microbiol. 2022;4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9175981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35693466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazur N.I., Bont L., Cohen A.L., et al. Severity of respiratory syncytial virus lower respiratory tract infection with viral coinfection in HIV-Uninfected children. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2017;64:443–450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5712444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27927871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aberle J.H., Aberle S.W., Pracher E., et al. Single versus dual respiratory virus infections in hospitalized infants: impact on clinical course of disease and interferon-gamma response. Pediatr. Infect. Dis. J. 2005;24:605–610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15999001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabatabai J., Ihling C.M., Manuel B., et al. Viral etiology and clinical characteristics of acute respiratory tract infections in hospitalized children in southern Germany (2014-2018) Open Forum Infect. Dis. 2023;10:ofad110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10034757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36968956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization WHO surveillance case definitions for ILI and SARI Influenza surveillance and monitoring. https://www.who.int/teams/global-influenza-programme/surveillance-and-monitoring/case-definitions-for-ili-and-sari Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leber A.L., Lisby J.G., Hansen G., et al. Multicenter evaluation of the QIAstat-dx respiratory panel for detection of viruses and bacteria in nasopharyngeal swab specimens. J. Clin. Microbiol. 2020;58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7180242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32132186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auksornkitti V., Kamprasert N., Thongkomplew S., et al. Molecular characterization of human respiratory syncytial virus, 2010-2011: identification of genotype ON1 and a new subgroup B genotype in Thailand. Arch. Virol. 2014;159:499–507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24068580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linsuwanon P., Payungporn S., Samransamruajkit R., et al. High prevalence of human rhinovirus C infection in Thai children with acute lower respiratory tract disease. J. Infect. 2009;59:115–121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19556008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S., Stecher G., Li M., et al. Mega X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. Mol. Biol. Evol. 2018;35:1547–1549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5967553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29722887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiew W.T., Chen Y.C., Hsiao H.L., et al. Impact of multiplex polymerase chain reaction syndromic panel on antibiotic use among hospitalized children with respiratory tract illness during COVID-19 pandemic. J. Microbiol. Immunol. Infect. 2023;S1684–1182(23) 00009-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9841733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36681556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamrani Hanchi A., Guennouni M., Rachidi M., et al. Epidemiology of respiratory pathogens in children with severe acute respiratory infection and impact of the multiplex PCR film array respiratory panel: a 2-year study. Internet J. Microbiol. 2021;2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8741400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35003265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolan V.G., Arnold S.R., Bramley A.M., et al. Etiology and impact of coinfections in children hospitalized with community-acquired pneumonia. J. Infect. Dis. 2018;218:179–188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29228381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thongpan I., Mauleekoonphairoj J., Vichiwattana P., et al. Respiratory syncytial virus genotypes NA1, ON1, and BA9 are prevalent in Thailand, 2012-2015. PeerJ. 2017;5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5661434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29085762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thongpan I., Vichaiwattana P., Vongpunsawad S., et al. Upsurge of human rhinovirus infection followed by a delayed seasonal respiratory syncytial virus infection in Thai children during the coronavirus pandemic. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15:711–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8542963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34350701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cason C., Zamagni G., Cozzi G., et al. Spread of respiratory pathogens during the COVID-19 pandemic among children in the northeast of Italy. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8988150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35401434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muloiwa R., Wolter N., Mupere E., et al. Pertussis in africa: findings and recommendations of the global pertussis initiative (GPI) Vaccine. 2018;36:2385–2393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29602703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akkoc G., Dogan C., Bayraktar S., et al. Evaluation of viral respiratory pathogens in children aged under five hospitalized with lower respiratory tract infections. North Clin Istanb. 2022;9:162–172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9039642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35582505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang H., Chen S., Zhang X., et al. Detection and clinical characteristics analysis of respiratory viruses in hospitalized children with acute respiratory tract infections by a GeXP-based multiplex-PCR assay. J. Clin. Lab. Anal. 2020;34</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7147121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31774213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Kholy A.A., Mostafa N.A., Ali A.A., et al. The use of multiplex PCR for the diagnosis of viral severe acute respiratory infection in children: a high rate of co-detection during the winter season. Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2016;35:1607–1613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7088036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27287764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goka E.A., Vallely P.J., Mutton K.J., et al. Single and multiple respiratory virus infections and severity of respiratory disease: a systematic review. Pediatr Respir Rev. 2014;15:363–370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7106320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24361079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ueno F., Tamaki R., Saito M., et al. Age-specific incidence rates and risk factors for respiratory syncytial virus-associated lower respiratory tract illness in cohort children under 5 years old in the Philippines. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2019;13:339–353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6586181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30891896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esper F.P., Spahlinger T., Zhou L. Rate and influence of respiratory virus co-infection on pandemic (H1N1) influenza disease. J. Infect. 2011;63:260–266.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3153592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21546090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhedin S., Lindstrand A., Rotzén-Östlund M., et al. Clinical utility of PCR for common viruses in acute respiratory illness. Pediatrics. 2014;133:e538–e545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24567027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacIntyre C.R., Chughtai A.A., Barnes M., et al. The role of pneumonia and secondary bacterial infection in fatal and serious outcomes of pandemic influenza a(H1N1)pdm09. BMC Infect. Dis. 2018;18(1):637.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6286525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30526505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendaus M.A., Jomha F.A., Alhammadi A.H. Virus-induced secondary bacterial infection: a concise review. Ther Clin Risk Manag. 2015;11:1265–1271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4554399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26345407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramony A., Zachariah P., Krones A., et al. Impact of multiplex polymerase chain reaction testing for respiratory pathogens on healthcare resource utilization for pediatric inpatients. J. Pediatr. 2016;173:196–201.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5452417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27039227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manatrey-Lancaster J.J., Bushman A.M., Caligiuri M.E., Rosa R. Impact of BioFire FilmArray respiratory panel results on antibiotic days of therapy in different clinical settings. Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol. 2021;1(1):e4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9495546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36168499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinh J., Hinkle C.F., Law A.C., et al. Effect of respiratory viral panel adoption on antibiotic use in ventilated patients. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2023 Sep 25 doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.202304-326OC. Epub ahead of print. PMID: 37748086.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202304-326OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37748086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suntronwong N., Thongpan I., Chuchaona W., et al. Impact of COVID-19 public health interventions on influenza incidence in Thailand. Pathog. Glob. Health. 2020;114:225–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7480427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>