<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38075402</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2772-431X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>1</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infectious medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Med (Beijing)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Likelihood of hospitalization for a chronic respiratory condition following pediatric infection with enterovirus and rhinovirus strains.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>245</StartPage><EndPage>252</EndPage><MedlinePgn>245-252</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.imj.2022.10.002</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Rhino-enteroviruses, particularly enterovirus strain D68 (EV-D68), have been associated with severe respiratory distress in children. The goal of this study was to compare the long-term outcomes of children with EV-D68 infection to that of children with other enterovirus / rhinovirus.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Nasopharyngeal swabs from 174 children presenting with respiratory distress were tested by PCR for respiratory viruses. The primary outcome was diagnosis of a chronic respiratory condition within the follow-up period. Admission to intensive care, and length of stay were recorded. Odds ratios were determined using multinomial logistic regression.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During 5 years of follow-up, the crude odds of diagnosis with a chronic respiratory condition were significantly more likely in EV-D68 cases (OR: 1.95, 95% CI: 1.02, 3.82), but failed to remain significant after adjusting for a past history of asthma. Upon admission for a primary concern of asthma, length of stay both in hospital and intensive care were significantly longer in EV-D68 cases (OR: 2.10 [95% CI: 1.56, 2.82, <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001]) and (OR: 5.18 [95% CI: 1.90, 6.28, <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001]), respectively. After adjustment for a history of asthma, EV-D68 cases had significantly longer length of stay in hospital, admitted for 1.94 days for each day that controls were admitted (95% CI: 1.40, 2.68). In admissions to intensive care, EV-D68 cases spent 2.74 days for each day of admission in controls (95% CI: 1.62, 4.97, <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Ours is first study to assess prognostic respiratory outcomes of patients infected with EV-D68 in childhood. Our study finds that EV-D68 cases were significantly more likely be hospitalized for longer than other enterovirus/rhinovirus controls in subsequent admissions for respiratory distress. Need for intensive care was significantly longer in EV-D68 infections. Our next steps will be validation in a larger sample size.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2022 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Switzer</LastName><ForeName>Charlotte</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Health Methods, Evaluation and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of St Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verschoor</LastName><ForeName>Chris P</ForeName><Initials>CP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Health Methods, Evaluation and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Sciences North Research Institute, Sudbury, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gavina</LastName><ForeName>Kenneth</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Pathology and Molecular Medicine, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of St Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mertz</LastName><ForeName>Dominik</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Health Methods, Evaluation and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Medicine, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luinstra</LastName><ForeName>Kathy</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of St Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pernica</LastName><ForeName>Jeffrey M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Health Methods, Evaluation and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Pediatrics, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smieja</LastName><ForeName>Marek</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Health Methods, Evaluation and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Pathology and Molecular Medicine, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Institute of St Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton, Hamilton, ON CANADA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>China</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Med (Beijing)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918663679306676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2772-431X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Asthma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus-D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pediatric infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Respiratory infection</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38075402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10699694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.imj.2022.10.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2772-431X(22)00051-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tran DN, Trinh QD, Pham NTK, et al. Human rhinovirus infections in hospitalized children: clinical, epidemiological and virological features. Epidemiol Infect. 2016;144(2):346–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26112743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen W-J, Arnold JC, Fairchok MP, et al. Epidemiologic, clinical, and virologic characteristics of human rhinovirus infection among otherwise healthy children and adults: rhinovirus among adults and children. J Clin Virol. 2015;64:74–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4347877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25728083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linder JE, Kraft DC, Mohamed Y, et al. Human rhinovirus C: age, season, and lower respiratory illness over the past 3 decades. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2013;131(1):66–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3748586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23146382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao Q, Zheng S, Zhou L, et al. Impact of human rhinovirus types and viral load on the severity of illness in hospitalized children with lower respiratory tract infections. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2015;34(11):1187–1192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26267309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asner SA, Petrich A, Hamid JS, et al. Clinical severity of rhinovirus/enterovirus compared to other respiratory viruses in children. Influenza Other Respi Viruses. 2014;8(4):436–442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4181803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24801963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukkarinen M, Koistinen A, Turunen R, et al. Rhinovirus-induced first wheezing episode predicts atopic but not nonatopic asthma at school age. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2017;140(4):988–995.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28347734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwane MK, Prill MM, Lu X, et al. Human rhinovirus species associated with hospitalizations for acute respiratory illness in young US children. J Infect Dis. 2011;204(11):1702–1710.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22013207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Megremis S, Niespodziana K, Cabauatan C, et al. Rhinovirus species-specific antibodies differentially reflect clinical outcomes in health and asthma. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2018;198(12):1490–1499. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201803-0575OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.201803-0575OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7212800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30134114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruning AHL, Thomas X V, van der Linden L, et al. Clinical, virological and epidemiological characteristics of rhinovirus infections in early childhood: a comparison between non-hospitalised and hospitalised children. J Clin Virol. 2015;73:120–126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7185867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26599608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom SC. Enterovirus and parechovirus infections in children: differences in clinical presentation, mechanisms for meningitis without pleocytosis and mechanisms involved in the neurological outcome. Minerva Pediatr. 2019;71(2):150–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30511561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thong WY, Han A, Wang SJF, et al. Enterovirus infections in Singaporean children: an assessment of neurological manifestations and clinical outcomes. Singapore Med J. 2017;58(4):189–195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5392603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27245861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spaeder MC, Custer JW, Miles AH, et al. A multicenter outcomes analysis of children with severe rhino/enteroviral respiratory infection. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2015;16(2):119–123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25647121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordey S, L’Huillier AG, Turin L, et al. Enterovirus and Parechovirus viraemia in young children presenting to the emergency room: unrecognised and frequent. J Clin Virol. 2015;68:69–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26071339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Graaf H, Pelosi E, Cooper A, et al. Severe enterovirus infections in hospitalized children in the south of england: clinical phenotypes and causative genotypes. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2016;35(7):723–727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4985250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26882165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom SCM, Rossen JWA, de Moor RA, et al. Prospective assessment of clinical symptoms associated with enterovirus and parechovirus genotypes in a multicenter study in Dutch children. J Clin Virol. 2016;77:15–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26875098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster JE, Miller JO, Selvarangan R, et al. Severe enterovirus 68 respiratory illness in children requiring intensive care management. J Clin Virol. 2015;70:77–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26305825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caylan E, Weinblatt E, Welter J, et al. Comparison of the severity of respiratory disease in children testing positive for enterovirus d68 and human rhinovirus. J Pediatr. 2018;197:147–153.e1..</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29655864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Hassan F, et al. Clinical course of enterovirus D68 in hospitalized children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2017;36(3):290–295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28187115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mertz D, Alawfi A, Pernica JM, et al. Clinical severity of pediatric respiratory illness with enterovirus D68 compared with rhinovirus or other enterovirus genotypes. CMAJ. 2015;187(17):1279–1284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4646747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26464137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong KC, Wong KT. Understanding enterovirus 71 neuropathogenesis and its impact on other neurotropic enteroviruses. Brain Pathol. 2015;25(5):614–624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8029433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26276025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenfeld AB, Warren AL, Racaniello VR. Neurotropism of enterovirus D68 isolates is independent of sialic acid and is not a recently acquired phenotype. MBio. 2019;10(5) doi: 10.1128/mBio.02370-19. 02370-19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.02370-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6805996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31641090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moyer K, Wang H, Salamon D, et al. Enterovirus D68 in hospitalized children: sequence variation, viral loads and clinical outcomes. PLoS One. 2016;11(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5119825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27875593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prazma CM, Gern JE, Weinstein SF, et al. The association between seasonal asthma exacerbations and viral respiratory infections in a pediatric population receiving inhaled corticosteroid therapy with or without long-acting beta-adrenoceptor agonist: a randomized study. Respir Med. 2015;109(10):1280–1286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7125883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26289742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Souef P. Viral infections in wheezing disorders. Eur Respir Rev. 2018;27(147)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9488549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29622672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loisel DA, Du G, Ahluwalia TS, et al. Genetic associations with viral respiratory illnesses and asthma control in children. Clin Exp Allergy. 2016;46(1):112–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4715666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26399222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy JL, Pham S, Borish L. Rhinovirus and Asthma Exacerbations. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am. 2019;39(3):335–344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6625523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31284924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert KA, Prendergast LA, Dharmage SC, et al. The role of human rhinovirus (HRV) species on asthma exacerbation severity in children and adolescents. J Asthma. 2018;55(6):596–602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29020463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bizzintino J, Lee W-M, Laing IA, et al. Association between human rhinovirus C and severity of acute asthma in children. Eur Respir J. 2011;37(5):1037–1042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3024467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20693244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turunen R, Jartti T, Bochkov YA, et al. Rhinovirus species and clinical characteristics in the first wheezing episode in children. J Med Virol. 2016;88(12):2059–2068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5140033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27232888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korppi M, Kotaniemi-Syrjanen A, Waris M, et al. Rhinovirus-associated wheezing in infancy: comparison with respiratory syncytial virus bronchiolitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2004;23(11):995–999.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15545853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jartti T, Gern JE. Role of viral infections in the development and exacerbation of asthma in children. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2017;140(4):895–906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28987219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moss RB. Enterovirus 68 infection–association with asthma. J allergy Clin Immunol Pract. 2016;4(2):226–228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26843407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granados A, Luinstra K, Chong S, et al. Use of an improved quantitative polymerase chain reaction assay to determine differences in human rhinovirus viral loads in different populations. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2012;74(4):384–387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23017257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Garcia ML, Calvo Rey C, Del Rosal Rabes T. Pediatric asthma and viral infection. Arch Bronconeumol. 2016;52(5):269–273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7105201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26766408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez FD. Childhood asthma inception and progression: role of microbial exposures, susceptibility to viruses and early allergic sensitization. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am. 2019;39(2):141–150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6613822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30954166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang C. Asthma in children and adolescents: a comprehensive approach to diagnosis and management. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. 2012;43(1-2):98–137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7091307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22187333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon BR. Asthma History and Presentation. Otolaryngol. Clin. North Am. 2008;41:375–385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18328375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal M. Differential diagnosis of asthma. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2002 Jun;3(2):148-53. PMID: 12297064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12297064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mb PJH. Issues in Pediatric Asthma. 2001;56:49-56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11475173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lockey RF. Asthma phenotypes : an approach to the diagnosis and treatment of asthma.:682-685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25439357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takeyama A, Hashimoto K, Sato M, et al. Rhinovirus load and disease severity in children with lower respiratory tract infections. J Med Virol. 2012;84(7):1135–1142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22585733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajput C, Han M, Bentley JK, et al. Enterovirus D68 infection induces IL-17-dependent neutrophilic airway inflammation and hyperresponsiveness. JCI Insight. 2018;3(16)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6141171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30135310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>