<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38058442</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Circulating trends of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Hubei Province, China: Impact from the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e22872</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e22872</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e22872</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22872</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study was performed to investigate the effect of non-pharmaceutical interventions on hand, foot, and mouth disease in Hubei Province China during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Data and samples were collected from the hand, foot, and mouth disease surveillance laboratory network in Hubei Province between 2018 and 2022. The samples were identified as Enterovirus A71, Coxsackievirus A6or Coxsackievirus A16 via real-time polymerase chain reaction. Representative Coxsackievirus A6 and Coxsackievirus A16 samples were sequenced and subjected to phylogenetic analyses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A noticeable 3-fold reduction in the number of hand, foot, and mouth disease cases was observed from 2019 to 2020. The age and sex distributions of patients with hand, foot, and mouth disease were approximately the same from 2018 to 2022. The proportion of Coxsackievirus A6 accounted for 86 % in 2020 and 75 % in 2021 for hand, foot, and mouth disease compared with 48 % in 2018, 53 % in 2019, and 29 % in 2022. The proportions of Coxsackievirus A16 in 2020 and 2021 were 2 % and 17 %, respectively, showing a sharp decline in 2018 (37.8 %) and 2019 (35 %). In 2022, Coxsackievirus A16 was the dominant serotype (46 %). Only slight differences were found in the VP1 sequences across the different years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Our study confirmed that a series of non-pharmaceutical interventions during the coronavirus disease 2019 period reduced the transmission of enteroviruses and that long-term restrictions could significantly change the prevalence of enterovirus serotypes causing hand, foot, and mouth disease.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Kangping</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, 35 North Zhuodaoquan, Hongshan District, Wuhan, 430079, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ding</LastName><ForeName>Zhihong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Xiangyang Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Xiangyang, Hubei, 441000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, 35 North Zhuodaoquan, Hongshan District, Wuhan, 430079, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhan</LastName><ForeName>Jianbo</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, 35 North Zhuodaoquan, Hongshan District, Wuhan, 430079, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cai</LastName><ForeName>Kun</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hubei Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, 35 North Zhuodaoquan, Hongshan District, Wuhan, 430079, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus serotypes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HFMD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-pharmaceutical interventions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogenetic analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38058442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10696181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(23)10080-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Guo X., Zhao N., et al. Effects of the enhanced public health intervention during the COVID-19 epidemic on respiratory and gastrointestinal infectious diseases in China. J. Med. Virol. 2022;94(5):2201–2211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9015532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35067944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keaveney S., Rupnik A., Fitzpatrick A., et al. Impact of COVID-19 nonpharmaceutical interventions on the extent of norovirus contamination in oyster production areas in Ireland during winter 2020 to 2021. J. Food Protect. 2022;85(10):1397–1403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35723550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen S.J., Azziz-Baumgartner E., Budd A.P., et al. Decreased influenza activity during the COVID-19 pandemic-United States, Australia, Chile, and South Africa, 2020. Am. J. Transplant. : official journal of the American Society of Transplantation and the American Society of Transplant Surgeons. 2020;20(12):3681–3685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7753605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C., Siegrist F., Petty T.J., et al. Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity with associated human diseases. Infect. Genet. Evol. : journal of molecular epidemiology and evolutionary genetics in infectious diseases. 2013;14:282–293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23201849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M., Guo W., Xu D., et al. Molecular characterization of echovirus 9 strains isolated from hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Kunming, Yunnan Province, China. Sci. Rep. 2022;12(1):2293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8831506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35145190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W., Liao Q., Viboud C., et al. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008-12: an epidemiological study. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2014;14(4):308–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4035015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24485991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamau E., Nguyen D., Celma C., et al. Seroprevalence and virologic surveillance of enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A6, United Kingdom, 2006-2017. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2021;27(9):2261–2268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8386771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34423767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D., Li Z., Zhang W., et al. Hand-washing: the main strategy for avoiding hand, foot and mouth disease. Int. J. Environ. Res. Publ. Health. 2016;13(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4924067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27322307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou X.N., Zhang X.Z., Wang B., et al. Etiologic and epidemiologic analysis of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Guangzhou city: a review of 4,753 cases. Braz. J. Infect. Dis. : an official publication of the Brazilian Society of Infectious Diseases. 2012;16(5):457–465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22964289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Z., Zheng C., Qi H., et al. Impact of the coronavirus disease 2019 interventions on the incidence of hand, foot, and mouth disease in mainland China. The Lancet regional health Western Pacific. 2022;20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8720138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35005671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu K., Ma X., Liu H., et al. Effects of different levels of non-pharmaceutical interventions on hand, foot and mouth disease in Guangzhou, China. BMC Publ. Health. 2022;22(1):2398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9767397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36539790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma E., Wong S., Wong C., et al. Effects of public health interventions in reducing transmission of hand, foot, and mouth disease. Pediatr. Infect. Dis. J. 2011;30(5):432–435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21343840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Y.H., Chongsuvivatwong V., Tan Y., et al. Important roles of public playgrounds in the transmission of hand, foot, and mouth disease. Epidemiol. Infect. 2015;143(7):1432–1441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25170900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan N., Luo L., Rui J., et al. Control measures during the COVID-19 outbreak reduced the transmission of hand, foot, and mouth disease. J. Saf. Sci. Resilience. 2021;2(2):63–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolbert M.E., Spalding C.D., Sinaii N., et al. Sharp decline in rates of community respiratory viral detection among patients at the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol. 2023;44(1):62–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9021590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35177161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santangelo O.E., Gianfredi V., Provenzano S., et al. Digital epidemiology and infodemiology of hand-foot-mouth disease (HFMD) in Italy. Disease trend assessment via Google and Wikipedia. Acta Biomed. : Atenei Parmensis. 2023;94(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10440772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37539609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M., Chen X., Wang W., et al. Genetic characteristics of Coxsackievirus A6 from children with hand, foot and mouth disease in Beijing, China, 2017-2019 [J]. Infection, genetics and evolution. journal of molecular epidemiology and evolutionary genetics in infectious diseases. 2022;106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36257478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y.F., Jia L.P., Yu F.Y., et al. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A16 circulating in children in Beijing, China from 2010 to 2019. World journal of pediatrics : WJP. 2021;17(5):508–516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8523403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34453285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan X., Zhang C., Wang X., et al. Molecular epidemiology and clinical features of hand, foot and mouth disease requiring hospitalization after the use of enterovirus A71 inactivated vaccine in chengdu, China, 2017-2022: a descriptive study. Emerg. Microb. Infect. 2022;11(1):2510–2519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9621254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36103331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Zhang S. Epidemiological characteristics and trends of hand-foot-mouth disease in Shanghai, China from 2011 to 2021. Front. Public Health. 2023;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10267978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37325298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J., Cao Z., Liu H., et al. Epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease and the genetic characteristics of Coxsackievirus A16 in Taiyuan, Shanxi, China from 2010 to 2021. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 2022;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9692002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36439232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y., Zhang Y., Ji T., et al. Persistent circulation of Coxsackievirus A6 of genotype D3 in mainland of China between 2008 and 2015. Sci. Rep. 2017;7(1):5491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5511160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28710474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomba Ngangas S., Bisseux M., Jugie G., et al. Coxsackievirus A6 recombinant subclades D3/A and D3/H were predominant in hand-foot-and-mouth disease outbreaks in the paediatric population. France, 2010-2018 [J]. Viruses. 2022;14(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9144281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35632819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He F., Rui J., Deng Z., et al. Surveillance, epidemiology and impact of EV-A71 vaccination on hand, foot, and mouth disease in nanchang, China, 2010-2019. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8770912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35069515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R., Lin C., Dong S., et al. Phylogenetics and phylogeographic characteristics of coxsackievirus A16 in hand foot and mouth disease and herpangina cases collected in Beijing, China from 2019 to 2021. J. Med. Virol. 2023;95(8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37515317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>