<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38164047</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Novel intertypic recombination of Echovirus 11 in the Enterovirus species B.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29323</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29323</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29323</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses (EVs), single-stranded, positive-sense RNA viruses, can be classified into four species (A-D), which have previously been linked to a diverse range of disease manifestations and infections affecting the central nervous system. In the Enterovirus species B (EV-B), Echovirus type 11 (E11) has been observed to occasionally circulate in Taiwan, which was responsible for an epidemic of enterovirus infections in 2018. Here, 48 clinical specimens isolated in 2003, 2004, 2009, and 2018 were collected for the high-throughput sequencing. Notably, we identified 2018 Taiwanese strains having potential recombinations in the 3D gene, as well as one 2003 strain having a double recombination with E6 and Coxsackievirus B5 in the P2 and P3 regions, respectively. Additionally, one amino acid signature mutated from the Histidine (H) in throat swab specimens to the Tyrosine (Y) in cerebral spinal fluid specimens was detected at position 1496 (or 57) of the genomic coordinate (or 3A gene) to further demonstrate intra-host evolution in different organs. In conclusion, this study identifies potential intertypic recombination events and an intra-host signature mutation in E11 strains, isolated during a 2018 neurological disease outbreak in Taiwan, contributing to our understanding of its evolution and pathogenesis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Nong</ForeName><Initials>YN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>International Master Degree Program for Molecular Medicine in Emerging Viral Infections, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute of Infectious Diseases and Vaccinology, National Health Research Institutes, Zhunan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Shu-Li</ForeName><Initials>SL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology and Laboratory Science, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yi-Ching</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yi-Chun</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Yhu-Chering</ForeName><Initials>YC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsao</LastName><ForeName>Kuo-Chien</ForeName><Initials>KC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology and Laboratory Science, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Ministry of Education</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NSTC 111-2221-E-182-053-MY3</GrantID><Agency>National Science and Technology Council</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CMRPG3K2091-2</GrantID><Agency>Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (CGMH)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CLRPG3L0022</GrantID><Agency>Virus Core Laboratory, Linkou CGMH</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011995" MajorTopicYN="N">Recombination, Genetic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Echovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">high-throughput sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neurological disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">recombination</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38164047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(3):793-797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Meng M, Xu H, et al. Analysis of enterovirus genotypes in the cerebrospinal fluid of children associated with aseptic meningitis in Liaocheng, China, from 2018 to 2019. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21(1):405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Yan D, Chen L, et al. Multiple genotypes of Echovirus 11 circulated in mainland China between 1994 and 2017. Sci Rep. 2019;9(1):10583.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Maher K, Kennett ML, et al. Molecular epidemiology and genetic diversity of echovirus type 30 (E30): genotypes correlate with temporal dynamics of E30 isolation. J Clin Microbiol. 1999;37(12):3928-3933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moline HL, Karachunski PI, Strain A, Griffith J, Kenyon C, Schleiss MR. Acute transverse myelitis caused by Echovirus 11 in a pediatric patient: case report and review of the current literature. Child Neurol Open. 2018;5:2329048X1775152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho SY, Chiu CH, Huang YC, et al. Investigation and successful control of an echovirus 11 outbreak in neonatal intensive care units. Pediatr Neonatol. 2019;61(2):180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caspar DLD, Klug A. Physical principles in the construction of regular viruses. Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol. 1962;27:1-24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukashev AN, Lashkevich VA, Koroleva GA, Ilonen J, Hinkkanen AE. Recombination in uveitis-causing enterovirus strains. J Gen Virol. 2004;85(Pt 2):463-470.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukashev AN, Lashkevich VA, Ivanova OE, Koroleva GA, Hinkkanen AE, Ilonen J. Recombination in circulating human enterovirus B: independent evolution of structural and non-structural genome regions. J Gen Virol. 2005;86(Pt 12):3281-3290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chevaliez S, Szendröi A, Caro V, et al. Molecular comparison of echovirus 11 strains circulating in Europe during an epidemic of multisystem hemorrhagic disease of infants indicates that evolution generally occurs by recombination. Virology. 2004;325(1):56-70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su T, Zhou Y, Zhu Y, et al. Molecular characterization of a new human echovirus 11 isolate associated with severe hand, foot and mouth disease in Yunnan, China, in 2010. Arch Virol. 2015;160(9):2343-2347.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu J, Kang M, Zeng H, et al. Tracking echovirus eleven outbreaks in Guangdong, China: a metatranscriptomic, phylogenetic, and epidemiological study. Virus Evol. 2020;6(1):veaa029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butsch R, Tapparel C, Keller P, et al. Family outbreak of an infection with a recombinant Coxsackie A virus in eastern Switzerland. Infection. 2013;41(1):231-235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolger AM, Lohse M, Usadel B. Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data. Bioinformatics. 2014;30(15):2114-2120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D, Langmead B, Salzberg SL. HISAT: a fast spliced aligner with low memory requirements. Nature Methods. 2015;12(4):357-360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bankevich A, Nurk S, Antipov D, et al. SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing. J Comput Biol. 2012;19(5):455-477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong YN, Chen GW, Yang SL, Lee CJ, Shih SR, Tsao KC. A next-generation sequencing data analysis pipeline for detecting unknown pathogens from mixed clinical samples and revealing their genetic diversity. PLoS One. 2016;11(3):e0151495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langmead B, Salzberg SL. Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2. Nature Methods. 2012;9(4):357-359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Standley DM. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30(4):772-780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stamatakis A. RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics. 2014;30(9):1312-1313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Nix WA, Kilpatrick DR, Flemister MR, Pallansch MA. Molecular epidemiology and type-specific detection of echovirus 11 isolates from the Americas, Europe, Africa, Australia, Southern Asia and the Middle East. Virus Res. 2003;91(2):241-248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rice P, Longden I, Bleasby A. EMBOSS: the European Molecular Biology Open Software Suite. TIG. 2000;16(6):276-277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lole KS, Bollinger RC, Paranjape RS, et al. Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination. J Virol. 1999;73(1):152-160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho M, Chen ER, Hsu KH, et al. An epidemic of enterovirus 71 infection in Taiwan. Taiwan Enterovirus Epidemic Working Group. N Engl J Med. 1999;341(13):929-935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Henquell C, Archimbaud C, et al. Prospective identification of enteroviruses involved in meningitis in 2006 through direct genotyping in cerebrospinal fluid. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46(1):87-96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin JY, Weng KF, Chang CK, et al. Enterovirus A71 induces neurological diseases and dynamic variants in oral infection of human SCARB2-transgenic weaned mice. J Virol. 2021;95:JVI0089721.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahllund L, Nissinen L, Pulli T, Hyttinen VP, Stanway G, Hyppiä T. The genome of echovirus 11. Virus Res. 1995;35(2):215-222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Wang Q, Sintchenko V, et al. Use of the 5′ untranslated region and VP1 region to examine the molecular diversity in enterovirus B species. J Med Microbiol. 2014;63(Pt 10):1339-1355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Lamonte A, Oberste MS, Pallansch M. Neonatal enterovirus infections reported to the national enterovirus surveillance system in the United States, 1983-2003. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2006;25(10):889-893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang JW, Lam TT, Zaraket H, et al. Global epidemiology of non-influenza RNA respiratory viruses: data gaps and a growing need for surveillance. Lancet Infect Dis. 2017;17(10):e320-e326.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>