<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38190645</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>43</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluating the Impact of the BioFire FilmArray in Childhood Meningitis: An Observational Cohort Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>345</StartPage><EndPage>349</EndPage><MedlinePgn>345-349</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004236</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Multiplex polymerase chain reaction assays have the potential to reduce antibiotic use and shorten length of inpatient stay in children with suspected central nervous system infection by obtaining an early microbiological diagnosis. The clinical impact of the implementation of the BioFire FilmArray Meningitis/Encephalitis Panel on the management of childhood meningitis was evaluated at the John Radcliffe Hospital in Oxford and Children's Health Ireland at Temple Street in Dublin.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Children who had lumbar punctures performed as part of a septic screen were identified retrospectively through clinical discharge coding and microbiology databases from April 2017 to December 2018. Anonymized clinical and laboratory data were collected. Comparison of antibiotic use, length of stay and outcome at discharge was made with a historical cohort in Oxford (2012-2016), presenting before implementation of the FilmArray.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study included 460 children who had a lumbar puncture as part of an evaluation for suspected central nervous system infection. Twelve bacterial cases were identified on the FilmArray that were not detected by conventional bacterial culture. Bacterial culture identified one additional case of bacterial meningitis, caused by Escherichia coli , which had not been identified on the FilmArray. Duration of antibiotics was shorter in children when FilmArray was used than before its implementation; enterovirus meningitis (median: 4 vs. 5 days), human parechovirus meningitis (median: 4 vs. 4.5 days) and culture/FilmArray-negative cerebrospinal fluid (median: 4 vs. 6 days).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The use of a FilmArray can identify additional bacterial cases of meningitis in children that had been negative by traditional culture methods. Children with viral meningitis and culture-negative meningitis received shorter courses of antibiotics and had shorter hospital stays when FilmArray was used. Large studies to evaluate the clinical impact and cost effectiveness of incorporating the FilmArray into routine testing are warranted.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kadambari</LastName><ForeName>Seilesh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3658-7635</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatric Infectious Diseases, Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children NHS Foundation Trust.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infection, Immunity and Inflammation department, University College London, Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Shuo</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Xinxue</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andersson</LastName><ForeName>Monique</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Oxford University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NDCLS, Radcliffe Department of Medicine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Waterfield</LastName><ForeName>Rebecca</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fodder</LastName><ForeName>Harriet</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jacquemot</LastName><ForeName>Aimee</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galal</LastName><ForeName>Ushma</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oxford Primary Care Clinical Trials Unit, Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rafferty</LastName><ForeName>Aisling</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Drew</LastName><ForeName>Richard J</ForeName><Initials>RJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Irish Meningitis and Sepsis Reference Laboratory, Children's Health Ireland at Temple Street.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Innovation Unit, Rotunda Hospital.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Microbiology, Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Republic of Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rodrigues</LastName><ForeName>Charlene</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatric Infectious Diseases, St Mary's Hospital, Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infection Biology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sadarangani</LastName><ForeName>Manish</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vaccine Evaluation Center, BC Children's Hospital Research Institute.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Riordan</LastName><ForeName>Andrew</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatric Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Alder Hey Children's NHS Foundation Trust, Liverpool, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin</LastName><ForeName>Natalie G</ForeName><Initials>NG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, University of Otago Christchurch, Christchurch, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Defres</LastName><ForeName>Sylviane</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Infection, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Infection, Veterinary and Ecological Sciences, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tropical and Infectious Diseases Unit, Liverpool University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Sciences and Education, Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Solomon</LastName><ForeName>Tom</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Pandemic Institute.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Infection, Microbiology, and Immunology (CIMI).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Infection, Veterinary &amp; Ecological Sciences.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Institute for Health and Care Research Health Protection Research Unit in Emerging and Zoonotic Infections, University of Liverpool.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Walton Centre NHS Foundation Trust, Liverpool, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pollard</LastName><ForeName>Andrew J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paulus</LastName><ForeName>Stephane</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Oxford Vaccine Group, Department of Paediatrics, University of Oxford, NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>none</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004660" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008581" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016920" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Bacterial</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001419" MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060885" MajorTopicYN="N">Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002494" MajorTopicYN="Y">Central Nervous System Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38190645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202404000-00009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Okike IO, Ribeiro S, Ramsay ME, et al. Trends in bacterial, mycobacterial, and fungal meningitis in England and Wales 2004-11: an observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:301–307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Sadarangani M, Pollard AJ, et al. Hospital admission rates for meningitis and septicaemia caused by Haemophilus influenzae , Neisseria meningitidis , and Streptococcus pneumoniae in children in England over five decades: a population-based observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:397–405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Okike I, Ribeiro S, et al. Seven-fold increase in viral meningo-encephalitis reports in England and Wales during 2004-2013. J Infect. 2014;69:326–332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Iro MA, Sadarangani M, et al. Hospital admissions for viral meningitis in children in England over five decades: a population-based observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16:1279–1287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Bukasa A, Okike IO, et al. Enterovirus infections in England and Wales, 2000-2011: the impact of increased molecular diagnostics. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2014;20:1289–1296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Braccio S, Ribeiro S, et al. Enterovirus and parechovirus meningitis in infants younger than 90 days old in the UK and Republic of Ireland: a British Paediatric Surveillance Unit study. Arch Dis Child. 2018;104:552–557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tansarli GS, Chapin KC. Diagnostic test accuracy of the BioFire® FilmArray® meningitis/encephalitis panel: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2019;26:281–290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin N, Defres S, Willis L, et al. Paediatric meningitis in the conjugate vaccine era and development of a novel clinical decision model to predict bacterial aetiology in 3,002 children with suspected meningitis. SSRN. 2023. doi:10.2139/ssrn.4506566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2139/ssrn.4506566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham JW, Hofer SM, Piccinin AM. Analysis with missing data in drug prevention research. NIDA Res Monogr. 1994;142:13–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer JL. Analysis of Incomplete Multivariate Data. 1997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Buuren S, Groothuis-Oudshoorn K. mice: Multivariate imputation by chained equations in R. J Stat Softw. 2011;45:173–196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leber AL, Everhart K, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. Multicenter evaluation of BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel for detection of bacteria, viruses, and yeast in cerebrospinal fluid specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2016;54:2251–2261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naccache SN, Lustestica M, Fahit M, et al. One year in the life of a rapid syndromic panel for meningitis/encephalitis: a pediatric tertiary care facility’s experience. J Clin Microbiol. 2018;56:e01940–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora HS, Asmar BI, Salimnia H, et al. Enhanced identification of group B Streptococcus and Escherichia coli in young infants with meningitis using the BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2017;36:685–687.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glode MP, Sutton A, Robbins JB, et al. Neonatal meningitis due to Escherichia coli K1. J Infect Dis. 1977;136:S93–S97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steiner I, Kennedy PGE, Pachner AR. The neurotropic herpes viruses: herpes simplex and varicella-zoster. Lancet Neurol. 2007;6:1015–1028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanson KE, Slechta ES, Killpack JA, et al. Preclinical assessment of a fully automated multiplex PCR panel for detection of central nervous system pathogens. J Clin Microbiol. 2016;54:785–787.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SH, Chen SY, Chien JY, et al. Usefulness of the FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis (M/E) panel for the diagnosis of infectious meningitis and encephalitis in Taiwan. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2019;52:760–768.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liesman RM, Strasburg AP, Heitman AK, et al. Evaluation of a commercial multiplex molecular panel for diagnosis of infectious meningitis and encephalitis. J Clin Microbiol. 2018;56:e01927–e01917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green DA, Pereira M, Miko B, et al. Clinical significance of human herpesvirus 6 positivity on the FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel. Clin Infect Dis. 2018;67:1125–1128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien MP, Francis JR, Marr IM, et al. Impact of cerebrospinal fluid multiplex assay on diagnosis and outcomes of central nervous system infections in children: a before and after cohort study. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2018;37:868–871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Breazeale G, Robinson CC, et al. Potential clinical impact of the film array meningitis encephalitis panel in children with suspected central nervous system infections. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2016;86:118–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Harvala H, Simmonds P, et al. Strategies to improve detection and management of human parechovirus infection in young infants. Lancet Infect Dis. 2019;19:e51–e58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadarangani M, Willis L, Kadambari S, et al. Childhood meningitis in the conjugate vaccine era: a prospective cohort study. Arch Dis Child. 2015;100:292–294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okike IO, Ladhani SN, Johnson AP, et al.; neoMen Study Group. Clinical characteristics and risk factors for poor outcome in infants less than 90 days of age with bacterial meningitis in the United Kingdom and Ireland. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2018;37:837–843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Palmer C, Gregoire L, et al. Clinical and financial impact of a diagnostic stewardship program for children with suspected central nervous system infection. J Pediatr. 2022;244:161–168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acuña M, Benadof D, Yohannessen K, et al. FilmArray® Meningoencephalitis panel in the diagnosis of central nervous system infections: stewardship and cost analysis in a paediatric hospital in Chile. BMC Pediatr. 2022;5:182.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>