<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38103032</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Emerging concerns of atypical hand foot and mouth disease caused by recombinant Coxsackievirus A6 variants in Henan, China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29316</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29316</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29316</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>An increasing number of studies have reported that atypical hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) is becoming a new concern for children's health. At present, there is no official definition for atypical HFMD, but some studies have defined that it occurs at anatomic sites not listed in the definition of HFMD issued by the World Health Organization. Several pathogens have been reported to cause atypical HFMD, such as Coxsackievirus (CV)A6. As one of the most prevalent enteroviruses in the world, CVA6 seems to affect a wider range of children and causes more severe and prolonged illness than other enteroviruses. The early lesions of atypical HFMD are very similar to the clinical presentations of other diseases, such as eczema, which poses a challenge for clinicians aiming to identify and diagnose HFMD in a timely manner. Here, we report on six atypical HFMD patients caused by recombinant CVA6 variants, and the atypical manifestations include eczema coxsackium, large herpes, rice-like red papules and herpes, purpuric rash, and onychomadesis, as well as and large red herpes on scalp, perianal, testicles, shoulders and neck, and other atypical eruption sites, hoping to draw the attention of other pediatricians. This study will provide scientific guidance for timely diagnosis of HFMD to prevent serious complications.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Shouhang</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-7717-113X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Wangquan</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Fang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaolong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NHC Key Laboratory of Birth Defects Prevention, Henan Key Laboratory of Population Defects Prevention, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Yuefei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yufeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>82372229</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82002147</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ZD202301</GrantID><Agency>Open Research Fund of National Health Commission Key Laboratory of Birth Defects Prevention &amp;amp; Henan Key Laboratory of Population Defects Prevention</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ERC202302</GrantID><Agency>Open Project of Henan Province Engineering Research Center of Diagnosis and Treatment of Pediatric Infection and Critical Care</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000914">Antibodies, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004485" MajorTopicYN="Y">Eczema</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000914" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005076" MajorTopicYN="Y">Exanthema</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CVA6</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HFMD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">atypical manifestations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">differential diagnosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genetic evolution</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38103032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Solomon T, Lewthwaite P, Perera D, Cardosa MJ, McMinn P, Ooi MH. Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of enterovirus 71. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10(11):778-790.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi MH, Wong SC, Lewthwaite P, Cardosa MJ, Solomon T. Clinical features, diagnosis, and management of enterovirus 71. Lancet Neurol. 2010;9(11):1097-1105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng H, Duan G, Zhang R, Zhang W. Time series analysis of hand-foot-mouth disease hospitalization in Zhengzhou: establishment of forecasting models using climate variables as predictors. PLoS One. 2014;9(1):e87916.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee BY, Wateska AR, Bailey RR, Tai JHY, Bacon KM, Smith KJ. Forecasting the economic value of an Enterovirus 71 (EV71) vaccine. Vaccine. 2010;28(49):7731-7736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merzel Sabovic EK, Tockova O, Ursic T, Zgavec B, Dolenc-Voljc M. Atypical hand, foot, and mouth disease in an adult patient: a case report and literature review. Acta Dermatovenerol Alp Pannonica Adriat. 2019;28(2):85-88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lizasoain A, Piegas S, Victoria M, Da Silva EE, Colina R. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease in uruguay: Coxsackievirus A6 identified as causative of an outbreak in a rural childcare center. J Med Virol. 2020;92(2):167-173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, le Sage FV, Pereira B, et al. Ambulatory pediatric surveillance of hand, foot, and mouth disease as signal of an outbreak of Coxsackievirus A6 infections, France, 2014-2015. Emerging Infect Dis. 2016;22(11):1884-1893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y, Zhang Y, Ji T, et al. Persistent circulation of Coxsackievirus A6 of genotype D3 in mainland of China between 2008 and 2015. Sci Rep. 2017;7(1):5491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian L, Wang Y, Yao X, Mao Q, Xu M, Liang Z. Coxsackievirus A6: a new emerging pathogen causing hand, foot and mouth disease outbreaks worldwide. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2015;13(9):1061-1071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anh NT, Nhu LNT, Van HMT, et al. Emerging Coxsackievirus A6 causing hand, foot and mouth disease, Vietnam. Emerging Infect Dis. 2018;24(4):654-662.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimmis BD, Downing C, Tyring S. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6 on the rise. Cutis. 2018;102(5):353-356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao TS, Du J, Sun DP, et al. A review and meta-analysis of the epidemiology and clinical presentation of coxsackievirus A6 causing hand-foot-mouth disease in China and global implications. Rev Med Virol. 2020;30(2):e2087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganguly S, Kuruvila S. Eczema Coxsackium. Indian J Dermatol. 2016;61(6):682-683.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei SH, Huang YP, Liu MC, et al. An outbreak of coxsackievirus A6 hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with onychomadesis in Taiwan, 2010. BMC Infect Dis. 2011;11:346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laga AC, Shroba SM, Hanna J. Atypical hand, foot and mouth disease in adults associated with coxsackievirus A6: a clinico-pathologic study. J Cutan Pathol. 2016;43(11):940-945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu YF, Jia LP, Yu FY, et al. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A16 circulating in children in Beijing, China from 2010 to 2019. World J Pediatrics. 2021;17(5):508-516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan F, Chen H, Ma J, Ma X, Zhan J. [Genetic characterization of Coxsackievirus A6 strains isolated in Ningxia region, China, 2013-2015]. Bing Du Xue Bao. 2016;32(6):702-706.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L, Wang T, Liu X, et al. Spatial-temporal-demographic and virological changes of hand, foot and mouth disease incidence after vaccination in a vulnerable region of China. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Xu D, Cong S, et al. Co-infection and enterovirus B: post EV-A71 mass vaccination scenario in China. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Zhang H, Zhao Y, Guo C, Yang Z, Ma S. Molecular characterization of a new human coxsackievirus B2 associated with severe hand-foot-mouth disease in Yunnan Province of China in 2012. Arch Virol. 2017;162(1):307-311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng H, Zhang Y, Liu L, et al. Isolation and characterization of a highly mutated Chinese isolate of enterovirus B84 from a patient with acute flaccid paralysis. Sci Rep. 2016;6:31059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muslin C, Mac Kain A, Bessaud M, Blondel B, Delpeyroux F. Recombination in enteroviruses, a multi-step modular evolutionary process. Viruses. 2019;11(9):859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Zheng Q, Li S, et al. Atomic structures of Coxsackievirus A6 and its complex with a neutralizing antibody. Nat Commun. 2017;8(1):505.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Li Y, Zhang C, et al. Clinical features and phylogenetic analysis of severe hand-foot-and-mouth disease caused by Coxsackievirus A6. Infect Genet Evol. 2020;77:104054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foronda JLM, Jiao MMAD, Climacosa FMM, Oshitani H, Apostol LNG. Epidemiological and molecular characterization of Coxsackievirus A6 causing hand, foot, and mouth disease in the Philippines, 2012-2017. Infect Genet Evol. 2023;114:105498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SH, Wang A, Liu PP, et al. Divergent pathogenic properties of circulating coxsackievirus A6 associated with emerging hand, foot, and mouth disease. J Virol. 2018;92(11):e00303-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Van Tan L, Luo K, et al. Genetic variation of multiple serotypes of enteroviruses associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Southern China. Virol Sinica. 2021;36(1):61-74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Liao Q, Ooi MH, et al. Epidemiology of recurrent hand, foot and mouth disease, China, 2008-2015. Emerging Infect Dis. 2018;24(3):432-442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Zhang Y, Li H, Liu L. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease-associated enterovirus and the development of multivalent HFMD vaccines. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;24(1):169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Jiang L, Zhang C, He W, Tan Y, Ning C. The changes in the epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease after the introduction of the EV-A71 vaccine. Vaccine. 2021;39(25):3319-3323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Zhou Y, Cheng Y, et al. Effectiveness of EV-A71 vaccination in prevention of paediatric hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with EV-A71 virus infection requiring hospitalisation in Henan, China, 2017-18: a test-negative case-control study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2019;3(10):697-704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L, Maimaiti H, Zhou L, Gao J, Lu Y. Changing serotypes of hand, foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, 2017-2019. Gut Pathog. 2022;14(1):12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buttery VW, Kenyon C, Grunewald S, Oberste MS, Nix WA. Atypical presentations of hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by Coxsackievirus A6-Minnesota, 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2015;64(29):805.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lott JP, Liu K, Landry ML, et al. Atypical hand-foot-and-mouth disease associated with coxsackievirus A6 infection. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2013;69(5):736-741.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Österback R, Vuorinen T, Linna M, Susi P, Hyypiä T, Waris M. Coxsackievirus A6 and hand, foot, and mouth disease, Finland. Emerging Infect Dis. 2009;15(9):1485-1488.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Dai B, Han S, et al. Arising concerns of atypical manifestations in patients with hand, foot, and mouth disease. Vaccines. 2023;11(2):405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feder Jr., HM, Bennett N, Modlin JF. Atypical hand, foot, and mouth disease: a vesiculobullous eruption caused by Coxsackie virus A6. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14(1):83-86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Henquell C, Archimbaud C, et al. Outbreak of hand, foot and mouth disease/herpangina associated with coxsackievirus A6 and A10 infections in 2010, France: a large citywide, prospective observational study. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2012;18(5):E110-E118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujimoto T, Iizuka S, Enomoto M, et al. Hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6, Japan, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18(2):337-339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathes EF, Oza V, Frieden IJ, et al. “Eczema coxsackium” and unusual cutaneous findings in an enterovirus outbreak. Pediatrics. 2013;132(1):e149-e157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justino MCA, da S. Mesquita D, Souza MF, et al. Atypical hand-foot-mouth disease in Belém, Amazon region, Northern Brazil, with detection of coxsackievirus A6. J Clin Virol. 2020;126:104307.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davia JL, Bel PH, Ninet VZ, et al. Onychomadesis outbreak in Valencia, Spain associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by enteroviruses. Pediatr Dermatol. 2011;28(1):1-5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmader K, Schmader K. Herpes Zoster. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169(3):ITC17-JITC32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damour A, Garcia M, Seneschal J, Lévêque N, Bodet C. Eczema herpeticum: clinical and pathophysiological aspects. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. 2020;59(1):1-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demain JG. Papular urticaria and things that bite in the night. Curr Allergy Asthma Rep. 2003;3(4):291-303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rook A, Frain-Bell W. Papular URTICARIA. Arch Dis Child. 1953;28(140):304-310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YX, Huang YM, Li QJ, et al. A highly conserved amino acid in VP1 regulates maturation of enterovirus 71. PLoS Pathog. 2017;13(9):e1006625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Chow VTK, Chan KP, Ling AE, Poh CL. RT-PCR, nucleotide, amino acid and phylogenetic analyses of enterovirus type 71 strains from Asia. J Virol Methods. 2000;88(2):193-204.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>