<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">38243751</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1530-6860</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>38</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>FASEB journal : official publication of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>FASEB J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Folate supports IL-25-induced tuft cell expansion following enteroviral infections.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e23430</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e23430</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1096/fj.202301928R</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Intestinal tuft cells, a kind of epithelial immune cells, rapidly expand in response to pathogenic infections, which is associated with infection-induced interleukin 25 (IL-25) upregulation. However, the metabolic mechanism of IL-25-induced tuft cell expansion is largely unknown. Folate metabolism provides essential purine and methyl substrates for cell proliferation and differentiation. Thus, we aim to investigate the roles of folate metabolism playing in IL-25-induced tuft cell expansion by enteroviral infection and recombinant murine IL-25 (rmIL-25) protein-stimulated mouse models. At present, enteroviruses, such as EV71, CVA16, CVB3, and CVB4, upregulated IL-25 expression and induced tuft cell expansion in the intestinal tissues of mice. However, EV71 did not induce intestinal tuft cell expansion in IL-25<sup>-/-</sup> mice. Interestingly, compared to the mock group, folate was enriched in the intestinal tissues of both the EV71-infected group and the rmIL-25 protein-stimulated group. Moreover, folate metabolism supported IL-25-induced tuft cell expansion since both folate-depletion and anti-folate MTX-treated mice had a disrupted tuft cell expansion in response to rmIL-25 protein stimulation. In summary, our data suggested that folate metabolism supported intestinal tuft cell expansion in response to enterovirus-induced IL-25 expression, which provided a new insight into the mechanisms of tuft cell expansion from the perspective of folate metabolism.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lyu</LastName><ForeName>Ruining</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7473-2181</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9111-3139</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Yating</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-2337-0580</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>You</LastName><ForeName>Qiao</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0008-6306-717X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qian</LastName><ForeName>Yajie</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5159-1179</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nanjing Stomatological Hospital, Affiliated Hospital of Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Na</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-5839-112X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cai</LastName><ForeName>Yurong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4515-2484</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Science, Ningxia University, Yinchuan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Deyan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7351-4617</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Zhiwei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0672-948X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Public Health Research, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Science, Ningxia University, Yinchuan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Analytical Chemistry for Life Science, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Molecular Medicine, Medical School, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>31970149</GrantID><Agency>MOST | National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>81900823</GrantID><Agency>MOST | National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U22A20335</GrantID><Agency>MOST | National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2018ZX10301406</GrantID><Agency>The Major Research and Development Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>FASEB J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8804484</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0892-6638</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D020381">Interleukin-17</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>935E97BOY8</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005492">Folic Acid</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049109" MajorTopicYN="N">Cell Proliferation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020381" MajorTopicYN="N">Interleukin-17</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000095491" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tuft Cells</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005492" MajorTopicYN="Y">Folic Acid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">folate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interleukin 25</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tuft cell</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vitamin B</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38243751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1096/fj.202301928R</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Nadjsombati MS, McGinty JW, Lyons-Cohen MR, et al. Detection of succinate by intestinal tuft cells triggers a type 2 innate immune circuit. Immunity. 2018;49(1):33-41.e7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ualiyeva S, Lemire E, Aviles EC, et al. Tuft cell-produced cysteinyl leukotrienes and IL-25 synergistically initiate lung type 2 inflammation. Sci Immunol. 2021;6(66):eabj0474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Wei C, Chen Y, et al. IL-33 induces thymic involution-associated naive T cell aging and impairs host control of severe infection. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):6881.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Neill CA, Monteleone G, McLaughlin JT, Paus R. The gut-skin axis in health and disease: a paradigm with therapeutic implications. Bioessays. 2016;38(11):1167-1176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rutsch A, Kantsjö JB, Ronchi F. The gut-brain Axis: how microbiota and host inflammasome influence brain physiology and pathology. Front Immunol. 2020;11:604179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider C, O'Leary CE, Locksley RM. Regulation of immune responses by tuft cells. Nat Rev Immunol. 2019;19(9):584-593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKinley ET, Sui Y, Al-Kofahi Y, et al. Optimized multiplex immunofluorescence single-cell analysis reveals tuft cell heterogeneity. JCI Insight. 2017;2(11):e93487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strine MS, Wilen CB. Tuft cells are key mediators of interkingdom interactions at mucosal barrier surfaces. PLoS Pathog. 2022;18(3):e1010318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerbe F, Sidot E, Smyth DJ, et al. Intestinal epithelial tuft cells initiate type 2 mucosal immunity to helminth parasites. Nature. 2016;529(7585):226-230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haber AL, Biton M, Rogel N, et al. A single-cell survey of the small intestinal epithelium. Nature. 2017;551(7680):333-339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon ED, Locksley RM, Fahy JV. Cross-talk between epithelial cells and type 2 immune signaling. The role of IL-25. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2016;193(9):935-936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Zhang F, Tao H, Nawaz W, Chen D, Wu Z. The potential roles of interleukin-25 in infectious diseases. Front Immunol. 2022;13:986118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norlander AE, Peebles RS. Innate type 2 responses to respiratory syncytial virus infection. Viruses. 2020;12(5):521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han M, Rajput C, Hong JY, et al. The innate cytokines IL-25, IL-33, and TSLP cooperate in the induction of type 2 innate lymphoid cell expansion and mucous metaplasia in rhinovirus-infected immature mice. J Immunol Baltim Md 1950. 2017;199(4):1308-1318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao M, Ren K, Xiong X, et al. Epithelial STAT6 O-GlcNAcylation drives a concerted anti-helminth alarmin response dependent on tuft cell hyperplasia and Gasdermin C. Immunity. 2022;55(4):623-638.e5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perniss A, Liu S, Boonen B, et al. Chemosensory cell-derived acetylcholine drives tracheal mucociliary clearance in response to virulence-associated formyl peptides. Immunity. 2020;52(4):683-699.e11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shulpekova Y, Nechaev V, Kardasheva S, et al. The concept of folic acid in health and disease. Molecules. 2021;26(12):3731.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y, Cantley LC. Toward a better understanding of folate metabolism in health and disease. J Exp Med. 2019;216(2):253-266.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chon J, Stover PJ, Field MS. Targeting nuclear thymidylate biosynthesis. Mol Aspects Med. 2017;53:48-56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rane CK, Jackson SR, Pastore CF, et al. Development of solitary chemosensory cells in the distal lung after severe influenza injury. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. 2019;316(6):L1141-L1149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fung C, Fraser LM, Barrón GM, et al. Tuft cells mediate commensal remodeling of the small intestinal antimicrobial landscape. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2023;120(23):e2216908120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C, Siegrist F, Petty TJ, Kaiser L. Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity with associated human diseases. Infect Genet Evol. 2013;14:282-293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitamura N, Adler C, Wimmer E. Structure and expression of the picornavirus genome. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1980;354:183-201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kok CC, McMinn PC. Picornavirus RNA-dependent RNA polymerase. Int J Biochem Cell Biol. 2009;41(3):498-502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lockhart A, Mucida D, Parsa R. Immunity to enteric viruses. Immunity. 2022;55(5):800-818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Lu H, Lee YH, et al. An interleukin-25-mediated autoregulatory circuit in keratinocytes plays a pivotal role in psoriatic skin inflammation. Immunity. 2018;48(4):787-798.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu XS, He XY, Ipsaro JJ, et al. OCA-T1 and OCA-T2 are coactivators of POU2F3 in the tuft cell lineage. Nature. 2022;607(7917):169-175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi J, Bergstrom K, Fu J, et al. Dclk1 in tuft cells promotes inflammation-driven epithelial restitution and mitigates chronic colitis. Cell Death Differ. 2019;26(9):1656-1669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGinty JW, Ting HA, Billipp TE, et al. Tuft-cell-derived leukotrienes drive rapid anti-helminth immunity in the small intestine but are dispensable for anti-protist immunity. Immunity. 2020;52(3):528-541.e7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uebanso T, Shimohata T, Mawatari K, Takahashi A. Functional roles of B-vitamins in the gut and gut microbiome. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2020;64(18):e2000426.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunisawa J, Sugiura Y, Wake T, et al. Mode of bioenergetic metabolism during B cell differentiation in the intestine determines the distinct requirement for vitamin B1. Cell Rep. 2015;13(1):122-131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koury MJ, Ponka P. New insights into erythropoiesis: the roles of folate, vitamin B12, and iron. Annu Rev Nutr. 2004;24:105-131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Y, Ren Z, Xu F, et al. Nicotinamide promotes cell survival and differentiation as kinase inhibitor in human pluripotent stem cells. Stem Cell Reports. 2018;11(6):1347-1356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang SY, Kang YJ, Sung B, et al. Folic acid is necessary for proliferation and differentiation of C2C12 myoblasts. J Cell Physiol. 2018;233(2):736-747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramanian VS, Ghosal A, Subramanya SB, Lytle C, Said HM. Differentiation-dependent regulation of intestinal vitamin B(2) uptake: studies utilizing human-derived intestinal epithelial Caco-2 cells and native rat intestine. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2013;304(8):G741-G748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathias PCF, Elmhiri G, de Oliveira JC, et al. Maternal diet, bioactive molecules, and exercising as reprogramming tools of metabolic programming. Eur J Nutr. 2014;53(3):711-722.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mc Auley MT, Mooney KM, Salcedo-Sora JE. Computational modelling folate metabolism and DNA methylation: implications for understanding health and ageing. Brief Bioinform. 2018;19(2):303-317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang SY, Sung B, Kim ND. Roles of folate in skeletal muscle cell development and functions. Arch Pharm Res. 2019;42(4):319-325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Moltke J, Ji M, Liang HE, Locksley RM. Tuft-cell-derived IL-25 regulates an intestinal ILC2-epithelial response circuit. Nature. 2016;529(7585):221-225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith PD, Meng G, Salazar-Gonzalez JF, Shaw GM. Macrophage HIV-1 infection and the gastrointestinal tract reservoir. J Leukoc Biol. 2003;74(5):642-649.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thuma N, Döhler D, Mielenz D, et al. A newly identified secreted larval antigen elicits basophil-dependent protective immunity against N. brasiliensis infection. Front Immunol. 2022;13:979491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kespohl M, Bredow C, Klingel K, et al. Protein modification with ISG15 blocks coxsackievirus pathology by antiviral and metabolic reprogramming. Sci Adv. 2020;6(11):eaay1109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laufman O, Perrino J, Andino R. Viral generated inter-organelle contacts redirect lipid flux for genome replication. Cell. 2019;178(2):275-289.e16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Guo R, Kim SH, et al. SARS-CoV-2 hijacks folate and one-carbon metabolism for viral replication. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):1676.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, You Q, Lyu R, et al. Folate metabolism negatively regulates OAS-mediated antiviral innate immunity via ADAR3/endogenous dsRNA pathway. Metabolism. 2023;143:155526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baggott JE, Tamura T. Folate-dependent purine nucleotide biosynthesis in humans. Adv Nutr. 2015;6(5):564-571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eisenreich W, Rudel T, Heesemann J, Goebel W. How viral and intracellular bacterial pathogens reprogram the metabolism of host cells to allow their intracellular replication. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2019;9:42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borowczyk J, Buerger C, Tadjrischi N, et al. IL-17E (IL-25) and IL-17A differentially affect the functions of human keratinocytes. J Invest Dermatol. 2020;140(7):1379-1389.e2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F, Liu Y, Wang S, et al. Interleukin-25-mediated-IL-17RB upregulation promotes cutaneous wound healing in diabetic mice by improving endothelial cell functions. Front Immunol. 2022;13:809755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeerawattanawart S, Siripurkpong P, Roytrakul S, Angkasekwinai P. IL-25 directly modulates adipocyte function and inflammation through the regulation of adiponectin. Inflamm Res. 2022;71(10-11):1229-1244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Czeizel AE, Dudás I, Vereczkey A, Bánhidy F. Folate deficiency and folic acid supplementation: the prevention of neural-tube defects and congenital heart defects. Nutrients. 2013;5(11):4760-4775.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clare CE, Brassington AH, Kwong WY, Sinclair KD. One-carbon metabolism: linking nutritional biochemistry to epigenetic programming of long-term development. Annu Rev Anim Biosci. 2019;7:263-287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang XM, Huang GW, Tian ZH, Ren DL, Wilson JX. Folate stimulates ERK1/2 phosphorylation and cell proliferation in fetal neural stem cells. Nutr Neurosci. 2009;12(5):226-232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan MR, Darnell AM, Reilly MF, et al. Methionine synthase is essential for cancer cell proliferation in physiological folate environments. Nat Metab. 2021;3(11):1500-1511.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McErlean P, Bell CG, Hewitt RJ, et al. DNA methylome alterations are associated with airway macrophage differentiation and phenotype during lung fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2021;204(8):954-966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloos PAC, Christensen J, Agger K, Helin K. Erasing the methyl mark: histone demethylases at the center of cellular differentiation and disease. Genes Dev. 2008;22(9):1115-1140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabharanjak S, Mayor S. Folate receptor endocytosis and trafficking. Adv Drug Deliv Rev. 2004;56(8):1099-1109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Han Y, Lyu R, et al. FOLR1-induced folate deficiency reduces viral replication via modulating APOBEC3 family expression. Virol Sin. 2023;38(3):409-418. https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1995820X23000287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawaz FZ, Kipreos ET. Emerging roles for folate receptor FOLR1 in signaling and cancer. Trends Endocrinol Metab. 2022;33(3):159-174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm J, Hansen SI. Characterization of soluble folate receptors (folate binding proteins) in humans. Biological roles and clinical potentials in infection and malignancy. Biochim Biophys Acta Proteins Proteom. 2020;1868(10):140466.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>