<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38259063</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2379-5042</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>mSphere</Title><ISOAbbreviation>mSphere</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Human B cells and dendritic cells are susceptible and permissive to enterovirus D68 infection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0052623</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0052623</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00526-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/msphere.00526-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) is predominantly associated with mild respiratory infections, but can also cause severe respiratory disease and extra-respiratory complications, including acute flaccid myelitis. Systemic dissemination of EV-D68 is crucial for the development of extra-respiratory diseases, but it is currently unclear how EV-D68 spreads systemically (viremia). We hypothesize that immune cells contribute to the systemic dissemination of EV-D68, as this is a mechanism commonly used by other enteroviruses. Therefore, we investigated the susceptibility and permissiveness of human primary immune cells for different EV-D68 isolates. In human peripheral blood mononuclear cells inoculated with EV-D68, only B cells were susceptible but virus replication was limited. However, in B cell-rich cultures, such as Epstein-Barr virus-transformed B-lymphoblastoid cell line (BLCL) and primary lentivirus-transduced B cells, which better represent lymphoid B cells, were productively infected. Subsequently, we showed that dendritic cells (DCs), particularly immature DCs, are susceptible and permissive for EV-D68 infection and that they can spread EV-D68 to autologous BLCL. Altogether, our findings suggest that immune cells, especially B cells and DCs, could play an important role in the pathogenesis of EV-D68 infection. Infection of these cells may contribute to systemic dissemination of EV-D68, which is an essential step toward the development of extra-respiratory complications.IMPORTANCEEnterovirus D68 (EV-D68) is an emerging respiratory virus that has caused outbreaks worldwide since 2014. EV-D68 infects primarily respiratory epithelial cells resulting in mild respiratory diseases. However, EV-D68 infection is also associated with extra-respiratory complications, including polio-like paralysis. It is unclear how EV-D68 spreads systemically and infects other organs. We hypothesized that immune cells could play a role in the extra-respiratory spread of EV-D68. We showed that EV-D68 can infect and replicate in specific immune cells, that is, B cells and dendritic cells (DCs), and that virus could be transferred from DCs to B cells. Our data reveal a potential role of immune cells in the pathogenesis of EV-D68 infection. Intervention strategies that prevent EV-D68 infection of immune cells will therefore potentially prevent systemic spread of virus and thereby severe extra-respiratory complications.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Laksono</LastName><ForeName>Brigitta M</ForeName><Initials>BM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5727-5019</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Sooksawasdi Na Ayudhya</LastName><ForeName>Syriam</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aguilar-Bretones</LastName><ForeName>Muriel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Embregts</LastName><ForeName>Carmen W E</ForeName><Initials>CWE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Nierop</LastName><ForeName>Gijsbert P</ForeName><Initials>GP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Riel</LastName><ForeName>Debby</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9753-3564</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>91718308</GrantID><Agency>Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (NWO)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Royal Thai Government Scholarship</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>874735, 101003589</GrantID><Agency>EC | Horizon 2020 Framework Programme (H2020)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>109986</GrantID><Agency>Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (NWO)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>mSphere</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101674533</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2379-5042</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030016" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus D, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020031" MajorTopicYN="Y">Epstein-Barr Virus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007963" MajorTopicYN="N">Leukocytes, Mononuclear</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004854" MajorTopicYN="N">Herpesvirus 4, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003713" MajorTopicYN="N">Dendritic Cells</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">B cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dendritic cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus D68</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">extra-respiratory infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immune cells</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">systemic spread</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral pathogenesis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38259063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10900886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00526-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Greninger AL, Naccache SN, Messacar K, Clayton A, Yu G, Somasekar S, Federman S, Stryke D, Anderson C, Yagi S, Messenger S, Wadford D, Xia D, Watt JP, Van Haren K, Dominguez SR, Glaser C, Aldrovandi G, Chiu CY. 2015. A novel outbreak enterovirus D68 strain associated with acute flaccid myelitis cases in the USA (2012-14): a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis 15:671–682. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(15)70093-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(15)70093-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6027625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25837569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Abzug MJ, Dominguez SR. 2016. The emergence of enterovirus-D68. Microbiol Spectr 4. doi:10.1128/microbiolspec.EI10-0018-2016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.EI10-0018-2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27337448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Schreiner TL, Van Haren K, Yang M, Glaser CA, Tyler KL, Dominguez SR. 2016. Acute flaccid myelitis: a clinical review of US cases 2012-2015. Ann Neurol 80:326–338. doi:10.1002/ana.24730</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ana.24730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5098271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27422805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Pretty K, Reno S, Dominguez SR. 2019. Continued biennial circulation of enterovirus D68 in Colorado. J Clin Virol 113:24–26. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2019.01.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2019.01.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30825833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer R, Sabatier M, Wirth T, Pichon M, Lina B, Schuffenecker I, Josset L. 2018. Molecular diversity and biennial circulation of enterovirus D68: a systematic screening study in Lyon, France, 2010 to 2016. Euro Surveill 23:1700711. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.37.1700711</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.37.1700711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6144471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30229724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop KS, Albert J, Anton A, Andrés C, Aranzamendi M, Armannsdóttir B, Bailly J-L, Baldanti F, Baldvinsdóttir GE, Beard S, et al. . 2021. Re-emergence of enterovirus D68 in Europe after easing the COVID-19 lockdown, September 2021. Euro Surveill 26:45. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.45.2100998</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.45.2100998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34763750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma KC, Winn A, Moline HL, Scobie HM, Midgley CM, Kirking HL, Adjemian J, Hartnett KP, Johns D, Jones JM, Lopez A, Lu X, Perez A, Perrine CG, Rzucidlo AE, McMorrow ML, Silk BJ, Stein Z, Vega E, Hall AJ, New Vaccine Surveillance Network Collaborators . 2022. Increase in acute respiratory illnesses among children and adolescents associated with rhinoviruses and enteroviruses, including enterovirus D68 - United States, July-September 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 71:1265–1270. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm7140e1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7140e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9541033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36201400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang G, Zhuge J, Huang W, Nolan SM, Gilrane VL, Yin C, Dimitrova N, Fallon JT. 2017. Enterovirus D68 subclade B3 strain circulating and causing an outbreak in the United States in 2016. Sci Rep 7:1242. doi:10.1038/s41598-017-01349-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-01349-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5430842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28455514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yip CCY, Lo JYC, Sridhar S, Lung DC, Luk S, Chan K-H, Chan JFW, Cheng VCC, Woo PCY, Yuen K-Y, Lau SKP. 2017. First report of a fatal case associated with EV-D68 infection in Hong Kong and emergence of an interclade recombinant in China revealed by genome analysis. Int J Mol Sci 18:18. doi:10.3390/ijms18051065</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms18051065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5454976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28509856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Clarke P, Tyler KL. 2019. Contemporary circulating enterovirus D68 strains infect and undergo retrograde axonal transport in spinal motor neurons independent of sialic acid. J Virol 93:16. doi:10.1128/JVI.00578-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00578-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6675884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31167912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans WJ, Hurst BL, Peterson CJ, Van Wettere AJ, Day CW, Smee DF, Tarbet EB. 2019. Development of a respiratory disease model for enterovirus D68 in 4-week-old mice for evaluation of antiviral therapies. Antiviral Res 162:61–70. doi:10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6997929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30521834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Zhang X, Dai W, Liu Q, Xiong P, Wang S, Geng L, Gong S, Huang Z. 2018. A mouse model of enterovirus D68 infection for assessment of the efficacy of inactivated vaccine. Viruses 10:58. doi:10.3390/v10020058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v10020058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29385753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng H-W, Sun M, Guo L, Wang J-J, Song J, Li J-Q, Li H-Z, Ning R-T, Yang Z-N, Fan H-T, He Z-L, Liu L-D. 2017. Nasal infection of enterovirus D68 leading to lower respiratory tract pathogenesis in ferrets (Mustela putorius furo). Viruses 9:104. doi:10.3390/v9050104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v9050104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5454417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28489053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Chidini G, Cinnante C, Napolitano L, Giannini A, Terranova L, Niesters H, Principi N, Calderini E. 2017. Acute flaccid myelitis associated with enterovirus-D68 infection in an otherwise healthy child. Virol J 14:4. doi:10.1186/s12985-016-0678-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-016-0678-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5234096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28081720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusabe Y, Takeshima A, Seino A, Nishida M, Takahashi M, Yamada S, Shimbo J, Sato A, Okamoto K, Igarashi S. 2017. [An adult case of enterovirus D68 encephalomyelitis presenting as bilateral facial nerve palsy and dysphagia]. Brain Nerve 69:957–961. doi:10.11477/mf.1416200848</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11477/mf.1416200848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28819079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chong PF, Kira R, Mori H, Okumura A, Torisu H, Yasumoto S, Shimizu H, Fujimoto T, Hanaoka N, Kusunoki S, Takahashi T, Oishi K, Tanaka-Taya K, Acute Flaccid Myelitis Collaborative Study Investigators . 2018. Clinical features of acute flaccid myelitis temporally associated with an enterovirus D68 outbreak: results of a nationwide survey of acute flaccid paralysis in Japan, August-December 2015. Clin Infect Dis 66:653–664. doi:10.1093/cid/cix860</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cix860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29028962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imamura T, Suzuki A, Lupisan S, Kamigaki T, Okamoto M, Roy CN, Olveda R, Oshitani H. 2014. Detection of enterovirus 68 in serum from pediatric patients with pneumonia and their clinical outcomes. Influenza Other Respir Viruses 8:21–24. doi:10.1111/irv.12206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/irv.12206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4177794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24209770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ElBadry M, Lednicky J, Cella E, Telisma T, Chavannes S, Loeb J, Ciccozzi M, Okech B, Beau De Rochars VM, Salemi M, Morris Jr JG. 2016. Isolation of an enterovirus D68 from blood from a child with pneumonia in rural Haiti: close phylogenetic linkage with New York strain. Pediatr Infect Dis J 35:1048–1050. doi:10.1097/INF.0000000000001283</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000001283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27331858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Haren K, Ayscue P, Waubant E, Clayton A, Sheriff H, Yagi S, Glenn-Finer R, Padilla T, Strober JB, Aldrovandi G, Wadford DA, Chiu CY, Xia D, Harriman K, Watt JP, Glaser CA. 2015. Acute flaccid myelitis of unknown etiology in California, 2012-2015. JAMA 314:2663–2671. doi:10.1001/jama.2015.17275</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.17275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26720027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreuter JD, Barnes A, McCarthy JE, Schwartzman JD, Oberste MS, Rhodes CH, Modlin JF, Wright PF. 2011. A fatal central nervous system enterovirus 68 infection. Arch Pathol Lab Med 135:793–796. doi:10.5858/2010-0174-CR.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5858/2010-0174-CR.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21631275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mena I, Perry CM, Harkins S, Rodriguez F, Gebhard J, Whitton JL. 1999. The role of B lymphocytes in coxsackievirus B3 infection. Am J Pathol 155:1205–1215. doi:10.1016/S0002-9440(10)65223-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)65223-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1867001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10514403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid R, Cannon MJ, Chow M. 2005. Dendritic cells and macrophages are productively infected by poliovirus. J Virol 79:401–409. doi:10.1128/JVI.79.1.401-409.2005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.79.1.401-409.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC538697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15596833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen L, Chen CY, Huang D, Wang R, Zhang M, Qian L, Zhu Y, Zhang AZ, Yang E, Qaqish A, Chumakov K, Kouiavskaia D, Vignuzzi M, Nathanson N, Macadam AJ, Andino R, Kew O, Xu J, Chen ZW. 2017. Pathogenic events in a nonhuman primate model of oral poliovirus infection leading to paralytic poliomyelitis. J Virol 91:14. doi:10.1128/JVI.02310-16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.02310-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5487571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28356537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer M, Schulte BM, Toonen LWJ, de Bruijni MAM, Galama JMD, Adema GJ, van Kuppeveld FJM. 2007. Echovirus infection causes rapid loss-of-function and cell death in human dendritic cells. Cell Microbiol 9:1507–1518. doi:10.1111/j.1462-5822.2007.00888.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2007.00888.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17298395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin YW, Wang SW, Tung YY, Chen SH. 2009. Enterovirus 71 infection of human dendritic cells. Exp Biol Med (Maywood) 234:1166–1173. doi:10.3181/0903-RM-116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3181/0903-RM-116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19596831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racaniello VR. 2006. One hundred years of poliovirus pathogenesis. Virology 344:9–16. doi:10.1016/j.virol.2005.09.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2005.09.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16364730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon T, Lewthwaite P, Perera D, Cardosa MJ, McMinn P, Ooi MH. 2010. Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of enterovirus 71. Lancet Infect Dis 10:778–790. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(10)70194-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(10)70194-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20961813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao T, Zhang Z, Zhang Y, Feng M, Fan S, Wang L, Liu L, Wang X, Wang Q, Zhang X, Wang J, Liao Y, He Z, Lu S, Yang H, Li Q. 2017. Dynamic interaction of enterovirus 71 and dendritic cells in infected neonatal rhesus macaques. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 7:171. doi:10.3389/fcimb.2017.00171</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2017.00171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5423916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28540257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing J, Wang K, Wang G, Li N, Zhang Y. 2022. Recent advances in enterovirus A71 pathogenesis: a focus on fatal human enterovirus A71 infection. Arch Virol 167:2483–2501. doi:10.1007/s00705-022-05606-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-022-05606-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36171507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Y, Ong KC, Gao Z, Zhao X, Anderson VM, McNutt MA, Wong KT, Lu M. 2014. Tonsillar crypt epithelium is an important extra-central nervous system site for viral replication in EV71 encephalomyelitis. Am J Pathol 184:714–720. doi:10.1016/j.ajpath.2013.11.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2013.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24378407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smura T, Ylipaasto P, Klemola P, Kaijalainen S, Kyllönen L, Sordi V, Piemonti L, Roivainen M. 2010. Cellular tropism of human enterovirus D species serotypes EV-94, EV-70, and EV-68 in vitro: implications for pathogenesis. J Med Virol 82:1940–1949. doi:10.1002/jmv.21894</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.21894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20872722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laksono BM, Grosserichter-Wagener C, de Vries RD, Langeveld SAG, Brem MD, van Dongen JJM, Katsikis PD, Koopmans MPG, van Zelm MC, de Swart RL. 2018. In vitro measles virus infection of human lymphocyte subsets demonstrates high susceptibility and permissiveness of both naive and memory B cells. J Virol 92:e00131-18. doi:10.1128/JVI.00131-18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.00131-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5874404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29437964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakabe S, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Takano R, Nidom CA, Le MTQ, Nagamura-Inoue T, Horimoto T, Yamashita N, Kawaoka Y. 2011. Cytokine production by primary human macrophages infected with highly pathogenic H5N1 or pandemic H1N1 2009 influenza viruses. J Gen Virol 92:1428–1434. doi:10.1099/vir.0.030346-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/vir.0.030346-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3168279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21367984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Videira PA, Amado IF, Crespo HJ, Algueró MC, Dall’Olio F, Cabral MG, Trindade H. 2008. Surface alpha 2-3- and alpha 2-6-sialylation of human monocytes and derived dendritic cells and its influence on endocytosis. Glycoconj J 25:259–268. doi:10.1007/s10719-007-9092-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10719-007-9092-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18080182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eash S, Tavares R, Stopa EG, Robbins SH, Brossay L, Atwood WJ. 2004. Differential distribution of the JC virus receptor-type sialic acid in normal human tissues. Am J Pathol 164:419–428. doi:10.1016/S0002-9440(10)63132-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)63132-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1602281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14742248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao W, Liu YJ. 2007. Innate immune functions of plasmacytoid dendritic cells. Curr Opin Immunol 19:24–30. doi:10.1016/j.coi.2006.11.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2006.11.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17113765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sioofy-Khojine A-B, Richardson SJ, Locke JM, Oikarinen S, Nurminen N, Laine A-P, Downes K, Lempainen J, Todd JA, Veijola R, Ilonen J, Knip M, Morgan NG, Hyöty H, Peakman M, Eichmann M. 2022. Detection of enterovirus RNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cells correlates with the presence of the predisposing allele of the type 1 diabetes risk gene IFIH1 and with disease stage. Diabetologia 65:1701–1709. doi:10.1007/s00125-022-05753-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00125-022-05753-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9477938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35867130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwakkenbos MJ, Diehl SA, Yasuda E, Bakker AQ, van Geelen CMM, Lukens MV, van Bleek GM, Widjojoatmodjo MN, Bogers W, Mei H, Radbruch A, Scheeren FA, Spits H, Beaumont T. 2010. Generation of stable monoclonal antibody-producing B cell receptor-positive human memory B cells by genetic programming. Nat Med 16:123–128. doi:10.1038/nm.2071</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nm.2071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2861345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20023635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenner J, Kerst G, Handgretinger R, Müller I. 2006. Increased alpha2,6-sialylation of surface proteins on tolerogenic, immature dendritic cells and regulatory T cells. Exp Hematol 34:1212–1218. doi:10.1016/j.exphem.2006.04.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2006.04.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16939814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Vainionpää R, Kettinen H, Hyypiä T. 1994. Coxsackievirus B3 infection in human leukocytes and lymphoid cell lines. Blood 84:823–829. doi:10.1182/blood.V84.3.823.823</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/blood.V84.3.823.823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8043865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horstmann DM. 1952. Poliomyelitis virus in blood of orally infected monkeys and chimpanzees. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 79:417–419. doi:10.3181/00379727-79-19398</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3181/00379727-79-19398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14920447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham NTK, Thongprachum A, Baba T, Okitsu S, Trinh QD, Komine-Aizawa S, Shimizu H, Hayakawa S, Ushijima H. 2017. A 3-month-old child with acute gastroenteritis with enterovirus D68 detected from stool specimen. Clin Lab 63:1269–1272. doi:10.7754/Clin.Lab.2017.170219</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7754/Clin.Lab.2017.170219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28792716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antona D, Kossorotoff M, Schuffenecker I, Mirand A, Leruez-Ville M, Bassi C, Aubart M, Moulin F, Lévy-Bruhl D, Henquell C, Lina B, Desguerre I. 2016. Severe paediatric conditions linked with EV-A71 and EV-D68, France, May to October 2016. Euro Surveill 21:11–14. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2016.21.46.30402</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2016.21.46.30402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5144948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27918268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang TH, Yang TI, Hsu WY, Huang LM, Chang LY, Lu CY. 2019. Case report: painful exanthems caused by enterovirus D68 in an adolescent. Medicine (Baltimore) 98:e16493. doi:10.1097/MD.0000000000016493</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000016493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6831410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31415349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Q, Berzofsky JA. 2013. Oral vaccines: directed safe passage to the front line of defense. Gut Microbes 4:246–252. doi:10.4161/gmic.24197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4161/gmic.24197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3669171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23493163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Binnendijk RS, Poelen MC, de Vries P, Voorma HO, Osterhaus AD, Uytdehaag FG. 1989. Measles virus-specific human T cell clones. Characterization of specificity and function of CD4+ helper/cytotoxic and CD8+ cytotoxic T cell clones. J Immunol 142:2847–2854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2467943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wang F, Wang R, Zhao P, Xia Q. 2015. 2A self-cleaving peptide-based multi-gene expression system in the silkworm Bombyx mori. Sci Rep 5:16273. doi:10.1038/srep16273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep16273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4633692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26537835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkinson GF. 1961. The Spearman-Karber method of estimating 50% endpoints. Contract No.: BU-141-M. Dept. of Biometrics: Biometrics Unit Technical Reports. Cornell University</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>