<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38258346</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Genotypic diversity and long-term impact of human bocavirus on diarrheal disease: Insights from historical fecal samples in Brazil.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29429</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29429</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29429</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study aimed to investigate the frequency and genotypic diversity of human bocavirus (HBoV) in historical fecal samples collected before 2005 in Brazil and understand its natural history in patients with diarrhea. Between 1998 and 2005, 3347 samples were tested for HBoV by RT-PCR, with a detection rate of 5.8% (195/3347). Coinfection with norovirus (NoV) and human adenovirus (HAdV) was found in 34.9% (68/195), indicating HBoV's potential role as a causative agent of diarrheal disease. The detection rate varied over the years (p &lt; 0.05), suggesting natural oscillatory fluctuations. HBoV was more prevalent in fall and winter, with higher positivity in children ≤5 years (p &lt; 0.05), reinforcing that HBoV is an important pathogen in childhood diarrhea. Genotyping (32.8%; 64/195) revealed the circulation of HBoV-1 (79.7%, 51/64), HBoV-3 (12.5%, 8/64), HBoV-2 (6.2%, 4/64), and the rare HBoV-4 (1.6%, 1/64). Difference in HBoV-1 and HBoV-2/-3 mono-infections prevalence (p &lt; 0.05), suggests a potential role of HBoV-1 in the pathogenicity of diarrheal disease. The study highlights HBoV's lasting impact on viral gastroenteritis in Brazil and emphasizes its genotypic diversity. Recommending screening for HBoV in public health laboratories is crucial for understanding its role in gastrointestinal diseases. The data also contribute to understanding the molecular characterization of enteric viruses in historical fecal samples.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Viana</LastName><ForeName>Ellen</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>França</LastName><ForeName>Yasmin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Azevedo</LastName><ForeName>Lais S</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Medeiros</LastName><ForeName>Roberta S</ForeName><Initials>RS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guiducci</LastName><ForeName>Raquel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guadagnucci</LastName><ForeName>Simone</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luchs</LastName><ForeName>Adriana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4131-990X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Disease Laboratory, Virology Center, Adolfo Lutz Institute, Sao Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior-Sistema de Controle de Bolsas e Auxílio (CAPES-SCBA)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Programa de Apoio à Pós-Graduação-Auxílio Financeiro a Projeto Educacional ou de Pesquisa (PROAP-AUXPE)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Especial de Saúde para Imunização em Massa e Controle de Doenças (FESIMA)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D056661" MajorTopicYN="Y">Human bocavirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003967" MajorTopicYN="N">Diarrhea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000260" MajorTopicYN="Y">Adenoviruses, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="N">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diarrhea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gastroenteritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human bocavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular characterization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38258346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adelodun B, Ajibade FO, Ighalo JO, et al. Assessment of socioeconomic inequality based on virus-contaminated water usage in developing countries: a review. Environ Res. 2021;192:110309. doi:10.1016/j.envres.2020.110309</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bányai K, Estes MK, Martella V, Parashar UD. Viral gastroenteritis. Lancet. 2018;392(10142):175-186. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31128-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho SR, Chae SJ, Jung S, et al. Trends in acute viral gastroenteritis among children aged ≤5 years through the national surveillance system in South Korea, 2013-2019. J Med Virol. 2021;93(8):4875-4882. doi:10.1002/jmv.26685</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossouw E, Brauer M, Meyer P, du Plessis NM, Avenant T, Mans J. Virus etiology, diversity and clinical characteristics in South African children hospitalised with gastroenteritis. Viruses. 2021;13(2):215. doi:10.3390/v13020215</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cilli A, Luchs A, Morillo SG, Costa FF, Carmona RC, Timenetsky MCST. Characterization of rotavirus and norovirus strains: a 6-year study (2004-2009). J Pediatr. 2011;87(5):445-449. doi:10.2223/JPED.2122</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allander T, Tammi MT, Eriksson M, Bjerkner A, Tiveljung-Lindell A, Andersson B. Cloning of a human parvovirus by molecular screening of respiratory tract samples. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2005;102(36):12891-12896. doi:10.1073/pnas.0504666102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guido M, Tumolo MR, Verri T, et al. Human bocavirus: current knowledge and future challenges. World J Gastroenterol. 2016;22(39):8684-8697. doi:10.3748/wjg.v22.i39.86848</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos N, Peret TCT, Humphrey CD, et al. Human bocavirus species 2 and 3 in Brazil. J Clin Virol. 2010;48(2):127-130. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2010.03.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khamrin P, Malasao R, Chaimongkol N, et al. Circulating of human bocavirus 1, 2, 3, and 4 in pediatric patients with acute gastroenteritis in Thailand. Infect Genet Evol. 2012;12(3):565-569. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2012.01.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lasure N, Gopalkrishna V. Molecular epidemiology and clinical severity of human bocavirus (HBoV) 1-4 in children with acute gastroenteritis from Pune, Western India. J Med Virol. 2017;89(1):17-23. doi:10.1002/jmv.24593</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trindade FDTB, Ramos ESF, Lobo PS, et al. Epidemiologic and clinical characteristics of human bocavirus infection in children with or without acute gastroenteritis in Acre, Northern Brazil. Viruses. 2023;15(4):1024. doi:10.3390/v15041024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De R, Liu L, Qian Y, et al. Risk of acute gastroenteritis associated with human bocavirus infection in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2017;12(9):e0184833. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0184833</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rikhotso MC, Kabue JP, Ledwaba SE, Traoré AN, Potgieter N. Prevalence of human bocavirus in Africa and other developing countries between 2005 and 2016: a potential emerging viral pathogen for diarrhea. J Trop Med. 2018;2018:1-15. doi:10.1155/2018/7875482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa TT, Souza M, Fiaccadori FS, Borges AMT, Costa PS, Cardoso DDP. Human bocavirus 1 and 3 infection in children with acute gastroenteritis in Brazil. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz. 2012;107(6):800-804. doi:10.1590/s0074-02762012000600015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levican J, Navas E, Orizola J, Avendaño LF, Gaggero A. Human bocavirus in children with acute gastroenteritis, Chile, 1985-2010. Emerging Infect Dis. 2013;19(11):1877-1880. doi:10.3201/eid1911.130601</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siqueira JAM, Sousa Júnior EC, Linhares AC, Gabbay YB. Molecular analysis of norovirus in specimens from children enrolled in a 1982-1986 study in Belém, Brazil: a community-based longitudinal study. J Med Virol. 2017;89(9):1539-1549. doi:10.1002/jmv.24817</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cannon JL, Baker M, Barclay L, Vinjé J. Impact of long-term storage of clinical samples collected from 1996 to 2017 on RT-PCR detection of norovirus. J Virol Methods. 2019;267:35-41. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2019.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souza YFVP, Souza EV, Azevedo LS, Medeiros RS, Timenetsky MCST, Luchs A. Enteric adenovirus epidemiology from historical fecal samples in Brazil (1998-2005): pre-rotavirus vaccine era. Infect Genet Evol. 2021;94:105007. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2021.105007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amaral MSC, Estevam GK, Penatti M, et al. The prevalence of norovirus, astrovirus and adenovirus infections among hospitalised children with acute gastroenteritis in Porto Velho, state of Rondônia, western Brazilian Amazon. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz. 2015;110(2):215-221. doi:10.1590/0074-02760140381</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papaiakovou M, Wright J, Pilotte N, et al. Pooling as a strategy for the timely diagnosis of soil-transmitted helminths in stool: value and reproducibility. Parasit Vectors. 2019;12(1):443. doi:10.1186/s13071-019-3693-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu X, Chittaganpitch M, Olsen SJ, et al. Real-time PCR assays for detection of bocavirus in human specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44(9):3231-3235. doi:10.1128/JCM.00889-06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapoor A, Simmonds P, Slikas E, et al. Human bocaviruses are highly diverse, dispersed, recombination prone, and prevalent in enteric infections. J Infect Dis. 2010;201(11):1633-1643. doi:10.1086/652416</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durigon GS, Oliveira DBL, Vollet SB, et al. Hospital-acquired human bocavirus in infants. J Hosp Infect. 2010;76(2):171-173. doi:10.1016/j.jhin.2010.04.028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Li M, Knyaz C, Tamura K. MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. Mol Biol Evol. 2018;35(6):1547-1549. doi:10.1093/molbev/msy096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morillo SG, Audrey C, Carmona RCC, Timenetsky MCST. Identification and molecular characterization of norovirus in São Paulo state, Brazil. Braz J Microbiol. 2008;39(4):619-622. doi:10.1590/S1517-83822008000400004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammad HA, Madi NM, Al-Nakib W. Analysis of viral diversity in stool samples from infants and children with acute gastroenteritis in Kuwait using metagenomics approach. Virol J. 2020;17(1):10. doi:10.1186/s12985-020-1287-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizk NM, Abd-Elmaksoud S, Farid TM, Abohashish MMA, Al-Herrawy AZ, Hamza IA. Etiology of diarrheal disease among children under 5 years in Egypt: a high incidence of human bocavirus. J Egypt Public Health Assoc. 2021;96(1):24. doi:10.1186/s42506-021-00084-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albuquerque MCM, Rocha LN, Benati FJ, et al. Human bocavirus infection in children with gastroenteritis, Brazil. Emerging Infect Dis. 2007;13(11):1756-1758. doi:10.3201/eid1311.070671</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campos GS, Silva Sampaio ML, Menezes ADL, et al. Human bocavirus in acute gastroenteritis in children in Brazil. J Med Virol. 2016;88(1):166-170. doi:10.1002/jmv.24293</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares LS, Lima ABF, Pantoja KC, et al. Molecular epidemiology of human bocavirus in children with acute gastroenteritis from North Region of Brazil. J Med Microbiol. 2019;68(8):1233-1239. doi:10.1099/jmm.0.001026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malta FC, Varella RB, Guimarães MAAM, Miagostovich MP, Fumian TM. Human bocavirus in Brazil: molecular epidemiology, viral load and co-infections. Pathogens. 2020;9(8):645. doi:10.3390/pathogens9080645</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rikhotso MC, Khumela R, Kabue JP, Traoré-Hoffman AN, Potgieter N. Predominance of human bocavirus genotype 1 and 3 in outpatient children with diarrhea from rural communities in South Africa, 2017-2018. Pathogens. 2020;9(4):245. doi:10.3390/pathogens9040245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tymentsev A, Tikunov A, Zhirakovskaia E, et al. Human bocavirus in hospitalized children with acute gastroenteritis in Russia from 2010 to 2012. Infect Genet Evol. 2016;37:143-149. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2015.11.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey SK, Sharif N, Sarkar OS, et al. Molecular epidemiology and surveillance of circulating rotavirus among children with gastroenteritis in Bangladesh during 2014-2019. PLoS One. 2020;15(11):e0242813. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0242813</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow BDW, Ou Z, Esper FP. Newly recognized bocaviruses (HBoV, HBoV2) in children and adults with gastrointestinal illness in the United States. J Clin Virol. 2010;47(2):143-147. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2009.11.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin MYC, Chan HC, Chi H, et al. Genetic diversity and phylogenetic analysis of human bocavirus 2 in pediatric patients with acute gastroenteritis in Taiwan. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(3):1086. doi:10.3390/ijerph17031086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam MM, Khurshid A, Shaukat S, et al. Human bocavirus in Pakistani children with gastroenteritis. J Med Virol. 2015;87(4):656-663. doi:10.1002/jmv.24090</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proenca-Modena JL, Martinez M, Amarilla AA, et al. Viral load of human bocavirus-1 in stools from children with viral diarrhoea in Paraguay. Epidemiol Infect. 2013;141(12):2576-2580. doi:10.1017/S095026881300023X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khor CS, Sam IC, Hooi PS, Quek KF, Chan YF. Epidemiology and seasonality of respiratory viral infections in hospitalized children in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia: a retrospective study of 27 years. BMC Pediatr. 2012;12:32. doi:10.1186/1471-2431-12-32</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau SKP, Yip CCY, Que T, et al. Clinical and molecular epidemiology of human bocavirus in respiratory and fecal samples from children in Hong Kong. J Infect Dis. 2007;196(7):986-993. doi:10.1086/521310</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chhabra P, Payne DC, Szilagyi PG, et al. Etiology of viral gastroenteritis in children &lt;5 years of age in the United States, 2008-2009. J Infect Dis. 2013;208(5):790-800. doi:10.1093/infdis/jit254</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JI, Chung JY, Han TH, Song MO, Hwang ES. Detection of human bocavirus in children hospitalized because of acute gastroenteritis. J Infect Dis. 2007;196(7):994-997. doi:10.1086/521366</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastien N, Brandt K, Dust K, Ward D, Li Y. Human bocavirus infection, Canada. Emerging Infect Dis. 2006;12(5):848-850. doi:10.3201/eid1205.051424</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro IA, Costa LDC, Oliveira ACR, et al. Circulation profile of respiratory viruses in symptomatic and asymptomatic children from Midwest Brazil. Braz J Microbiol. 2020;51(4):1729-1735. doi:10.1007/s42770-020-00368-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medgyesi D, Brogan J, Sewell D, Creve-Coeur J, Kwong L, Baker K. Where children play: young child exposure to environmental hazards during play in public areas in a transitioning internally displaced persons community in Haiti. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2018;15(8):1646. doi:10.3390/ijerph15081646</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee HR, Wang FY, Li JL, Chou TY, Ho HL. Real-world evaluation of a sample pooling strategy for large-scale rapid COVID-19 testing. J Clin Virol. 2022;149:105133. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2022.105133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Rosa G, Della Libera S, Iaconelli M, et al. Human bocavirus in children with acute gastroenteritis in Albania. J Med Virol. 2016;88(5):906-910. doi:10.1002/jmv.24415</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leitão GAA, Olivares AIO, Pimenta YC, et al. Human bocavirus genotypes 1 and 2 detected in younger Amazonian children with acute gastroenteritis or respiratory infections, respectively. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;95:32-37. doi:10.1016/j.ijid.2020.03.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proenca-Modena JL, Paula FE, Buzatto GP, et al. Hypertrophic adenoid is a major infection site of human bocavirus 1. J Clin Microbiol. 2014;52(8):3030-3037. doi:10.1128/JCM.00870-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa TT, Almeida TNV, Fiaccadori FS, Souza M, Badr KR, Cardoso DDP. Identification of human bocavirus type 4 in a child asymptomatic for respiratory tract infection and acute gastroenteritis-Goiânia, Goiás, Brazil. Braz J Infect Dis. 2017;21(4):472-476. doi:10.1016/j.bjid.2017.03.012</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>