<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">38229319</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>06</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-0461</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>38</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of biochemical and molecular toxicology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Biochem Mol Toxicol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>High mobility group box 1 knockdown inhibits EV71 replication and attenuates cell pyroptosis through TLR4/NF-κB/NLRP3 axis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e23620</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e23620</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jbt.23620</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus 71 (EV71) is a major causative agent of hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) in children. Nowadays, there are still no effective antiviral drugs for EV71 infection. High mobility group box 1 (HMGB1) is reported to be highly expressed in HFMD patients. However, the role and underlying mechanism of HMGB1 in EV71-associated HFMD are still unclear. HMGB1 expression was detected using RT-qPCR and western blot assays. Loss- and gain-function experiments were performed to evaluate the effects of HMGB1 on EV71-infected cells. The virus titer was examined by TCID50. CCK-8 and flow cytometry assays were applied to detect the cell viability and cell cycle. Oxidative stress was determined by relative commercial kits. HMGB1 level was elevated in the serum of EV71-infected patients with HFMD and EV71-induced RD cells. EV71 infection induced the transfer of HMGB1 from the nucleus into the cytoplasm. HMGB1 knockdown inhibited virus replication, viral protein (VP1) expression and promoted antiviral factor expression. In addition, the inhibition of HMGB1 improved cell viability, protected against S phase arrest, and inhibited EV71-induced cell injury and oxidative stress, whereas HMGB1 overexpression showed the opposite effects. In terms of mechanism, HMGB1 overexpression activated the TLR4/NF-κB/NLRP3 signaling pathway and promoted cell pyroptosis. The inhibition of TLR4 and NF-κB reversed the effects of HMGB1 overexpression on virus replication, oxidative stress, and pyroptosis. In conclusion, HMGB1 knockdown inhibits EV71 replication and attenuates pyroptosis through TLR4/NF-κB/NLRP3 axis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yufeng</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7286-1131</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deng</LastName><ForeName>Huiling</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Xi'an Central Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wan</LastName><ForeName>Han</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of General Surgery, Xi'an No. 3 Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Pengfei</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Ruiqing</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Tiantian</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xi'an Children's Hospital, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2022D05</GrantID><Agency>Shaanxi Health Research Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Biochem Mol Toxicol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9717231</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1095-6670</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D024243">HMGB1 Protein</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016328">NF-kappa B</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000071199">NLR Family, Pyrin Domain-Containing 3 Protein</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C495345">TLR4 protein, human</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D051197">Toll-Like Receptor 4</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C585491">HMGB1 protein, human</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D024243" MajorTopicYN="Y">HMGB1 Protein</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016328" MajorTopicYN="N">NF-kappa B</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071199" MajorTopicYN="N">NLR Family, Pyrin Domain-Containing 3 Protein</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069292" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pyroptosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051197" MajorTopicYN="N">Toll-Like Receptor 4</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014779" MajorTopicYN="Y">Virus Replication</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EV71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HMGB1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NLRP3</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oxidative stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pyroptosis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38229319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jbt.23620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>K. P. Chan, K. T. Goh, C. Y. Chong, E. S. Teo, G. Lau, A. E. Ling, Emerging Infect. Dis. 2003, 9, 78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. C. Zhuang, Z. Q. Kou, Y. J. Bai, X. Cong, L. H. Wang, C. Li, L. Zhao, X. J. Yu, Z. Y. Wang, H. L. Wen, Viruses 2015, 7, 6400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Solomon, P. Lewthwaite, D. Perera, M. J. Cardosa, P. McMinn, M. H. Ooi, Lancet Infect. Dis. 2010, 10, 778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Nayak, S. K. Bhuyan, R. Bhuyan, A. Sahu, D. Kar, A. Kuanar, Beni-Suef Univ. J. Basic Appl. Sci. 2022, 11, 78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Shih, C. C. Liao, Y. S. Chang, S. Y. Wu, C. S. Chang, A. T. Liou, Viruses 2018, 10, 674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Mao, Y. Wang, L. Bian, M. Xu, Z. Liang, Expert Rev. Vaccines 2016, 15, 599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Yang, H. Wang, U. Andersson, Front. Immunol. 2020, 11, 484.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Degryse, T. Bonaldi, P. Scaffidi, S. Müller, M. Resnati, F. Sanvito, G. Arrigoni, M. E. Bianchi, J. Cell. Biol. 2001, 152, 1197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Y. Kim, M. H. Hong, J. J. Yoon, D. S. Kim, S. W. Na, Y. J. Jang, Y. J. Lee, D. G. Kang, H. S. Lee, Nutrients 2020, 12, 3096.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Mi, Y. Zhang, Y. Xu, X. Zheng, X. Zhang, Z. Wang, M. Xue, X. Jin, Biomed. Pharmacother. 2019, 116, 109005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Andersson, H. Wang, K. Palmblad, A. C. Aveberger, O. Bloom, H. Erlandsson-Harris, A. Janson, R. Kokkola, M. Zhang, H. Yang, K. J. Tracey, J. Exp. Med. 2000, 192, 565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Zheng, H. Shi, Y. Chen, Z. Xu, J. Chen, L. Jin, Medicine 2017, 96, e6764.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. F. Zhang, J. Yuan, R. Q. Liu, P. F. Xu, J. Wang, H. L. Deng, Chin. Ped. Emerg. Med. 2021, 28, 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Luo, D. Yan, Q. Sun, J. Tao, L. Xu, H. Sun, H. Zhao, J. Cell. Biochem. 2020, 121, 2994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Xiang, T. Chen, Y. Mou, H. Wu, P. Xie, G. Lu, X. Gong, Q. Hu, Y. Zhang, H. Ji, Inflamm. Res. 2015, 64, 799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. S. Sutterwala, S. Haasken, S. L. Cassel, Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 2014, 1319, 82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Duewell, H. Kono, K. J. Rayner, C. M. Sirois, G. Vladimer, F. G. Bauernfeind, G. S. Abela, L. Franchi, G. Nuñez, M. Schnurr, T. Espevik, E. Lien, K. A. Fitzgerald, K. L. Rock, K. J. Moore, S. D. Wright, V. Hornung, E. Latz, Nature 2010, 464, 1357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Tschopp, K. Schroder, Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2010, 10, 210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Zhou, A. S. Yazdi, P. Menu, J. Tschopp, Nature 2011, 469, 221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. L. Cheng, S. F. Weng, C. H. Kuo, H. Y. Ho, PLoS One 2014, 9, e113234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Meng, L. Li, S. Lu, K. Li, Z. Su, Y. Wang, X. Fan, X. Li, G. Zhao, Mol. Immunol. 2018, 94, 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. E. D. E. S. El-Sisi, S. S. Sokar, A. M. Shebl, D. Z. Mohamed, S. E. S. Abu-Risha, Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol. 2021, 410, 115340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Wang, C. Zhou, F. Gao, Q. Zhu, Y. Jiang, X. Ma, Y. Hu, L. Shi, X. Wang, C. Zhang, B. Liu, L. Shen, Q. Mao, G. Liu, Vaccine 2021, 39, 4296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhu, W. Xu, J. Xia, Z. Liang, Y. Liu, X. Zhang, X. Tan, L. Wang, Q. Mao, J. Wu, Y. Hu, T. Ji, L. Song, Q. Liang, B. Zhang, Q. Gao, J. Li, S. Wang, Y. Hu, S. Gu, J. Zhang, G. Yao, J. Gu, X. Wang, Y. Zhou, C. Chen, M. Zhang, M. Cao, J. Wang, H. Wang, N. Wang, N. Engl. J. Med. 2014, 370, 818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. L. Kuo, S. R. Shih, Virol. J. 2013, 10, 28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Simpson, Z. Loh, M. A. Ullah, J. P. Lynch, R. B. Werder, N. Collinson, V. Zhang, Y. Dondelinger, M. J. M. Bertrand, M. L. Everard, C. C. Blyth, G. Hartel, A. J. Van Oosterhout, P. J. Gough, J. Bertin, J. W. Upham, K. M. Spann, S. Phipps, Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 2020, 201, 1358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhang, H. Ren, J. Li, R. Xue, H. Liu, Z. Zhu, C. Pan, Y. Lin, A. Hu, P. Gou, J. Cai, J. Zhou, W. Zhu, X. Shi, Am. J. Cancer Res. 2021, 11, 479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Gustafsson, Pathogens 2021, 10, 57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Andersson, H. Yang, H. Harris, Expert Opin. Ther. Targets 2018, 22, 263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Liu, X. Wang, X. Duan, D. Poorun, J. Xu, S. Zhang, L. Gan, M. He, K. Zhu, Z. Ming, F. Hu, H. Chen, Sci. Rep. 2017, 7, 7100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Fang, B. Dou, J. Liang, W. Hou, C. Ma, Q. Zhang, Evid Based Complement. Alternat. Med. 2021, 2021, 2898995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Li, Y. Huang, M. Sun, H. Ji, H. Dou, J. Hu, Y. Yan, X. Wang, L. Chen, Antiviral Res. 2018, 152, 117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Leisching, I. Wiid, B. Baker, J. Infect. Dis. 2018, 217, 1517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Verhelst, P. Hulpiau, X. Saelens, Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 2013, 77, 551.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Yu, L. Zhang, P. Ren, T. Zhong, Z. Li, Z. Wang, J. Li, X. Liu, K. Zhao, W. Zhang, X. F. Yu, Cell Cycle 2015, 14, 425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Dang, C. Zhang, R. Zhang, W. Wu, S. Chen, J. Ren, P. Zhang, G. Zhou, D. Feng, T. Sun, Y. Li, Q. Liu, M. Li, Y. Xi, Y. Jin, G. Duan, Oncotarget 2017, 8, 81014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Gao, Y. Qiu, L. Gao, L. Zhang, X. Li, Y. Liu, C. Zhao, Food Chem X 2022, 13, 100244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Liu, P. Guo, A. Liu, Q. Wu, X. Xue, M. Dai, H. Hao, W. Qu, S. Xie, X. Wang, Z. Yuan, Food Chem. Toxicol. 2017, 102, 11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Shin, S. Na, O. S. Kim, Y. S. Choi, S. H. Kim, Y. J. Oh, Yonsei Med. J. 2016, 57, 238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Xuan, Q. Shi, G. J. Liu, Q. X. Luan, Y. Cai, Clin. Lab. 2017, 63, 1627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Yang, H. Yin, Y. Cao, Z. Jiang, Y. Li, M. Song, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, R. Yang, Y. Jiang, J. Sun, B. Liu, C. Wang, Cell. Physiol. Biochem. 2018, 49, 728.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Y. Ho, M. L. Cheng, S. F. Weng, Y. L. Leu, D. T. Y. Chiu, J. Agric. Food Chem. 2009, 57, 6140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Yu, S. Jiang, Y. Tao, P. Li, J. Yin, Q. Zhou, J. Cell. Physiol. 2019, 234, 13431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Chu, Y. Jing, X. Zhao, M. Wang, M. Zhang, R. Ma, W. Ma, Y. Lv, L. Zhu, J. Neuroimmunol. 2021, 352, 577480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Li, W. Song, Y. Tong, X. Zhang, J. Zhao, X. Gao, J. Yong, H. Wang, J. Neuroinflammation 2021, 18, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Xu, H. Chen, H. Ni, Q. Dai, Atherosclerosis 2021, 317, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. E. Brodsky, R. Medzhitov, Curr. Biol. 2011, 21, R72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Wang, H. Y. Lei, L. Y. Su, J. M. Wu, C. K. Yu, J. R. Wang, C. C. Liu, Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 2007, 13, 677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhang, J. Hao, C. Sun, J. Du, Q. Han, Q. Li, Exp. Ther. Med. 2022, 23, 237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, Y. Qin, T. Wang, Y. Chen, X. Lang, J. Zheng, S. Gao, S. Chen, X. Zhong, Y. Mu, X. Wu, F. Zhang, W. Zhao, Z. Zhong, Sci. Rep. 2018, 8, 2887.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>