<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38231263</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>90</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied and environmental microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Environ Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Wastewater contaminants in a fractured bedrock aquifer and their potential use as enteric virus indicators.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0121323</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0121323</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e01213-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/aem.01213-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Domestic wastewater is a source of persistent organic pollutants and pathogens to the aquatic environment, including groundwater aquifers. Wastewater contaminants include a variety of personal care products, pharmaceuticals, endocrine disrupters, bacteria, and viruses. Groundwater from 22 wells completed in a semi-confined to confined, fractured Silurian dolostone aquifer in southern Wellington County, Ontario, Canada, was analyzed for 14 organic wastewater contaminants (4 artificial sweeteners, 10 pharmaceuticals) as well as <i>E. coli</i>, total coliforms, and 6 human enteric viruses. Enteric viruses were detected in 8.6% of 116 samples, and at least one organic wastewater contaminant was detected in 82% of the wells (in order of decreasing detection frequency: acesulfame, ibuprofen, sulfamethoxazole, triclosan, carbamazepine, and saccharin). Virus indicator metrics [positive and negative predictive values (PPV, NPV), sensitivity, specificity] were calculated at the sample and well level for the organic wastewater compounds, <i>E. coli</i>, and total coliforms. Fecal bacteria were not good predictors of virus presence (PPV = 0%-8%). Of the potential chemical indicators, triclosan performed the best at the sample level (PPV = 50%, NPV = 100%), and ibuprofen performed the best at the well level (PPV = 60%, NPV = 67%); however, no samples had triclosan or ibuprofen concentrations above their practical quantification limits. Therefore, none of the compounds performed sufficiently well to be considered reliable for assessing the potential threat of enteric viruses in wastewater-impacted groundwater in this bedrock aquifer. Future studies need to evaluate the indicator potential of persistent organic wastewater contaminants in different types of aquifers, especially in fractured rock where heterogeneity is strong.IMPORTANCEAssessing the potential risk that human enteric viruses pose in groundwater aquifers used for potable water supply is complicated by several factors, including: (i) labor-intensive methods for the isolation and quantification of viruses in groundwater, (ii) the temporal variability of these viruses in domestic wastewater, and (iii) their potentially rapid transport in the subsurface, especially in fractured rock aquifers. Therefore, aquifer risk assessment would benefit from the identification of suitable proxy indicators of enteric viruses that are easier to analyze and less variable in wastewater sources. Traditional fecal indicators (e.g., <i>E. coli</i> and coliforms) are generally poor indicators of enteric viruses in groundwater. While many studies have examined the use of pharmaceutical and personal care products as tracers of domestic wastewater and fecal pollution in the environment, there is a paucity of data on the potential use of these chemical tracers as enteric virus indicators, especially in groundwater.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Race</LastName><ForeName>Amy S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Morwick G360 Groundwater Research Institute, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Now with: Tesla, Spring Creek, Nevada, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Spoelstra</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9912-6807</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Water Science and Technology Directorate, Environment and Climate Change Canada, Burlington, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parker</LastName><ForeName>Beth L</ForeName><Initials>BL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Morwick G360 Groundwater Research Institute, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>RE03-061</GrantID><Agency>Ontario Research Fund Research Excellence Round 3</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Environ Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605801</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0099-2240</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>WK2XYI10QM</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D007052">Ibuprofen</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>4NM5039Y5X</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014260">Triclosan</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009930">Organic Chemicals</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D003358">Cosmetics</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D004364">Pharmaceutical Preparations</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014874">Water Pollutants, Chemical</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004926" MajorTopicYN="N">Escherichia coli</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007052" MajorTopicYN="N">Ibuprofen</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014260" MajorTopicYN="Y">Triclosan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Groundwater</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009930" MajorTopicYN="N">Organic Chemicals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003358" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cosmetics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004364" MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmaceutical Preparations</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009864" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ontario</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014874" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Pollutants, Chemical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">artificial sweeteners</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coliforms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">groundwater</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathogens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">persistent organic pollutants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pharmaceuticals</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38231263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10880619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01213-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Cizmas L, Sharma VK, Gray CM, McDonald TJ. 2015. Pharmaceuticals and personal care products in waters: occurrence, toxicity, and risk. Environ Chem Lett 13:381–394. doi:10.1007/s10311-015-0524-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10311-015-0524-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5459316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28592954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preisner M, Neverova-Dziopak E, Kowalewski Z. 2020. Analysis of eutrophication potential of municipal wastewater. Water Sci Technol 81:1994–2003. doi:10.2166/wst.2020.254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wst.2020.254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32666952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chambers PA, Allard M, Walker SL, Marsalek J, Lawrence J, Servos M, Busnarda J, Munger KS, Adare K, Jefferson C, Kent RA, Wong MP. 1997. Impacts of municipal wastewater effluents on Canadian waters: a review. Water Qual Res J 32:659–714. doi:10.2166/wqrj.1997.038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wqrj.1997.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Focazio MJ, Kolpin DW, Barnes KK, Furlong ET, Meyer MT, Zaugg SD, Barber LB, Thurman ME. 2008. A national reconnaissance for pharmaceuticals and other organic wastewater contaminants in the United States—II) untreated drinking water sources. Sci Total Environ 402:201–216. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.02.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.02.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18433838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brausch JM, Connors KA, Brooks BW, Rand GM. 2012. Human pharmaceuticals in the aquatic environment: a review of recent toxicological studies and considerations for toxicity testing. Rev Environ Contam Toxicol 218:1–99. doi:10.1007/978-1-4614-3137-4_1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-3137-4_1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22488604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sano D, Amarasiri M, Hata A, Watanabe T, Katayama H. 2016. Risk management of viral infectious diseases in wastewater reclamation and reuse. Environ Int 91:220–229. doi:10.1016/j.envint.2016.03.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2016.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7111293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26985655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glassmeyer ST, Furlong ET, Kolpin DW, Cahill JD, Zaugg SD, Werner SL, Meyer MT, Kryak DD. 2005. Transport of chemical and microbial compounds from known wastewater discharges: potential for use as indicators of human fecal contamination. Environ Sci Technol 39:5157–5169. doi:10.1021/es048120k</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es048120k</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16082943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes KK, Kolpin DW, Furlong ET, Zaugg SD, Meyer MT, Barber LB. 2008. A national reconnaissance of pharmaceuticals and other organic wastewater contaminants in the United States-I) groundwate. Sci Total Environ 402:192–200. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.04.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2008.04.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18556047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loos R, Locoro G, Comero S, Contini S, Schwesig D, Werres F, Balsaa P, Gans O, Weiss S, Blaha L, Bolchi M, Gawlik BM. 2010. Pan-European survey on the occurrence of selected polar organic persistent pollutants in ground water. Water Res 44:4115–4126. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2010.05.032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2010.05.032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20554303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fram MS, Belitz K. 2011. Occurrence and concentrations of pharmaceutical compounds in groundwater used for public drinking-water supply in California. Sci Total Environ 409:3409–3417. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2011.05.053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2011.05.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21684580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bexfield LM, Toccalino PL, Belitz K, Foreman WT, Furlong ET. 2019. Hormones and pharmaceuticals in groundwater used as a source of drinking water across the United States. Environ Sci Technol 53:2950–2960. doi:10.1021/acs.est.8b05592</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b05592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30834750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunting SY, Lapworth DJ, Crane EJ, Grima-Olmedo J, Koroša A, Kuczyńska A, Mali N, Rosenqvist L, van Vliet ME, Togola A, Lopez B. 2021. Emerging organic compounds in European groundwater. Environ Pollut 269:115945. doi:10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115945</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33261962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Brorström-Lundén E, Svenson A, Viktor T, Woldegiorgis A, Remberger M, Kaj L, Dye C, Bjerke A, Schlabach M. 2008. Measurements of sucralose in the Swedish Screening Program 2007: PART I; Sucralose in surface waters and STP samples. Available from: http://naturvardsverket.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:658036/FULLTEXT01.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buerge IJ, Buser H-R, Kahle M, Müller MD, Poiger T. 2009. Ubiquitous occurrence of the artificial sweetener acesulfame in the aquatic environment: an ideal chemical marker of domestic wastewater in groundwater. Environ Sci Technol 43:4381–4385. doi:10.1021/es900126x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es900126x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19603650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buerge IJ, Keller M, Buser H-R, Müller MD, Poiger T. 2011. Saccharin and other artificial sweeteners in soils: estimated inputs from agriculture and households, degradation, and leaching to groundwater. Environ Sci Technol 45:615–621. doi:10.1021/es1031272</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es1031272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21142066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheurer M, Brauch H-J, Lange FT. 2009. Analysis and occurrence of seven artificial sweeteners in German waste water and surface water and in soil aquifer treatment (SAT). Anal Bioanal Chem 394:1585–1594. doi:10.1007/s00216-009-2881-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-009-2881-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19533103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran NH, Hu J, Li J, Ong SL. 2014. Suitability of artificial sweeteners as indicators of raw wastewater contamination in surface water and groundwater. Water Res 48:443–456. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2013.09.053</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2013.09.053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24156949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snider DM, Roy JW, Robertson WD, Garda DI, Spoelstra J. 2017. Concentrations of artificial sweeteners and their ratios with nutrients in septic system wastewater. Groundwater Monitoring Rem 37:94–102. doi:10.1111/gwmr.12229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/gwmr.12229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spoelstra J, Senger ND, Schiff SL. 2017. Artificial sweeteners reveal septic system effluent in rural groundwater. J Environ Qual 46:1434–1443. doi:10.2134/jeq2017.06.0233</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2134/jeq2017.06.0233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29293857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spoelstra J, Schiff SL, Brown SJ. 2020. Septic systems contribute artificial sweeteners to streams through groundwater. J Hydrol X 7:100050. doi:10.1016/j.hydroa.2020.100050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hydroa.2020.100050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, O’Brien JW, Tscharke BJ, Choi PM, Zheng Q, Ahmed F, Thompson J, Li J, Mueller JF, Sun H, Thomas KV. 2020. National wastewater reconnaissance of artificial sweetener consumption and emission in Australia. Environ Int 143:105963. doi:10.1016/j.envint.2020.105963</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32688159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Stempvoort DR, Robertson WD, Brown SJ. 2011. Artificial sweeteners in a large septic plume. Groundwater Monitoring Rem 31:95–102. doi:10.1111/j.1745-6592.2011.01353.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-6592.2011.01353.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Stempvoort DR, Brown SJ, Spoelstra J, Garda D, Robertson WD, Smyth SA. 2020. Variable persistence of artificial sweeteners during wastewater treatment: Implications for future use as tracers. Water Res 184:116124. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2020.116124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2020.116124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32755735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasser G, Rona M, Voloshenko A, Shelkov R, Tal N, Pankratov I, Elhanany S, Lev O. 2010. Quantitative evaluation of tracers for quantification of wastewater contamination of potable water sources. Environ Sci Technol 44:3919–3925. doi:10.1021/es100604c</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es100604c</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20429595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Ganesh A. 2013. Water quality indicators: bacteria, coliphages, enteric viruses. Int J Environ Health Res 23:484–506. doi:10.1080/09603123.2013.769201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/09603123.2013.769201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23438312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Häfliger D, Hübner P, Lüthy J. 2000. Outbreak of viral gastroenteritis due to sewage-contaminated drinking water. Int J Food Microbiol 54:123–126. doi:10.1016/s0168-1605(99)00176-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0168-1605(99)00176-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10746582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pusch D, Oh DY, Wolf S, Dumke R, Schröter-Bobsin U, Höhne M, Röske I, Schreier E. 2005. Detection of enteric viruses and bacterial indicators in German environmental waters. Arch Virol 150:929–947. doi:10.1007/s00705-004-0467-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-004-0467-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15645371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt MA, Bradbury KR, Alexander EC, Kolberg RJ, Alexander SC, Archer JR, Braatz LA, Forest BM, Green JA, Spencer SK. 2011. Norovirus outbreak caused by a new septic system in a dolomite aquifer. Ground Water 49:85–97. doi:10.1111/j.1745-6584.2010.00686.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-6584.2010.00686.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20199588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele M, Odumeru J. 2004. Irrigation water as source of foodborne pathogens on fruit and vegetables. J Food Prot 67:2839–2849. doi:10.4315/0362-028x-67.12.2839</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-67.12.2839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15633699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mäde D, Trübner K, Neubert E, Höhne M, Johne R. 2013. Detection and typing of norovirus from frozen strawberries involved in a large-scale gastroenteritis outbreak in Germany. Food Environ Virol 5:162–168. doi:10.1007/s12560-013-9118-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12560-013-9118-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3753465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23888384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernard H, Faber M, Wilking H, Haller S, Höhle M, Schielke A, Ducomble T, Siffczyk C, Merbecks SS, Fricke G, Hamouda O, Stark K, Werber D, Outbreak Investigation Team . 2014. Large multistate outbreak of norovirus gastroenteritis associated with frozen strawberries, Germany, 2012. Euro Surveill 19:20719. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.es2014.19.8.20719</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.es2014.19.8.20719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24602278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy HM, McGinnis S, Blunt R, Stokdyk J, Wu J, Cagle A, Denno DM, Spencer S, Firnstahl A, Borchardt MA. 2020. Septic systems and rainfall influence human fecal marker and indicator organism occurrence in private wells in southeastern Pennsylvania. Environ Sci Technol 54:3159–3168. doi:10.1021/acs.est.9b05405</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.9b05405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32073835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt MA, Stokdyk JP, Kieke BA, Muldoon MA, Spencer SK, Firnstahl AD, Bonness DE, Hunt RJ, Burch TR. 2021. Sources and risk factors for nitrate and microbial contamination of private household wells in the fractured dolomite aquifer of northeastern Wisconsin. Environ Health Perspect 129:67004. doi:10.1289/EHP7813</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/EHP7813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8221036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34160249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keswick BH, Gerba CP. 1980. Viruses in groundwater. Environ Sci Technol 14:1290–1297. doi:10.1021/es60171a602</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es60171a602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsey BD, Rasberry JS, Zimmerman TM. Microbiological quality of water from noncommunity supply wells in carbonate and crystalline aquifers of Pennsylvania. Water, Resources Investigations Report 01-4268. Department of the Interior and U.S. Geological Survey</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt MA, Bertz PD, Spencer SK, Battigelli DA. 2003. Incidence of enteric viruses in groundwater from household wells in Wisconsin. Appl Environ Microbiol 69:1172–1180. doi:10.1128/AEM.69.2.1172-1180.2003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.2.1172-1180.2003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC143602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12571044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J, Long SC, Das D, Dorner SM. 2011. Are microbial indicators and pathogens correlated? A statistical analysis of 40 years of research. J Water Health 9:265–278. doi:10.2166/wh.2011.117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wh.2011.117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21942192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fout GS, Borchardt MA, Kieke BA, Karim MR. 2017. Human virus and microbial indicator occurrence in public-supply groundwater systems: meta-analysis of 12 international studies. Hydrogeol J 25:903–919. doi:10.1007/s10040-017-1581-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10040-017-1581-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6145489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30245581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt RJ, Borchardt MA, Richards KD, Spencer SK. 2010. Assessment of sewer source contamination of drinking water wells using tracers and human enteric viruses. Environ Sci Technol 44:7956–7963. doi:10.1021/es100698m</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es100698m</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20822128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradbury KR, Borchardt MA, Gotkowitz M, Spencer SK, Zhu J, Hunt RJ. 2013. Source and transport of human enteric viruses in deep municipal water supply wells. Environ Sci Technol 47:4096–4103. doi:10.1021/es400509b</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es400509b</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23570447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt RJ, Johnson WP. 2017. Pathogen transport in groundwater systems: contrasts with traditional solute transport. Hydrogeol J 25:921–930. doi:10.1007/s10040-016-1502-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10040-016-1502-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen AS. 2013. Vulnerability of a fractured bedrock aquifer to emerging sewage-derived contaminants and their use as indicators of virus contamination. MSc thesis. University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen AS, Borchardt MA, Kieke BA, Dunfield KE, Parker BL. 2017. Virus occurrence in private and public wells in a fractured dolostone aquifer in Canada. Hydrogeol J 25:1117–1136. doi:10.1007/s10040-017-1557-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10040-017-1557-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Belan KP. 2010. Characterizing a fractured rock aquifer with hydraulic testing at a contaminated municipal well using flexible liner methods and depth discrete monitoring (Doctoral dissertation, University of Guelph). Available from: https://atrium.lib.uoguelph.ca/xmlui/handle/10214/19938</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Munn J. 2012. High-resolution discrete fracture network characterization using inclined coreholes in a Silurian dolostone aquifer in Guelph, Ontario (Doctoral dissertation, University of Guelph). Available from: https://atrium.lib.uoguelph.ca/xmlui/handle/10214/3242</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lake Erie Region Source Protection Committee . 2012. Grand river source protection area: approved assessment report</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
2011. Statistics Canada. Available from: http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/geo/bound-limit/bound-limit-2011-eng.cfm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Ontario Ministry of Northern Development, Mines, Natural Resources and Forestry . 2013. OGS Earth. Available from: http://www.mndm.gov.on.ca/en/mines-and-minerals/applications/ogsearth#simple-table-of-contents-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Millen HT, Gonnering JC, Berg RK, Spencer SK, Jokela WE, Pearce JM, Borchardt JS, Borchardt MA. 2012. Glass wool filters for concentrating Waterborne viruses and agricultural zoonotic pathogens. J Vis Exp 61:e3930. doi:10.3791/3930</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3791/3930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3466626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22415031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt MA, Spencer SK, Kieke BA, Lambertini E, Loge FJ. 2012. Viruses in nondisinfected drinking water from municipal wells and community incidence of acute gastrointestinal illness. Environ Health Perspect 120:1272–1279. doi:10.1289/ehp.1104499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.1104499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3440111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22659405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor CB. 1977. Tritium enrichment of environmental waters by electrolysis: development of cathodes exhibiting high isotopic separation and precise measurement of tritium enrichment factors Proceedings of the International Conference of Low-Radioactivity Measurements and Applications, p 131–140Slovenski Pedagogicke Nakladatelstvo, Bratislava</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao X, Metcalfe CD. 2008. Characterizing and compensating for matrix effects using atmospheric pressure chemical ionization liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry: analysis of neutral pharmaceuticals in municipal wastewater. Anal Chem 80:2010–2017. doi:10.1021/ac701633m</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac701633m</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18290635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Stempvoort DR, Roy JW, Brown SJ, Bickerton G. 2011. Artificial sweeteners as potential tracers in groundwater in urban environments. J Hydrol 401:126–133. doi:10.1016/j.jhydrol.2011.02.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2011.02.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
United States Environmental Protection Agency (US EPA) . 2002. EPA-821-R-02-024. Method 1604: total coliforms and Escherichia coli in water by membrane filtration using a simultaneous detection technique (MI Medium). Available from: https://www.epa.gov/sites/default/files/2015-08/documents/method_1604_2002.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sox HC, Blatt MA, Higgins MC, Marton KI. 1998. Medical decision making. Butterworth-Heinemann, Boston, Mass.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Locas A, Barthe C, Barbeau B, Carrière A, Payment P. 2007. Virus occurrence in municipal groundwater sources in Quebec, Canada. Can J Microbiol 53:688–694. doi:10.1139/W07-034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/W07-034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17668028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokdyk JP, Firnstahl AD, Walsh JF, Spencer SK, de Lambert JR, Anderson AC, Rezania L-IW, Kieke BA, Borchardt MA. 2020. Viral, bacterial, and protozoan pathogens and fecal markers in wells supplying groundwater to public water systems in Minnesota, USA. Water Res 178:115814. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2020.115814</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2020.115814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32325219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gougeon R, Spidel M, Lee K, Field CJ. 2004. Canadian diabetes association national nutrition committee technical review: non-nutritive intense sweeteners in diabetes management. Can J Diabetes 28:385–399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lange FT, Scheurer M, Brauch H-J. 2012. Artificial sweeteners—a recently recognized class of emerging environmental contaminants: a review. Anal Bioanal Chem 403:2503–2518. doi:10.1007/s00216-012-5892-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00216-012-5892-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22543693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson WD, Van Stempvoort DR, Solomon DK, Homewood J, Brown SJ, Spoelstra J, Schiff SL. 2013. Persistence of artificial sweeteners in a 15-year-old septic system plume. J Hydrol 477:43–54. doi:10.1016/j.jhydrol.2012.10.048</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2012.10.048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold DL, Krewski D, Munro IC. 1983. Saccharin: a toxicological and historical perspective. Toxicology 27:179–256. doi:10.1016/0300-483x(83)90021-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0300-483x(83)90021-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6353664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Chen WP, Wu LS, Green R, Chang AC. 2009. Leachability of some emerging contaminants in reclaimed municipal wastewater-irrigated turf grass fields. Environ Toxicol Chem 28:1842–1850. doi:10.1897/08-471.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1897/08-471.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19355791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oppel J, Broll G, Löffler D, Meller M, Römbke J, Ternes T. 2004. Leaching behaviour of pharmaceuticals in soil-testing-systems: a part of an environmental risk assessment for groundwater protection. Sci Total Environ 328:265–273. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.02.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.02.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15207589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrara C, Ptacek CJ, Robertson WD, Blowes DW, Moncur MC, Sverko E, Backus S. 2008. Fate of pharmaceutical and trace organic compounds in three septic system plumes, Ontario, Canada. Environ Sci Technol 42:2805–2811. doi:10.1021/es070344q</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es070344q</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18497127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halden RU, Paull DH. 2005. Co-occurrence of triclocarban and triclosan in U.S. water resources. Environ Sci Technol 39:1420–1426. doi:10.1021/es049071e</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/es049071e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15819193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clara M, Strenn B, Kreuzinger N. 2004. Carbamazepine as a possible anthropogenic marker in the aquatic environment: investigations on the behaviour of Carbamazepine in wastewater treatment and during groundwater infiltration. Water Res 38:947–954. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2003.10.058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2003.10.058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14769414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drewes JE, Heberer T, Rauch T, Reddersen K. 2003. Fate of pharmaceuticals during ground water recharge. Groundwater Monitoring Rem 23:64–72. doi:10.1111/j.1745-6592.2003.tb00684.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-6592.2003.tb00684.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz BG, Griffin DW, Davis JH. 2009. Groundwater quality impacts from the land application of treated municipal wastewater in a large karstic spring basin: chemical and microbiological indicators. Sci Total Environ 407:2872–2886. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2009.01.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2009.01.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19232432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaider LA, Rudel RA, Ackerman JM, Dunagan SC, Brody JG. 2014. Pharmaceuticals, perfluorosurfactants, and other organic wastewater compounds in public drinking water wells in a shallow sand and gravel aquifer. Sci Total Environ 468–469:384–393. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.08.067</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.08.067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24055660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Godfrey E, Woessner WW, Benotti MJ. 2007. Pharmaceuticals in on-site sewage effluent and ground water, Western Montana. Ground Water 45:263–271. doi:10.1111/j.1745-6584.2006.00288.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1745-6584.2006.00288.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17470115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang Y, Karnjanapiboonwong A, Chase DA, Wang J, Morse AN, Anderson TA. 2012. Occurrence, fate, and persistence of gemfibrozil in water and soil. Environ Toxicol Chem 31:550–555. doi:10.1002/etc.1725</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/etc.1725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22180293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards QA, Sultana T, Kulikov SM, Garner-O’Neale LD, Metcalfe CD. 2019. Micropollutants related to human activity in groundwater resources in Barbados, West Indies. Sci Total Environ 671:76–82. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.314</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30927730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen AS. 2013. Rate of modern meprobamate prescriptions. Personal communication with pharmacist.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hass U, Dünnbier U, Massmann G. 2012. Occurrence of psychoactive compounds and their metabolites in groundwater downgradient of a decommissioned sewage farm in Berlin (Germany). Environ Sci Pollut Res 19:2096–2106. doi:10.1007/s11356-011-0707-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-011-0707-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22227832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nham HTT, Greskowiak J, Hamann E, Meffe R, Hass U, Massmann G. 2016. Long-term transport behavior of psychoactive compounds in sewage-affected groundwater. Grundwasser 21:321–332. doi:10.1007/s00767-016-0336-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00767-016-0336-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King-Sharp KJ, Frape SK. 2020. Fate and transport of tritium in the Laurentian great lakes system. J Great Lakes Res 46:500–507. doi:10.1016/j.jglr.2020.02.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jglr.2020.02.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles KJ, Shore J, Sellwood J, Laverick M, Hart A, Pedley S. 2009. Assessment of the stability of human viruses and coliphage in groundwater by PCR and infectivity methods. J Appl Microbiol 106:1827–1837. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2672.2009.04150.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2009.04150.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19298517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogorzaly L, Bertrand I, Paris M, Maul A, Gantzer C. 2010. Occurrence, survival, and persistence of human adenoviruses and F-specific RNA phages in raw Groundwater. Appl Environ Microbiol 76:8019–8025. doi:10.1128/AEM.00917-10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00917-10</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3008255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20952644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris GD, Adams VD, Sorensen DL, Curtis MS. 1987. Ultraviolet inactivation of selected bacteria and viruses with photoreactivation of the bacteria. Water Research 21:687–692. doi:10.1016/0043-1354(87)90080-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0043-1354(87)90080-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novick A, Szilard L. 1949. Experiments on light-reactivation of ultra-violet inactivated bacteria. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 35:591–600. doi:10.1073/pnas.35.10.591</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.35.10.591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1063088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15400410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H, Kim M, Lee JE, Lim M, Kim M, Kim JM, Jheong WH, Kim J, Ko G. 2011. Investigation of norovirus occurrence in groundwater in metropolitan Seoul, Korea. Sci Total Environ 409:2078–2084. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2011.01.059</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2011.01.059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21440930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yates MV, Gerba CP, Kelley LM. 1985. Virus persistence in groundwater. Appl Environ Microbiol 49:778–781. doi:10.1128/aem.49.4.778-781.1985</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.49.4.778-781.1985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC238444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4004211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edberg SC, Rice EW, Karlin RJ, Allen MJ. 2000. Escherichia coli: the best biological drinking water indicator for public health protection. J Appl Microbiol 88:106S–116S. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2672.2000.tb05338.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2000.tb05338.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10880185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>