<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38235792</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antibody-dependent enhancement and neutralization against CVB4 investigated in vitro and in silico through an agent-based model.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29399</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29399</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29399</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The infection with coxsackievirus B4 (CVB4) can be enhanced in vitro by antibodies directed against the viral capsid protein VP4. In peripheral blood mononuclear cells, antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) of CVB4 infection leads to the production of interferon alpha (IFN-α). To investigate ADE of CVB4-induced production of IFN-α, an agent-based model was constructed with enhancing and neutralizing antibodies. The model recapitulates viral neutralization and ADE in silico. The enhancing and neutralizing activities of serum samples were evaluated in vitro to confront the model predictions with experimental results. Increasing the incubation time of CVB4 with serum samples improves virus neutralization in silico as well as in vitro. It also results in ADE at lower antibody numbers in silico, which is confirmed in vitro with IFN-α production at lower serum concentrations. Furthermore, incubation of CVB4 with serum at a low temperature does not induce IFN-α production in vitro. Thus, taken together our results suggest that enhancing antibodies bind cryptic epitopes, more accessible with longer incubation time and at higher temperature due to changes in capsid conformation, consistent with previous results indicating that enhancing antibodies are anti-VP4 antibodies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morvan</LastName><ForeName>Corentin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-8125-2436</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Univ Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nekoua</LastName><ForeName>Magloire Pandoua</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2981-0803</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Univ Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Debuysschere</LastName><ForeName>Cyril</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5522-4296</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Univ Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alidjinou</LastName><ForeName>Enagnon Kazali</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1106-9826</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Univ Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hober</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4301-2074</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie ULR3610, Univ Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Ministère de l'Education Nationale, de la Recherche et de la Technologie, Université de Lille, CHU Lille</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019138">Antibodies, Blocking</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000914">Antibodies, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016898">Interferon-alpha</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007963" MajorTopicYN="Y">Leukocytes, Mononuclear</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019067" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibody-Dependent Enhancement</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019138" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Blocking</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000914" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016898" MajorTopicYN="N">Interferon-alpha</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">agent-based model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibody-dependent enhancement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus B4</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">in silico</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">in vitro</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neutralization</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38235792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Tapparel C, Siegrist F, Petty TJ, Kaiser L. Picornavirus and enterovirus diversity with associated human diseases. Infect Genet Evol. 2013;14:282-293. doi:10.1016/j.meegid.2012.10.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuckert RR. Picornaviridae: the viruses and their replication. In: Fields BN, Knipe DM, Howley PM, eds. Fields Virology. Lippincott-Raven; 1996:609-654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baggen J, Thibaut HJ, Strating JRPM, van Kuppeveld FJM. The life cycle of non-polio enteroviruses and how to target it. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2018;16(6):368-381. doi:10.1038/s41579-018-0005-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martino TA, Petric M, Weingartl H, et al. The coxsackie-adenovirus receptor (CAR) is used by reference strains and clinical isolates representing all six serotypes of coxsackievirus group B and by swine vesicular disease virus. Virology. 2000;271(1):99-108. doi:10.1006/viro.2000.0324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tariq N, Kyriakopoulos C. Group B Coxsackie Virus. StatPearls Publishing; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavakoli NP, Wang H, Nattanmai S, Dupuis M, Fusco H, Hull R. Detection and typing of enteroviruses from CSF specimens from patients diagnosed with meningitis/encephalitis. J Clin Virol. 2008;43(2):207-211. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2008.06.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marjomäki V, Flodström-Tullberg M. Coxsackie B virus. Trends Microbiol. 2022;30(6):606-607. doi:10.1016/j.tim.2022.01.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyöty H. Viruses in type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes. 2016;17(suppl 22):56-64. doi:10.1111/pedi.12370</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hober D, Sauter P. Pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus: interplay between enterovirus and host. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2010;6(5):279-289. doi:10.1038/nrendo.2010.27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Alidjinou EK, Hober D. Persistent coxsackievirus B infection and pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2022;18(8):503-516. doi:10.1038/s41574-022-00688-1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sane F, Bertin A, Sioofy-Khojine AB, et al. Enhancing and neutralizing anti-coxsackievirus activities in serum samples from patients prior to development of type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2020;36(6):e3305. doi:10.1002/dmrr.3305</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla R, Ramasamy V, Shanmugam RK, Ahuja R, Khanna N. Antibody-dependent enhancement: a challenge for developing a safe dengue vaccine. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2020;10:572681. doi:10.3389/fcimb.2020.572681</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katzelnick LC, Gresh L, Halloran ME, et al. Antibody-dependent enhancement of severe dengue disease in humans. Science. 2017;358(6365):929-932. doi:10.1126/science.aan6836</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bournazos S, Gupta A, Ravetch JV. The role of IgG Fc receptors in antibody-dependent enhancement. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020;20(10):633-643. doi:10.1038/s41577-020-00410-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierson TC, Sánchez MD, Puffer BA, et al. A rapid and quantitative assay for measuring antibody-mediated neutralization of West Nile virus infection. Virology. 2006;346(1):53-65. doi:10.1016/j.virol.2005.10.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierson TC, Diamond MS. A game of numbers: the stoichiometry of antibody-mediated neutralization of flavivirus infection. Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci. 2015;129:141-166. doi:10.1016/bs.pmbts.2014.10.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hober D, Chehadeh W, Bouzidi A, Wattré P. Antibody-dependent enhancement of coxsackievirus B4 infectivity of human peripheral blood mononuclear cells results in increased interferon-α synthesis. J Infect Dis. 2001;184(9):1098-1108. doi:10.1086/323801</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Sané F, Engelmann I, Hober D. Serum-dependent enhancement of coxsackievirus B4-induced production of IFNα, IL-6 and TNFα by peripheral blood mononuclear cells. J Mol Biol. 2013;425(24):5020-5031. doi:10.1016/j.jmb.2013.10.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmastour F, Jaïdane H, Benkahla M, et al. Anti-coxsackievirus B4 (CV-B4) enhancing activity of serum associated with increased viral load and pathology in mice reinfected with CV-B4. Virulence. 2016;8(6):908-923. doi:10.1080/21505594.2016.1252018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chehadeh W, Lobert PE, Sauter P, et al. Viral protein VP4 is a target of human antibodies enhancing coxsackievirus B4- and B3-induced synthesis of alpha interferon. J Virol. 2005;79(22):13882-13891. doi:10.1128/JVI.79.22.13882-13891.2005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauter P, Chehadeh W, Lobert PE, et al. A part of the VP4 capsid protein exhibited by coxsackievirus B4 E2 is the target of antibodies contained in plasma from patients with type 1 diabetes. J Med Virol. 2008;80(5):866-878. doi:10.1002/jmv.21171</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flatt JW, Domanska A, Seppälä AL, Butcher SJ. Identification of a conserved virion-stabilizing network inside the interprotomer pocket of enteroviruses. Commun Biol. 2021;4(1):250. doi:10.1038/s42003-021-01779-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Yafal AG, Lee YM, Hogle J, Chow M. Poliovirus neutralization by antibodies to internal epitopes of VP4 and VP1 results from reversible exposure of these sequences at physiological temperature. J Virol. 1994;68(6):3965-3970. doi:10.1128/JVI.68.6.3965-3970.1994</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bothner B, Dong XF, Bibbs L, Johnson JE, Siuzdak G. Evidence of viral capsid dynamics using limited proteolysis and mass spectrometry. J Biol Chem. 1998;273(2):673-676. doi:10.1074/jbc.273.2.673</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Lee LY, Roivainen M, Filman DJ, Hogle JM, Belnap DM. Structure of the Fab-labeled “breathing” state of native poliovirus. J Virol. 2012;86(10):5959-5962. doi:10.1128/JVI.05990-11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowd KA, Pierson TC. The many faces of a dynamic virion: implications of viral breathing on flavivirus biology and immunogenicity. Ann Rev Virol. 2018;5(1):185-207. doi:10.1146/annurev-virology-092917-043300</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gangel M, Seiler M, Collins A. Exploring the foreclosure contagion effect using agent-based modeling. February 13, 2013. Accessed May 19, 2022. https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=2216943</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helbing D. Agent-based modeling. In: Helbing D, ed. Social Self-Organization: Agent-Based Simulations and Experiments to Study Emergent Social Behavior. Understanding Complex Systems. Springer; 2012:25-70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bissett KR, Cadena J, Khan M, Kuhlman CJ. Agent-based computational epidemiological modeling. J Indian Inst Sci. 2021;101(3):303-327. doi:10.1007/s41745-021-00260-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B, DeAngelis DL. An overview of agent-based models in plant biology and ecology. Ann Bot. 2020;126(4):539-557. doi:10.1093/aob/mcaa043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonabeau E. Agent-based modeling: methods and techniques for simulating human systems. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2002;99(suppl 3):7280-7287. doi:10.1073/pnas.082080899</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeAngelis DL, Grimm V. Individual-based models in ecology after four decades. F1000Prime Rep. 2014;6:39. doi:10.12703/P6-39</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soheilypour M, Mofrad MRK. Agent-based modeling in molecular systems biology. BioEssays. 2018;40(7):1800020. doi:10.1002/bies.201800020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klasse PJ, Sattentau QJ. Occupancy and mechanism in antibody-mediated neutralization of animal viruses. J Gen Virol. 2002;83(pt 9):2091-2108. doi:10.1099/0022-1317-83-9-2091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szallasi Z, Stelling J, Periwal V, eds. System Modeling in Cellular Biology: From Concepts to Nuts and Bolts. The MIT Press; 2006. doi:10.7551/mitpress/9780262195485.001.0001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehnert T, Figge MT. Dimensionality of motion and binding valency govern receptor-ligand kinetics as revealed by agent-based modeling. Front Immunol. 2017;8:1692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierson TC, Xu Q, Nelson S, et al. The stoichiometry of antibody-mediated neutralization and enhancement of West Nile virus infection. Cell Host Microbe. 2007;1(2):135-145. doi:10.1016/j.chom.2007.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klasse PJ. Neutralization of virus infectivity by antibodies: old problems in new perspectives. Adv Biol. 2014;2014:e157895. doi:10.1155/2014/157895</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brioen P, Boeyé A. Poliovirus neutralization and the percentage law. Arch Virol. 1985;83(1-2):105-111. doi:10.1007/BF01310968</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowd KA, Jost CA, Durbin AP, Whitehead SS, Pierson TC. A dynamic landscape for antibody binding modulates antibody-mediated neutralization of West Nile virus. PLoS Pathog. 2011;7(6):e1002111. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1002111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabo MC, Luca VC, Ray SC, Bukh J, Fremont DH, Diamond MS. Hepatitis C virus epitope exposure and neutralization by antibodies is affected by time and temperature. Virology. 2012;422(2):174-184. doi:10.1016/j.virol.2011.10.023</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>