<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38230282</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2575-9108</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ACS pharmacology &amp; translational science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ACS Pharmacol Transl Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Recent Applications of Protoberberines as Privileged Starting Materials for the Development of Novel Broad-Spectrum Antiviral Agents: A Concise Review (2017-2023).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>48</StartPage><EndPage>71</EndPage><MedlinePgn>48-71</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1021/acsptsci.3c00292</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Berberine is a well-known phytochemical with significant antiviral activity against a wide range of viruses. Due to having a unique backbone consisting of four interconnected rings, it can be used as a platform for the design and development of novel semisynthetic antiviral agents. The question here is whether novel broad-spectrum antiviral drugs with enhanced activity and toxicity potential can be obtained by attempting to modify the structure of this privileged lead compound. The present study aims to review the results of recent studies in which berberine and its close analogues (protoberberine alkaloids) have been used as starting materials for the production of new semisynthetic antiviral structures. For this purpose, relevant studies published in high-quality journals indexed in databases such as Scopus, Web of Science, PubMed, etc. in the time frame of 2017 to 2023 were collected. Our selection criterion in the current review focuses on the studies in which protoberberines were used as starting materials for the production of semisynthetic agents with antiviral activity during the indicated time period. Correspondingly, studies were identified in which semisynthetic derivatives with significant inhibitory activity against a wide range of viruses including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), enterovirus 71 (EV71), zika virus (ZIKV), influenza A/B, cytomegalovirus (CMV), respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), and coxsackieviruses were designed and synthesized. Our conclusion is that, despite the introduction of diverse semisynthetic derivatives of berberine with improved activity profiles compared to the parent natural leads, sufficient derivatization has not been done yet and more studies are needed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2023 American Chemical Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valipour</LastName><ForeName>Mehdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6689-3743</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Razi Drug Research Center, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran 1449614535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zakeri Khatir</LastName><ForeName>Zahra</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari 6964114483, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari 6964114483, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdollahi</LastName><ForeName>Elaheh</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, School of Pharmacy, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran 1449614535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayati</LastName><ForeName>Adileh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Sciences Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran 1416753955, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ACS Pharmacol Transl Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101721411</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2575-9108</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38230282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10789142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.3c00292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Imanshahidi M.; Hosseinzadeh H. Pharmacological and therapeutic effects of Berberis vulgaris and its active constituent, berberine. Phytotherapy research 2008, 22 (8), 999–1012. 10.1002/ptr.2399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.2399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18618524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imenshahidi M.; Hosseinzadeh H. Berberine and barberry (Berberis vulgaris): a clinical review. Phytotherapy Research 2019, 33 (3), 504–523. 10.1002/ptr.6252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.6252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30637820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoshandam A.; Imenshahidi M.; Hosseinzadeh H. Pharmacokinetic of berberine, the main constituent of Berberis vulgaris L.: A comprehensive review. Phytotherapy Research 2022, 36 (11), 4063–4079. 10.1002/ptr.7589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.7589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36221815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yarmohammadi F.; Hayes A. W.; Karimi G. The therapeutic effects of berberine against different diseases: A review on the involvement of the endoplasmic reticulum stress. Phytotherapy Research 2022, 36 (8), 3215–3231. 10.1002/ptr.7539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.7539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35778942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A.; Ekavali; Chopra K.; Mukherjee M.; Pottabathini R.; Dhull D. K. Current knowledge and pharmacological profile of berberine: An update. European journal of pharmacology 2015, 761, 288–297. 10.1016/j.ejphar.2015.05.068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2015.05.068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26092760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M.; Hosseini A.; Di Sotto A.; Irannejad H. Dual action anti-inflammatory/antiviral isoquinoline alkaloids as potent naturally occurring anti-SARS-CoV-2 agents: A combined pharmacological and medicinal chemistry perspective. Phytotherapy Research 2023, 37, 2168.10.1002/ptr.7833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.7833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37039761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarabasz D.; Kukula-Koch W. Palmatine: a review of pharmacological properties and pharmacokinetics. Phytotherapy Research 2020, 34 (1), 33–50. 10.1002/ptr.6504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.6504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31496018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long J.; Song J.; Zhong L.; Liao Y.; Liu L.; Li X. Palmatine: a review of its pharmacology, toxicity and pharmacokinetics. Biochimie 2019, 162, 176–184. 10.1016/j.biochi.2019.04.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2019.04.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31051209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong F.; Chen Y.; Chen J.; Liao H.; Li Y.; Ma Y. Jatrorrhizine: a review of sources, pharmacology, pharmacokinetics and toxicity. Frontiers in Pharmacology 2022, 12, 783127.10.3389/fphar.2021.783127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.783127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8793695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35095493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rolle J.; Asante D. O.; Kok-Fong L. L.; Boucetta H.; Seidu T. A.; Tai L. L.; Alolga R. N. Jatrorrhizine: a review of its pharmacological effects. J. Pharm. Pharmacol. 2021, 73 (6), 709–719. 10.1093/jpp/rgaa065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jpp/rgaa065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33822109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu J.; Luo Y.; Deng D.; Su S.; Li S.; Xiang L.; Hu Y.; Wang P.; Meng X. Coptisine from Coptis chinensis exerts diverse beneficial properties: A concise review. Journal of cellular and molecular medicine 2019, 23 (12), 7946–7960. 10.1111/jcmm.14725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcmm.14725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6850926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31622015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C.-S.; Zheng Y.-R.; Zhang Y.-F.; Long X.-Y. Research progress on berberine with a special focus on its oral bioavailability. Fitoterapia 2016, 109, 274–282. 10.1016/j.fitote.2016.02.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2016.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26851175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X.; Qiu F.; Jiang J.; Gao C.; Tan Y. Intestinal absorption mechanisms of berberine, palmatine, jateorhizine, and coptisine: involvement of P-glycoprotein. Xenobiotica 2011, 41 (4), 290–296. 10.3109/00498254.2010.529180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/00498254.2010.529180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21319959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye M.; Fu S.; Pi R.; He F. Neuropharmacological and pharmacokinetic properties of berberine: a review of recent research. J. Pharm. Pharmacol. 2009, 61 (7), 831–837. 10.1211/jpp/61.07.0001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1211/jpp/61.07.0001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19589224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X.; Li Q.; Xin H.; Yu A.; Zhong M. Effects of berberine on the blood concentration of cyclosporin A in renal transplanted recipients: clinical and pharmacokinetic study. Eur. J. Clin Pharmacol 2005, 61 (8), 567–572. 10.1007/s00228-005-0952-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00228-005-0952-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16133554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahibzada M. U. K.; Sadiq A.; Faidah H. S.; Khurram M.; Amin M. U.; Haseeb A.; Kakar M. Berberine nanoparticles with enhanced in vitro bioavailability: characterization and antimicrobial activity. Drug design, development and therapy 2018, 12, 303–312. 10.2147/DDDT.S156123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/DDDT.S156123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5817421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29491706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal T.; Mishra G.; Jaggi M.; Khar R. K.; Talegaonkar S. Effect of P-glycoprotein inhibitor, verapamil, on oral bioavailability and pharmacokinetics of irinotecan in rats. european journal of pharmaceutical sciences 2009, 36 (4–5), 580–590. 10.1016/j.ejps.2008.12.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejps.2008.12.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19135530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang N.; Sun R.-B.; Chen X.-L.; Zhen L.; Ge C.; Zhao Y.-Q.; He J.; Geng J.-L.; Guo J.-H.; Yu X.-Y.; et al. In vitro assessment of the glucose-lowering effects of berberrubine-9-O-β-D-glucuronide, an active metabolite of berberrubine. Acta Pharmacologica Sinica 2017, 38 (3), 351–361. 10.1038/aps.2016.120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/aps.2016.120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5342660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28042874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng X.; Wang K.; Cao S.; Ding L.; Qiu F. Pharmacokinetics and excretion of berberine and its nine metabolites in rats. Frontiers in Pharmacology 2021, 11, 594852.10.3389/fphar.2020.594852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2020.594852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7874128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33584274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma J. Y.; Feng R.; Tan X. S.; Ma C.; Shou J. W.; Fu J.; Huang M.; He C. Y.; Chen S. N.; Zhao Z. X.; et al. Excretion of berberine and its metabolites in oral administration in rats. J. Pharm. Sci. 2013, 102 (11), 4181–4192. 10.1002/jps.23718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jps.23718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24006193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K.; Feng X.; Chai L.; Cao S.; Qiu F. The metabolism of berberine and its contribution to the pharmacological effects. Drug Metab Rev. 2017, 49 (2), 139–157. 10.1080/03602532.2017.1306544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03602532.2017.1306544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28290706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K.; Feng X.; Chai L.; Cao S.; Qiu F. The metabolism of berberine and its contribution to the pharmacological effects. Drug metabolism reviews 2017, 49 (2), 139–157. 10.1080/03602532.2017.1306544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03602532.2017.1306544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28290706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma J. Y.; Feng R.; Tan X. S.; Ma C.; Shou J. W.; Fu J.; Huang M.; He C. Y.; Chen S. N.; Zhao Z. X.; et al. Excretion of berberine and its metabolites in oral administration in rats. J. Pharm. Sci. 2013, 102 (11), 4181–4192. 10.1002/jps.23718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jps.23718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24006193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y. T.; Yu Y. Q.; Yan X. X.; Wang W. J.; Tian X. T.; Wang L.; Zhu W. L.; Gong L. K.; Pan G. Y. Different structures of berberine and five other protoberberine alkaloids that affect P-glycoprotein-mediated efflux capacity. Acta Pharmacol Sin 2019, 40 (1), 133–142. 10.1038/s41401-018-0183-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41401-018-0183-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6318324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30442987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K.; Chai L.; Ding L.; Qiu F. Identification of metabolites of palmatine in rats after oral administration using ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography/quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry. Rapid communications in mass spectrometry: RCM 2017, 31 (6), 523–537. 10.1002/rcm.7819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rcm.7819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28044413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K.; Qiao M.; Chai L.; Cao S.; Feng X.; Ding L.; Qiu F. Identification of berberrubine metabolites in rats by using ultra-high performance liquid chromatography coupled with quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry. Fitoterapia 2018, 124, 23–33. 10.1016/j.fitote.2017.10.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2017.10.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28993283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y.; Zhou Y.; Si N.; Han L.; Ren W.; Xin S.; Wang H.; Zuo R.; Wei X.; Yang J.; et al. Comparative Metabolism Study of Five Protoberberine Alkaloids in Liver Microsomes from Rat, Rhesus Monkey, and Human. Planta Med. 2017, 83 (16), 1281–1288. 10.1055/s-0043-108249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0043-108249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28399592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi R.; Zhou H.; Ma B.; Ma Y.; Wu D.; Wang X.; Luo H.; Cheng N. Pharmacokinetics and metabolism of jatrorrhizine, a gastric prokinetic drug candidate. Biopharmaceutics &amp; Drug Disposition 2012, 33 (3), 135–145. 10.1002/bdd.1779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bdd.1779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22344858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy V.; Jadhav A. S.; Anand R. V. A room-temperature protocol to access isoquinolines through Ag (I) catalysed annulation of o-(1-alkynyl) arylaldehydes and ketones with NH 4 OAc: Elaboration to berberine and palmatine. Organic &amp; Biomolecular Chemistry 2015, 13 (12), 3732–3741. 10.1039/C4OB02641A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C4OB02641A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25687222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou S.; Tong R. A. general, concise strategy that enables collective total syntheses of over 50 protoberberine and five aporhoeadane alkaloids within four to eight steps. Chem.—Eur. J. 2016, 22 (21), 7084–7089. 10.1002/chem.201601245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/chem.201601245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26990887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajiri M.; Yamada R.; Hotsumi M.; Makabe K.; Konno H. The total synthesis of berberine and selected analogues, and their evaluation as amyloid beta aggregation inhibitors. European Journal of Medicinal Chemistry 2021, 215, 113289.10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33611188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajiri M.; Yamada R.; Hotsumi M.; Makabe K.; Konno H. The total synthesis of berberine and selected analogues, and their evaluation as amyloid beta aggregation inhibitors. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2021, 215, 113289.10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33611188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatland A. E.; Pilgrim B. S.; Procopiou P. A.; Donohoe T. J. Short and Efficient Syntheses of Protoberberine Alkaloids using Palladium-Catalyzed Enolate Arylation. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2014, 53 (52), 14555–14558. 10.1002/anie.201409164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/anie.201409164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4502971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25348493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mori-Quiroz L. M.; Hedrick S. L.; De Los Santos A. R.; Clift M. D. A Unified strategy for the syntheses of the isoquinolinium alkaloids berberine, coptisine, and jatrorrhizine. Org. Lett. 2018, 20 (14), 4281–4284. 10.1021/acs.orglett.8b01702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.orglett.8b01702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6426129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29952573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prajwala B.; Raghu N.; Gopenath T.; Shanmukhappa B.; Karthikeyan M.; Ashok G.; Ranjith M.; Srinivasan V.; Kanthesh M. B. Berberine and its pharmacology potential: a review. Eur. J. Biomed 2020, 7 (5), 115–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy N. S.; Choi I.-Y.; Um T.; Jeon M. J.; Kim B.-Y.; Kim Y.-D.; Yu J.-K.; Kim S.; Kim N.-S. Gene expression and isoform identification of PacBio full-length cDNA sequences for berberine biosynthesis in Berberis koreana. Plants 2021, 10 (7), 1314.10.3390/plants10071314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants10071314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8308982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34203474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S.; Pathak N.; Fatima E.; Negi A. S. Plant isoquinoline alkaloids: Advances in the chemistry and biology of berberine. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2021, 226, 113839.10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2021.113839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34536668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy N. S.; Park N.-I.; Kim N.-S.; Park Y.; Kim B.-Y.; Kim Y.-D.; Yu J.-K.; Kim Y.-I.; Um T.; Kim S.; et al. Comparative Transcriptomics for Genes Related to Berberine and Berbamine Biosynthesis in Berberidaceae. Plants 2022, 11 (20), 2676.10.3390/plants11202676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/plants11202676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9610958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36297700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winkler A.; Łyskowski A.; Riedl S.; Puhl M.; Kutchan T. M.; Macheroux P.; Gruber K. A concerted mechanism for berberine bridge enzyme. Nat. Chem. Biol. 2008, 4 (12), 739–741. 10.1038/nchembio.123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nchembio.123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18953357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han J.; Li S. De novo biosynthesis of berberine and halogenated benzylisoquinoline alkaloids in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Communications Chemistry 2023, 6 (1), 27.10.1038/s42004-023-00821-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s42004-023-00821-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9911778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36759716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma M.; Koul A.; Sharma D.; Kaul S.; Swamy M. K.; Dhar M. K. Metabolic engineering strategies for enhancing the production of bio-active compounds from medicinal plants. Natural Bio-active Compounds: Volume 3: Biotechnology, Bioengineering, and Molecular Approaches 2019, 287–316. 10.1007/978-981-13-7438-8_12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-13-7438-8_12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mora-Vásquez S.; Abascal G. G. W.; Leal C. E.; Cardineau G. A.; Lara S. G. Application of metabolic engineering to enhance the content of alkaloids in medicinal plants. Metabolic Engineering Communications 2022, 14, e0019410.1016/j.mec.2022.e00194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mec.2022.e00194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8881666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35242556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang P.; Liu W.; Xu M.; Jiang R.; Xia L.; Wang P.; Li H.; Tang Z.; Zheng Q.; Zeng J. Modulation of benzylisoquinoline alkaloid biosynthesis by overexpression berberine bridge enzyme in Macleaya cordata. Sci. Rep. 2018, 8 (1), 17988.10.1038/s41598-018-36211-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36211-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6301961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30573738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M. Different Aspects of Emetine’s Capabilities as a Highly Potent SARS-CoV-2 Inhibitor against COVID-19. ACS Pharmacology &amp; Translational Science 2022, 5 (6), 387–399. 10.1021/acsptsci.2c00045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.2c00045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9159504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35702393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M.; Irannejad H.; Emami S. Papaverine, a promising therapeutic agent for the treatment of COVID-19 patients with underlying cardiovascular diseases (CVDs). Drug Dev. Res. 2022, 83 (6), 1246–1250. 10.1002/ddr.21961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ddr.21961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9350394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35706384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M.; Irannejad H.; Emami S. Application of emetine in SARS-CoV-2 treatment: Regulation of p38 MAPK signaling pathway for preventing emetine-induced cardiac complications. Cell Cycle 2022, 21 (22), 2379–2386. 10.1080/15384101.2022.2100575.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15384101.2022.2100575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9645258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35852390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M.; Zarghi A.; Ebrahimzadeh M. A.; Irannejad H. Therapeutic potential of chelerythrine as a multi-purpose adjuvant for the treatment of COVID-19. Cell Cycle 2021, 20 (22), 2321–2336. 10.1080/15384101.2021.1982509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15384101.2021.1982509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8506812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34585628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warowicka A.; Nawrot R.; Goździcka-Józefiak A. Antiviral activity of berberine. Arch. Virol. 2020, 165 (9), 1935–1945. 10.1007/s00705-020-04706-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-020-04706-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7320912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32594322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chin L. W.; Cheng Y.-W.; Lin S.-S.; Lai Y.-Y.; Lin L.-Y.; Chou M.-Y.; Chou M.-C.; Yang C.-C. Anti-herpes simplex virus effects of berberine from Coptidis rhizoma, a major component of a Chinese herbal medicine, Ching-Wei-San. Archives of virology 2010, 155, 1933–1941. 10.1007/s00705-010-0779-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-010-0779-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20686799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zha W.; Liang G.; Xiao J.; Studer E. J.; Hylemon P. B.; Pandak W. M. Jr; Wang G.; Li X.; Zhou H. Berberine inhibits HIV protease inhibitor-induced inflammatory response by modulating ER stress signaling pathways in murine macrophages. PLoS One 2010, 5 (2), e906910.1371/journal.pone.0009069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2817721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20161729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahata S.; Bharti A. C.; Shukla S.; Tyagi A.; Husain S. A.; Das B. C. Berberine modulates AP-1 activity to suppress HPV transcription and downstream signaling to induce growth arrest and apoptosis in cervical cancer cells. Molecular cancer 2011, 10, 1–14. 10.1186/1476-4598-10-39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-10-39</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3098825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21496227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin H.-B.; Choi M.-S.; Yi C.-M.; Lee J.; Kim N.-J.; Inn K.-S. Inhibition of respiratory syncytial virus replication and virus-induced p38 kinase activity by berberine. International Immunopharmacology 2015, 27 (1), 65–68. 10.1016/j.intimp.2015.04.045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2015.04.045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25939536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim J.-H.; Weeratunga P.; Kim M. S.; Nikapitiya C.; Lee B.-H.; Uddin M. B.; Kim T.-H.; Yoon J.-E.; Park C.; Ma J. Y.; et al. Inhibitory effects of an aqueous extract from Cortex Phellodendri on the growth and replication of broad-spectrum of viruses in vitro and in vivo. BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine 2016, 16 (1), 1–13. 10.1186/s12906-016-1206-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1206-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4970287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27484768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H.; Li K.; Ma L.; Wu S.; Hu J.; Yan H.; Jiang J.; Li Y. Berberine inhibits enterovirus 71 replication by downregulating the MEK/ERK signaling pathway and autophagy. Virology Journal 2017, 14 (1), 1–8. 10.1186/s12985-016-0674-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-016-0674-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5234143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28081706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hung T.-C.; Jassey A.; Liu C.-H.; Lin C.-J.; Lin C.-C.; Wong S. H.; Wang J. Y.; Yen M.-H.; Lin L.-T. Berberine inhibits hepatitis C virus entry by targeting the viral E2 glycoprotein. Phytomedicine 2019, 53, 62–69. 10.1016/j.phymed.2018.09.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2018.09.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30668413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luganini A.; Mercorelli B.; Messa L.; Palù G.; Gribaudo G.; Loregian A. The isoquinoline alkaloid berberine inhibits human cytomegalovirus replication by interfering with the viral Immediate Early-2 (IE2) protein transactivating activity. Antiviral Res. 2019, 164, 52–60. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.02.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.02.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30738836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botwina P.; Owczarek K.; Rajfur Z.; Ochman M.; Urlik M.; Nowakowska M.; Szczubiałka K.; Pyrc K. Berberine hampers influenza a replication through inhibition of MAPK/ERK pathway. Viruses 2020, 12 (3), 344.10.3390/v12030344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v12030344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7150991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32245183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ratanakomol T.; Roytrakul S.; Wikan N.; Smith D. R. Berberine inhibits dengue virus through dual mechanisms. Molecules 2021, 26 (18), 5501.10.3390/molecules26185501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26185501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8470584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34576974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su M.; Tang R.; Wang H.; Lu L. Suppression effect of plant-derived berberine on cyprinid herpesvirus 2 proliferation and its pharmacokinetics in Crucian carp (Carassius auratus gibelio). Antiviral Res. 2021, 186, 105000.10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.105000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.105000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33359191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandenon Seteyen A.-L.; Guiraud P.; Gasque P.; Girard-Valenciennes E.; Sélambarom J. In Vitro Analyses of the Multifocal Effects of Natural Alkaloids Berberine, Matrine, and Tabersonine against the O’nyong-nyong Arthritogenic Alphavirus Infection and Inflammation. Pharmaceuticals 2023, 16 (8), 1125.10.3390/ph16081125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph16081125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10459185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37631040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z. Z.; Li K.; Maskey A. R.; Huang W.; Toutov A. A.; Yang N.; Srivastava K.; Geliebter J.; Tiwari R.; Miao M. A small molecule compound berberine as an orally active therapeutic candidate against COVID-19 and SARS: A computational and mechanistic study. FASEB J. 2021, 35 (4), e21360.10.1096/fj.202001792R.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1096/fj.202001792R</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33749932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B.; Chen M.; Chen X.; Cao K.; You Y.; Qian Y.; Yu W. Berberine reduces circulating inflammatory mediators in patients with severe COVID-19. British Journal of Surgery 2021, 108 (1), e910.1093/bjs/znaa021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bjs/znaa021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33640910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu I.; Zhu W. Dose-dependent effect of berberine on SARS-CoV-2 spike protein induced inflammatory host cell response. Int. J. Med. Sci. Health Res. 2021, 5, 169–181. 10.51505/IJMSHR.2021.5116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.51505/IJMSHR.2021.5116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katare A. K.; Singh B.; Shukla P.; Gupta S.; Singh B.; Yalamanchili K.; Kulshrestha N.; Bhanwaria R.; Sharma A. K.; Sharma S.; et al. Rapid determination and optimization of berberine from Himalayan Berberis lycium by soxhlet apparatus using CCD-RSM and its quality control as a potential candidate for COVID-19. Natural Product Research 2022, 36 (3), 868–873. 10.1080/14786419.2020.1806274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14786419.2020.1806274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32787584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majdalawieh A.; Yousef S.; Abu-Yousef I.; Nasrallah G. Immunomodulatory and Anti-Inflammatory Effects of Berberine in Lung Tissue and its Potential Application in Prophylaxis and Treatment of COVID-19. Front. Biosci. 2022, 27, 166.10.31083/j.fbl2705166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31083/j.fbl2705166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35638433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Z.; Li X.; Nie K.; Wang X.; Liang W.; Yang F.; Zheng K.; Zheng Y. Identification of berberine as a potential therapeutic strategy for kidney clear cell carcinoma and COVID-19 based on analysis of large-scale datasets. Frontiers in Immunology 2023, 14, 1038651.10.3389/fimmu.2023.1038651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1038651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10076552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37033923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizzorno A.; Padey B.; Dubois J.; Julien T.; Traversier A.; Dulière V.; Brun P.; Lina B.; Rosa-Calatrava M.; Terrier O. In vitro evaluation of antiviral activity of single and combined repurposable drugs against SARS-CoV-2. Antiviral research 2020, 181, 104878.10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32679055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varghese F. S.; van Woudenbergh E.; Overheul G. J.; Eleveld M. J.; Kurver L.; van Heerbeek N.; van Laarhoven A.; Miesen P.; den Hartog G.; de Jonge M. I.; et al. Berberine and obatoclax inhibit SARS-Cov-2 replication in primary human nasal epithelial cells in vitro. Viruses 2021, 13 (2), 282.10.3390/v13020282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v13020282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7918080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33670363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Rodriguez B. A.; Noval M. G.; Kaczmarek M. E.; Jang K. K.; Thannickal S. A.; Cifuentes Kottkamp A.; Brown R. S.; Kielian M.; Cadwell K.; Stapleford K. A. Atovaquone and Berberine Chloride reduce SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro. Viruses 2021, 13 (12), 2437.10.3390/v13122437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v13122437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8706021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34960706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babalghith A. O.; Al-Kuraishy H. M.; Al-Gareeb A. I.; De Waard M.; Al-Hamash S. M.; Jean-Marc S.; Negm W. A.; Batiha G. E.-S. The role of berberine in Covid-19: potential adjunct therapy. Inflammopharmacology 2022, 30 (6), 2003–2016. 10.1007/s10787-022-01080-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10787-022-01080-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9526677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36183284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M.; Irannejad H.; Keyvani H. An Overview on Anti-COVID-19 Drug Achievements and Challenges Ahead. ACS Pharmacology &amp; Translational Science 2023, 6, 1248.10.1021/acsptsci.3c00121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.3c00121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10496143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37705590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cecil C. E.; Davis J. M.; Cech N. B.; Laster S. M. Inhibition of H1N1 influenza A virus growth and induction of inflammatory mediators by the isoquinoline alkaloid berberine and extracts of goldenseal (Hydrastis canadensis). International immunopharmacology 2011, 11 (11), 1706–1714. 10.1016/j.intimp.2011.06.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2011.06.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21683808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y.; Li J.-q.; Kim Y.-j.; Wu J.; Wang Q.; Hao Y. In vivo and in vitro antiviral effects of berberine on influenza virus. Chinese journal of integrative medicine 2011, 17, 444–452. 10.1007/s11655-011-0640-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11655-011-0640-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21660679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodiwala H. S.; Sabde S.; Mitra D.; Bhutani K. K.; Singh I. P. Synthesis of 9-substituted derivatives of berberine as anti-HIV agents. European journal of medicinal chemistry 2011, 46 (4), 1045–1049. 10.1016/j.ejmech.2011.01.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2011.01.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21295891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song S.; Qiu M.; Chu Y.; Chen D.; Wang X.; Su A.; Wu Z. Downregulation of cellular c-Jun N-terminal protein kinase and NF-κB activation by berberine may result in inhibition of herpes simplex virus replication. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 2014, 58 (9), 5068–5078. 10.1128/AAC.02427-14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AAC.02427-14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4135844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24913175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varghese F. S.; Kaukinen P.; Gläsker S.; Bespalov M.; Hanski L.; Wennerberg K.; Kümmerer B. M.; Ahola T. Discovery of berberine, abamectin and ivermectin as antivirals against chikungunya and other alphaviruses. Antiviral research 2016, 126, 117–124. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2015.12.012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2015.12.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26752081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varghese F. S.; Thaa B.; Amrun S. N.; Simarmata D.; Rausalu K.; Nyman T. A.; Merits A.; McInerney G. M.; Ng L. F.; Ahola T. The antiviral alkaloid berberine reduces chikungunya virus-induced mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling. Journal of virology 2016, 90 (21), 9743–9757. 10.1128/JVI.01382-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JVI.01382-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5068526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27535052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y.-X.; Yang L.; Wang H.-Q.; Zhao X.-Q.; Liu T.; Li Y.-H.; Zeng Q.-X.; Li Y.-H.; Song D.-Q. Synthesis and evolution of berberine derivatives as a new class of antiviral agents against enterovirus 71 through the MEK/ERK pathway and autophagy. Molecules 2018, 23 (8), 2084.10.3390/molecules23082084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules23082084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6222558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30127288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao J.; Zeng D.; Tian S.; Liu G.; Fu J. Identification of the natural product berberine as an antiviral drug. AMB Express 2020, 10 (1), 1–11. 10.1186/s13568-020-01088-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13568-020-01088-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7479080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32897426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui Y.; Zhang L.; Hu D.; Yang Y. Berberine inhibits herpes simplex virus 1 replication in HEK293T cells. Computational and Mathematical Methods in Medicine 2022, 2022, 1.10.1155/2022/7137401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/7137401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9586773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36276998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui G.; Wang H.; Yang C.; Zhou X.; Wang J.; Wang T.; Ma T. Berberine prevents lethal EV71 neurological infection in newborn mice. Frontiers in Pharmacology 2022, 13, 1027566.10.3389/fphar.2022.1027566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.1027566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9640474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36386168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannone D. A.; Piccini L. E.; Brunetti J. E.; Quintana V. M.; Damonte E. B.; Castilla V. Berberine inhibitory action against zika and dengue viruses in cell cultures. Acta Virologica 2023, 67, 11931.10.3389/av.2023.11931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/av.2023.11931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valipour M. Chalcone-amide, a privileged backbone for the design and development of selective SARS-CoV/SARS-CoV-2 papain-like protease inhibitors. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2022, 240, 114572.10.1016/j.ejmech.2022.114572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2022.114572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9250826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35797899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enkhtaivan G.; Kim D. H.; Park G. S.; Pandurangan M.; Nicholas D. A.; Moon S. H.; Kadam A. A.; Patel R. V.; Shin H.-S.; Mistry B. M. Berberine-piperazine conjugates as potent influenza neuraminidase blocker. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2018, 119, 1204–1210. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.08.047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.08.047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30099043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry B.; Keum Y.-S.; Kim D. H. Synthesis and biological evaluation of berberine derivatives bearing 4-aryl-1-piperazine moieties. Journal of Chemical Research 2015, 39 (8), 470–474. 10.3184/174751915X14381686689721.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3184/174751915X14381686689721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry B.; Keum Y. S.; Pandurangan M.; Patel R. V.; Kim D. H. Synthesis of berberine-piperazine conjugates as potential antioxidant and cytotoxic agents. Medicinal Chemistry Research 2016, 25, 2461–2470. 10.1007/s00044-016-1662-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00044-016-1662-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng Q.-X.; Wang H.-Q.; Wei W.; Guo T.-T.; Yu L.; Wang Y.-X.; Li Y.-H.; Song D.-Q. Synthesis and biological evaluation of berberine derivatives as a new class of broad-spectrum antiviral agents against Coxsackievirus B. Bioorganic Chemistry 2020, 95, 103490.10.1016/j.bioorg.2019.103490.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bioorg.2019.103490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31855821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen C. Q.; Nguyen T. H. M.; Nguyen T. T. T.; Bui T. B. H.; Nguyen T. T.; Huynh N. T.; Le T. D.; Nguyen T. M. P.; Nguyen D. T.; Nguyen M. T.; et al. Designs, synthesis, docking studies, and biological evaluation of novel berberine derivatives targeting zika virus. Journal of Chemistry 2021, 2021, 1–10. 10.1155/2021/5567111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/5567111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M.; Chung S.-M.; Enkhtaivan G.; Patel R. V.; Shin H.-S.; Mistry B. M. Molecular docking studies and biological evaluation of berberine-benzothiazole derivatives as an anti-influenza agent via blocking of neuraminidase. International journal of molecular sciences 2021, 22 (5), 2368.10.3390/ijms22052368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22052368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7956587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33673431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enkhtaivan G.; Muthuraman P.; Kim D. H.; Mistry B. Discovery of berberine based derivatives as anti-influenza agent through blocking of neuraminidase. Bioorg. Med. Chem. 2017, 25 (20), 5185–5193. 10.1016/j.bmc.2017.07.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2017.07.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28958846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry B.; Patel R. V.; Keum Y. S.; Noorzai R.; Gansukh E.; Kim D. H. Synthesis of Mannich base derivatives of berberine and evaluation of their anticancer and antioxidant effects. Journal of Chemical Research 2016, 40 (2), 73–77. 10.3184/174751916X14525986827769.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3184/174751916X14525986827769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry B.; Keum Y.-S.; Noorzai R.; Gansukh E.; Kim D. H. Synthesis of piperazine based N-Mannich bases of berberine and their antioxidant and anticancer evaluations. Journal of the Iranian Chemical Society 2016, 13, 531–539. 10.1007/s13738-015-0762-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13738-015-0762-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistry B.; Patel R. V.; Keum Y.-S.; Kim D. H. Synthesis of N-Mannich bases of berberine linking piperazine moieties revealing anticancer and antioxidant effects. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences 2017, 24 (1), 36–44. 10.1016/j.sjbs.2015.09.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2015.09.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5198934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28053569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das B.; Srinivas K. Conversion of berberine into berberrubine by selective demethylation under microwave irradiation. Synthetic communications 2002, 32 (19), 3027–3029. 10.1081/SCC-120012993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1081/SCC-120012993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>