<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38242053</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-3171</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Poultry science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Poult Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The role of turmeric and black pepper oil nanoemulsion in attenuating cytokine storm triggered by duck hepatitis A virus type I (DHAV-I)-induced infection in ducklings.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>103404</StartPage><MedlinePgn>103404</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">103404</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.psj.2023.103404</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0032-5791(23)00924-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The cytokine storm induced by duck hepatitis A virus type 1 (DHAV-1) infection significantly contributes to severe, rapid deaths and economic losses in the duck industry in Egypt. This study aimed to investigate the potential inhibitory effect of a nanoemulsion containing turmeric and black pepper oil on the immune response and pathogenesis of DHAV-1 in ducklings. A total of 105 ducklings from nonvaccinated breeders were divided into 5 experimental groups, each comprising 21 birds. The negative control group (G1) remained noninfected with DHAV-1 and nontreated with nanoemulsion, while the positive control group (G2) was infected with DHAV-1 but not treated with nanoemulsion. The other 2 groups (G3, the supplemented group which was noninfected with DHAV-1), and group 4 (the prophylactic group G4) which was infected with DHAV-1, both received nanoemulsion throughout the experiment. Group 5 (G5, the therapeutic group), on the other hand, which was infected with DHAV-1 received nanoemulsion only from the onset of clinical signs. At 5 days old, the ducklings in the positive control (G2), the prophylactic (G4), and the therapeutic group (G5) were infected with DHAV-1. All the ducklings in the infected groups exhibited depression, anorexia, and opisthotonos, and their livers displayed various degrees of ecchymotic hemorrhage, liver enlargement, and microscopic pathological lesions. Notably, the positive control group (G2) experienced the most severe and pronounced effects compared to the other infected groups treated with the nanoemulsion. Meanwhile, the viral RNA loads were lower in the liver tissues of the infected ducklings treated with the nanoemulsion (G4, and G5) compared to the positive control group G2. Additionally, the nanoemulsion effectively modulated proinflammatory cytokine expression, antioxidant enzymes, liver enzymes, and lipid profile of treated ducklings. In conclusion, the turmeric and black pepper oil nanoemulsion has the potential to be a therapeutic agent for regulating and modulating the immune response, decreasing DHAV-1-induced cytokine storms, and minimizing mortality and economic losses in the duck business. More research is needed to understand how turmeric and black pepper oil nanoemulsion alleviates DHVA-1-induced cytokine storms and lowers duckling mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Sayed</LastName><ForeName>Hemat S</ForeName><Initials>HS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Poultry Diseases, Animal Health Research Institute, Benha-Branch, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Benha 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saad</LastName><ForeName>Aalaa S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotechnology Department, Animal Health Research Institute, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Giza 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tawfik</LastName><ForeName>Wesam A</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Holding Company for Biological Products and Vaccines, Dokki, Giza 12311, Egypt; NaQaa Nanotechnology Network (NNN), Giza, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adel</LastName><ForeName>Amany</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Reference Laboratory for Veterinary Quality Control on Poultry Production, Animal Health Research Institute, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Giza 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdelmagid</LastName><ForeName>Marwa A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Reference Laboratory for Veterinary Quality Control on Poultry Production, Animal Health Research Institute, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Giza 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Momenah</LastName><ForeName>Maha Abdullah</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, College of Science, Princess Nourah bint Abdulrahman University, Riyadh 11671, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azab</LastName><ForeName>Dalia M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biochemistry Department (Pharmacology), Animal Health Research Institute, Benha-Branch, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Benha 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Omar</LastName><ForeName>Sabry E</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Poultry Diseases, Animal Health Research Institute, Benha-Branch, Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Benha 12618, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Habbaa</LastName><ForeName>Ayman S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Benha University, Moshtohor 13736, Qalyubia, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bahshwan</LastName><ForeName>Safia M A</ForeName><Initials>SMA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biological Sciences Department, College of Science and Arts, King Abdulaziz University, Rabigh 21911, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alghamdi</LastName><ForeName>Amira M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Science, King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Saadony</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed T</ForeName><Initials>MT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural Microbiology, Faculty of Agriculture, Zagazig University, Zagazig 44511, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Tarabily</LastName><ForeName>Khaled A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, College of Science, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain 15551, United Arab Emirates. Electronic address: ktarabily@uaeu.ac.ae.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Mayet</LastName><ForeName>Fouad S</ForeName><Initials>FS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Benha University, Moshtohor 13736, Qalyubia, Egypt; Department of Veterinary Pathobiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK 74078, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Poult Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0401150</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0032-5791</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C000723805">black pepper oil</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010938">Plant Oils</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000080424" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cytokine Release Syndrome</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030024" MajorTopicYN="N">Curcuma</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004372" MajorTopicYN="N">Ducks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004371" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hepatitis Virus, Duck</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002645" MajorTopicYN="N">Chickens</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010938" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plant Oils</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029222" MajorTopicYN="Y">Piper nigrum</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Black pepper</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DHAV-1</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">curcumin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cytokine storm</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ducklings</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nano-emulsion</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38242053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10831264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2023.103404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0032-5791(23)00924-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anand P., Kunnumakkara A.B., Newman R.A., Aggarwal B.B. Bioavailability of curcumin: problems and promises. Mol. Pharm. 2007;4:807–818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17999464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashokkumar K., Murugan M., Dhanya M.K., Pandian A., Warkentin T.D. Phytochemistry and therapeutic potential of black pepper [Piper nigrum (L.)] essential oil and piperine: a review. Clin. Phytosci. 2021;7:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atia M.M., Abdel-Tawab H.S., Mostafa A.M., Mobarak S.A. Nanocurcumin and curcumin prevent N, N’-methylenebisacrylamide-induced liver damage and promotion of hepatic cancer cell growth. Sci. Rep. 2022;12:8319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9117224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35585174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boozari M., Butler A.E., Sahebkar A. Impact of curcumin on toll-like receptors. J. Cell. Physiol. 2019;234:12471–12482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30623441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai Y.S., Chen Y.Q., Lin S.H., Xie K., Wang C.J., Yang Y.Z., Xu F. Curcumin regulates the differentiation of naïve CD4+T cells and activates IL-10 immune modulation against acute lung injury in mice. Biomed. Pharmacother. 2020;125</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32004976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couper K.N., Blount D.G., Riley E.M. Immunology IL-10: the master regulator of immunity to infection. J. Immunol. 2008;180:5771–5777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18424693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cron R.Q. One-two punch of cytokine storm syndrome (2020) Blood. 2020;136:645–646.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32761218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai C., Zhang X., Zhang K. New discovery of curcumin combination therapy and action mechanism. Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med. 2020;2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7085841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32215039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalton T.P., Dieter M.Z., Yang Y., Shertzer H.G., Nebert D.W. Knockout of the mouse glutamate cysteine ligase catalytic subunit (Gclc) gene: embryonic lethal when homozygous, and proposed model for moderate glutathione deficiency when heterozygous. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 2000;279:324–329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11118286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Desoky G.E., Wabaidur S.M., Alothman Z.A., Habila M.A. Regulatory role of nano-curcumin against tartrazine-induced oxidative stress, apoptosis-related genes expression, and genotoxicity in rats. Molecules. 2020;25:5801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7763955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33316931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Kazafy S.A., Fouad Y.M., Said A.F., Assal H.H., Ali T.M., Ahmed A.E., Elesawy B.H., Ahmed O.M. Correlations between cytokine levels, liver function markers, and neuropilin-1 expression in patients with COVID-19. Vaccines. 2022;10:1636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9611321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36298501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EL-Sayed H.E.M.A.T., Mady W., Saif M., Tawfik W. efficacy of quercetin nanoparticles as a new antiviral against h5n1 influenza virus replication. Assiut Vet. Med. J. 2018;64:60–67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gayathri K., Bhaskaran M., Selvam C., Thilagavathi R. Nano formulation approaches for curcumin delivery - a review. J. Drug. Deliv. Sci. Technol. 2023;82</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson-Corley K.N., Olivier A.K., Meyerholz D.K. Principles for valid histopathologic scoring in research. Vet. Pathol. 2013;50:1007–1015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3795863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23558974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu C.Q., Xie C.Q., Hu X.Y., Zhang W.P., Bi D.R., Cheng G.F. Cytokine gene expression in the livers of ducklings infected with duck hepatitis virus-1 JX strain. Poult. Sci. 2012;91:583–591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22334733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hani U., Shivakumar H.G. Solubility enhancement and delivery systems of curcumin a herbal medicine: a review. Curr. Drug. Deliv. 2014;11:792–804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25176028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan S.K., Mousa A.M., Eshak M.G., Farrag A.E.R.H., Badawi A.E.F.M. Therapeutic and chemopreventive effects of nano curcumin against diethylnitrosamine induced hepatocellular carcinoma in rats. Int. J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci. 2014;6:54–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellebrekers P., Vrisekoop N., Koenderman L. Neutrophil phenotypes in health and disease. Eur. J. Clin. Invest. 2018;48:e12943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29682724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hisham I., Ellakany H.F., Selim A.A., Abdalla M.A.M., Zain El-Abideen M.A., Kilany W.H., Ali A., Elbestawy A.R. Comparative pathogenicity of duck hepatitis a virus-1 isolates in experimentally infected Pekin and Muscovy ducklings. Front. Vet. Sci. 2020;7:234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7326108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32671102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jarczak D., Nierhaus A. Cytokine storm—definition, causes, and implications. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022;23:11740.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9570384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36233040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin X., Zhang W., Zhang W., Gu C., Cheng G., Hu X. Identification and molecular analysis of the highly pathogenic duck hepatitis virus type 1 in Hubei province of China. Res. Vet. Sci. 2008;85:595–598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18486957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakran M., Sahoo N.G., Li L., Judeh Z. Fabrication of quercetin nanoparticles by anti-solvent precipitation method for enhanced dissolution. Powder. Technol. 2012;223:59–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamomae M., Kameyama M., Ishii J., Nabe M., Ogura Y., Iseki H., Yamamoto Y., Mase M. An outbreak of duck hepatitis a virus type 1 infection in Japan. J. Vet. Med. Sci. 2017;79:917–920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5447982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28413174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M.A., Khan M.J. Nano-gold displayed anti-inflammatory property via NF-kB pathways by suppressing COX-2 activity. Artif. Cells. Nanomed. Biotechnol. 2018;46:1149–1158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29553845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kheiripour N., Plarak A., Heshmati A., Asl S.S., Mehri F., Ebadollahi-Natanzi A., Ranjbar A., Hosseini A. Evaluation of the hepatoprotective effects of curcumin and nanocurcumin against paraquat-induced liver injury in rats: modulation of oxidative stress and Nrf2 pathway. J. Biochem. Mol. Toxicol. 2021;35:e22739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33544450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai Y., Xia X., Cheng A., Wang M., Ou X., Mao S., Sun D., Zhang S., Yang Q., Wu Y., Zhu D., Jia R., Chen S., Liu M., Zhao X.X., Huang J., Gao Q., Tian B., Liu Y., Yu Y., Zhang L., Pan L. DHAV-1 blocks the signaling pathway upstream of type i interferon by inhibiting the interferon regulatory factor 7 protein. Front. Microbiol. 2021;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8633874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34867836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z., Ying Y. The inhibitory effect of curcumin on virus-induced cytokine storm and its potential use in the associated severe pneumonia. Front. Cell. Dev. Biol. 2020;8:479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7303286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32596244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Q., Zhou Y.-H., Yang Z.-Q. The cytokine storm of severe influenza and development of immunomodulatory therapy. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 2016;13:3–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4711683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26189369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu K., Zhu Y., Cao X., Liu Y., Ying R., Huang Q., Gao P., Zhang C. Curcumin as an antiviral agent and immune-inflammatory modulator in COVID-19: a scientometric analysis. Heliyon. 2023;9:e21648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10661356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38027776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao S., Wang M., Ou X., Sun D., Cheng A., Zhu D., Chen S., Jia R., Liu M., Sun K., Yang Q., Wu Y., Zhao X., Chen X. Virologic and immunologic characteristics in mature ducks with acute duck hepatitis A virus 1 infection. Front. Immunol. 2017;8:1574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5696325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29201029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maurya V.K., Kumar S., Prasad A.K., Bhatt M.L.B., Saxena S.K. Structure-based drug designing for potential antiviral activity of selected natural products from Ayurveda against SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein and its cellular receptor. Virus Dis. 2020;31:179–193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7245990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32656311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Memarzia A., Khazdair M.R., Behrouz S., Gholamnezhad Z., Jafarnezhad M., Saadat S., Boskabady M.H. Experimental and clinical reports on anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and immunomodulatory effects of Curcuma longa and curcumin, an updated and comprehensive review. Biofactors. 2021;47:311–350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33606322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moghadamtousi S.Z., Kadir H.A., Hassandarvish P., Tajik H., Abubakar S., Zandi K. A review on antibacterial, antiviral, and antifungal activity of curcumin. Biomed. Res. Int. 2014;2014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4022204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24877064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosmann T. Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays. J. Immunol. Methods. 1983;65:55–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6606682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafa A., Kandeil A., Elshaier Y.A.M.M., Kutkat O., Moatasim Y., Rashad A.A., Shehata M., Gomaa M.R., Mahrous N., Mahmoud S.H., GabAllah M., Abbas H., El Taweel A., Kayed A.E., Kamel M.N., ElSays M., Mahmoud D.B., Kamel M.N., ElSays M., Mahmoud D.B., El-Sheshney R., Kayali G., Ali M.A. FDA-approved drugs with potent in vitro antiviral activity against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2. Pharmaceuticals. 2020;13:443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7761982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33291642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naslednikova I.O., Konenkov V.I., Ryazantseva N.V., Novitskii V.V., Tkachenko S.B., Zima A.P., Avdoshina V.V., Beloborodova E.I., Beloborodova E.V., Dortman V.V. Role of genetically determined production of immunoregulatory cytokines in immunopathogenesis of chronic viral hepatitides. Bull. Exp. Biol. Med. 2007;143:706–712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18239807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omosa L.K., Midiwo J.O., Kuete V. In: Pages 425–435 Medicinal Spices and Vegetables From Africa: Therapeutic Potential Against Metabolic, Inflammatory, Infectious and Systemic Diseases. Kuete V, editor. Academic Press; San Diego, CA: 2017. Chapter-19 Curcuma longa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou X., Mao S., Cao J., Ma Y., Ma G., Cheng A., Wang M., Zhu D., Chen S., Jia R., Liu M., Sun K., Yang Q., Wu Y., Chen X. The neglected avian hepatotropic virus induces acute and chronic hepatitis in ducks: an alternative model for hepatology. Oncotarget. 2017;8:1851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5669852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29137226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panahi Y., Khalili N., Sahebi E., Namazi S., Simental-Mendía L.E., Majeed M., Sahebkar A. Effects of curcuminoids plus piperine on glycemic, hepatic and inflammatory biomarkers in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Drug Res. 2018;68:403–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29458218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peter A.E., Sandeep B.V., Rao B.G., Kalpana V.L. Calming the Storm: natural immunosuppressants as adjuvants to target the cytokine storm in COVID-19. Front. Pharmacol. 2021;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7941276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33708109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrusevska M., Atanasovska E., Zendelovska D., Eftimov A., Spasovska K. In: Chemokines Updates. Şentürk M., editor. IntechOpen; London, United Kingdom: 2022. Alteration of cytokines level and oxidative stress parameters in COVID-19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahardjo B., Widjajanto E., Sujuti H., Keman K. Curcumin decreased level of proinflammatory cytokines in monocyte cultures exposed to preeclamptic plasma by affecting the transcription factors NF-κB and PPAR-γ. Biomark. Med. 2014;6:105–115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjbar A., Gholami L., Ghasemi H., Kheiripour N. EEffects of nano-curcumin and curcumin on the oxidant and antioxidant system of the liver mitochondria in aluminum phosphide-induced experimental toxicity Effects of nano-curcumin and curcumin on the oxidant and antioxidant system of the liver mitochondria in aluminum phosphide-induced experimental toxicity. Nanomed. J. 2020;7:58–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reda F.M., El-Saadony M.T., Elnesr S.S., Alagawany M., Tufarelli V. Effect of dietary supplementation of biological curcumin nanoparticles on growth and carcass traits, antioxidant status, immunity and caecal microbiota of Japanese quails. Animals. 2020;10:754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7277682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32357410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz de Porras V., Figols M., Font A., Pardina E. Curcumin as a hepatoprotective agent against chemotherapy-induced liver injury. Life Sci. 2023;332</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37741319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarzi-Puttini P., Giorgi V., Sirotti S., Marotto D., Ardizzone S., Rizzardini G., Antinori S., Galli M. Review COVID-19, cytokines and immunosuppression: what can we learn from severe acute respiratory syndrome? Clin. Exp. Rheumatol. 2020;38:337–342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu K., Funamoto M., Sunagawa Y., Shimizu S., Katanasaka Y., Miyazaki Y., Wada H., Hasegawa K., Morimoto T. Anti-inflammatory action of curcumin and its use in the treatment of lifestyle-related diseases. Eur. Cardiol. 2019;14:117–122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6659038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31360234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoba G., Joy D., Joseph T., Majeed M., Rajendran R., Srinivas P.S. Influence of piperine on the pharmacokinetics of curcumin in animals and human volunteers. Planta. Med. 1998;64:353–356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9619120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh D., Srinivasan K. Tissue distribution and elimination of capsaicin, piperine and curcumin following oral intake in rats. Indian J. Med. Res. 2010;131:682–691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20516541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suvarna K.S., Layton C., Bancroft J.D. 8th ed. Elsevier; Amsterdam, the Netherlands: 2019. Pages 584 in Bancroft's Theory and Practice of Histological Techniques E-Book.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S., Le T.Q., Kurihara N., Chida J., Cisse Y., Yano M., Kido H. Influenza virus-cytokine-protease cycle in the pathogenesis of vascular hyperpermeability in severe influenza. J. Infect. Dis. 2010;202:991–1001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20731583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen H., Han L., Zhang X., Lian C., Zhao L., Si C., Chen H. Duck hepatitis A virus (DHAV) genotype definition: comment on the article by Cha et al. Vet. Microbiol. 2014;170:462–464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24636163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia X., Cheng A., Wang M., Ou X., Sun D., Zhang S., Mao S., Yang Q., Tian B., Wu Y., Huang J., Gao Q., Jia R., Chen S., Liu M., Zhao X.X., Zhu D., Yu Y., Zhang L. DHAV 3CD targets IRF7 and RIG-I proteins to block the type I interferon upstream signaling pathway. Vet. Res. 2023;54:5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9878786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36703166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie J., Wang M., Cheng A., Zhao X.X., Liu M., Zhu D., Chen S., Jia R., Yang Q., Wu Y., Zhang S. Cytokine storms are primarily responsible for the rapid death of ducklings infected with duck hepatitis A virus type 1. Sci. Rep. 2018;8:6596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5920089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29700351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong W., Chen Y., Wang Y., Liu J. Roles of the antioxidant properties of icariin and its phosphorylated derivative in the protection against duck virus hepatitis. BMC Vet. Res. 2014;10:226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4177705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25244948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang M., Cheng A., Wang M., Xing H. Development and application of a one-step real-time Taqman RT-PCR assay for detection of Duck hepatitis virus type1. J. Virol. Methods. 2008;153:55–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18611411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Q., Wang B., Mao J. The pathogenesis and treatment of the “Cytokine Storm” in COVID-19. J. Infect. 2020;80:607–613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32283152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan S., Jiang S.C., Zhang Z.W., Fu Y.F., Hu J., Li Z.L. Quantification of cytokine storms during virus infections. Front. Immunol. 2021;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8165266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34079547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai S.S., Ruan D., Zhu Y.W., Li M.C., Ye H., Wang W.C., Yang L. Protective effect of curcumin on ochratoxin A-induced liver oxidative injury in duck is mediated by modulating lipid metabolism and the intestinal microbiota. Poult. Sci. 2020;99:1124–1134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7587726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32036964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai W.J., Zhang Z.B., Xu N.N., Guo Y.F., Qiu C., Li C.Y., Deng G.Z., Guo M.Y. Piperine plays an anti-inflammatory role in Staphylococcus aureus endometritis by inhibiting activation of NF-B and MAPK pathways in mice. Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med. 2016;2016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4880693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27293467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Cao C., Qu Z., Zhang W., Liu Y., Qi H., Hao C., Zhang W., Gao M., Wang J., Ma B. Pathogenicity of duck hepatitis A virus type 3 and innate immune responses of the ducklings to virulent DHAV-3. Mol. Immunol. 2018;95:30–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29407574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Paget M., Wang C., Zhu Z., Zheng H. Innate immune evasion by picornaviruses. Eur. J. Immunol. 2020;50:1268–1282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32767562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Wang X., Vikash V., Ye Q., Wu D., Liu Y., Dong W. ROS and ROS-mediated cellular signaling. Oxid. Med. Cell. Longev. 2016;2016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4779832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26998193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>