<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38258311</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Study on the epidemiological characteristics of enterovirus among pediatric patients in Hangzhou, China: A comparison between the pre-COVID-19, COVID-19 pandemic, and post-COVID-19 periods.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29412</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29412</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29412</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Nonpharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) not only reduce the prevalence of this disease among children but also influence the transmission of other viruses. This retrospective study investigated the impact of NPIs on human enterovirus (HEV) infection in children diagnosed with hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) or herpangina (HA) in Hangzhou, China. We collected and analyzed the laboratory results and clinical data of children diagnosed with HFMD or HA during the following periods: pre-COVID-19 (January 2019 to December 2019), the COVID-19 pandemic (January 2020 to December 2022), and post-COVID-19 (January to December 2023). A total of 41 742 specimens that met the inclusion criteria were obtained, of which 1998 (4.79%) tested positive for enterovirus. In comparison to those in the pre-COVID-19 period, which had 695 (5.63%) HEV-positive specimens, the numbers dramatically decreased to 69 (1.19%), 398 (5.12%), and 112 (1.58%) in 2020, 2021, and 2022, respectively, but significantly increased to 724 (8.27%) in 2023. Seasonal peaks of infections occurred in May, June, July, and August each year, with the total detection rate ranging from 2019 to 2023 being 9.41% in May, 22.47% in June, 28.23% in July, and 12.16% in August, respectively. The difference in the detection rates of HEV infection between males and females was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.005), with 5.11% (1221/23 898) of males and 4.35% (777/17 844) of females testing positive, resulting in a male-to-female positive ratio of 1.57:1. Among the age groups, 11.25% (378/3360) of the children aged 3-5 years had the highest detection rate, which steadily decreased with increasing or decreasing age. The detection of HEV indicated that &gt;95% of the viruses were other types than the previously commonly reported enterovirus 71 (EV-A71) and coxsackievirus A16 (CV-A16). In conclusion, NPIs for COVID-19 may be effective at reducing the transmission of HEV. However, with the relaxation of NPIs, the detection rate of HEVs increased slowly to a certain extent. Active awareness and surveillance of the epidemiological characteristics of HEV are essential for preventing, controlling, and managing the development of HFMD and HA, as well as contributing to the development of a multivalent HFMD vaccine.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Yanhong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9825-5698</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Jianming</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nie</LastName><ForeName>Wenjian</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tian</LastName><ForeName>Dandan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7540-4072</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ye</LastName><ForeName>Qing</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6756-0630</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, National Clinical Research Center for Child Health, National Children's Regional Medical Center, The Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000956">Antigens, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000956" MajorTopicYN="N">Antigens, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hand, foot, and mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">herpangina</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38258311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China. National Health Commission Press Conference. 2022. http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/zhengcwj/202212/6630916374874368b9fea6c2253289e1.shtml</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding D, Zhang R. China's COVID-19 control strategy and its impact on the global pandemic. Front Public Health. 2022;10:857003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao H, Shu W, Li M, et al. Social distancing among medical students during the 2019 coronavirus disease pandemic in China: disease awareness, anxiety disorder, depression, and behavioral activities. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(14):5047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Pan L, Tang S, Ji JS, Shi X. Mask use during COVID-19: a risk adjusted strategy. Environ Pollut. 2020;266(Pt 1):115099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei H, Wu X, Wang X, et al. Different transmission dynamics of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) and influenza suggest the relative efficiency of isolation/quarantine and social distancing against COVID-19 in China. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73(11):e4305-e4311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiu NC, Chi H, Tai YL, et al. Impact of wearing masks, hand hygiene, and social distancing on influenza, enterovirus, and all-cause pneumonia during the coronavirus pandemic: retrospective national epidemiological surveillance study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22(8):e21257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh DY, Buda S, Biere B, et al. Trends in respiratory virus circulation following COVID-19-targeted nonpharmaceutical interventions in Germany, January - September 2020: analysis of national surveillance data. Lancet Reg Health - Europe. 2021;6:100112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marriott D, Beresford R, Mirdad F, et al. Concomitant marked decline in prevalence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and other respiratory viruses among symptomatic patients following public health interventions in Australia: data from St Vincent's Hospital and associated screening clinics, Sydney, NSW. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72(10):649.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P, Xu M, Lu L, et al. The changing pattern of common respiratory and enteric viruses among outpatient children in Shanghai, China: two years of the COVID-19 pandemic. J Med Virol. 2022;94(10):4696-4703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung AKC, Lam JM, Barankin B, Leong KF, Hon KL. Hand, foot, and mouth disease: a narrative review. Recent Adv Inflamm Allergy Drug Discov. 2022;16(2):77-95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Li XW, Liu QB, et al. Diagnosis and treatment of herpangina: Chinese expert consensus. World J Pediatr. 2020;16(2):129-134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posovszky C, Buderus S, Classen M, Lawrenz B, Keller KM, Koletzko S. Acute infectious gastroenteritis in infancy and childhood. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2020;117(37):615-624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Gao H, Zhang Q, et al. Large outbreak of herpangina in children caused by enterovirus in summer of 2015 in Hangzhou, China. Sci Rep. 2016;6:35388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Cao J, Ye Q. Nonpharmaceutical interventions against the COVID-19 pandemic significantly decreased the spread of enterovirus in children. J Med Virol. 2022;94(8):3581-3588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo J, Cao Z, Liu H. Epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease and the genetic characteristics of Coxsackievirus A16 in Taiyuan, Shanxi, China from 2010 to 2021. Front Cell Infect Microbiol, 2022;12:1040414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li XW, Ni X, Qian SY, et al. Chinese guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of hand, foot and mouth disease (2018 edition). World J Pediatr. 2018;14(5):437-447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saguil A, Kane SF, Lauters R, Mercado MG. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease: rapid evidence review. Am Fam Physician. 2019;100(7):408-414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akpolat ND, Karaca N. Nail changes secondary to hand-foot-mouth disease. Turk J Pediatr. 2016;58(3):287-290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Principi N. Hand, foot and mouth disease: current knowledge on clinical manifestations, epidemiology, aetiology and prevention. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2018;37(3):391-398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Repass GL, Palmer WC, Stancampiano FF. Hand, foot, and mouth disease: identifying and managing an acute viral syndrome. Cleve Clin J Med. 2014;81(9):537-543.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun T, Li D, Dai X, et al. Local immune dysregulation and subsequent inflammatory response contribute to pulmonary edema caused by Enterovirus infection in mice. J Med Virol. 2023;95(2):e28454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabenau HF, Richter M, Doerr HW. Hand, foot and mouth disease: seroprevalence of Coxsackie A16 and Enterovirus 71 in Germany. Med Microbiol Immunol. 2010;199(1):45-51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Zhang X, Chen X, et al. Epidemiology of childhood enterovirus infections in Hangzhou, China. Virol J. 2015;12:58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Liu F, Chang L, et al. Molecular epidemiology and clinical characteristics of enteroviruses associated HFMD in Chengdu, China, 2013-2022. Virol J. 2023;20(1):202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin DA, Spieker AJ, Perez A, et al. Circulation of rhinoviruses and/or enteroviruses in pediatric patients with acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(2):e2254909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Q, Wang D. Epidemiological changes of common respiratory viruses in children during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Med Virol. 2022;94(5):1990-1997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Guo X, Zhao N, et al. Effects of the enhanced public health intervention during the COVID-19 epidemic on respiratory and gastrointestinal infectious diseases in China. J Med Virol. 2022;94(5):2201-2211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakatani H. Aging and shrinking population: the looming demographic challenges of super-aged and super-low fertility society starting from Asia. Global Health Med. 2023;5(5):257-263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Q, Wang A, Song X, et al. Fertility intentions to have a second or third child among the childbearing-age population in Central China under China's three-child policy: a cross-sectional study. J Glob Health. 2023;13:04072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Zhou Y, Cheng Y, et al. Effectiveness of EV-A71 vaccination in prevention of paediatric hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with EV-A71 virus infection requiring hospitalisation in Henan, China, 2017-18: a test-negative case-control study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2019;3(10):697-704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu FC, Meng FY, Li JX, et al. Efficacy, safety, and immunology of an inactivated alum-adjuvant enterovirus 71 vaccine in children in China: a multicentre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2013;381(9882):2024-2032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu F, Xu W, Xia J, et al. Efficacy, safety, and immunogenicity of an enterovirus 71 vaccine in China. N Engl J Med. 2014;370(9):818-828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimmis BD, Downing C, Tyring S. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6 on the rise. Cutis. 2018;102(5):353-356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai K, Wang Y, Guo Z, et al. Clinical characteristics and managements of severe hand, foot and mouth disease caused by enterovirus A71 and coxsackievirus A16 in Shanghai, China. BMC Infect Dis. 2019;19(1):285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang CY, Liu CC. Recent development of enterovirus A vaccine candidates for the prevention of hand, foot, and mouth disease. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2018;17(9):819-831.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoa-Tran TN, Dao ATH, Nguyen AT, et al. Coxsackieviruses A6 and A16 associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease in Vietnam, 2008-2017: essential information for rational vaccine design. Vaccine. 2020;38(52):8273-8285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Ge W, Yan J. Analysis of the epidemiologic characteristics of children with hand, foot and mouth disease in China. Iran J Public Health. 2023;52(4):773-779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang P, Goggins WB, Chan EYY. Hand, foot and mouth disease in Hong Kong: a time-series analysis on its relationship with weather. PLoS ONE. 2016;11(8):e0161006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tseng FC, Huang HC, Chi CY, et al. Epidemiological survey of enterovirus infections occurring in Taiwan between 2000 and 2005: analysis of sentinel physician surveillance data. J Med Virol. 2007;79(12):1850-1860.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Ding J, Cao J, Huang Q, Hong C, Yang B. Epidemiological and etiological characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Wuhan, China from 2012 to 2013: outbreaks of coxsackieviruses A10. J Med Virol. 2015;87(6):954-960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu FC, Liang ZL, Meng FY, et al. Retrospective study of the incidence of HFMD and seroepidemiology of antibodies against EV71 and CoxA16 in prenatal women and their infants. PLoS ONE. 2012;7(5):e37206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SM, Ho TS, Lin HC, Lei HY, Wang JR, Liu CC. Reemerging of enterovirus 71 in Taiwan: the age impact on disease severity. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2012;31(6):1219-1224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu P, Ji W, Li D, et al. Current status of hand-foot-and-mouth disease. J Biomed Sci. 2023;30(1):15.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>