<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38341981</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0291</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>196</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Marine environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mar Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive analysis and assessment of exposure to enteric viruses and bacteria in shellfish.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>106404</StartPage><MedlinePgn>106404</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.marenvres.2024.106404</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-1136(24)00065-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Shellfish species, including oysters, clams, and mussels, are extensively cultured in coastal waters. Its location is determined by factors such as nutrient availability, water temperature, tidal cycle, and the presence of contaminants such as Escherichia coli and enteric viruses. With the expansion and intensification of human activities at vicinities, the presence of anthropogenic contaminants has increased, threatening shellfish farms and consumer safety give the prevalent consumption of raw shellfish. This literature review aims to provide a comprehensive analysis of the dietary exposure and assess the risk associated with enteric viruses and bacteria detected in shellfish. The predominant bacteria and viruses detected in shellfish are reported, and the potential interrelation is discussed. The main characteristics of each contaminant and shellfish were reviewed for a more comprehensive understanding. To facilitate a direct estimation of exposure, the estimated daily intake (EDI) of bacteria was calculated based on the average levels of E. coli in shellfish, as reported in the literature. The mean daily ingestion of seafood in each of the five continents was considered. Asia exhibited the highest intake of contaminants, with an average of ±5.6 E. coli units/day.kg body weight in cockles. Simulations were conducted using recommended shellfish consumption levels established by state agencies, revealing significantly lower (p &lt; 0.01) EDI for all continents compared to estimations based on recommended levels. This indicates a higher risk associated with healthy shellfish ingestion, potentially leading to increased intoxication incidents with a change in dietary habits. To promote a healthier lifestyle through increased shellfish consumptions, it is imperative to reduce the exposure of shellfish species to bacteria and enteric viruses. The conventional use of E. coli as the sole indicator for consumption safety and water quality in shellfish farms has been deemed insufficient. Instances where shellfish met E. coli limits established by state agencies were often found to be contaminated with human enteric viruses. Therefore, a holistic approach considering the entire production chain is necessary to support the shellfish industry and ensure food safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fehrenbach</LastName><ForeName>Gustavo Waltzer</ForeName><Initials>GW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Materials Research Institute, Technological University of the Shannon, Midlands Campus, N37 HD68, Athlone, Ireland. Electronic address: gustavo.fehrenbach@tus.ie.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Murphy</LastName><ForeName>Emma</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Materials Research Institute, Technological University of the Shannon, Midlands Campus, N37 HD68, Athlone, Ireland; LIFE - Health and Biosciences Research Institute, Technological University of the Shannon, Midwest Campus, V94 EC5T, Limerick, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pogue</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Post-Graduate Program in Genomic Sciences and Biotechnology, Catholic University of Brasilia, 71966-700, Brasilia, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carter</LastName><ForeName>Frank</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Coney Island Shellfish Ltd., F91 YH56, Sligo, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Clifford</LastName><ForeName>Eoghan</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Engineering, National University of Ireland Galway, H91 HX31, Galway, Ireland; Ryan Institute, National University of Ireland Galway, H91 HX31, Galway, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Major</LastName><ForeName>Ian</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Materials Research Institute, Technological University of the Shannon, Midlands Campus, N37 HD68, Athlone, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Mar Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9882895</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-1136</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004926" MajorTopicYN="N">Escherichia coli</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012758" MajorTopicYN="N">Shellfish</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049872" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bivalvia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017747" MajorTopicYN="N">Seafood</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bacteria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Exposure assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Seafood safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Seawater contamination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viruses</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38341981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.marenvres.2024.106404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-1136(24)00065-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>