<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38333447</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diagnostic Accuracy of Cerebrospinal Fluid Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction Panel Testing in Patients With Suspected Central Nervous System Infections: A Multi-Center Study in the United Arab Emirates.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e51906</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e51906</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e51906</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.51906</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Delays in diagnosis and treatment of central nervous system (CNS) infections can lead to significant morbidity and mortality among children and adults. Prior antibiotic treatment is a major hurdle to accurate diagnosis due to falsely negative cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) cultures in partially treated patients. Increasingly, molecular diagnostic methods using multiplex polymerase chain reaction (mPCR) testing on CSF samples are being utilized in clinical practice for timely and accurate diagnosis. However, there is no data regarding the diagnostic accuracy or clinical impact of CSF mPCR testing in the Middle East region. We sought to compare the diagnostic accuracy of an automated mPCR CSF panel with routine CSF culture, the current gold standard, in the United Arab Emirates (UAE).  Methods This single-gated, multi-center, diagnostic accuracy study included patients from birth onwards who were admitted to any of the three participating hospitals with an initial diagnosis of meningitis or encephalitis, between January 2017 and March 2021, and had CSF samples collected for mPCR and culture. Sociodemographic, clinical, and molecular data were collected for all. Results A total of 353 CSF samples were collected from patients from 0-90 years old hospitalized for suspected CNS infection. Children constituted 51% of the study population, and males were slightly over-represented (55.2%). Pathogens were detected by mPCR in 78 (22%) CSF samples, of which 19 (24%) were bacteria and 59 (76%) were viruses. No fungal pathogens were detected. Enteroviruses were the most prevalent CNS pathogen among our cohort (40%), followed by <i>herpes simplex virus type 2</i> (HSV-2) (12.5%). Children constituted 69% of positive samples for enterovirus, while HSV-2 was exclusively detected among adults. Using CSF culture as the diagnostic gold standard, the mPCR panel demonstrated high specificity (100%) and sensitivity (96.3%) in diagnosing CNS infection among all age groups. mPCR testing demonstrated a high overall percentage of agreement (OPA) with CSF culture (98.9%). Patients with bacterial meningitis had a significantly longer hospitalization (p=0.004) and duration of antibiotic therapy (p=0.001) compared to those with viral meningitis. Three CSF samples were negative on mPCR testing but positive on culture. These pathogens included: methicillin-sensitive <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i>(MSSA)<i>, Bacillus cereus, </i>and <i>Mycobacterium Tuberculosis</i> (MTB). In addition, 13 patients had negative CSF cultures but tested positive on CSF mPCR. These pathogens included <i>Streptococcus pneumoniae</i> (seven patients), <i>Haemophilus influenzae</i> (three patients), <i>Streptococcus agalactiae</i> (two patients), and <i>Escherichia coli</i> (one patient). All discordant results were confirmed by reviewing the patient's clinical presentation, CSF analysis, clinical course, and final diagnosis. Conclusion CSF mPCR panel is a highly sensitive and specific diagnostic tool for the diagnosis of CNS infections among all age groups in the UAE. Routine use of CSF mPCR panels can decrease healthcare costs by reducing the length of stay and can also aid antibiotic stewardship efforts by reducing antibiotic overuse in patients with viral CSF infections. CSF culture and mPCR complement each other by identifying CNS pathogens in patients with prior antibiotic exposure who would otherwise be missed if relying on CSF culture alone. However, concomitant CSF culture samples should be sent to avoid missing unusual CNS pathogens.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ghoweba et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghoweba</LastName><ForeName>Yousra</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics, Mohammed Bin Rashid University Of Medicine and Health Sciences, Dubai, ARE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Safizadeh Shabestari</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Ali</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Mohammed Bin Rashid University Of Medicine and Health Sciences, Dubai, ARE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malik</LastName><ForeName>Zainab A</ForeName><Initials>ZA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics and Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Mohammed Bin Rashid University of Medicine and Health Sciences, Dubai, ARE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics and Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Genesis Healthcare, Dubai, ARE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cns</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">csf</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">encephalitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meningitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">middle east</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mpcr</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38333447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10851033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.51906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Progress and challenges in bacterial meningitis: a review. Hasbun R. JAMA. 2022;328:2147–2154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36472590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute bacterial meningitis. Wall EC, Chan JM, Gil E, Heyderman RS. Curr Opin Neurol. 2021;34:386–395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7610733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33767093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dilemmas in the diagnosis of acute community-acquired bacterial meningitis. Brouwer MC, Thwaites GE, Tunkel AR, van de Beek D. Lancet. 2012;380:1684–1692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23141617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global and regional risk of disabling sequelae from bacterial meningitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Edmond K, Clark A, Korczak VS, Sanderson C, Griffiths UK, Rudan I. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10:317–328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20417414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>When to include a lumbar puncture in the evaluation for neonatal sepsis. Aleem S, Greenberg RG. Neoreviews. 2019;20:0–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31261050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The BioFire® FilmArray® Meningitis/Encephalitis (ME) Panel. 2021. https://www.biofiredx.com/products/the-filmarray-panels/filmarrayme/ https://www.biofiredx.com/products/the-filmarray-panels/filmarrayme/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prospective study of a real-time PCR that is highly sensitive, specific, and clinically useful for diagnosis of meningococcal disease in children. Bryant PA, Li HY, Zaia A, Griffith J, Hogg G, Curtis N, Carapetis JR. J Clin Microbiol. 2004;42:2919–2925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC446275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15243039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multicenter evaluation of BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel for detection of bacteria, viruses, and yeast in cerebrospinal fluid specimens. Leber AL, Everhart K, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. J Clin Microbiol. 2016;54:2251–2261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5005480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27335149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of cerebrospinal fluid syndromic testing in the management of children with suspected central nervous system infection. Posnakoglou L, Siahanidou T, Syriopoulou V, Michos A. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2020;39:2379–2386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32683594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evaluation of the BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel for the detection of bacteria and yeast in Chinese children. Du B, Hua C, Xia Y, et al. Ann Transl Med. 2019;7:437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6803227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31700873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapid and accurate diagnosis of acute pyogenic meningitis due to Streptococcus Pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae type B and Neisseria meningitidis using a multiplex PCR assay. Seth R, Murthy PS, Sistla S, Subramanian M, Tamilarasu K. J Clin Diagn Res. 2017;11:0–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5713747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29207725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparative evaluation of the FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis molecular panel in a pediatric population. Graf EH, Farquharson MV, Cárdenas AM. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2017;87:92–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27771208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effect of antibiotic pretreatment on cerebrospinal fluid profiles of children with bacterial meningitis. Nigrovic LE, Malley R, Macias CG, et al. Pediatrics. 2008;122:726–730.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18829794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic accuracy of cerebrospinal fluid procalcitonin in bacterial meningitis patients with empiric antibiotic pretreatment. Li W, Sun X, Yuan F, et al. J Clin Microbiol. 2017;55:1193–1204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5377847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28179405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between preadmission oral antibiotic therapy and cerebrospinal fluid findings and sequelae caused by Haemophilus influenzae type B meningitis. Kaplan SL, Smith EO, Wills C, Feigin RD. Pediatr Infect Dis. 1986;5:626–632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3491977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The clinical impact of the FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis (ME) panel on antimicrobial utilization in a tertiary hospital setting. Walker M, Taylor K, Beaulieu R 3rd, Laurent M, Hamer D, O'Neal C. Am J Med Sci. 2021;361:550–552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33051025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Analysis of the clinical impact of the BioFire FilmArray meningitis encephalitis panel on antimicrobial use and duration of therapy at an academic medical center. Markovich K, Wingler MJ, Stover KR, Barber KE, Wagner JL, Cretella DA. Diseases. 2022;10:110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9680255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36412604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerebrospinal fluid analysis with the BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis molecular panel reduces length of hospital stay in patients with suspected central nervous system infections. DiDiodato G, Bradbury N. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2019;6:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6483125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31041338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Test characteristics and interpretation of cerebrospinal fluid gram stain in children. Neuman MI, Tolford S, Harper MB. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2008;27:309–313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18316992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>