<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38323723</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>104</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Isolation and identification of active components from Grifola frondosa and its anti-EV71 virus effect.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>4453</StartPage><EndPage>4464</EndPage><MedlinePgn>4453-4464</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13332</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">It is reported that anti-enterovirus 71 (EV71) drugs have some side effects on human health. Notably, fungi plays a crucial role in promoting human health and anti-virus. Grifola frondosa is a type of large medicinal and edible fungi, rich in active substances. The present study aimed to investigate the anti-EV71 effect of G. frondosa and the potential active substances.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In the present study, the water extract of G. frondosa was subjected to ethanol precipitation to obtain the water-extracted supernatant of G. frondosa (GFWS) and water-extracted precipitation of G. frondosa. Their inhibitory effects on EV71 virus were studied based on a cell model. The results showed that GFWS had stronger security and anti-EV71 effects. In addition, the chemical constituents of GFWS were identified by ultra-high performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry, which were selected for further separation and purification. Three compounds, N-butylaniline, succinic acid and l-tryptophan, were isolated from GFWS by NMR spectroscopy. It is noteworthy that N-butylaniline and l-tryptophan were isolated and identified from the G. frondosa fruiting bodies for the first time. Our study found that l-tryptophan has anti-EV71 virus activity, which reduced EV71-induced apoptosis and significantly inhibited the replication process after virus adsorption. Furthermore, it could also bind to capsid protein VP1 to prevent the virus from attaching to the cells.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">l-tryptophan was an inhibitor of the EV71 virus, which could be used in infant nutrition and possibly provide a new drug to treat hand, foot and mouth disease. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiong</LastName><ForeName>Wenyu</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4454-075X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Engineering, South China University of Technology, Guangzhou, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoqin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Junqiang</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhong</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ge</LastName><ForeName>Xiaodong</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Marine and Bioengineering, Yancheng Institute of Technology, Yancheng, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6219-3093</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Engineering Research Center of JUNCAO Technology, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeng</LastName><ForeName>Feng</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8629-8578</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Engineering Research Center of Fujian Subtropical Fruit and Vegetable Processing, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Engineering Research Center of JUNCAO Technology, Fuzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2023YFD1000500</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>XKJC-712021030</GrantID><Agency>Interdisciplinary Integration to Promote the High-quality Development Projects of Juncao Science and Industry</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2020N3002</GrantID><Agency>Regional Development Project of Fujian Science and Technology Department</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021I0008</GrantID><Agency>Fujian Provincial Department of Science and Technology Foreign Cooperation Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>8DUH1N11BX</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014364">Tryptophan</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>059QF0KO0R</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014867">Water</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D048691" MajorTopicYN="Y">Grifola</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014364" MajorTopicYN="N">Tryptophan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014867" MajorTopicYN="N">Water</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002851" MajorTopicYN="N">Chromatography, High Pressure Liquid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">l‐tryptopha</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus 71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Grifola frondosa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Isolation and identification</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38323723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Nassef C, Ziemer C and Morrell DS, Hand‐foot‐and‐mouth disease: a new look at a classic viral rash. Curr Opin Pediatr 27:486–491 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Tong A, Gao X, Yuan S, Zhong R and Zhao C, Treponema primitia α1‐2‐fucosyltransferase‐catalyzed one‐pot multienzyme synthesis of fucosylated oligosaccharide lacto‐N‐fucopentaose I with antiviral activity against enterovirus 71. Food Chem X 14:100273 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Zeng J, Zhang X, Gan Z, Fan J, Chen Y et al., Short‐term dynamic changes in neutralizing antibodies against enterovirus 71 after vaccination. Hum Vaccines Immunother 16:1595–1601 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du ZC, Huang Y, Lawrence WR, Xu J, Yang Z, Lu J et al., Leading enterovirus genotypes causing hand, foot, and mouth disease in Guangzhou, China: relationship with climate and vaccination against EV71. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 18:292 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beigel J and Bray M, Current and future antiviral therapy of severe seasonal and avian influenza. Antiviral Res 78:91–102 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng Y, Yin S, Jing X and Zheng Y, Design, synthesis, and antiviral activities evaluation of novel quinazoline derivatives containing sulfonamide moiety. Heterocycl Commun 29:20220160 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhang G and Ling J, Medicinal fungi with antiviral effect. Molecules 27:4457 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripodi F, Falletta E, Leri M, Angeloni C, Beghelli D, Giusti L et al., Anti‐aging and neuroprotective properties of Grifola frondosa and Hericium erinaceus extracts. Nutrients 14:4368 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Zhu LF, Qi XP, Zhou T, Li Y, Cai M et al., Immunostimulatory and antioxidant activities of the selenized polysaccharide from edible Grifola frondosa. Food Sci Nutr 10:1289–1298 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu JY, Siu KC and Geng P, Bioactive ingredients and medicinal values of Grifola frondosa (maitake). Foods 10:95 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan YY, Zeng F, Guo WL, Li TT, Jia RB, Huang ZR et al., Effect of Grifola frondosa 95% ethanol extract on lipid metabolism and gut microbiota composition in high‐fat diet‐fed rats. Food Funct 9:6268–6278 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo WL, Deng JC, Pan YY, Xu JX, Hong JL, Shi FF et al., Hypoglycemic and hypolipidemic activities of Grifola frondosa polysaccharides and their relationships with the modulation of intestinal microflora in diabetic mice induced by high‐fat diet and streptozotocin. Int J Biol Macromol 153:1231–1240 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao C, Gao L, Wang C, Liu B, Jin Y and Xing Z, Structural characterization and antiviral activity of a novel heteropolysaccharide isolated from Grifola frondosa against enterovirus 71. Carbohyd Polym 144:382–389 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He JQ, Xiong WY, Zhao LN, Liu B and Huang Y, Anti‐α‐glucosidase, anti‐proliferative and anti‐enterovirus 71 activity of secondary metabolites identified from Grifola frondosa. Plant Foods Hum Nutr 78:783–789 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omnia HA, Eman MO, John RF, Yehia DS, Marie PS, Nodwell JR et al., Metabolomics analysis and biological investigation of three Malvaceae plants. Phytochem Analysis 31:204–214 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gustavo M, Fernando ACS and Evaristo JAM, Aging‐related compensated hypogonadism: role of metabolomic analysis in physiopathological and therapeutic evaluation. J Steroid Biochem 183:39–50 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner CE, Elsohly MA and Boeren EG, Constituents of Cannabis sativa L. XVII. a review of the natural constituents. J Nat Pro 43:169–234 (1980).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui C, Xu Y, Jin G, Zong J, Peng C, Cai H et al., Machine learning applications for identify the geographical origin, variety and processing of black tea using 1H NMR chemical fingerprinting. Food Control 148:109686 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie H, Huang SQ, Li XC, Gong J, Wu F, Yin J et al., Identification of compounds from chufa (Eleocharis dulcis) peels with inhibitory acrylamide formation activity. Rev Bras Farmacogn 29:483–487 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchida M, Oyanagi E, Kremenik MJ, Sasaki J and Yano H, Interferon‐beta, but not tumor necrosis factor‐alpha, production in response to poly I: C is maintained despite exhaustive exercise in mice. J Physiol Sci 62:59–62 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimosaki S, Tsurunaga Y, Itamura H and Nakamura M, Anti‐allergic effect of the flavonoid myricitrin from Myrica rubra leaf extracts in vitro and in vivo. J Asian Nat Prod Res 25:374–380 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitsunori N, Keiko I, Hisa M, Yoshida M, Mitani T and Hajime KA, Antiviral and virucidal activities against herpes simplex viruses of umesu phenolics extracted from Japanese apricot. Microbiol Immunol 63:359–366 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho OV, Botelho CV, Ferreira CGT, Ferreira HCC, Santos MR, Diaz MAN et al., In vitro inhibition of canine distemper virus by flavonoids and phenolic acids: implications of structural differences for antiviral design. Res Vet Sci 95:714–724 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma DWL, Seo J, Davidson LA, Callaway ES, Fan Y, Lupton JR et al., n‐3 PUFA alter caveolae lipid composition and resident protein localization in mouse colon. FASEB J 18:1040–1042 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ana RT, Maria IO, Giuseppina N, Giuseppina N, Zucatelli MR and Adelaide FC, Polyunsaturated fatty acids from Phyllocaulis boraceiensis mucus block the replication of influenza virus. Arch microbiol 200:961–970 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long L, Xue C, Shi J, Dong J and Wang L, Efficacy of hepatoprotective agents with or without antiviral drugs on liver function and fibrosis in patients with hepatitis B: a meta‐analysis. Hepat Mon 15:e29052 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC, North TW, Rigg R, Reading C, Higgins J, Leutenegger C et al., 16α‐Bromo‐epiandrosterone therapy modulates experimental feline immunodeficiency virus viremia: initial enhancement leading to long‐term suppression. Vet Immunol Immunopathol 94:133–148 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L and Huang GL, The antiviral activity of polysaccharides and their derivatives. Int J Biol Macromol 115:77–82 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontham V, Ippakayala B and Madhu D, Synthesis of β‐carboline fatty alcohol hybrid molecules and characterization of their biological and antioxidant activities. Arab J Chem 14:103163 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee A and Panda G, Total synthesis of selected bioactive alkaloids, their structure‐function relationships and molecular target interactions: a comparative synthetic analysis of tryptophan originated chiral pool approaches vs other synthons. Results Chem 3:100215 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang B, Jiang L, Wu Z and Dai Z, L‐tryptophan differentially regulated glucose and amino acid transporters in the small intestine of rat challenged with lipopolysaccharide. Animals 12:3045 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambarapu S, Tilwe K, Pandit R, Gaikwad B, Meshram H, Choudhary J et al., Serotonin syndrome masquerading as status epilepticus following ingestion of tranylcypromine and clomipramine and L‐tryptophan: a case report. Ann Indian Acad Neurol 25:960–962 (2022).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>