<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">38308795</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1568-5608</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>32</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Inflammopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Inflammopharmacology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Observational analysis of the immunogenicity and safety of various types of spinal muscular atrophy vaccines.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1025</StartPage><EndPage>1038</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1025-1038</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10787-023-01395-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This study aimed to evaluate the immunogenicity and safety of different types of poliovirus vaccines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A randomized, blinded, single-center, parallel-controlled design was employed, and 360 infants aged ≥ 2 months were selected as study subjects. They were randomly assigned to bOPV group (oral Sabin vaccine) and sIPV group (Sabin strain inactivated polio vaccine), with 180 infants in each group. Adverse reaction events in the vaccinated subjects were recorded. The micro-neutralization test using cell culture was conducted to determine the geometric mean titer (GMT) of neutralizing antibodies against poliovirus types I, II, and III in different groups, and the seroconversion rates were calculated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Both groups exhibited a 100% seropositivity rate after booster immunization. The titers of neutralizing antibodies for the three types were predominantly distributed within the range of 1:128 to 1:512. The fold increase of type I antibodies differed markedly between the two groups (P &lt; 0.05). Moreover, the fold increase of type II and type III antibodies for poliovirus differed slightly between the two groups (P &gt; 0.05). The fourfold increase rate in sIPV group was drastically superior to that in bOPV group (P &lt; 0.05). When comparing the post-immunization GMT levels of type I antibodies in individuals who completed the full course of spinal muscular atrophy vaccination, bOPV group showed greatly inferior levels to sIPV group (P &lt; 0.05). For type II and type III antibodies, individuals in bOPV group demonstrated drastically superior post-immunization GMT levels to those in sIPV group (P &lt; 0.05). The incidence of adverse reactions between the bOPV and sIPV groups differed slightly (P &gt; 0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These findings indicated that both the oral vaccine and inactivated vaccine had good safety and immunogenicity in infants aged ≥ 2 months. The sIPV group generated higher levels of neutralizing antibodies in serum, particularly evident in the post-immunization GMT levels for types II and III.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Switzerland AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Guojuan</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunization Program Department, Daqing Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Daqing, 163000, Heilongjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Guangzhi</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology Department, Daqing People's Hospital, Daqing, 163000, Heilongjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhong</LastName><ForeName>Heng</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-3751-6607</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Endocrinology Department, Heilongjiang Provincial Hospital, Harbin, 150036, Heilongjiang, China. hengzhong@mailfence.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016449">Randomized Controlled Trial</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Inflammopharmacology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9112626</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0925-4692</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D057134">Antibodies, Neutralizing</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000914">Antibodies, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057134" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Neutralizing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000914" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007115" MajorTopicYN="N">Immunization Schedule</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000139" MajorTopicYN="N">chemically induced</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019370" MajorTopicYN="N">Observation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immunogenicity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inactivated vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sabin oral vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Safety</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38308795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10787-023-01395-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10787-023-01395-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Arora M, Lakshmi R (2021) Vaccines - safety in pregnancy. Best Pract Res Clin Obstet Gynaecol 76:23–40</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7992376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bpobgyn.2021.02.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bashorun AO, Badjie Hydara M, Adigweme I, Umesi A, Danso B, Johnson N, Sambou NA, Fofana S, Kanu FJ, Jeyaseelan V, Verma H, Weldon WC, Oberste MS, Sutter RW, Jeffries D, Wathuo M, Mach O, Clarke E (2022) Intradermal administration of fractional doses of the inactivated poliovirus vaccine in a campaign: a pragmatic, open-label, non-inferiority trial in The Gambia. Lancet Glob Health 10:e257–e268</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34951974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00497-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayliss J, Nissen M, Prakash D, Richmond P, Oh KB, Nolan T (2021) Control of vaccine preventable diseases in Australian infants: reviewing a decade of experience with DTPa-HBV-IPV/Hib vaccine. Hum Vaccin Immunother 17:176–190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32573398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2020.1764826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bravo LC, Carlos JC, Gatchalian SR, Montellano MEB, Tabora CFCB, Thierry-Carstensen B, Tingskov PN, Sørensen C, Wachmann H, Bandyopadhyay AS, Nielsen PI, Kusk MV (2020) Immunogenicity and safety of an adjuvanted inactivated polio vaccine, IPV-Al, compared to standard IPV: a phase 3 observer-blinded, randomised, controlled trial in infants vaccinated at 6, 10, 14 weeks and 9 months of age. Vaccine 38:530–538</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31703934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6983932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2019.10.064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR, Sil A, Tadesse BT, Saluja T, Teshome S, Alberto E, Kim DR, Park EL, Park JY, Yang JS, Chinaworapong S, Park J, Jo SK, Chon Y, Yang SY, Ryu JH, Cheong I, Shim KY, Lee Y, Kim H, Lynch JA, Kim JH, Excler JL, Wartel TA, Sahastrabuddhe S (2020) Safety and immunogenicity of Vi-DT conjugate vaccine among 6–23-month-old children: phase II, randomized, dose-scheduling, observer-blind study. EClinicalMedicine 27:100540</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33150320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7599314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR, Gomez-Go GD, Oberdorfer P, Borja-Tabora C, Bravo L, Carlos J, Tangsathapornpong A, Uppala R, Laoprasopwattana K, Yang Y, Han S, Wittawatmongkol O (2022) Safety and immunogenicity of a new inactivated polio vaccine made from sabin strains: a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled, phase 2/3 seamless study. J Infect Dis 226:308–318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33351072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiaa770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chumakov K, Ehrenfeld E, Agol VI, Wimmer E (2021) Polio eradication at the crossroads. Lancet Glob Health 9:e1172–e1175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34118192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00205-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cramer JP, Jimeno J, Han HH, Lin S, Hartmann K, Borkowski A, Sáez-Llorens X (2020) Safety and immunogenicity of experimental stand-alone trivalent, inactivated Sabin-strain polio vaccine formulations in healthy infants: a randomized, observer-blind, controlled phase 1/2 trial. Vaccine 38:5313–5323</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32563609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7347011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.05.081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dakin A, Borrow R, Arkwright PD (2023) A review of the DTaP-IPV-HB-PRP-T Hexavalent vaccine in pediatric patients. Expert Rev Vaccines 22:104–117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36545777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14760584.2023.2161519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Coster I, Leroux-Roels I, Bandyopadhyay AS, Gast C, Withanage K, Steenackers K, De Smedt P, Aerssens A, Leroux-Roels G, Oberste MS, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Weldon WC, Fix A, Konz J, Wahid R, Modlin J, Clemens R, Costa Clemens SA, Bachtiar NS, Van Damme P (2021) Safety and immunogenicity of two novel type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine candidates compared with a monovalent type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine in healthy adults: two clinical trials. Lancet 397:39–50</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33308429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7811203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32541-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leo DE, Cappelli V, Massaro MG, Tosti C, Morgante G (2017) Evaluation of the effects of a natural dietary supplement with cranberry, Noxamicina® and D-mannose in recurrent urinary infections in perimenopausal women. Minerva Ginecol 69:336–341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28608666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhingra MS, Namazova-Baranova L, Arredondo-Garcia JL, Kim KH, Limkittikul K, Jantarabenjakul W, Perminova O, Kobashi IAR, Bae CW, Ojeda J, Park J, Chansinghakul D, B’Chir S, Neveu D, Bonaparte M, Jordanov E (2021) Immunogenicity and safety of a quadrivalent meningococcal tetanus toxoid-conjugate vaccine administered concomitantly with other paediatric vaccines in toddlers: a phase III randomised study. Epidemiol Infect 149:e90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33814028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8080229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268821000698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duintjer Tebbens RJ, Thompson KM (2018) Polio endgame risks and the possibility of restarting the use of oral poliovirus vaccine. Expert Rev Vaccines 17:739–751</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30056767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6168953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14760584.2018.1506333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadlyana E, Dhamayanti M, Tarigan R, Mulia Sari R, Sjafri Bachtiar N, Kartasasmita CB, Rusmil K (2020) Immunogenicity and safety profile of a primary dose of bivalent oral polio vaccine given simultaneously with DTwP-Hb-Hib and inactivated poliovirus vaccine at the 4th visit in Indonesian infants. Vaccine 38:1962–1967</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31982261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.01.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falleiros-Arlant LH, Ayala SEG, Domingues C, Brea J, Colsa-Ranero A (2020) Current status of poliomyelitis in Latin America. Rev Chilena Infectol 37:701–709</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33844811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4067/S0716-10182020000600701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng G, Jiang D, Han W, Xie Z, Jiang Z, Huang L, Wang J, Zhang W, Xu L, Tan J, You W, Cui G, Li C, Wang Y (2023) Safety, immunogenicity, and lot-to-lot consistency of a multidose Sabin strain-based inactivated polio vaccine: a phase III, randomized, blinded, positive-control clinical trial in infants aged 2 months. Int J Infect Dis 130:20–27</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36682682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2023.01.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferlito C, Visco V, Biselli R, Cattaruzza MS, Carreras G, Salerno G, Lista F, Capobianchi MR, Castilletti C, Lapa D, Antonelli G, Gentile M, Sorice M, Riitano G, Lucania G, Riccieri V, Mainiero F, Angeloni A, Lucarelli M, Ferraguti G, Autore A, Lastilla M, Salemi S, Biondo MI, Picchianti-Diamanti A, Caporuscio S, Teloni R, Mariotti S, Nisini R, D’Amelio R (2021) Safety of multiple vaccinations and durability of vaccine-induced antibodies in an Italian military cohort 5 years after immunization. Biomedicines 10:6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35052686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8773007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10010006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukushima S, Nakano T, Shimizu H, Hamada A (2022) Immunogenicity of catch-up immunization with conventional inactivated polio vaccine among Japanese adults. Vaccines (basel) 10:2160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10122160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao S, Wei M, Chu K, Li J, Zhu F (2022) Effects of maternal antibodies in infants on the immunogenicity and safety of inactivated polio vaccine in infants. Hum Vaccin Immunother 18:2050106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35394898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9196670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2022.2050106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD (2020) Release 1, vaccine coverage collaborators (2021) measuring routine childhood vaccination coverage in 204 countries and territories, 1980–2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2020, release 1. Lancet 398:503–521</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Silva M, Rabinovich NR (2021) Some lessons for malaria from the global polio eradication initiative. Malar J 20:210</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33933088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8087877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-021-03690-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haq ZU, Rana MS (2021) Synergized immunization programming: Pakistan’s road to polio eradication. J Glob Health 11:03103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34552719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8442572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7189/jogh.11.03103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaiswal N, Singh S, Agarwal A, Chauhan A, Thumburu KK, Kaur H, Singh M (2019) Equivalent schedules of intradermal fractional dose versus intramuscular full dose of inactivated polio vaccine for prevention of poliomyelitis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 12:CD011780</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31858595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang R, Liu X, Sun X, Wang J, Huang Z, Li C, Li Z, Zhou J, Pu Y, Ying Z, Yin Q, Zhao Z, Zhang L, Lei J, Bao W, Jiang Y, Dou Y, Li J, Yang H, Cai W, Deng Y, Che Y, Shi L, Sun M (2021) Immunogenicity and safety of the inactivated poliomyelitis vaccine made from Sabin strains in a phase IV clinical trial for the vaccination of a large population. Vaccine 39:1463–1471</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33487470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.01.027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juan-Giner A, Kimathi D, Grantz KH, Hamaluba M, Kazooba P, Njuguna P, Fall G, Dia M, Bob NS, Monath TP, Barrett AD, Hombach J, Mulogo EM, Ampeire I, Karanja HK, Nyehangane D, Mwanga-Amumpaire J, Cummings DAT, Bejon P, Warimwe GM, Grais RF (2021) Immunogenicity and safety of fractional doses of yellow fever vaccines: a randomised, double-blind, non-inferiority trial. Lancet 397:119–127</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33422245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7794660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32520-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Xu J, Tan H, Zhang C, Chen J, Ni L, Yun X, Huang Y, Wang W (2020) Safety of pentavalent DTaP-IPV/Hib combination vaccine in post-marketing surveillance in Guangzhou, China, from 2011 to 2017. Int J Infect Dis 99:149–155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32795602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.07.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao G, Li R, Li C, Sun M, Jiang S, Li Y, Mo Z, Xia J, Xie Z, Che Y, Yang J, Yin Z, Wang J, Chu J, Cai W, Zhou J, Wang J, Li Q (2016) Phase 3 trial of a sabin strain-based inactivated poliovirus vaccine. J Infect Dis 214:1728–1734</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27658691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiw433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu B, Cao B, Wang C, Han B, Sun T, Miao Y, Lu Q, Cui F (2022) Immunogenicity and safety of childhood combination vaccines: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Vaccines (basel) 10:472</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35335107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10030472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lohiniva AL, Nurzhynska A, Alhassan H, Shetye M, Ayiku P (2022) Understanding factors influencing polio vaccine uptake in Ghana-developing meaningful community mobilization and engagement strategies in collaboration with religious leaders. Am J Trop Med Hyg 107:1345–1350</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36315999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9768250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.22-0271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorson CL, Rindt H, Shababi M (2010) Spinal muscular atrophy: mechanisms and therapeutic strategies. Hum Mol Genet 19:R111–R118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20392710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2875050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddq147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mangarule S, Palkar S, Mitra M, Ravi MD, Singh R, Moureau A, Jayanth MV, Patel DM, Ravinuthala S, Patnaik BN, Jordanov E, Noriega F (2022) Antibody persistence following administration of a hexavalent DTwP-IPV-HB-PRP∼T vaccine versus separate DTwP-HB-PRP∼T and IPV vaccines at 12–24 months of age and safety and immunogenicity of a booster dose of DTwP-IPV-HB-PRP∼T in healthy infants in India. Vaccine X 11:100190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35899104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9309395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jvacx.2022.100190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansoor I, Eassa HA, Mohammed KHA, Abd El-Fattah MA, Abdo MH, Rashad E, Eassa HA, Saleh A, Amin OM, Nounou MI, Ghoneim O (2022) Microneedle-based vaccine delivery: review of an emerging technology. AAPS PharmSciTech 23:103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35381906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1208/s12249-022-02250-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modlin JF, Bandyopadhyay AS, Sutter R (2021) Immunization against poliomyelitis and the challenges to worldwide poliomyelitis eradication. J Infect Dis 224:S398–S404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34590135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8482017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiaa622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakayama T, Vidor E, Tsuzuki D, Nishina S, Sasaki T, Ishii Y, Mizukami H, Tsuge H (2020) Immunogenicity and safety of a DTaP-IPV/Hib pentavalent vaccine given as primary and booster vaccinations in healthy infants and toddlers in Japan. J Infect Chemother 26:651–659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32307307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2019.11.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS (2018) Progress of polio eradication and containment requirements after eradication. Transfusion 58:3078–3083</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30536438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8963859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/trf.15018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu X, Chen K, Tong L, Shu X, Lü X, Wen H, Deng C (2004) Effects of moxibustion at shenque (CV 8) on serum IL-12 level and NK cell activities in mice with transplanted tumor. J Tradit Chin Med 24:56–58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15119180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sáez-Llorens X, Chan M, DeAntonio R, Petersen T, Olesen C, Jensen JS, Sørensen C, Ekstrand LM, Czort MK, Kristensen HH, Thulstrup N, Christoffersen DB (2022) Persistence of protective anti-poliovirus antibody levels in 4-year-old children previously primed with Picovax®, a trivalent, aluminium-adjuvanted reduced dose inactivated polio vaccine. Vaccine 40:5835–5841</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36064670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9488130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.06.084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebghati M, Khalil A (2021) Uptake of vaccination in pregnancy. Best Pract Res Clin Obstet Gynaecol 76:53–65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33965331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8021457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bpobgyn.2021.03.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma H, Lalwani S, Parekh S, Pujari P, Shewale S, Palkar S, Hanumante N, Gokhale S, Ks J, Kumar R, Sharma I, Gairola S (2022) A phase I, open label, clinical study to assess the safety and immunogenicity of indigenously developed liquid (DTwP-HepB-IPV-Hib) hexavalent combination vaccine in healthy toddlers aged 16–24 months. Hum Vaccin Immunother 18:2146435</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36412272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9746440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2022.2146435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirima SB, Ouedraogo A, Barry N, Siribie M, Tiono A, Nébié I, Konaté A, Berges GD, Diarra A, Ouedraogo M, Bougouma EC, Soulama I, Hema A, Datta S, Liang Y, Rotrosen ET, Tracy JK, Jamka LP, Oshinsky JJ, Pasetti MF, Neuzil KM, Laurens MB (2021a) Safety and immunogenicity of Vi-typhoid conjugate vaccine co-administration with routine 9-month vaccination in Burkina Faso: a randomized controlled phase 2 trial. Int J Infect Dis 108:465–472</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34082090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8298254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.05.061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirima SB, Ouedraogo A, Barry N, Siribie M, Tiono AB, Nébié I, Konaté AT, Berges GD, Diarra A, Ouedraogo M, Soulama I, Hema A, Datta S, Liang Y, Rotrosen ET, Tracy JK, Jamka LP, Neuzil KM, Laurens MB (2021b) Safety and immunogenicity of co-administration of meningococcal type A and measles-rubella vaccines with typhoid conjugate vaccine in children aged 15–23 months in Burkina Faso. Int J Infect Dis 102:517–523</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33176205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7762715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.10.103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sultan MA (2022) Emerging challenges to realizing global polio eradication and their solutions. East Mediterr Health J 28:515–520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26719/emhj.22.045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Xu Y, Tang F, Xiao Y, Wang Z, Wang B, Zhu X, Yang X, Chen H (2022) Immunogenicity and safety of concomitant administration of the chinese inactivated poliovirus vaccine with the diphtheria-tetanus-acellular pertussis (DTaP) vaccine in children: a multicenter, randomized, non-inferiority, controlled trial. Front Immunol 13:905634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35958596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9361845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.905634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed YY (2019) DTaP-IPV-HepB-Hib vaccine (Hexyon®): an updated review of its use in primary and booster vaccination. Paediatr Drugs 21:397–408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31444785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6794236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40272-019-00353-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson KM, Kalkowska DA (2021) Reflections on Modeling Poliovirus Transmission and the Polio Eradication Endgame. Risk Anal 41:229–247</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32339327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/risa.13484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tseha ST (2021) Polio: the disease that reemerged after six years in Ethiopia. Ethiop J Health Sci 31:897–902</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34703190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8512932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood N, Nolan T, Marshall H, Richmond P, Gibbs E, Perrett K, McIntyre P (2018) Immunogenicity and safety of monovalent acellular pertussis vaccine at birth: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Pediatr 172:1045–1052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30208475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6248137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.2349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamoah P, Bangalee V, Oosthuizen F (2020) A review of the safety of vaccines used in routine immunization in Africa. Afr Health Sci 20:227–237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33402911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7750064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/ahs.v20i1.28</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang K, Kim H, Ortiz E, Huoi C, Kang J (2023) Post-marketing safety surveillance of a childhood pentavalent diphtheria-tetanus-acellular pertussis-polio and haemophilus influenzae type B (DTaP-IPV//Hib) vaccine in South Korea. Infect Dis Ther 12:499–511</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36520326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40121-022-00724-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaman K, Bandyopadhyay AS, Hoque M, Gast C, Yunus M, Jamil KM, Mainou BA, Konopka-Anstadt JL, Hendley WS, Vincent A, Clemens R, Clemens SAC, Ross AG, Clemens JD, Tritama E (2023) Evaluation of the safety, immunogenicity, and faecal shedding of novel oral polio vaccine type 2 in healthy newborn infants in Bangladesh: a randomised, controlled, phase 2 clinical trial. Lancet 401:131–139</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36495882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9860215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)02397-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Guo Y, Dong Y, Liu Y, Zhao Y, Yu S, Li S, Wu C, Yang B, Li W, Wei X, Zhang Y, Huang Y, Wang H, Yang X (2022) Safety and immunogenicity of a combined DTacP-sIPV-Hib vaccine in animal models. Hum Vaccin Immunother 18:2160158</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36576263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9891680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2022.2160158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao T, Mo Z, Ying Z, Huang T, Che Y, Li G, Yang X, Sun M, Jiang L, Shi L, Ye H, Zhao Z, Liu X, Li J, Li Y, Li R, Jiang R, Wang J, Fu Y, Ma R, Shi H, Yang H, Li C, Yang J, Li Q (2021) Post hoc analysis of two clinical trials to compare the immunogenicity and safety of different polio immunization schedules in Chinese infants. Ann Transl Med 9:253</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33708880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7940937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21037/atm-20-2537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y, Ying Z, Zou Y, Zhu T, Qian D, Han W, Jiang Y, Jiang Z, Li X, Wang J, Lei J, Xu L, Jiang D, Li C, Liu X (2022) Safety, immunogenicity and lot-to-lot consistency of sabin-strain inactivated poliovirus vaccine in 2-month-old infants: a double-blind. Randomized phase III trial. Vaccines (basel) 10:254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35214712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10020254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>