<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38353496</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>15</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of enterovirus concentration, species identification, and cerebrospinal fluid parameters in patients of different ages with aseptic meningitis in São Paulo, Brazil.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29471</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29471</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29471</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Human enteroviruses (EV) are the most common cause of aseptic meningitis worldwide. Data on EV viral load in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and related epidemiological studies are scarce in Brazil. This study investigated the influence of EV viral load on CSF parameters, as well as identifying the involved species. CSF samples were collected in 2018-2019 from 140 individuals at The Hospital das Clínicas, São Paulo. The EV viral load was determined using real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction, while EV species were identified by 5'UTR region sequencing. Median viral load was 5.72 log<sub>10</sub>  copies/mL and did not differ by subjects' age and EV species. Pleocytosis was observed in 94.3% of cases, with the highest white blood cell (WBC) counts in younger individuals. Viral load and WBC count were correlated in children (p = 0.0172). Elevated lactate levels were observed in 60% of cases and correlated with the viral load in preteen-teenagers (p = 0.0120) and adults (p = 0.0184). Most individuals had normal total protein levels (70.7%), with higher in preteen-teenagers and adults (p &lt; 0.0001). By sequencing, 8.2% were identified as EV species A and 91.8% as species B. Age-specific variations in CSF characteristics suggest distinct inflammatory responses in each group.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Honorato</LastName><ForeName>Layla</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7084-3095</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Noely Evangelista</ForeName><Initials>NE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Domingues</LastName><ForeName>Renan Barros</ForeName><Initials>RB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Senne Liquor Diagnóstico, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Senne</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Senne Liquor Diagnóstico, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leite</LastName><ForeName>Fernando Brunale Vilela de Moura</ForeName><Initials>FBVM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Senne Liquor Diagnóstico, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santos</LastName><ForeName>Márcio Vega Dos</ForeName><Initials>MVD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Senne Liquor Diagnóstico, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fernandes</LastName><ForeName>Gustavo Bruniera Peres</ForeName><Initials>GBP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Senne Liquor Diagnóstico, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Laboratory, Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paião</LastName><ForeName>Heuder Gustavo Oliveira</ForeName><Initials>HGO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vilas Boas</LastName><ForeName>Lucy Santos</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>da Costa</LastName><ForeName>Antonio Charlys</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tozetto-Mendoza</LastName><ForeName>Tânia Regina</ForeName><Initials>TR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5659-1052</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Witkin</LastName><ForeName>Steven S</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Weill Cornel Medicine, New York, New York, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mendes-Correa</LastName><ForeName>Maria Cássia</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology (LIM 52), Department of Infectious Diseases, Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>FAPESP 2020/05623-0</GrantID><Agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>MISP # 60384</GrantID><Agency>Merck Investigator Studies Program</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008582" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Aseptic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000134" MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002555" MajorTopicYN="N">Cerebrospinal Fluid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral load</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral meningitis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38353496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Chen BS, Lee HC, Lee KM, Gong YN, Shih SR. Enterovirus and encephalitis. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:1-15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Moreni G, Wolthers KC, Pajkrt D. World-wide prevalence and genotype distribution of enteroviruses. Viruses. 2021;13(3):434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posnakoglou L, Tatsi EB, Chatzichristou P, et al. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus in children with central nervous system infections. Viruses. 2021;13(1):100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhazmi A, Lazrek M, Alidjinou EK, Descombes G, Engelmann I, Hober D. Paediatric enterovirus meningitis without cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis. J Infect. 2019;79(6):612-625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vollbach S, Müller A, Drexler JF, et al. Prevalence, type and concentration of human enterovirus and parechovirus in cerebrospinal fluid samples of pediatric patients over a 10-year period: a retrospective study. Virol J. 2015;12(1):199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang YY, Huang YC. Enteroviral infection in neonates. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2019;52(6):851-857.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song C, Li Y, Zhou Y, et al. Enterovirus genomic load and disease severity among children hospitalised with hand, foot and mouth disease. EBioMedicine. 2020;62:103078.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aberle SW, Aberle JH, Steininger C, Puchhammer-Stöckl E. Quantitative real time PCR detection of varicella-zoster virus DNA in cerebrospinal fluid in patients with neurological disease. Med Microbiol Immunol. 2005;194(1-2):7-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Růžek D, Piskunova N, Žampachová E. High variability in viral load in cerebrospinal fluid from patients with herpes simplex and varicella-zoster infections of the central nervous system. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2007;13(12):1217-1219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yen MH, Tsao KC, Huang YC, et al. Viral load in blood is correlated with disease severity of neonatal coxsackievirus B3 infection: early diagnosis and predicting disease severity is possible in severe neonatal enterovirus infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;44(10):e78-e81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volle R, Bailly JL, Mirand A, et al. Variations in cerebrospinal fluid viral loads among enterovirus genotypes in patients hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed meningitis due to enterovirus. J Infect Dis. 2014;210(4):576-584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawashima H, Ioi H, Ishii C, et al. Viral loads of cerebrospinal fluid in infants with enterovirus meningitis. J Clin Lab Anal. 2008;22(3):216-219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordey S, Schibler M, L'Huillier AG, et al. Comparative analysis of viral shedding in pediatric and adult subjects with central nervous system-associated enterovirus infections from 2013 to 2015 in Switzerland. J Clin Virol. 2017;89:22-29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocha LC, Estofolete CF, Milhim BHGA, et al. Enteric viruses circulating in undiagnosed central nervous system infections at tertiary hospital in São José do Rio Preto, São Paulo, Brazil. J Med Virol. 2021;93(6):3539-3548.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalwai A, Ahmad S, Pacsa A, Al-Nakib W. Echovirus type 9 is an important cause of viral encephalitis among infants and young children in Kuwait. J Clin Virol. 2009;44(1):48-51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compagnoli Carmona RC, Caetano Machado B, Aparecida de Sousa C, et al. Distribution of species enterovirus B in patients with central nervous system infections in São Paulo State, Brazil. J Med Virol. 2020;92(12):3849-3856.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal LRR, Almeida SM, Messias-Reason IJ, et al. Enterovirus and herpesviridae family as etiologic agents of lymphomonocytary meningitis, Southern Brazil. Arq Neuropsiquiatr. 2011;69(3):475-481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machado RS, de Sousa IP, Monteiro JC, Ferreira JL, dos Santos Alves JC, Tavares FN. Detection and identification of enteroviruses circulating in children with acute gastroenteritis in Pará State, Northern Brazil (2010-2011). Virol J. 2020;17(1):156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramalho E, Sousa I, Burlandy F, et al. Identification and phylogenetic characterization of human enteroviruses isolated from cases of aseptic meningitis in Brazil, 2013-2017. Viruses. 2019;11(8):690.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Minor BL, et al. The REDCap consortium: building an international community of software platform partners. J Biomed Inf. 2019;95:103208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun KW, Choi EH, Cheon DS, et al. Enteroviral meningitis without pleocytosis in children. Arch Dis Child. 2012;97(10):874-878.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kestenbaum LA, Ebberson J, Zorc JJ, Hodinka RL, Shah SS. Defining cerebrospinal fluid white blood cell count reference values in neonates and young infants. Pediatrics. 2010;125(2):257-264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leen WG, Willemsen MA, Wevers RA, Verbeek MM. Cerebrospinal fluid glucose and lactate: age-specific reference values and implications for clinical practice. PLoS One. 2012;7(8):e42745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emery SL, Erdman DD, Bowen MD, et al. Real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction assay for SARS-associated coronavirus. Emerging Infect Dis. 2004;10(2):311-316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verstrepen WA, Kuhn S, Kockx MM, Van De Vyvere ME, Mertens AH. Rapid detection of enterovirus RNA in cerebrospinal fluid specimens with a novel single-tube real-time reverse transcription-PCR assay. J Clin Microbiol. 2001;39(11):4093-4096.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tourinho RS. Application of synthetic standard curves for absolute quantification of hepatitis A and E by real-time PCR. J Genet Genome Res. 2015;22(1):23-25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin SA, Benes V, Garson JA, et al. The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments. Clin Chem. 2009;55(4):611-622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>INMET. Banco de Dados Meteorológicos para Ensino e Pesquisa (BDMEP). Brasília: Instituto Nacional de Metereologia (INMET). 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han SH, Choi HY, Kim JM, Park KR, Youn YC, Shin HW. Etiology of aseptic meningitis and clinical characteristics in immune-competent adults. J Med Virol. 2016;88(1):175-179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volle R, Nourrisson C, Mirand A, et al. Quantitative real-time RT-PCR assay for research studies on enterovirus infections in the central nervous system. J Virol Methods. 2012;185(1):142-148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan NWH, Lee EY, Khoo GMC, Tee NWS, Krishnamoorthy S, Choong CT. Cerebrospinal fluid white cell count: discriminatory or otherwise for enteroviral meningitis in infants and young children? J Neurovirol. 2016;22(2):213-217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braunova A, Krbkova L, Rainetova P, et al. Clinical and laboratory characteristics of enteroviral meningitis in children, including qRT-PCR and sequencing analysis. Biomed Pap. 2019;163(4):355-361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negrini B, Kelleher KJ, Wald ER. Cerebrospinal fluid findings in aseptic versus bacterial meningitis. Pediatrics. 2000;105(2):316-319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa IP, Dos Santos FB, de Paula VS, et al. Viral and prion infections associated with central nervous system syndromes in Brazil. Viruses. 2021;13(7):1370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastos MS, Lessa N, Naveca FG, et al. Detection of Herpesvirus, Enterovirus, and Arbovirus infection in patients with suspected central nervous system viral infection in the Western Brazilian Amazon. J Med Virol. 2014;86(9):1522-1527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa IP, Oliveira MLA, Burlandy FM, et al. Molecular characterization and epidemiological aspects of non-polio enteroviruses isolated from acute flaccid paralysis in Brazil: a historical series (2005-2017). Emerg Microbes Infect. 2020;9(1):2536-2546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyeon JY, Hwang S, Kim H, et al. Accuracy of diagnostic methods and surveillance sensitivity for human enterovirus, South Korea, 1999-2011. Emerging Infect Dis. 2013;19(8):1268-1275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Sun Z, Li W, Liu L, Gao F, Pan D. Epidemiological characteristics and cerebrospinal fluid cytokine profiles of enterovirus encephalitis in children in Hangzhou, China. J Med Virol. 2022;94(6):2645-2652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumaidi K, Al-Jawabreh A. Molecular detection and genotyping of enteroviruses from CSF samples of patients with suspected sepsis-like illness and/or aseptic meningitis from 2012 to 2015 in West Bank, Palestine. PLoS One. 2017;12(2):e0172357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadakis G, Chibo D, Druce J, Catton M, Birch C. Detection and genotyping of enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid in patients in Victoria, Australia, 2007-2013. J Med Virol. 2014;86(9):1609-1613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistchenko AS, Viegas M, Latta MPD, Barrero PR. Molecular and epidemiologic analysis of enterovirus B neurological infection in Argentine children. J Clin Virol. 2006;37(4):293-299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons-Salort M, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA, et al. The seasonality of nonpolio enteroviruses in the United States: patterns and drivers. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2018;115(12):3078-3083.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girardi V, Mena KD, Albino SM, et al. Microbial risk assessment in recreational freshwaters from southern Brazil. Sci Total Environ. 2019;651:298-308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanrewaju AA, Enitan-Folami AM, Sabiu S, Edokpayi JN, Swalaha FM. Global public health implications of human exposure to viral contaminated water. Front Microbiol. 2022;13:13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farías A, Cabrerizo M, Ré V, et al. Molecular identification of human enteroviruses in children with neurological infections from the central region of Argentina. Arch Virol. 2011;156(1):129-133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Li J, Liu Y, Sun Q, Liu Z. Pathogenesis of enterovirus infection in central nervous system. Biosaf Health. 2023;5(4):233-239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulholm T, Yeang M, Nguyen I, et al. Molecular typing of enteroviruses: comparing 5′ UTR, VP1 and whole genome sequencing methods. Pathology. 2022;54:779-783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Iro MA, Sadarangani M, Goldacre R, Pollard AJ, Goldacre MJ. Hospital admissions for viral meningitis in children in England over five decades: a population-based observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16(11):1279-1287.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>