<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38488486</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diversity of enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid specimens collected from hospitalised patients in the private and public sector in South Africa.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29514</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29514</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29514</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses cause a wide range of neurological illnesses such as encephalitis, meningitis, and acute flaccid paralysis. Two types of enteroviruses, echovirus E4 and E9, have recently been detected in South Africa and are known to be associated with meningitis and encephalitis. The objective of this study was to characterize enterovirus strains detected in cerebrospinal fluid specimens of hospitalized patients in the private and public sector to identify genotypes associated with meningitis and encephalitis. From January 2019 to June 2021 enterovirus positive nucleic acid samples were obtained from a private (n = 116) and a public sector (n = 101) laboratory. These enteroviruses were typed using a nested set of primers targeting the VP1 region of the enterovirus genome, followed by Sanger sequencing and BLASTn analysis. Forty-two percent (91/217) of the strains could be genotyped. Enterovirus B species was the major species detected in 95% (86/91) of the specimens, followed by species C in 3% (3/91) and species A in 2% (2/91) of the specimens. Echovirus E4 and E9 were the two major types identified in this study and were detected in 70% (64/91) and in 10% (9/91) of specimens, respectively. Echovirus E11 has previously been identified in sewage samples from South Africa, but this study is the first to report Echovirus E11 in cerebrospinal fluid specimens from South African patients. The genotypes identified during this study are known to be associated with encephalitis and meningitis. The predominant detection of echovirus E4 followed by E9 corresponds with other studies conducted in South Africa.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Janse van Rensburg</LastName><ForeName>Megan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2399-6969</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Virology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mans</LastName><ForeName>Janet</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6721-1177</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Virology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mafuyeka</LastName><ForeName>Rendani T</ForeName><Initials>RT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0056-1329</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Virology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Health Laboratory Service, Tshwane Academic Division, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Strydom</LastName><ForeName>Kathy-Anne</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0771-8608</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>AMPATH laboratories, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Myburgh</LastName><ForeName>Marcelle</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7702-580X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>AMPATH laboratories, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Zyl</LastName><ForeName>Walda B</ForeName><Initials>WB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7344-7060</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Virology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Health Laboratory Service, Tshwane Academic Division, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>94792</GrantID><Agency>National Health Laboratory Service Research Trust</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Research Committee of the University of Pretoria</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013019" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South Africa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017150" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Sector</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008581" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004660" MajorTopicYN="Y">Encephalitis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002555" MajorTopicYN="N">Cerebrospinal Fluid</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">South Africa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">echovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meningitis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38488486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Nikonov OS, Chernykh ES, Garber MB, Nikonova EY. Enteroviruses: classification, diseases they cause, and approaches to development of antiviral drugs. Biochemistry (Moscow). 2017;82(13):1615-1631. doi:10.1134/S0006297917130041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells AI, Coyne CB. Enteroviruses: a gut-wrenching game of entry, detection, and evasion. Viruses. 2019;11(5):460. doi:10.3390/v11050460</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(3):793-797. doi:10.1007/s00705-019-04520-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo H, Li Y, Liu G, et al. A second open reading frame in human enterovirus determines viral replication in intestinal epithelial cells. Nat Commun. 2019;10(1):4066. doi:10.1038/s41467-019-12040-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin JY, Huang HI. Autophagy is induced and supports virus replication in Enterovirus A71-infected human primary neuronal cells. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):15234. doi:10.1038/s41598-020-71970-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richter J, Tryfonos C, Christodoulou C. Molecular epidemiology of enteroviruses in Cyprus 2008-2017. PLoS One. 2019;14(8):e0220938. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0220938</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vareil M, Wille H, Kassab S, et al. Clinical and biological features of enteroviral meningitis among adults and children and factors associated with severity and length of stay. J Clin Virol. 2018;104:56-60. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2018.04.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang YY, Huang YC. Enteroviral infection in neonates. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2019;52(6):851-857. doi:10.1016/j.jmii.2019.08.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao MMA, Apostol LN, de Quiroz-Castro M, et al. Non-polio enteroviruses among healthy children in the Philippines. BMC Public Health. 2020;20(1):167. doi:10.1186/s12889-020-8284-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isaacs SR, Foskett DB, Maxwell AJ, et al. Viruses and type 1 diabetes: from enteroviruses to the virome. Microorganisms. 2021;9(7):1519. doi:10.3390/microorganisms9071519</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ai J, Xie Z, Liu G, et al. Etiology and prognosis of acute viral encephalitis and meningitis in Chinese children: a multicentre prospective study. BMC Infect Dis. 2017;17(1):494. doi:10.1186/s12879-017-2572-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Fischer M, Dominguez SR, Tyler KL, Abzug MJ. Encephalitis in US children. Infect Dis Clin North Am. 2018;32(1):145-162. doi:10.1016/j.idc.2017.10.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla B, Aguilera EA, Salazar L, Wootton SH, Kaewpoowat Q, Hasbun R. Aseptic meningitis in adults and children: diagnostic and management challenges. J Clin Virol. 2017;94:110-114. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2017.07.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dittrich T, Marsch S, Egli A, et al. Predictors of infectious meningitis or encephalitis: the yield of cerebrospinal fluid in a cross-sectional study. BMC Infect Dis. 2020;20(1):304. doi:10.1186/s12879-020-05022-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McIntyre JP, Keen GA. Laboratory surveillance of viral meningitis by examination of cerebrospinal fluid in Cape Town, 1981-9. Epidemiol Infect. 1993;111(2):357-371. doi:10.1017/s095026880005706x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfaardt M, Büchner A, Myburgh M, Avenant T, du Plessis NM, Taylor MB. Molecular characterisation of enteroviruses and clinical findings from a cluster of paediatric viral meningitis cases in Tshwane, South Africa 2010-2011. J Clin Virol. 2014;61(3):400-405. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2014.08.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smuts H, Cronje S, Thomas J, Brink D, Korsman S, Hardie D. Molecular characterization of an outbreak of enterovirus-associated meningitis in Mossel Bay, South Africa, December 2015-January 2016. BMC Infect Dis. 2018;18(1):709. doi:10.1186/s12879-018-3641-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nkosi N, Preiser W, van Zyl G, et al. Molecular characterisation and epidemiology of enterovirus-associated aseptic meningitis in the Western and Eastern Cape Provinces, South Africa 2018-2019. J Clin Virol. 2021;139:104845. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nijhuis M, van Maarseveen N, Schuurman R, et al. Rapid and sensitive routine detection of all members of the genus enterovirus in different clinical specimens by real-time PCR. J Clin Microbiol. 2002;40(10):3666-3670. doi:10.1128/JCM.40.10.3666-3670.2002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44(8):2698-2704. doi:10.1128/JCM.00542-06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroneman A, Vennema H, Deforche K, et al. An automated genotyping tool for enteroviruses and noroviruses. J Clin Virol. 2011;51(2):121-125. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2011.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ. Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol. 1990;215(3):403-410. doi:10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall TA. BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT. Nucleic Acids Symp Ser. 1999;41:95-98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura M. A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences. J Mol Evol. 1980;16(2):111-120. doi:10.1007/BF01731581</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>South African government. 2020. Disaster management Act: Regulations to address, prevent and combat the spread of Coronavirus COVID-19; Amendment. [Internet]. Accessed May 15, 2022. https://www.gov.za/documents/disaster-management-act-regulations-address-prevent-and-combat-spread-coronavirus-covid-19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop KSM, Broberg EK, Hodcroft E, et al. Molecular epidemiology and evolutionary trajectory of emerging echovirus 30, Europe. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27(6):1616-1626. doi:10.3201/eid2706.203096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Cuerpo M, Gonzalez de Audicana J, Fernandez-Garcia MD, et al. Epidemiology of Echovirus 30 infections detected in a university hospital in Catalonia, Spain, in 1995-2020. Microorganisms. 2022;10(3):592. doi:10.3390/microorganisms10030592</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opanda SM, Wamunyokoli F, Khamadi S, Coldren R, Bulimo WD. Genotyping of enteroviruses isolated in Kenya from pediatric patients using partial VP1 region. SpringerPlus. 2016;5(1):158. doi:10.1186/s40064-016-1834-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glenet M, N'guyen Y, Mirand A, et al. Major 5′ terminally deleted enterovirus populations modulate type I IFN response in acute myocarditis patients and in human cultured cardiomyocytes. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):11947. doi:10.1038/s41598-020-67648-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Yan D, Song Y, et al. Whole-genome analysis of coxsackievirus B3 reflects its genetic diversity in China and worldwide. Virol J. 2022;19(1):69. doi:10.1186/s12985-022-01796-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Z, Zhang Y, Huang K, et al. Two Coxsackievirus B3 outbreaks associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease in China and the evolutionary history worldwide. BMC Infect Dis. 2019;19(2019):466. doi:10.1186/s12879-019-4107-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Moreni G, Wolthers KC, Pajkrt D. World-wide prevalence and genotype distribution of enteroviruses. Viruses. 2021;13(3):434. doi:10.3390/v13030434</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, van der Sanden SMG, Calis JCJ, et al. High frequency of polio-like enterovirus C strains with differential clustering of CVA-13 and EV-C99 subgenotypes in a cohort of Malawian children. Arch Virol. 2018;163(10):2645-2653. doi:10.1007/s00705-018-3878-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumdar M, Celma C, Pegg E, Polra K, Dunning J, Martin J. Detection and typing of human enteroviruses from clinical samples by Entire-Capsid next generation sequencing. Viruses. 2021;13(4):641. doi:10.3390/v13040641</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard W, Savulescu D, Berrie L, Puren AJ. Description of non-polio enteroviruses identified in two national surveillance programmes in South Africa. S Afr J Infect Dis. 2020;35(1):7. doi:10.4102/sajid.v35i1.196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faleye TOC, Adewumi MO, Coker BA, Nudamajo FY, Adeniji JA. Direct detection and identification of enteroviruses from faeces of healthy Nigerian children using a cell-culture independent RT-seminested PCR assay. Adv Virol. 2016;2016:1-12. doi:10.1155/2016/1412838</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kupila, L, Vuorinen, T, Vainionpaa, R, Marttila, RJ, Kotilainen, P, 2005. Diagnosis of enteroviral meningitis by use of polymerase chain reaction of cerebrospinal fluid, stool, and serum specimens. Clin Infect Dis 40(7), 982-987. doi:10.1086/428581.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>