<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38432386</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-1026</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>926</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Science of the total environment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Total Environ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessing the nucleic acid decay of human wastewater markers and enteric viruses in estuarine waters in Sydney, Australia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>171389</StartPage><MedlinePgn>171389</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.171389</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0048-9697(24)01530-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This research investigated the in-situ decay rates of four human wastewater-associated markers (Bacteroides HF183 (HF183), Lachnospiraceae Lachno3 (Lachno3), cross-assembling phage (crAssphage), pepper mild mottle virus (PMMoV) and three enteric viruses (human adenovirus 40/41 (HAdV 40/41), enterovirus (EV) and human norovirus GII (HNoV GII) in two estuarine water environments (Davidson Park (DP) and Hen and Chicken Bay (HCB) in temperate Sydney, NSW, Australia, employing qPCR and RT-qPCR assays. The study also aimed to compare decay rates observed in mesocosms with previously published laboratory microcosms, providing insights into the persistence of markers and viruses in estuarine environments. Results indicated varying decay rates between DP and HCB mesocosms, with HF183 exhibiting relatively faster decay rates compared to other markers and enteric viruses in sunlight and dark mesocosms. In DP mesocosms, HF183 decayed the fastest, contrasting with PMMoV, which exhibited the slowest. Sunlight induced higher decay rates for all markers and viruses in DP mesocosms. In HCB sunlight mesocosms, HF183 nucleic acid decayed most rapidly compared to other markers and enteric viruses. In dark mesocosms, crAssphage showed the fastest decay, while PMMoV decayed at the slowest rate in both sunlight and dark mesocosms. Comparisons with laboratory microcosms revealed faster decay of markers and enteric viruses in laboratory microcosms than the mesocosms, except for crAssphage and HAdV 40/41 in dark, and PMMoV in sunlight mesocosms. The study concludes that decay rates of markers and enteric viruses vary between estuarine mesocosms, emphasizing the impact of sunlight exposure, which was potentially influenced by the elevated turbidity at HCB estuarine waters. The generated decay rates contribute valuable insights for establishing site-specific risk-based thresholds of human wastewater-associated markers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Warish</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia. Electronic address: Warish.Ahmed@csiro.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korajkic</LastName><ForeName>Asja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United States Environmental Protection Agency, 26W Martin Luther King Jr. Drive, Cincinnati, OH 45268, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gabrewold</LastName><ForeName>Metasebia</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CSIRO Environment, Ecosciences Precinct, 41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park, QLD 4102, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Payyappat</LastName><ForeName>Sudhi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cassidy</LastName><ForeName>Michele</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrison</LastName><ForeName>Nathan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Besley</LastName><ForeName>Colin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Water, 1 Smith Street, Parramatta, NSW 2150, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>EPA999999</GrantID><Acronym>ImEPA</Acronym><Agency>Intramural EPA</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Total Environ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0330500</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0048-9697</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Organism" UI="C000623922">Pepper mild mottle virus</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002645" MajorTopicYN="N">Chickens</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001315" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Australia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001435" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bacteriophages</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014871" MajorTopicYN="N">Water Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005243" MajorTopicYN="N">Feces</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017898" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tobamovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Decay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Estuarine waters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human health risks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial source tracking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater pollution</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38432386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1987903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11070875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.171389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0048-9697(24)01530-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abdelzaher AM, Wright ME, Ortega C, Solo-Gabriele HM, Miller G, Elmir S, Newman X, Shih P, Bonilla JA, Bonilla TD, Palmer CJ, Scott T, Lukasik J, Harwood VJ, McQuaig S, Sinigalliano C, Gidley M, Plano LRW, Zhu X, Wang JD, Fleming LE, 2010. Presence of pathogens and indicator microbes at a non-point source subtropical recreational marine beach. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 76, 724–732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2812993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19966020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abia AL, Ubomba-Jaswa E, Momba MN, 2016. Competitive survival of Escherichia coli, Vibrio cholerae, salmonella typhimurium and Shigella dysenteriae in riverbed sediments. Microb. Ecol. 72, 881–889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27193001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Sritharan T, Palmer A, Sidhu JP, Toze S, 2013. Evaluation of bovine feces-associated microbial source tracking markers and their correlations with fecal indicators and zoonotic pathogens in a Brisbane, Australia, reservoir. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 79, 2682–2691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3623195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23417003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Hamilton KA, Lobos A, Hughes B, Staley C, Sadowsky MJ, Harwood VJ, 2018. Quantitative microbial risk assessment of microbial source tracking markers in recreational water contaminated with fresh untreated and secondary treated sewage. Environ. Int. 117, 243–249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29772486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Bivins A, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2022. Distribution of human fecal marker genes and their association with pathogenic viruses in untreated wastewater determined using quantitative PCR. Water Res. 226, 119093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36252296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Gyawali P, Feng S, McLellan SL, 2019. Host specificity and sensitivity of established and novel sewage-associated marker genes in human and nonhuman fecal samples. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 85 e00641–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6606881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31076423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2023a. Microbial source tracking of untreated human wastewater and animal scats in urbanized estuarine waters. Sci. Total Environ. 877, 162764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36907409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Korajkic A, Smith WJ, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2023b. Comparing the decay of human wastewater-associated marker genes and enteric viruses in laboratory microcosms simulating estuarine waters in a temperate climatic zone. Sci. Total Environ. 23, 167845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11070876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37879463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Payyappat S, Cassidy M, Harrison N, Besley C, 2023c. Reduction of human fecal markers and enteric viruses in Sydney estuarine waters receiving wet weather overflows. Sci. Total Environ. 896, 165008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37348731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin MT, Han M, 2009. Roof-harvested rainwater for potable purposes: application of solar disinfection (SODIS) and limitations. Water Sci. Technol. 60, 419–431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19633384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson KL, Whitlock JE, Harwood VJ, 2005. Persistence and differential survival of fecal indicator bacteria in subtropical waters and sediments. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 71, 3041–3048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1151827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15933000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Araújo S, Henriques IS, Leandro SM, Alves A, Pereira A, Correia A, 2014. Gulls identified as major source of fecal pollution in coastal waters: a microbial source tracking study. Sci. Total Environ. 470–471, 84–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24140684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae S, Wuertz S, 2012. Survival of host-associated bacteroidales cells and their relationship with Enterococcus spp., Campylobacter jejuni, Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium, and adenovirus in freshwater microcosms as measured by propidium monoazide-quantitative PCR. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 78, 922–932.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3272992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22139002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm AB, Silverman AI, Schriewer A, Goodwin K, 2019. Systematic review and meta-analysis of decay rates of waterborne mammalian viruses and coliphages in surface waters. Water Res. 164, 114898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31404902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks LE, Field KG, 2016. Bayesian meta-analysis to synthesize decay rate constant estimates for common fecal indicator bacteria. Water Res. 104, 262–271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27543910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustin SA, Benes V, Garson JA, Hellemans J, Huggett J, Kubista M, Mueller R, Nolan T, Pfaffl MW, Shipley GL, Vandesompele J, Wittwer CT, 2009. The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments. Clin. Chem. 55, 611–622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19246619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byappanahalli MN, Roll BM, Fujioka RS, 2012. Evidence for occurrence, persistence, and growth potential of Escherichia coli and enterococci in Hawaii’s soil environments. Microbes Environ. 27, 164–170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4036009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22791049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cashdollar JL, Brinkman NE, Griffin SM, McMinn BR, Rhodes ER, Varughese EA, Grimm AC, Parshioniker SU, Wymer L, Fout GS, 2013. Development and evaluation of EPA method 1615 for detection of enterovirus and norovirus in water. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 79, 215–223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3536115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23087037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chick H, 1908. An investigation of the laws of disinfection. J. Hyg. (Lond). 8, 92–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2167134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20474353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collier SA, Deng L, Adam EA, Benedict KM, Beshearse EM, Blackstock AJ, Bruce BB, Derado G, Edens C, Fullerton KE, Gargano JW, Geissler AL, Hall AJ, Havelaar AH, Hill VR, Hoekstra RM, Reddy SC, Scallan E, Stokes EK, Yoder JS, Beach MJ, 2021. Estimate of burden and direct healthcare cost of infectious waterborne disease in the United States. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 27, 140–149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7774540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33350905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demeter K, Linke R, Ballesté E, Reischer G, Mayer RE, Vierheilig J, Kolm C, Stevenson ME, Derx J, Kirschner AKT, Sommer R, Shanks OC, Blanch AR, Rose JB, Ahmed W, Farnleitner AH, 2023. Have genetic targets for faecal pollution diagnostics and source tracking revolutionized water quality analysis yet? FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 47, fuad028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10368376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37286726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desmarais TR, Solo-Gabriele HM, Palmer CJ, 2002. Influence of soil on fecal indicator organisms in a tidally influenced subtropical environment. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 68, 1165–1172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC123749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11872464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng S, Bootsma M, McLellan SL, 2018. Novel human associated Lachnospiraceae genetic markers improve detection of fecal pollution sources in urban waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 84, e00309–e00318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6029095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29728386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu S, Yang Q, Sheng Y, Wang Q, Wu J, Qiu Z, Lan R, Wang Y, Liu Y, 2021. Metagenomics combined with comprehensive validation as a public health risk assessment tool for urban and agricultural run-off. Water Res. 209, 117941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34920315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greaves J, Stone D, Wu Z, Bibby K, 2020. Persistence of emerging viral fecal indicators in large-scale freshwater mesocosms. Water Res. X. 9, 100067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7516186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32995735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green HC, Haugland RA, Varma M, Millen HT, Borchardt MA, Field KG, Walters WA, Knight R, Sivaganesan M, Kelty CA, Shanks OC, 2014. Improved HF183 quantitative real-time PCR assay for characterization of human fecal pollution in ambient surface water samples. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 80, 3086–3094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4018914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24610857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamza IA, Jurzik L, Überla K, Wilhelm M, 2011. Evaluation of pepper mild mottle virus, human picobirnavirus and torque Teno virus as indicators of fecal contamination in river water. Water Res. 45, 1358–1368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21074236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E, Kitajima M, Kishida N, Konno Y, Katayama H, Asami M, Akiba M, 2013. Occurrence of pepper mild mottle virus in drinking water sources in Japan. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 79, 7413–7418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3837739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24056461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harwood VJ, Staley C, Badgley BD, Borges K, Korajkic A, 2014. Microbial source tracking markers for detection of fecal contamination in environmental waters: relationships between pathogens and human health outcomes. FEMS Microbiology Rev 38, 1–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23815638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haugland RA, Siefring SC, Wymer LJ, Brenner KP, Dufour AP, 2005. Comparison of Enterococcus measurements in freshwater at two recreational beaches by quantitative polymerase chain reaction and membrane filter culture analysis. Water Res. 39, 559–568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15707628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Hu Y, Wang L, Wang Y, Li N, Guo Y, Feng Y, Xiao L, 2017. Environmental transport of emerging human-pathogenic Cryptosporidium species and subtypes through combined sewer overflow and wastewater. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 83 e00682–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5541217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28600310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes B, Beale DJ, Dennis PG, Cook S, Ahmed W, 2017. Cross-comparison of human wastewater-associated molecular markers in relation to fecal indicator bacteria and enteric viruses in recreational beach waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 83 e00028–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5377505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28159789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishii S, Ksoll WB, Hicks RE, Sadowsky MJ, 2006. Presence and growth of naturalized Escherichia coli in temperate soils from Lake Superior watersheds. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 72, 612–621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1352292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16391098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jothikumar N, Lowther JA, Henshilwood K, Lees DN, Hill VR, Vinjé J, 2005. Rapid and sensitive detection of noroviruses by using TaqMan-based one-step reverse transcription-PCR assays and application to naturally contaminated shellfish samples. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 71, 1870–1875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1082570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15812014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kay D, Stapleton CM, Wyer MD, McDonald AT, Crowther J, Paul N, Jones K, Francis C, Watkins J, Wilkinson J, Humphrey N, Lin B, Yang L, Falconer RA, Gardner S, 2005. Decay of intestinal enterococci concentrations in high-energy estuarine and coastal waters: towards real-time T90 values for modelling faecal indicators in recreational waters. Water Res. 39, 655–667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15707639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M, Iker BC, Pepper IL, Gerba CP, 2014. Relative abundance and treatment reduction of viruses during wastewater treatment processes – identification of potential viral indicators. Sci. Total Environ. 488–489, 290–296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24836386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M, Sassi HP, Torrey JR, 2018. Pepper mild mottle virus as a water quality indicator. npj Clean Water 1, 19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko G, Jothikumar N, Hill VR, Sobsey M, 2005. Rapid detection of infectious adenovirus by mRNA real-time RT-PCR. J. Virol. Methods 127, 148–153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15967237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, McMinn BR, Shanks OC, Sivaganesan M, Fout GS, Ashbolt NJ, 2014. Biotic interactions and sunlight affect persistence of fecal indicator bacteria and microbial source tracking genetic markers in the upper Mississippi river. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 80, 3952–3961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4054226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24747902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, Wanjugi P, Brooks L, Cao Y, Harwood VJ, 2019. Persistence and decay of fecal microbiota in aquatic habitats. Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 83, e00005–e00019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7405076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31578217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korajkic A, McMinn BR, Harwood VJ, 2023. The effect of protozoa indigenous to lakewater and wastewater on decay of fecal indicator bacteria and coliphage. Pathogens 12, 378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10053992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36986300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linke RB, Kebede G, Mushi D, Lakew A, Hayes DS, Graf W, Farnleitner AH, 2021. Assessing the faecal source sensitivity and specificity of ruminant and human genetic microbial source tracking markers in the central Ethiopian highlands. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 72, 458–466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7986238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33300161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma JY, Li MY, Qi ZZ, Fu M, Sun TF, Elsheikha HM, Cong W, 2022. Waterborne protozoan outbreaks: an update on the global, regional, and national prevalence from 2017 to 2020 and sources of contamination. Sci. Total Environ. 806, 150562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34852432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maraccini PA, Mattioli MC, Sassoubre LM, Cao Y, Griffith JF, Ervin JS, Van De Werfhorst LC, Boehm AB, 2016. Solar inactivation of enterococci and Escherichia coli in natural waters: effects of water absorbance and depth. Environ. Sci. Technol. 50, 5068–5076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27119980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattioli MC, Sassoubre LM, Russell TL, Boehm AB, 2017. Decay of sewage-sourced microbial source tracking markers and fecal indicator bacteria in marine waters. Water Res. 108, 106–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27855952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn BR, Rhodes ER, Huff EM, Korajkic A, 2020. Decay of infectious adenovirus and coliphages in freshwater habitats is differentially affected by ambient sunlight and the presence of indigenous protozoa communities. Virol. J. 17, 1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6945520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31906972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montoya D, 2015. Pollution in Sydney Harbour: sewage, toxic chemicals and microplastics. Briefing Paper No 03/2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson KL, Boehm AB, Davies-Colley RJ, Dodd MC, Kohn T, Linden KG, Liu Y, Maraccini PA, McNeill K, Mitch WA, Nguyen TH, Parker KM, Rodriguez RA, Sassoubre LM, Silverman AI, Wigginton KR, Zepp RG, 2018. Sunlight-mediated inactivation of health-relevant microorganisms in water: a review of mechanisms and modeling approaches. Environ Sci Process Impacts 16, 1089–1122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7064263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30047962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OEH, 2011. Beachwatch Programs. Protocol for Assessment and Management of Microbial Risks in Recreational Waters. Office of Environment and Heritage, NSW.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramírez-Castillo FY, Loera-Muro A, Jacques M, Garneau P, Avelar-González FJ, Harel J, Guerrero-Barrera AL, 2015. Waterborne pathogens: detection methods and challenges. Pathogens 4, 307–334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4493476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26011827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rochelle-Newall E, Nguyen TM, Le TP, Sengtaheuanghoung O, Ribolzi O, 2015. A short review of fecal indicator bacteria in tropical aquatic ecosystems: knowledge gaps and future directions. Front. Microbiol. 6, 308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4400915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25941519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosario K, Symonds EM, Sinigalliano C, Stewart J, Breitbart M, 2009. Pepper mild mottle virus as an indicator of fecal pollution. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 75, 7261–7267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2786529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19767474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott TM, Rose JB, Jenkins TM, Farrah SR, Lukasik J, 2002. Microbial source tracking: current methodology and future directions. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 68, 5796–5803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC134426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12450798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E, Kelty C, Sivaganesan M, Li X, Bibby K, Shanks OC, 2017. Quantitative CrAssphage PCR assays for human fecal pollution measurement. Environ. Sci. Technol. 51, 9146–9154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28700235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staley C, Gordon KV, Schoen ME, Harwood VJ, 2012. Performance of two quantitative PCR methods for microbial source tracking of human sewage and implications for microbial risk assessment in recreational waters. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 78, 7317–7326.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3457114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22885746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele JA, Blackwood AD, Griffith JF, Noble RT, Schiff KC, 2018. Quantification of pathogens and markers of fecal contamination during storm events along popular surfing beaches in San Diego, California. Water Res. 136, 137–149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29501758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds EM, Verbyla EM, Lukasik JO, Kafle RC, Breitbart M, Mihelcic JR, 2014. A case study of enteric virus removal and insights into the associated risk of water reuse for two wastewater treatment pond systems in Bolivia. Water Res. 65, 257–270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25129566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari A, Oliver DM, Bivins A, Sherchan SP, Pitkänen T, 2021. Bathing water quality monitoring practices in Europe and the United States. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 18, 5513.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8196636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34063910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari A, Kauppinen A, Räsänen P, Salonen J, Wessels L, Juntunen J, Miettinen IT, Pitkänen T, 2023. Effects of temperature and light exposure on the decay characteristics of fecal indicators, norovirus, and Legionella in mesocosms simulating subarctic river water. Sci. Total Environ. 859 (Pt 2), 160340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36423850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbyla ME, Symonds EM, Kafle RC, Cairns MR, Iriarte M, Mercado Guzman A, Coronado O, Breitbart M, Ledo C, Mihelcic JR, 2016. Managing microbial risks from indirect wastewater reuse for irrigation in urbanizing watersheds. Environ. Sci. Technol. 50, 6803–6813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26992352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wade TJ, Sams E, Brenner KP, Haugland R, Chern E, Beach M, Wymer L, Rankin CC, Love D, Li Q, Noble R, Dufour AP, 2010. Rapidly measured indicators of recreational water quality and swimming-associated illness at marine beaches: a prospective cohort study. Environ. Health 9, 66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2990738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21040526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitman RL, Nevers MB, Korinek GC, Byappanahalli MN, 2004. Solar and temporal effects on Escherichia coli concentration at a Lake Michigan swimming beach. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 70, 4276–4285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC444827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15240311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wyn-Jones AP, Carducci A, Cook N, D’Agostino M, Divizia M, Fleischer J, Gantzer C, Gawler A, Girones R, Holler C, de Roda Husman AM, Kay D, Kozyra I, Lopez-Pila J, Muscillo M, Nascimento MSJ, Papageorgiou P, Rutjes S, Sellwood J, Szewzyk R, Wyer M, 2011. Surveillance of adenoviruses and noroviruses in European recreational waters. Water Res. 45, 1025–1038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21093010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>