<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38411118</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2379-5042</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>mSphere</Title><ISOAbbreviation>mSphere</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A retrospective longitudinal study of adenovirus group F, norovirus GI and GII, rotavirus, and enterovirus nucleic acids in wastewater solids at two wastewater treatment plants: solid-liquid partitioning and relation to clinical testing data.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0073623</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0073623</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00736-23</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/msphere.00736-23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteric infections are important causes of morbidity and mortality, yet clinical surveillance is limited. Wastewater-based epidemiology (WBE) has been used to study community circulation of individual enteric viruses and panels of respiratory diseases, but there is limited work studying the concurrent circulation of a suite of important enteric viruses. A retrospective WBE study was carried out at two wastewater treatment plants located in California, United States. Using digital droplet polymerase chain reaction (PCR), we measured concentrations of human adenovirus group F, enteroviruses, norovirus genogroups I and II, and rotavirus nucleic acids in wastewater solids two times per week for 26 months (<i>n</i> = 459 samples) between February 2021 and mid-April 2023. A novel probe-based PCR assay was developed and validated for adenovirus. We compared viral nucleic acid concentrations to positivity rates for viral infections from clinical specimens submitted to a local clinical laboratory to assess concordance between the data sets. We detected all viral targets in wastewater solids. At both wastewater treatment plants, human adenovirus group F and norovirus GII nucleic acids were detected at the highest concentrations (median concentrations greater than 10<sup>5</sup> copies/g), while rotavirus RNA was detected at the lowest concentrations (median on the order of 10<sup>3</sup> copies/g). Rotavirus, adenovirus group F, and norovirus nucleic acid concentrations were positively associated with clinical specimen positivity rates. Concentrations of tested viral nucleic acids exhibited complex associations with SARS-CoV-2 and other respiratory viral nucleic acids in wastewater, suggesting divergent transmission patterns.IMPORTANCEThis study provides evidence for the use of wastewater solids for the sensitive detection of enteric virus targets in wastewater-based epidemiology programs aimed to better understand the spread of enteric disease at a localized, community level without limitations associated with testing many individuals. Wastewater data can inform clinical, public health, and individual decision-making aimed to reduce the transmission of enteric disease.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boehm</LastName><ForeName>Alexandria B</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8162-5090</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, School of Engineering and Doerr School of Sustainability, Stanford University, Stanford, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shelden</LastName><ForeName>Bridgette</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences LLC, South San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duong</LastName><ForeName>Dorothea</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences LLC, South San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Banaei</LastName><ForeName>Niaz</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8501-3000</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, School of Medicine, Stanford University, Palo Alto, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>White</LastName><ForeName>Bradley J</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences LLC, South San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wolfe</LastName><ForeName>Marlene K</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gangarosa Department of Environmental Health, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Sergey Brin Family Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>mSphere</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101674533</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2379-5042</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009696">Nucleic Acids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Organism" UI="C000623855">Human mastadenovirus F</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000256" MajorTopicYN="N">Adenoviridae</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012401" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rotavirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029322" MajorTopicYN="Y">Norovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008137" MajorTopicYN="N">Longitudinal Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009696" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nucleic Acids</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018508" MajorTopicYN="Y">Water Purification</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000257" MajorTopicYN="Y">Adenoviridae Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000260" MajorTopicYN="Y">Adenoviruses, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adenovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enteric illness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gastrointestinal illness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">norovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rotavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wastewater solids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wastewater-based epidemiology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>B.H., D.D., and B.W. are employees of Verily Life Sciences, LLC.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38411118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10964402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00736-23</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Troeger C, Forouzanfar M, Rao PC, Khalil I, Brown A, Reiner RC, Fullman N, Thompson RL, Abajobir A, Ahmed M. 2017. Estimates of global, regional, and national morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of diarrhoeal diseases: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2015. Lancet Infect Dis 17:909–948. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30276-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30276-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5589208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28579426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotloff KL, Nataro JP, Blackwelder WC, Nasrin D, Farag TH, Panchalingam S, Wu Y, Sow SO, Sur D, Breiman RF, et al. . 2013. Burden and aetiology of diarrhoeal disease in infants and young children in developing countries (the global enteric multicenter study, GEMS): a prospective, case-control study. Lancet 382:209–222. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60844-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60844-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23680352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chansaenroj J, Tuanthap S, Thanusuwannasak T, Duang-In A, Klinfueng S, Thaneskongtong N, Vutithanachot V, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y. 2017. Human enteroviruses associated with and without diarrhea in Thailand between 2010 and 2016. PLoS One 12:e0182078. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0182078</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0182078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5531555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28750058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones TF, McMillian MB, Scallan E, Frenzen PD, Cronquist AB, Thomas S, Angulo FJ. 2007. A population-based estimate of the substantial burden of diarrhoeal disease in the United States; FoodNet, 1996–2003. Epidemiol Infect 135:293–301. doi:10.1017/S0950268806006765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268806006765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17291364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Zhang J, Xiao A, Gu X, Lee WL, Armas F, Kauffman K, Hanage W, Matus M, Ghaeli N, Endo N, Duvallet C, Poyet M, Moniz K, Washburne AD, Erickson TB, Chai PR, Thompson J, Alm EJ. 2020. SARS-CoV-2 titers in wastewater are higher than expected from clinically confirmed cases. mSystems 5:e00614-20. doi:10.1128/mSystems.00614-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00614-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7566278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32694130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm AB, Hughes B, Duong D, Chan-Herur V, Buchman A, Wolfe MK, White BJ. 2023. Wastewater concentrations of human influenza, metapneumovirus, parainfluenza, respiratory syncytial virus, rhinovirus, and seasonal coronavirus nucleic-acids during the COVID-19 pandemic: a surveillance study. Lancet Microbe 4:e340–e348. doi:10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00386-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(22)00386-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10032662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36965504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm AB, Wolfe MK, White BJ, Hughes B, Duong D, Banaei N, Bidwell A. 2023. Human norovirus (HuNoV) GII RNA in wastewater solids at 145 United States wastewater treatment plants: comparison to positivity rates of clinical specimens and modeled estimates of HuNoV GII shedders. J Expo Sci Environ Epidemiol. doi:10.1038/s41370-023-00592-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41370-023-00592-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11222142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37550566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diemert S, Yan T. 2019. Clinically unreported salmonellosis outbreak detected via comparative genomic analysis of municipal wastewater Salmonella isolates. Appl Environ Microbiol 85:e00139-19. doi:10.1128/AEM.00139-19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00139-19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6498150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30902850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe MK, Yu AT, Duong D, Rane MS, Hughes B, Chan-Herur V, Donnelly M, Chai S, White BJ, Vugia DJ, Boehm AB. 2023. Use of wastewater for Mpox outbreak surveillance in California. N Engl J Med 388:570–572. doi:10.1056/NEJMc2213882</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2213882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36652340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber C, Crank K, Papp K, Innes GK, Schmitz BW, Chavez J, Rossi A, Gerrity D. 2023. Community-scale wastewater surveillance of Candida auris during an ongoing outbreak in Southern Nevada. Environ Sci Technol 57:1755–1763. doi:10.1021/acs.est.2c07763</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c07763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9893721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36656763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin Z, Voice TC, Tarabara VV, Xagoraraki I. 2018. Sorption of human adenovirus to wastewater solids. J Environ Eng 144:06018008. doi:10.1061/(ASCE)EE.1943-7870.0001463</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1061/(ASCE)EE.1943-7870.0001463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roldan-Hernandez L, Boehm AB. 2023. Adsorption of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), rhinovirus, SARS-CoV-2, and F+ bacteriophage MS2 RNA onto wastewater solids from raw wastewater. Environ Sci Technol 57:13346–13355. doi:10.1021/acs.est.3c03376</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.3c03376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10501194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37647137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Churqui MP, Tunovic T, Enache L, Johansson A, Lindh M, Lagging M, Nyström K, Norder H. 2023. Measures against COVID-19 affected the spread of human enteric viruses in a Swedish community, as found when monitoring wastewater. Sci Total Environ 895:165012. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.165012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.165012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10284612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37353026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chacón L, Morales E, Valiente C, Reyes L, Barrantes K. 2021. Wastewater-based epidemiology of enteric viruses and surveillance of acute gastrointestinal illness outbreaks in a resource-limited region. Am J Trop Med Hyg 105:1004–1012. doi:10.4269/ajtmh.21-0050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.21-0050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8592140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34339385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisseux M, Colombet J, Mirand A, Roque-Afonso A-M, Abravanel F, Izopet J, Archimbaud C, Peigue-Lafeuille H, Debroas D, Bailly J-L, Henquell C. 2018. Monitoring human enteric viruses in wastewater and relevance to infections encountered in the clinical setting: a one-year experiment in central France, 2014 to 2015. Euro Surveill 23:17-00237. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.7.17-00237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.7.17-00237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5824128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jothikumar N, Kang G, Hill VR. 2009. Broadly reactive TaqMan assay for real-time RT-PCR detection of rotavirus in clinical and environmental samples. J Virol Methods 155:126–131. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2008.09.025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2008.09.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18951923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jothikumar N, Lowther JA, Henshilwood K, Lees DN, Hill VR, Vinjé J. 2005. Rapid and sensitive detection of noroviruses by using TaqMan-based one-step reverse transcription-PCR assays and application to naturally contaminated shellfish samples. Appl Environ Microbiol 71:1870–1875. doi:10.1128/AEM.71.4.1870-1875.2005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.4.1870-1875.2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1082570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15812014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loisy F, Atmar RL, Guillon P, Le Cann P, Pommepuy M, Le Guyader FS. 2005. Real-time RT-PCR for norovirus screening in shellfish. J Virol Methods 123:1–7. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2004.08.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2004.08.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15582692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gregory JB, Litaker RW, Noble RT. 2006. Rapid one-step quantitative reverse transcriptase PCR assay with competitive internal positive control for detection of enteroviruses in environmental samples. Appl Environ Microbiol 72:3960–3967. doi:10.1128/AEM.02291-05</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02291-05</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1489662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16751503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm AB, Wolfe MK, Wigginton KR, Bidwell A, White BJ, Hughes B, Duong D, Chan-Herur V, Bischel HN, Naughton CC. 2023. Human viral nucleic acids concentrations in wastewater solids from central and coastal California USA. Sci Data 10:396. doi:10.1038/s41597-023-02297-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41597-023-02297-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10287720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37349355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe MK, Topol A, Knudson A, Simpson A, White B, Vugia DJ, Yu AT, Li L, Balliet M, Stoddard P, Han GS, Wigginton KR, Boehm AB. 2021. High-frequency, high-throughput quantification of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater settled solids at eight publicly owned treatment works in Northern California shows strong association with COVID-19 incidence. mSystems 6:e0082921. doi:10.1128/mSystems.00829-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00829-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8547422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34519528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topol A, Wolfe M, White B, Wigginton K, Boehm A. 2021. High throughput pre-analytical processing of wastewater settled solids for SARS-CoV-2 RNA analyses V1. doi:10.17504/protocols.io.btyqnpvw</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17504/protocols.io.btyqnpvw</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topol A, Wolfe M, Wigginton K, White B, Boehm A. 2021. High throughput RNA extraction and PCR inhibitor removal of settled solids for wastewater surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 RNA V1. doi:10.17504/protocols.io.btyrnpv6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17504/protocols.io.btyrnpv6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds EM, Nguyen KH, Harwood VJ, Breitbart M. 2018. Pepper mild mottle virus: a plant pathogen with a greater purpose in (waste)water treatment development and public health management. Water Res 144:1–12. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2018.06.066</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2018.06.066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6162155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30005176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roldan-Hernandez L, Graham KE, Duong D, Boehm AB. 2022. Persistence of endogenous SARS-CoV-2 and pepper mild mottle virus RNA in wastewater-settled solids. ACS EST Water 2:1944–1952. doi:10.1021/acsestwater.2c00003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsestwater.2c00003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8938836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36380769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt MA, Boehm AB, Salit M, Spencer SK, Wigginton KR, Noble RT. 2021. The environmental microbiology minimum information (EMMI) guidelines: QPCR and dPCR quality and reporting for environmental microbiology. Environ Sci Technol 55:10210–10223. doi:10.1021/acs.est.1c01767</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c01767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34286966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisman D. 2012. Seasonality of viral infections: mechanisms and unknowns. Clin Microbiol Infect 18:946–954. doi:10.1111/j.1469-0691.2012.03968.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2012.03968.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22817528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NA, Gonzalez G, Reynolds LJ, Bennett C, Campbell C, Nolan TM, Byrne A, Fennema S, Holohan N, Kuntamukkula SR, et al. . 2023. Adeno-associated virus 2 and human adenovirus F41 in wastewater during outbreak of severe acute hepatitis in children, Ireland. Emerg Infect Dis 29:751–760. doi:10.3201/eid2904.221878</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2904.221878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10045691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36957994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyne MI, Allen DM, Levickas A, Allingham P, Lock J, Fitzgerald A, McSparron C, Nejad BF, McKinley J, Lee A, Bell SH, Quick J, Houldcroft CJ, Bamford CGG, Gilpin DF, McGrath JW. 2023. Detection of human adenovirus F41 in wastewater and its relationship to clinical cases of acute hepatitis of unknown aetiology. Sci Total Environ 857:159579. doi:10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159579</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36270375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Zhou N, Zhang S, Yi Y, Han Y, Liu M, Han Y, Shi N, Yang L, Wang Q, Cui T, Jin H. 2022. Norovirus detection in wastewater and its correlation with human gastroenteritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int 29:22829–22842. doi:10.1007/s11356-021-18202-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-18202-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8769679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35048346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eftim SE, Hong T, Soller J, Boehm A, Warren I, Ichida A, Nappier SP. 2017. Occurrence of norovirus in raw sewage – a systematic literature review and meta-analysis. Water Res 111:366–374. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2017.01.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2017.01.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28110140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke NA, Stevenson RE, Chang SL, Kabler PW. 1961. Removal of enteric viruses from sewage by activated sludge treatment. Am J Public Health Nations Health 51:1118–1129. doi:10.2105/ajph.51.8.1118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/ajph.51.8.1118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1522247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13693898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba CP, Goyal SM, Hurst CJ, Labelle RL. 1980. Type and strain dependence of enterovirus adsorption to activated sludge, soils and estuarine sediments. Water Res 14:1197–1198. doi:10.1016/0043-1354(80)90176-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0043-1354(80)90176-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilker VL, Kamdar RS, Frommhagen LH. 1980. Capacity of activated sludge solids for virus adsorption. Chem Eng Commun 4:569–575. doi:10.1080/00986448008935932</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00986448008935932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arraj A, Bohatier J, Laveran H, Traore O. 2005. Comparison of bacteriophage and enteric virus removal in pilot scale activated sludge plants. J Appl Microbiol 98:516–524. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2672.2004.02485.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2004.02485.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15659206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balluz SA, Butler M, Jones HH. 1978. The behaviour of f2 coliphage in activated sludge treatment. J Hyg (Lond) 80:237–242. doi:10.1017/s0022172400053584</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0022172400053584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2129988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">632563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balluz SA, Jones HH, Bulter M. 1977. The persistence of poliovirus in activated sludge treatment. J Hyg (Lond) 78:165–173. doi:10.1017/s0022172400056060</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0022172400056060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2129849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">191521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malina JF, Ranganathan KR, Sagik BP, Moore BE. 1975. Poliovirus inactivation by activated sludge. J Water Pollut Control Fed 47:2178–2183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">170427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalapati Rao V, Metcalf TG, Melnick JL. 1987. Removal of indigenous rotaviruses during primary settling and activated-sludge treatment of raw sewage. Water Res 21:171–177. doi:10.1016/0043-1354(87)90046-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0043-1354(87)90046-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Y, Ellenberg RM, Graham KE, Wigginton KR. 2016. Survivability, partitioning, and recovery of enveloped viruses in untreated municipal wastewater. Environ Sci Technol 50:5077–5085. doi:10.1021/acs.est.6b00876</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b00876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27111122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama H, Haramoto E, Oguma K, Yamashita H, Tajima A, Nakajima H, Ohgaki S. 2008. One-year monthly quantitative survey of noroviruses, enteroviruses, and adenoviruses in wastewater collected from six plants in Japan. Water Res 42:1441–1448. doi:10.1016/j.watres.2007.10.029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2007.10.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17996920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arts PJ, Kelly JD, Midgley CM, Anglin K, Lu S, Abedi GR, Andino R, Bakker KM, Banman B, Boehm AB, Briggs-Hagen M, Brouwer AF, Davidson MC, Eisenberg MC, Garcia-Knight M, Knight S, Peluso MJ, Pineda-Ramirez J, Diaz Sanchez R, Saydah S, Tassetto M, Martin JN, Wigginton KR. 2023. Longitudinal and quantitative fecal shedding dynamics of SARS-CoV-2, pepper mild mottle virus, and crAssphage. mSphere 8:e0013223. doi:10.1128/msphere.00132-23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00132-23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10506459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37338211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>