<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38405019</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1662-680X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Case reports in neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Case Rep Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A First Case of Acute Flaccid Myelitis Related to Enterovirus D68 in Belgium: Case Report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>41</StartPage><EndPage>47</EndPage><MedlinePgn>41-47</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1159/000535316</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We describe the first case of acute flaccid myelitis (AFM) related to enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) infection in Belgium. The clinical and radiological presentation of AFM associated with EV-D68 although well described currently remains a challenging diagnosis. Through this interesting clinical case, we aimed to review the differential diagnosis of acute flaccid palsy in a child and discuss the specific point of interest related to AFM.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CASE PRESENTATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We present the case of a 4-year-old girl with a torticollis associated with an acute palsy of the right upper limb. The magnetic resonance imaging revealed an increased T2 signal intensity of the entire central gray matter of the cervical cord with involvement of the posterior brainstem. A polymerase chain reaction (PCR) conducted on a nasopharyngeal swab was found positive for EV-D68. The definition of AFM proposed by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) is an acute-onset flaccid weakness of one or more limbs in the absence of a clear alternative diagnosis and the radiological evidence of gray matter involvement on an MRI picture, and our case fits these two criteria. A prompt and detailed workup is required to distinguish this emergent disease from other forms of acute flaccid palsy. The functional prognosis of AFM is poor, and there are no evidence-based treatment guidelines so far.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">AFM is an emerging pathology that requires the attention of pediatricians to quickly rule out differential diagnoses and adequately manage the patient. Further research is needed to optimize treatments, improve outcomes, and provide scientifically based guidelines.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by S. Karger AG, Basel.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rodesch</LastName><ForeName>Marine</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sculier</LastName><ForeName>Claudine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuropediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lolli</LastName><ForeName>Valentina</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Remiche</LastName><ForeName>Gauthier</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre de Référence Neuromusculaire, Department of Neurology, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Delpire</LastName><ForeName>Iris</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fricx</LastName><ForeName>Christophe</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vermeulen</LastName><ForeName>Françoise</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Christiaens</LastName><ForeName>Florence</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuropediatrics, Hôpital Erasme, Université Libre de Bruxelles (ULB), Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Case Rep Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101517693</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1662-680X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Acute flaccid palsy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Motor deficit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spinal cord</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38405019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10890805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000535316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">535316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Maloney JA, Mirsky DM, Messacar K, Dominguez SR, Schreiner T, Stence NV. MRI findings in children with acute flaccid paralysis and cranial nerve dysfunction occurring during the 2014 enterovirus D68 outbreak. Am J Neuroradiol. 2015;36(2):245–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7965662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25414005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy O, Messacar K, Benson L, Bove R, Carpenter J, Crawford T, et al. . Acute flaccid myelitis: cause, diagnosis, and management. Lancet. 2021;397(10271):334–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7909727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33357469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary A, Sharma S, Sankhyan N, Gulati S, Kalra V, Banerjee B, et al. . Midbrain and spinal cord magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) changes in poliomyelitis. J Child Neurol. 2010;25(4):497–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20139405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jang S, Suh S, Ha SM, Byeon JH, Eun BL, Lee YH, et al. . Enterovirus 71-related encephalomyelitis: usual and unusual magnetic resonance imaging findings. Neuroradiology. 2012;54(3):239–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21861081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng H, Wen F, Gan Y, Huang W. MRI and associated clinical characteristics of EV71-induced brainstem encephalitis in children with hand-foot-mouth disease. Neuroradiology. 2012;54(6):623–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22200974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson GR, Bonkowsky JL, Doll E, Green M, Hedlund GL, Moore KR, et al. . Recognition and management of acute flaccid myelitis in children. Pediatr Neurol. 2016;55:17–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26621554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Asturias E, Hixon A, Van Leer-Buter C, Niesters H, Tyler K, et al. . Enterovirus D68 and acute flaccid myelitis: evaluating the evidence for causality. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18(8):e239–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6778404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29482893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Schreiner TL, Van Haren K, Yang M, Glaser CA, Tyler KL, et al. . Acute flaccid myelitis: a clinical review of US cases 2012-2015. Ann Neurol. 2016;80(3):326–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5098271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27422805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wollants E, Beller L, Beuselinck K, Bloemen M, Lagrou K, Reynders M, et al. . A decade of Enterovirus genetic diversity in Belgium. J Clin Virol. 2019;121:104205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31722268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kidd S, Lopez A, Nix WA, Anyalechi G, Itoh M, Yee E, et al. . Vital signs: clinical characteristics of patients with confirmed acute flaccid myelitis, United States, 2018. MMWR. 2020;69(31):1031–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7454900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32759919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shindarov LM, Chumakov MP, Voroshilova MK, Bojinov S, Vasilenko SM, Iordanov I, et al. . Epidemiological, clinical, and pathomorphological characteristics of epidemic poliomyelitis-like disease caused by enterovirus 71. J Hyg Epidemiol Microbiol Immunol. 1979;23(3):284–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">231067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hurst BL, Evans WJ, Smee DF, Van Wettere AJ, Tarbet EB. Evaluation of antiviral therapies in respiratory and neurological disease models of Enterovirus D68 infection in mice. Virology. 2019;526:146–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6309259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30390563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Spence-Davizon E, Osborne C, Press C, Schreiner T, Martin J, et al. . Clinical characteristics of enterovirus A71 neurological disease during an outbreak in children in Colorado, USA, in 2018: an observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2019;S1473-3009(19):30632–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11284833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31859216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devos D, Magot A, Perrier-Boeswillwald J, Fayet G, Leclair-Visonneau L, Ollivier Y, et al. . Guillain–Barré syndrome during childhood: particular clinical and electrophysiological features. Muscle Nerve. 2013;48(2):247–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23813561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helfferich J, Knoester M, Van Leer-Buter C, Neuteboom R, Meiners L, Niesters H, et al. . Acute flaccid myelitis and enterovirus D68: lessons from the past and present. Eur J Pediatr. 2019;178(9):1305–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6694036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31338675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Absoud M, Greenberg B, Lim M, Lotze T, Thomas T, Deiva K. Pediatric transverse myelitis. Neurology. 2016;87(9 Suppl 2):s46–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27572861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Sillau S, Hopkins S, Otten C, Wilson-Murphy M, Wong B, et al. . Safety, tolerability, and efficacy of fluoxetine as an antiviral for acute flaccid myelitis. Neurology. 2019;92(18):e2118–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6512883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30413631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruggieri V, Paz MI, Peretti MG, Rugilo C, Bologna R, Freire C, et al. . Enterovirus D68 infection in a cluster of children with acute flaccid myelitis, Buenos Aires, Argentina, 2016. Eur J Paediatr Neurol. 2017;21(6):884–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28747261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saltzman E, Rancy S, Sneag D, Feinberg Md JH, Lange D, Wolfe S. Nerve transfers for enterovirus D68-associated acute flaccid myelitis: a case series. Pediatr Neurol. 2018;88:25–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30301588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Tyler K. Enterovirus D68-associated acute flaccid myelitis rising to the clinical and research challenges. JAMA. 2019;321(9):831–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30768149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>