<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38496499</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Nasopharyngeal metatranscriptomics reveals host-pathogen signatures of pediatric sinusitis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.03.03.24303663</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.03.03.24303663</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Acute sinusitis (AS) is the fifth leading cause of antibiotic prescriptions in children. Distinguishing bacterial AS from common viral upper respiratory infections in children is crucial to prevent unnecessary antibiotic use but is challenging with current diagnostic methods. Despite its speed and cost, untargeted RNA sequencing of clinical samples from children with suspected AS has the potential to overcome several limitations of other methods. However, the utility of sequencing-based approaches in analysis of AS has not been fully explored. Here, we performed RNA-seq of nasopharyngeal samples from 221 children with clinically diagnosed AS to characterize their pathogen and host-response profiles. Results from RNA-seq were compared with those obtained using culture for three common bacterial pathogens and qRT-PCR for 12 respiratory viruses. Metatranscriptomic pathogen detection showed high concordance with culture or qRT-PCR, showing 87%/81% sensitivity (sens) / specificity (spec) for detecting bacteria, and 86%/92% (sens/spec) for viruses, respectively. We also detected an additional 22 pathogens not tested for in the clinical panel, and identified plausible pathogens in 11/19 (58%) of cases where no organism was detected by culture or qRT-PCR. We assembled genomes of 205 viruses across the samples including novel strains of coronaviruses, respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), and enterovirus D68. By analyzing host gene expression, we identified host-response signatures that distinguished bacterial and viral infections and correlated with pathogen abundance. Ultimately, our study demonstrates the potential of untargeted metatranscriptomics for in depth analysis of the etiology of AS, comprehensive host-response profiling, and using these together to work towards optimized patient care.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AbuMazen</LastName><ForeName>Nooran</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Waterloo Centre for Microbial Research, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chu</LastName><ForeName>Vivian</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Waterloo Centre for Microbial Research, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hunjan</LastName><ForeName>Manjot</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Waterloo Centre for Microbial Research, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lobb</LastName><ForeName>Briallen</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Waterloo Centre for Microbial Research, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Sojin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC, Division of General Academic Pediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kurs-Lasky</LastName><ForeName>Marcia</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC, Division of General Academic Pediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Williams</LastName><ForeName>John V</ForeName><Initials>JV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>MacDonald</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC, Division of General Academic Pediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johnson</LastName><ForeName>Monika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hirota</LastName><ForeName>Jeremy A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2429-4165</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Firestone Institute for Respiratory Health, St. Joseph's Hospital, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of British Columbia, Department of Medicine, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>McMaster University, Department of Medicine, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaikh</LastName><ForeName>Nader</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1602-343X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC, Division of General Academic Pediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doxey</LastName><ForeName>Andrew C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2015-099X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Waterloo Centre for Microbial Research, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cheriton School of Computer Science, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>McMaster University, Department of Medicine, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>U01 AI118506</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Competing interests: The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38496499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10942525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.03.03.24303663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.03.03.24303663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Brook I., Acute sinusitis in children. Pediatr Clin North Am 60, 409–424 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23481108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung A. K. C., Hon K. L., Chu W. C. W., Acute bacterial sinusitis in children: an updated review. Drugs Context 9 (2020), doi:10.7573/DIC.2020-9-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7573/DIC.2020-9-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33281908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming-Dutra K. E., Hersh A. L., Shapiro D. J., Bartoces M., Enns E. A., File T. M., Finkelstein J. A., Gerber J. S., Hyun D. Y., Linder J. A., Lynfield R., Margolis D. J., May L. S., Merenstein D., Metlay J. P., Newland J. G., Piccirillo J. F., Roberts R. M., V Sanchez G., Suda K. J., Thomas A., Woo T. M., Zetts R. M., Hicks L. A., Prevalence of Inappropriate Antibiotic Prescriptions Among US Ambulatory Care Visits, 2010–2011. JAMA 315, 1864–73 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27139059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wald E. R., Milmoe G. J., Bowen A., Ledesma-Medina J., Salamon N., Bluestone C. D., Acute maxillary sinusitis in children. N Engl J Med 304, 749–54 (1981).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6970333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlton C. L., Babady E., Ginocchio C. C., Hatchette T. F., Jerris R. C., Li Y., Loeffelholz M., McCarter Y. S., Miller M. B., Novak-Weekley S., Schuetz A. N., Tang Y. W., Widen R., Drews S. J., Practical Guidance for Clinical Microbiology Laboratories: Viruses Causing Acute Respiratory Tract Infections. Clin Microbiol Rev 32 (2018), doi:10.1128/CMR.00042-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00042-18</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6302358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30541871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh N., Hoberman A., Shope T. R., Jeong J.-H., Kurs-Lasky M., Martin J. M., Bhatnagar S., Muniz G. B., Block S. L., Andrasko M., Lee M. C., Rajakumar K., Wald E. R., Identifying Children Likely to Benefit From Antibiotics for Acute Sinusitis: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA 330, 349–358 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10370259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37490085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knipe D. M., Howley P., Fields Virology (Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, ed. 6, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brook I., Microbiology of sinusitis. Proc Am Thorac Soc 8, 90–100 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21364226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tada A., Hanada N., Opportunistic respiratory pathogens in the oral cavity of the elderly. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol 60, 1–17 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20579096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu W., Miller S., Chiu C. Y., Clinical Metagenomic Next-Generation Sequencing for Pathogen Detection. Annu Rev Pathol 14, 319–338 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6345613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30355154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiu C. Y., Miller S. A., Clinical metagenomics. Nat Rev Genet 20, 341–355 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6858796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30918369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie F., Duan Z., Zeng W., Xie S., Xie M., Fu H., Ye Q., Xu T., Xie L., Clinical metagenomics assessments improve diagnosis and outcomes in community-acquired pneumonia. BMC Infect Dis 21 (2021), doi:10.1186/S12879-021-06039-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/S12879-021-06039-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8047593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33858378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlaberg R., Queen K., Simmon K., Tardif K., Stockmann C., Flygare S., Kennedy B., Voelkerding K., Bramley A., Zhang J., Eilbeck K., Yandell M., Jain S., Pavia A. T., Tong S., Ampofo K., Viral Pathogen Detection by Metagenomics and Pan-Viral Group Polymerase Chain Reaction in Children With Pneumonia Lacking Identifiable Etiology. J Infect Dis 215, 1407–1415 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5565793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28368491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Tan L., Thi Thu Hong N., My Ngoc N., Tan Thanh T., Thanh Lam V., Anh Nguyet L., Nguyen Truc Nhu L., Thi Ha Ny N., Ngoc Quang Minh N., Nguyen Huy Man D., Thi Ty Hang V., Nguyen Quoc Khanh P., Chanh Xuan T., Thanh Phong N., Nguyen Hoang Tu T., Tinh Hien T., Manh Hung L., Thanh Truong N., Min Yen L., Thanh Dung N., Thwaites G., Van Vinh Chau N., for OUCRU COVID-19 research group, SARS-CoV-2 and co-infections detection in nasopharyngeal throat swabs of COVID-19 patients by metagenomics. J Infect 81, e175–e177 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7403860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32562797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piantadosi A., Mukerji S. S., Ye S., Leone M. J., Freimark L. M., Park D., Adams G., Lemieux J., Kanjilal S., Solomon I. H., Ahmed A. A., Goldstein R., Ganesh V., Ostrem B., Cummins K. C., Thon J. M., Kinsella C. M., Rosenberg E., Frosch M. P., Goldberg M. B., Cho T. A., Sabeti P., Enhanced Virus Detection and Metagenomic Sequencing in Patients with Meningitis and Encephalitis. mBio 12, e0114321 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8406231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34465023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramesh A., Nakielny S., Hsu J., Kyohere M., Byaruhanga O., de Bourcy C., Egger R., Dimitrov B., Juan Y.-F., Sheu J., Wang J., Kalantar K., Langelier C., Ruel T., Mpimbaza A., Wilson M. R., Rosenthal P. J., DeRisi J. L., Metagenomic next-generation sequencing of samples from pediatric febrile illness in Tororo, Uganda. PLoS One 14, e0218318 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6586300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31220115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsalik E. L., Henao R., Nichols M., Burke T., Ko E. R., McClain M. T., Hudson L. L., Mazur A., Freeman D. H., Veldman T., Langley R. J., Quackenbush E. B., Glickman S. W., Cairns C. B., Jaehne A. K., Rivers E. P., Otero R. M., Zaas A. K., Kingsmore S. F., Lucas J., Fowler V. G., Carin L., Ginsburg G. S., Woods C. W., Host gene expression classifiers diagnose acute respiratory illness etiology. Sci Transl Med 8, 322ra11 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4905578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26791949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaas A. K., Chen M., Varkey J., Veldman T., Hero A. O., Lucas J., Huang Y., Turner R., Gilbert A., Lambkin-Williams R., Øien N. C., Nicholson B., Kingsmore S., Carin L., Woods C. W., Ginsburg G. S., Gene expression signatures diagnose influenza and other symptomatic respiratory viral infections in humans. Cell Host Microbe 6, 207–17 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2852511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19664979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukutani K. F., Nascimento-Carvalho C. M., Bouzas M. L., Oliveira J. R., Barral A., Dierckx T., Khouri R., Nakaya H. I., Andrade B. B., Van Weyenbergh J., de Oliveira C. I., In situ Immune Signatures and Microbial Load at the Nasopharyngeal Interface in Children With Acute Respiratory Infection. Front Microbiol 9, 2475 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6238668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30473680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsao Y.-T., Tsai Y.-H., Liao W.-T., Shen C.-J., Shen C.-F., Cheng C.-M., Differential Markers of Bacterial and Viral Infections in Children for Point-of-Care Testing. Trends Mol Med 26, 1118–1132 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7522093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33008730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashkenazi-Hoffnung L., Oved K., Navon R., Friedman T., Boico O., Paz M., Kronenfeld G., Etshtein L., Cohen A., Gottlieb T. M., Eden E., Chistyakov I., Srugo I., Klein A., Ashkenazi S., Scheuerman O., A host-protein signature is superior to other biomarkers for differentiating between bacterial and viral disease in patients with respiratory infection and fever without source: a prospective observational study. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis 37, 1361–1371 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6015097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29700762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mick E., Tsitsiklis A., Kamm J., Kalantar K. L., Caldera S., Lyden A., Tan M., Detweiler A. M., Neff N., Osborne C. M., Williamson K. M., Soesanto V., Leroue M., Maddux A. B., Simões E. A., Carpenter T. C., Wagner B. D., DeRisi J. L., Ambroggio L., Mourani P. M., Langelier C. R., Integrated host/microbe metagenomics enables accurate lower respiratory tract infection diagnosis in critically ill children. J Clin Invest 133 (2023), doi:10.1172/JCI165904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1172/JCI165904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10065066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37009900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez S. M. C., Martin J. M., Johnson M., Kurs-Lasky M., Horne W. T., Marshall C. W., Cooper V. S., Williams J. V., Shaikh N., A method of processing nasopharyngeal swabs to enable multiple testing. Pediatr Res 86, 651–654 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6851467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31288247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood D. E., Lu J., Langmead B., Improved metagenomic analysis with Kraken 2. Genome Biol 20 (2019), doi:10.1186/S13059-019-1891-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/S13059-019-1891-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6883579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31779668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcock B. P., Raphenya A. R., Lau T. T. Y., Tsang K. K., Bouchard M., Edalatmand A., Huynh W., Nguyen A. L. V., Cheng A. A., Liu S., Min S. Y., Miroshnichenko A., Tran H. K., Werfalli R. E., Nasir J. A., Oloni M., Speicher D. J., Florescu A., Singh B., Faltyn M., Hernandez-Koutoucheva A., Sharma A. N., Bordeleau E., Pawlowski A. C., Zubyk H. L., Dooley D., Griffiths E., Maguire F., Winsor G. L., Beiko R. G., Brinkman F. S. L., Hsiao W. W. L., Domselaar G. V., McArthur A. G., CARD 2020: antibiotic resistome surveillance with the comprehensive antibiotic resistance database. Nucleic Acids Res 48, D517–D525 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7145624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31665441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Abreu V. A. C., Perdigão J., Almeida S., Metagenomic Approaches to Analyze Antimicrobial Resistance: An Overview. Front Genet 11, 575592 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33537056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graf E. H., Simmon K. E., Tardif K. D., Hymas W., Flygare S., Eilbeck K., Yandell M., Schlaberg R., Unbiased Detection of Respiratory Viruses by Use of RNA Sequencing-Based Metagenomics: a Systematic Comparison to a Commercial PCR Panel. J Clin Microbiol 54, 1000–7 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4809917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26818672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorburn F., Bennett S., Modha S., Murdoch D., Gunson R., Murcia P. R., The use of next generation sequencing in the diagnosis and typing of respiratory infections. J Clin Virol 69, 96–100 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4533236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26209388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waites K. B., Atkinson T. P., The role of Mycoplasma in upper respiratory infections. Curr Infect Dis Rep 11, 198–206 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19366562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blasi F., Clinical features of Chlamydia pneumoniae acute respiratory infection. Clin Microbiol Infect 1 Suppl 1, S14–S18 (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7162363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11866789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Chaparro P. J., Gonçalves C., Figueiredo L. C., Faveri M., Lobão E., Tamashiro N., Duarte P., Feres M., Newly identified pathogens associated with periodontitis: a systematic review. J Dent Res 93, 846–58 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4541103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25074492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olijve L., Jennings L., Walls T., Human Parechovirus: an Increasingly Recognized Cause of Sepsis-Like Illness in Young Infants. Clin Microbiol Rev 31 (2018), doi:10.1128/CMR.00047-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00047-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5740974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29142080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zoll J., Erkens Hulshof S., Lanke K., Verduyn Lunel F., Melchers W. J. G., Schoondermark-van de Ven E., Roivainen M., Galama J. M. D., van Kuppeveld F. J. M., Saffold virus, a human Theiler’s-like cardiovirus, is ubiquitous and causes infection early in life. PLoS Pathog 5, e1000416 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2670511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19412527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venter M., van Niekerk S., Rakgantso A., Bent N., Identification of deletion mutant respiratory syncytial virus strains lacking most of the G protein in immunocompromised children with pneumonia in South Africa. J Virol 85, 8453–8457 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3147957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21680500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sims J. T., Poorbaugh J., Chang C.-Y., Holzer T. R., Zhang L., Engle S. M., Beasley S., Doman T. N., Naughton L., Higgs R. E., Kallewaard N., Benschop R. J., Relationship between gene expression patterns from nasopharyngeal swabs and serum biomarkers in patients hospitalized with COVID-19, following treatment with the neutralizing monoclonal antibody bamlanivimab. J Transl Med 20, 134 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8931785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35303909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheemarla N. R., Hanron A., Fauver J. R., Bishai J., Watkins T. A., Brito A. F., Zhao D., Alpert T., Vogels C. B. F., Ko A. I., Schulz W. L., Landry M. L., Grubaugh N. D., van Dijk D., Foxman E. F., Nasal host response-based screening for undiagnosed respiratory viruses: a pathogen surveillance and detection study. Lancet Microbe 4, e38–e46 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9835789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36586415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wesolowska-Andersen A., Everman J. L., Davidson R., Rios C., Herrin R., Eng C., Janssen W. J., Liu A. H., Oh S. S., Kumar R., Fingerlin T. E., Rodriguez-Santana J., Burchard E. G., Seibold M. A., Dual RNA-seq reveals viral infections in asthmatic children without respiratory illness which are associated with changes in the airway transcriptome. Genome Biol 18, 12 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5244706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28103897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler D., Mozsary C., Meydan C., Foox J., Rosiene J., Shaiber A., Danko D., Afshinnekoo E., MacKay M., Sedlazeck F. J., Ivanov N. A., Sierra M., Pohle D., Zietz M., Gisladottir U., Ramlall V., Sholle E. T., Schenck E. J., Westover C. D., Hassan C., Ryon K., Young B., Bhattacharya C., Ng D. L., Granados A. C., Santos Y. A., Servellita V., Federman S., Ruggiero P., Fungtammasan A., Chin C. S., Pearson N. M., Langhorst B. W., Tanner N. A., Kim Y., Reeves J. W., Hether T. D., Warren S. E., Bailey M., Gawrys J., Meleshko D., Xu D., Couto-Rodriguez M., Nagy-Szakal D., Barrows J., Wells H., O’Hara N. B., Rosenfeld J. A., Chen Y., Steel P. A. D., Shemesh A. J., Xiang J., Thierry-Mieg J., Thierry-Mieg D., Iftner A., Bezdan D., Sanchez E., Campion T. R., Sipley J., Cong L., Craney A., Velu P., Melnick A. M., Shapira S., Hajirasouliha I., Borczuk A., Iftner T., Salvatore M., Loda M., Westblade L. F., Cushing M., Wu S., Levy S., Chiu C., Schwartz R. E., Tatonetti N., Rennert H., Imielinski M., Mason C. E., Shotgun transcriptome, spatial omics, and isothermal profiling of SARS-CoV-2 infection reveals unique host responses, viral diversification, and drug interactions. Nat Commun 12 (2021), doi:10.1038/S41467-021-21361-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/S41467-021-21361-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7954844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33712587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combaret L., Taillandier D., Polge C., Béchet D., Attaix D., in The Molecular Nutrition of Amino Acids and Proteins, (Elsevier, 2016), pp. 27–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu P., Zhang X., Liu N., Tang L., Peng C., Chen X., Pyroptosis: mechanisms and diseases. Signal Transduct Target Ther 6, 128 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33776057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tristram S., Jacobs M. R., Appelbaum P. C., Antimicrobial resistance in Haemophilus influenzae. Clin Microbiol Rev 20, 368–389 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1865592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17428889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Eldere J., Slack M. P. E., Ladhani S., Cripps A. W., Non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae, an under-recognised pathogen. Lancet Infect Dis 14, 1281–92 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25012226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobb B., Lee M. C., McElheny C. L., Doi Y., Yahner K., Hoberman A., Martin J. M., Hirota J. A., Doxey A. C., Shaikh N., Genomic classification and antimicrobial resistance profiling of Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae isolates associated with paediatric otitis media and upper respiratory infection. BMC Infect Dis 23, 596 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10498559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37700242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saravia-Butler A. M., Schisler J. C., Taylor D., Beheshti A., Butler D., Meydan C., Foox J., Hernandez K., Mozsary C., Mason C. E., Meller R., Host transcriptional responses in nasal swabs identify potential SARS-CoV-2 infection in PCR negative patients. iScience 25, 105310 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9540688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36246576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landry M. L., Foxman E. F., Antiviral Response in the Nasopharynx Identifies Patients With Respiratory Virus Infection. J Infect Dis 217, 897–905 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5853594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29281100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheemarla N. R., Watkins T. A., Mihaylova V. T., Wang B., Zhao D., Wang G., Landry M. L., Foxman E. F., Dynamic innate immune response determines susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infection and early replication kinetics. J Exp Med 218 (2021), doi:10.1084/jem.20210583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1084/jem.20210583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8210587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34128960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karalus R., Campagnari A., Moraxella catarrhalis: a review of an important human mucosal pathogen. Microbes Infect 2, 547–59 (2000).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10865200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henriques-Normark B., Normark S., Commensal pathogens, with a focus on Streptococcus pneumoniae, and interactions with the human host. Exp Cell Res 316, 1408–14 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20227406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews S., FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. (2010) (available at http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S., Zhou Y., Chen Y., Gu J., fastp: an ultra-fast all-in-one FASTQ preprocessor. Bioinformatics 34, i884–i890 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6129281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30423086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewels P., Magnusson M., Lundin S., Käller M., MultiQC: summarize analysis results for multiple tools and samples in a single report. Bioinformatics 32, 3047–3048 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5039924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27312411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altschul S. F., Madden T. L., Schäffer A. A., Zhang J., Zhang Z., Miller W., Lipman D. J., Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: A new generation of protein database search programs. Nucleic Acids Res 25, 3389–3402 (1997).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC146917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9254694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ondov B. D., Treangen T. J., Melsted P., Mallonee A. B., Bergman N. H., Koren S., Phillippy A. M., Mash: fast genome and metagenome distance estimation using MinHash. Genome Biol 17, 132 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4915045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27323842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrenko P., Lobb B., Kurtz D. A., Neufeld J. D., Doxey A. C., MetAnnotate: function-specific taxonomic profiling and comparison of metagenomes. BMC Biol 13, 92 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4636000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26541816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H., ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis (Springer-Verlag, New York, 2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bankevich A., Nurk S., Antipov D., Gurevich A. A., Dvorkin M., Kulikov A. S., Lesin V. M., Nikolenko S. I., Pham S., Prjibelski A. D., V Pyshkin A., V Sirotkin A., Vyahhi N., Tesler G., Alekseyev M. A., Pevzner P. A., SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing. J Comput Biol 19, 455–77 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3342519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22506599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bushnell B., BBMap: A Fast, Accurate, Splice-Aware Aligner https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1241166 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edgar R. C., MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput. Nucleic Acids Res 32, 1792–7 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC390337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15034147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price M., Dehal P., Arkin A., FastTree 2--approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments. PLoS One 5 (2010), doi:10.1371/JOURNAL.PONE.0009490.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/JOURNAL.PONE.0009490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2835736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20224823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patro R., Duggal G., Love M. I., Irizarry R. A., Kingsford C., Salmon provides fast and bias-aware quantification of transcript expression. Nat Methods 14, 417–419 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5600148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28263959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love M. I., Huber W., Anders S., Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol 15 (2014), doi:10.1186/S13059-014-0550-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/S13059-014-0550-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4302049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25516281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuleshov M. V., Jones M. R., Rouillard A. D., Fernandez N. F., Duan Q., Wang Z., Koplev S., Jenkins S. L., Jagodnik K. M., Lachmann A., McDermott M. G., Monteiro C. D., Gundersen G. W., Maayan A., Enrichr: a comprehensive gene set enrichment analysis web server 2016 update. Nucleic Acids Res 44, W90–W97 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4987924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27141961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>