<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38492637</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2320-2890</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biomedical journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biomed J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Reflecting on the 1998 enterovirus outbreak: A 25-year retrospective and learned lessons.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100715</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100715</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.bj.2024.100715</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2319-4170(24)00018-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus A71 (EV-A71) infections pose a significant public health concern in the Asia-Pacific region. EV-A71 is primarily responsible for causing hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) in children. However, this virus can also lead to severe and potentially fatal neurological consequences in affected individuals. This review aims to provide a comprehensive understanding of the molecular virology, epidemiology, and recombination events associated with EV-A71. The literature extensively covers the clinical manifestations and neurological symptoms that accompany EV-A71 infections. One of the complications explored in this review is brainstem encephalitis, which can arise as a result of EV-A71 infections. Brainstem encephalitis refers to inflammation of the brainstem, a critical region responsible for various bodily functions. The review examines the underlying mechanisms, diagnostic criteria, treatment options, and prognosis for central nervous system infections involving EV-A71. Neurological complications associated with EV-A71 infections are diverse and can have severe consequences. These complications may include aseptic meningitis, acute flaccid paralysis, and acute transverse myelitis. The review delves into the pathophysiology of these complications, shedding light on the molecular mechanisms through which EV-A71 affects the central nervous system. Accurate diagnosis of EV-A71 infections is crucial for appropriate management and treatment. Treatment options for EV-A71 infections primarily focus on supportive care, as there are currently no specific antiviral drugs available for this virus. The review highlights the importance of managing symptoms, such as fever, dehydration, and pain relief, to alleviate the burden on affected individuals. Prognosis for individuals with central nervous system (CNS) infections involving EV-A71 can vary depending on the severity of the complications. The review provides insights into the long-term outcomes and potential neurological sequelae associated with EV-A71 infections. In conclusion, EV-A71 infections have emerged as a major public health concern in the Asia-Pacific region. This review aims to enhance our understanding of the molecular virology, epidemiology, and neurological complications associated with EV-A71. By examining the underlying mechanisms, diagnostic criteria, treatment options, and prognosis, this review contributes to the development of effective strategies for the prevention, diagnosis, and management of EV-A71 infections. The paper presents a comprehensive analysis of worldwide data pertaining to outbreaks of EV-A71 and HFMD. The subsequent discourse delves into the advancement and strategic formulation pertaining to the creation of vaccines targeting EV-A71. In summary, this study provides a comprehensive examination of the potential obstacles and considerations involved in the management and treatment of EV-A71 infections. Additionally, it proposes suggestions for future research and development endeavors with the objective of formulating efficacious treatment approaches for this viral infection.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Peng-Nien</ForeName><Initials>PN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsia</LastName><ForeName>Shao-Hsuan</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Critical Care Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Department of Pediatric Respiratory Therapy, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan; College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Kuan-Ying Arthur</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan; College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Chih-Jung</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan; College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>En-Tzu</ForeName><Initials>ET</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Acute Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shih</LastName><ForeName>Shin-Ru</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Emerging Viral Infections, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Department of Medical Biotechnology and Laboratory Science, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Department of Laboratory Medicine, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Research Center for Chinese Herbal Medicine, Research Center for Food and Cosmetic Safety, and Graduate Institute of Health Industry Technology, College of Human Ecology, Chang Gung University of Science and Technology, Taoyuan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Tzou-Yien</ForeName><Initials>TY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, Taiwan; Department of Pediatrics, College of Medicine, Chang Gung University, Taoyuan, Taiwan. Electronic address: tzuen@cgmh.org.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Biomed J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101599820</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2319-4170</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38492637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bj.2024.100715</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2319-4170(24)00018-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>