<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38552101</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>13</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of FilmArray respiratory panel test for hospitalized pediatric respiratory tract infection in Taiwan: A 3-year single-center cohort study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37320</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37320</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37320</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000037320</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Respiratory tract infections are prevalent and clinically significant in pediatric populations globally. However, pathogen testing often involves time-consuming processes, resulting in delays in diagnosis. To date, commercial testing machines, such as the FilmArray respiratory panel, have been proposed for hospitals. Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the impact of the FilmArray respiratory panel at a single center. This study utilized the medical records of our hospital to select pediatric inpatients with respiratory tract infections who underwent the FilmArray respiratory panel between September 2020 and April 2021 and those who did not undergo nucleic acid detection (a rapid test group) between September 2019 and April 2020. FilmArray is a polymerase chain reaction-based diagnostic tool. The FilmArray respiratory panel group was scheduled to recruit 150 patients (final 137 patients), whereas the rapid test group was scheduled to recruit 300 patients (final 267 patients). Differences in continuous variables between the 2 groups were analyzed using independent Student t tests. The FilmArray respiratory panel group had a longer length of inpatient days, longer duration of antibiotic use, and higher proportion of pathogens that tested positive, with significant differences than those in the rapid test group. Fever duration showed no significant difference between the 2 groups. For the polymerase chain reaction method, respiratory syncytial virus was the most commonly detected pathogen causing pneumonia, followed by human rhinovirus/enterovirus and parainfluenza virus. Mycoplasma was detected using the rapid test but not with the FilmArray respiratory panel. The FilmArray respiratory panel provides clinicians with a rapid and useful diagnostic tool. The effect was quite good for virus detection, but not for bacteria. Given its limited adoption, the tool may not aid clinicians in the diagnosis of mild cases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Jen-Jan</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taiwan Adventist Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Da-Ling</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Taiwan Adventist Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tzeng</LastName><ForeName>I-Shiang</ForeName><Initials>IS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9047-8141</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Education and Research, Taiwan Adventist Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, National Taipei University, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014780" MajorTopicYN="Y">Viruses</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013624" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Taiwan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D025202" MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular Diagnostic Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018113" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Syncytial Virus, Human</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38552101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10977531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000037320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202403290-00069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Chen AP, Chuang C, Huang YC, et al. . The epidemiology and etiologies of respiratory tract infection in Northern Taiwan during the early phase of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2021;54:801–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8217336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34217634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shih HI, Wang HC, Su IJ, et al. . Viral respiratory tract infections in adult patients attending outpatient and emergency departments, Taiwan, 2012-2013: a PCR/electrospray ionization mass spectrometry study. Medicine (Baltimore). 2015;94:e1545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4635751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26402811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dion CF, Ashurst JV. Streptococcus pneumoniae. [Updated 2022 Aug 8]. In: StatPearls. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2022. Available at: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK470537/.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29261971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khattak ZE, Anjum F. Haemophilus influenzae. [Updated 2022 Sep 12]. In: StatPearls. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2022. Available at: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562176/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwanaga Y, Yamasaki K, Nemoto K, et al. . Combined radiographic features and age can distinguish mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia from other bacterial pneumonias: analysis using the 16S rRNA gene sequencing data. J Clin Med. 2022;11:2201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9032927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35456296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattila S, Paalanne N, Honkila M, et al. . Effect of point-of-care testing for respiratory pathogens on antibiotic use in children: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:e2216162.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9185185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35679047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogl T, Klompus S, Leviatan S, et al. . Population-wide diversity and stability of serum antibody epitope repertoires against human microbiota. Nat Med. 2021;27:1442–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34282338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>S Pavia C, M Plummer M. The evolution of rapid antigen detection systems and their application for COVID-19 and other serious respiratory infectious diseases. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2021;54:776–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8234251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34272205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong D, Song L, Tao J, et al. . An efficient multiplex PCR-based assay as a novel tool for accurate inter-serovar discrimination of salmonella enteritidis, S. Pullorum/Gallinarum and S. Dublin. Front Microbiol. 2017;8:420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5352712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28360901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butt SA, Maceira VP, McCallen ME, et al. . Comparison of three commercial RT-PCR systems for the detection of respiratory viruses. J Clin Virol. 2014;61:406–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25183359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy CN, Fowler R, Balada-Llasat JM, et al. . Multicenter evaluation of the BioFire FilmArray pneumonia/pneumonia plus panel for detection and quantification of agents of lower respiratory tract infection. J Clin Microbiol. 2020;58:e00128–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7315029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32350043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitano T, Nishikawa H, Suzuki R, et al. . The impact analysis of a multiplex PCR respiratory panel for hospitalized pediatric respiratory infections in Japan. J Infect Chemother. 2020;26:82–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7128379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31383498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark TW, Lindsley K, Wigmosta TB, et al. . Rapid multiplex PCR for respiratory viruses reduces time to result and improves clinical care: results of a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect. 2023;86:462–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36906153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soucek DK, Dumkow LE, VanLangen KM, et al. . Cost justification of the BioFire FilmArray meningitis/encephalitis panel versus standard of care for diagnosing meningitis in a community hospital. J Pharm Pract. 2019;32:36–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29092659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyriazopoulou E, Karageorgos A, Liaskou-Antoniou L, et al. . BioFire® FilmArray® pneumonia panel for severe lower respiratory tract infections: subgroup analysis of a randomized clinical trial. Infect Dis Ther. 2021;10:1437–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8197784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34120316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tirore LL, Abame DE, Sedoro T, et al. . Time to recovery from severe pneumonia and its predictors among children 2-59 months of age admitted to pediatric ward of Nigist Eleni Mohammed memorial comprehensive specialized hospital, Hossana, Ethiopia: retrospective cohort study. Pediatric Health Med Ther. 2021;12:347–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8312316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Tao Y, Tang M, et al. . Rapid detection of respiratory organisms with the FilmArray respiratory panel in a large children’s hospital in China. BMC Infect Dis. 2018;18:510.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6180626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30305033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh EE, Hall CB. Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). In: Mandell, Douglas, and Bennett’s Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases. 2015:1948–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnstone J, Majumdar SR, Fox JD, et al. . Viral infection in adults hospitalized with community-acquired pneumonia: prevalence, pathogens, and presentation. Chest. 2008;134:1141–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18689592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiley KT, Van Deerlin VM, Miller WT, Jr. Chest CT features of community-acquired respiratory viral infections in adult inpatients with lower respiratory tract infections. J Thorac Imaging. 2010;25:68–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20160606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamma PD, Cosgrove SE, Maragakis LL. Combination therapy for treatment of infections with gram-negative bacteria. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2012;25:450–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3416487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22763634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaherman V, Li S, Ragins A, et al. . Respiratory syncytial virus testing during bronchiolitis episodes of care in an integrated health care delivery system: a retrospective cohort study. Clin Ther. 2010;32:2220–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21316538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Mencacci A, Cenci E, et al. . Multiplex platforms for the identification of respiratory pathogens: are they useful in pediatric clinical practice? Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2019;9:196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6593267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31275863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Ji W, Wang Y, et al. . Epidemiology and associations with climatic conditions of Mycoplasma pneumoniae and Chlamydophila pneumoniae infections among Chinese children hospitalized with acute respiratory infections. Ital J Pediatr. 2013;39:34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3691665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23705964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prendki V, Huttner B, Marti C, et al. . Accuracy of comprehensive PCR analysis of nasopharyngeal and oropharyngeal swabs for CT-scan-confirmed pneumonia in elderly patients: a prospective cohort study. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2019;25:1114–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30641227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trenti T, Pecoraro V, Pirotti T, et al. . IgM anti-SARS-CoV-2-specific determination: useful or confusing? Big Data analysis of a real-life scenario. Intern Emerg Med. 2021;16:2327–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8088482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33934298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soo RJJ, Chiew CJ, Ma S, et al. . Decreased influenza incidence under COVID-19 control measures, Singapore. Emerg Infect Dis. 2020;26:1933–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32339092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>