<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38590253</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>10</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence and genetic diversity of human rhinovirus among patients with acute respiratory infections in China, 2012-2021.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29582</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29582</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29582</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>To understand the prevalence of rhinovirus (RV) among acute respiratory infection (ARI) patients, 10-year ARI surveillance in multiple provinces of China were conducted during 2012-2021. Of 15 645 ARI patients, 1180 (7.54%) were confirmed to have RV infection and 820 (69.49%) were children under 5 years of age. RV typing was performed on the 527 VP1 gene sequences, and species A, B, and C accounted for 73.24%, 4.93%, and 21.82%, respectively. Although no significant difference in the proportions of age groups or disease severity was found between RV species, RV-C was more frequently detected in children under 5 years of age, RV-A was more frequently detected in elderly individuals (≥60), and the proportions of pneumonia in RV-A and RV-C patients were higher than those in RV-B patients. The epidemic peak of RV-A was earlier than that of RV-C. A total of 57 types of RV-A, 13 types of RV-B, and 35 types of RV-C were identified in RV-infected patients, and two uncertain RV types were also detected. The findings showed a few differences in epidemiological and clinical features between RV species in ARI patients, and RV-A and RV-C were more prevalent than RV-B.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cui</LastName><ForeName>Aili</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xia</LastName><ForeName>Baicheng</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8305-4634</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Haoran</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Qi</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9422-3066</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Hebei Province Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Shijiazhuang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Liwei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Precision Medicine Research Center, Children's Hospital of Changchun, Changchun, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Henan Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Kongxin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Health Inspection and Quarantine, Chinese Academy of Inspection and Quarantine, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Zhibo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3327-453X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yage</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Runan</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Virology, Beijing Key Laboratory of Etiology of Viral Diseases in Children, Capital Institute of Pediatrics, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Chaoyang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Hunan Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Changsha, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Zhong</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Viral Diseases, Institute for Communicable Disease Control and Prevention, Shandong Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Jinan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Viral Disease Department, Shaanxi Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Wenyang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Frontier Experimental Center, School of Medicine, Anhui University of Science and Technology, Huainan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Virus Laboratory, Gansu Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Lanzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Zhenguo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Infectious Disease Prevention and Treatment, Xinjiang Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Wulumuqi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Feng</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viral Diseases, Qingdao Municipal Centre for Disease Control and Prevention, Qingdao Institute of Prevention Medicine, Qingdao, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Immunization and Prevention, Beijing Center for Disease Prevention and Control, Beijing Academy for Preventive Medicine, Beijing Institute of Tuberculosis Control Research and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Intelligent Tracking and Forecasting for Infectious Diseases (NITFID), NHC Key Laboratory of Medical Virology and Viral Diseases, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>ZDGW21-131031103000180005</GrantID><Agency>The National Health Commission Major Public Health Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2013ZX10004202</GrantID><Agency>The Key Technologies Research and Development Program of the National Ministry of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2018ZX10713002</GrantID><Agency>The Key Technologies Research and Development Program of the National Ministry of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012229" MajorTopicYN="N">Rhinovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="Y">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014644" MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic Variation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute respiratory infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genetic diversity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human rhinovirus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38590253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Jacobs SE, Lamson DM, St George K, Walsh TJ. Human rhinoviruses. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2013;26:135‐162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Costa Souza L, Bello EJM, dos Santos EM, Nagata T. Molecular and clinical characteristics related to rhinovirus infection in Brasília, Brazil. Braz J Microbiol. 2021;52:289‐298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li ZJ, Zhang HY, Ren LL, et al. Etiological and epidemiological features of acute respiratory infections in China. Nat Commun. 2021;12:5026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piedra PA. Prospective multicenter study of viral etiology and hospital length of stay in children with severe bronchiolitis. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2012;166:700‐706.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ledford RM, Patel NR, Demenczuk TM, et al. VP1 sequencing of all human rhinovirus serotypes: insights into genus phylogeny and susceptibility to antiviral capsid‐binding compounds. J Virol. 2004;78:3663‐3674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui A, Xie Z, Xu J, et al. Comparative analysis of the clinical and epidemiological characteristics of human influenza virus versus human respiratory syncytial virus versus human metapneumovirus infection in nine provinces of China during 2009‐2021. J Med Virol. 2022;94:5894‐5903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Ren L, Yu H. Pathogen Surveillance and Detection Techniques: Febrile Respiratory Syndrome (in Chinese). Sun Yat‐Sen University Press; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Xie Z, Xia B, Wang Y, Xu W, Zhang Y. Identification of two proposed novel human rhinovirus types: Bpat107 and Cpat58. J Med Virol. 2023;95(2):e28531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McIntyre CL, Knowles NJ, Simmonds P. Proposals for the classification of human rhinovirus species A, B and C into genotypically assigned types. J Gen Virol. 2013;94(Pt 8):1791‐1806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui AL, Zhu Z, Mao NY, et al. [Analysis of common viral infection in surveillance cases of febrile respiratory syndrome in 9 provinces of China from 2009 to 2021]. Zhonghua yu fang yi xue za zhi [Chinese J Preventive Med]. 2022;56:912‐918.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baillie VL, Moore DP, Mathunjwa A, Morailane P, Simões EAF, Madhi SA. Molecular subtyping of human rhinovirus in children from three sub‐saharan African countries. J Clin Microbiol. 2019;57:e00723‐19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia B, Ma Y, Sun L, et al. Infection status and molecular typing of rhinovirus in children acute respiratory tract infection cases in Changchun city from 2019 to 2021. Dis Surveill. 2022;37:469‐474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Wang H, Liu A, et al. Comparison of 11 respiratory pathogens among hospitalized children before and during the COVID‐19 epidemic in Shenzhen, China. Virol J. 2021;18:202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng KT, Oong XY, Lim SH, et al. Viral load and sequence analysis reveal the symptom severity, diversity, and transmission clusters of rhinovirus infections. Clin Infect Dis. 2018;67:261‐268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naughtin M, Sareth R, Sentilhes AC, et al. Genetic diversity of human rhinoviruses in Cambodia during a three‐year period reveals novel genetic types. Infect Genet Evol. 2015;35:42‐49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa LF, Queiróz DAO, Lopes da Silveira H, et al. Human rhinovirus and disease severity in children. Pediatrics. 2014;133:e312‐e321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amat F, Plantard C, Mulliez A, et al. RSV‐hRV co‐infection is a risk factor for recurrent bronchial obstruction and early sensitization 3 years after bronchiolitis. J Med Virol. 2018;90:867‐872.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida LM, Suzuki M, Nguyen HA, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus: co‐infection and paediatric lower respiratory tract infections. Eur Respir J. 2013;42:461‐469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu A, Mihaylova VT, Landry ML, Foxman EF. Interference between rhinovirus and influenza a virus: a clinical data analysis and experimental infection study. Lancet Microbe. 2020;1:e254‐e262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li ZJ, Yu LJ, Zhang HY, et al. Broad impacts of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID‐19) pandemic on acute respiratory infections in China: an observational study. Clin Infect Dis. 2022;75:e1054‐e1062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinky L, Dobrovolny HM. SARS‐CoV‐2 coinfections: could influenza and the common cold be beneficial? J Med Virol. 2020;92:2623‐2630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esneau C, Duff AC, Bartlett NW. Understanding rhinovirus circulation and impact on illness. Viruses. 2022;14:141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fry AM, Lu X, Olsen SJ, et al. Human rhinovirus infections in rural Thailand: epidemiological evidence for rhinovirus as both pathogen and bystander. PLoS One. 2011;6:e17780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pretorius MA, Tempia S, Treurnicht FK, et al. Genetic diversity and molecular epidemiology of human rhinoviruses in South Africa. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2014;8:567‐573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Yu B, Zhou J, et al. Genetic diversity and epidemiology of human rhinovirus among children with severe acute respiratory tract infection in Guangzhou, China. Virol J. 2021;18:174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adam DC, Chen X, Scotch M, MacIntyre CR, Dwyer D, Kok J. The molecular epidemiology and clinical phylogenetics of rhinoviruses among paediatric cases in Sydney, Australia. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;110:69‐74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linder JE, Kraft DC, Mohamed Y, et al. Human rhinovirus C: age, season, and lower respiratory illness over the past 3 decades. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2013;131:69‐77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau S, Yip C, Woo P, Yuen KY. Human rhinovirus C: a newly discovered human rhinovirus species. Emerg Health Threats J. 2010;3:e2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sansone M, Andersson M, Brittain‐Long R, et al. Rhinovirus infections in Western Sweden: a four‐year molecular epidemiology study comparing local and globally appearing types. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2013;32:947‐954.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Shen J, Wu B, Liu G, Lu R, Tan W. Genotypic diversity and epidemiology of human rhinovirus among children with severe acute respiratory tract infection in Shanghai, 2013‐2015. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:1836.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrés C, Peremiquel‐Trillas P, Gimferrer L, et al. Genetic diversity of rhinoviruses detected at a tertiary hospital in Catalonia (Spain) during the 2014‐2017 seasons. Future Microbiol. 2018;13:1565‐1573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luka MM, Kamau E, Adema I, et al. Molecular epidemiology of human rhinovirus from 1‐year surveillance within a school setting in rural coastal Kenya. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2020;7:ofaa385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang T, Wang W, Bessaud M, et al. Evidence of recombination and genetic diversity in human rhinoviruses in children with acute respiratory infection. PLoS One. 2009;4:e6355.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>