<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38659511</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Nemaline Myopathy in a Hypotonic Neonate: Diagnostic Approach for Early Detection and Management.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e56866</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e56866</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e56866</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.56866</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Neonatal hypotonia presents with low muscle tone and an array of symptoms that vary depending on the etiology. The differential diagnosis for this condition is complex. It is crucial to exclude life-threatening causes before following a diagnostic algorithm and performing additional tests. Given the wide range of clinical symptoms and etiologies for neonatal hypotonia, rapid genetic testing has the potential to expedite diagnosis, reduce invasive testing such as muscle biopsy, reduce hospital stays, and guide condition management.  A four-week-old girl was admitted to the emergency department (ED) with a one-day history of lethargy, poor feeding, congestion, cough, and hypoxemia. Given positive rhino-enterovirus testing and high inflammatory markers, antibiotics were administered. Imaging, venous blood gas, and blood cultures were negative, and the patient was admitted to the pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) for hypoxemia. After speech-language pathology (SLP) and occupational therapy (OT) evaluation, weak orofacial muscles and feeding issues resulted in a nasogastric tube placement. A swallow study revealed decreased pharyngeal contraction and post-swallow liquid residue. Laryngoscopy showed mild laryngomalacia and dysphagia with aspiration. Genetic testing identified an ACTA1 mutation and confirmed nemaline myopathy (NM). The patient's oxygen levels dropped further during sleep, resulting in diagnoses of severe obstructive and moderate-severe central sleep apnea. Treatment included oxygen therapy, SLP, physical therapy, albuterol, and cough assists. After discharge, the patient was frequently re-admitted with chronic respiratory failure and bronchiolitis and later had gastrostomy and tracheostomy tubes inserted.  This specific case highlights the importance of implementing a diagnostic algorithm for neonatal hypotonia. It is also important for physicians, especially emergency medicine (EM) providers, to first exclude infection, sepsis, and cardiac and respiratory organ failure before looking into other tests. Then, physicians should evaluate for more rare etiologies. In this patient's case, the hypotonia was due to a rare genetic disease, nemaline myopathy, and a multidisciplinary approach was used for this patient's care.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Vu et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vu</LastName><ForeName>Annie</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Michigan State University College of Human Medicine, East Lansing, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nanda</LastName><ForeName>Subah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Michigan State University College of Human Medicine, East Lansing, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chassee</LastName><ForeName>Todd</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Helen DeVos Children's Hospital, Grand Rapids, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hypoxemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multidisciplinary care team</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nemaline myopathy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neonatal hypotonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rapid genetic testing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38659511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11040521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.56866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Multicenter Consensus Approach to Evaluation of Neonatal Hypotonia in the Genomic Era: A Review. Morton SU, Christodoulou J, Costain G, et al. JAMA Neurol. 2022;79:405–413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10134401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35254387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A schematic approach to hypotonia in infancy. Leyenaar J, Camfield P, Camfield C. Paediatr Child Health. 2005;10:397–400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2722561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19668647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overview of Peripheral Nerve and Muscle Disorders Causing Hypotonia in the Newborn. Bodamer Bodamer, Olaf A. https://www.uptodate.com/contents/overview-of-peripheral-nerve-and-muscle-disorders-causing-hypotonia-in-the-newborn UpToDate, 8 Sept. 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Approach to the infant with hypotonia and weaknes. Bodamer Bodamer, Olaf A. https://www.uptodate.com/contents/approach-to-the-infant-with-hypotonia-and-weakness UpToDate, 22 Sept. 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The floppy infant: contribution of genetic and metabolic disorders. Prasad AN, Prasad C. Brain Dev. 2003;25:457–476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13129589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A structured approach to the assessment of a floppy neonate. Ahmed MI, Iqbal M, Hussain N. J Pediatr Neurosci. 2016;11:2–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4862282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27195025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infections at the maternal-fetal interface: an overview of pathogenesis and defence. Megli CJ, Coyne CB. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2022;20:67–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8386341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34433930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Current State of Newborn Screening in the United States. Fabie NA, Pappas KB, Feldman GL. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2019;66:369–386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30819343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infant botulism following honey ingestion. Abdulla CO, Ayubi A, Zulfiquer F, Santhanam G, Ahmed MA, Deeb J. BMJ Case Rep. 2012;2012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3448763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22962382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The evaluation of the hypotonic infant. Bodensteiner JB. Semin Pediatr Neurol. 2008;15:10–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18342256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The floppy infant: evaluation of hypotonia. Peredo DE, Hannibal MC. Pediatr Rev. 2009;30:0–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19726697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neonatal hypotonia. Sparks SE. Clin Perinatol. 2015;42:363-71, ix.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26042909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical evaluation of the floppy infant. Crawford TO. Pediatr Ann. 1992;21:348–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1620559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic approach to neonatal hypotonia: retrospective study on 144 neonates. Laugel V, Cossée M, Matis J, et al.  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00431-007-0539-3. Eur J Pediatr. 2008;167:517–523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17641914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recent advances in nemaline myopathy. Laitila J, Wallgren-Pettersson C. Neuromuscul Disord. 2021;31:955–967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34561123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Role of Muscle Biopsy in Diagnostic Process of Infant Hypotonia: From Clinical Classification to the Genetic Outcome. Veneruso M, Fiorillo C, Broda P, et al. Front Neurol. 2021;12:735488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8523832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34675869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muscle biopsy evaluation in neuromuscular disorders. Joyce NC, Oskarsson B, Jin LW. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2012;23:609–631.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4590778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22938878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The background puzzle: how identical mutations in the same gene lead to different disease symptoms. Kammenga JE. FEBS J. 2017;284:3362–3373.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28390082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recent advances in nemaline myopathy. Romero NB, Sandaradura SA, Clarke NF. Curr Opin Neurol. 2013;26:519–526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23995272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>