<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38678424</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1477-8920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of water and health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Water Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Poliomyelitis and COVID-19: a repeated history.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>717</StartPage><EndPage>720</EndPage><MedlinePgn>717-720</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2166/wh.2024.327</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The measurement of the enterovirus and the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in sewage water is relevant in the early detection of the introduction or disappearance of these viruses in the ecosystem. We evaluated the co-circulation of the enteroviruses and SARS-CoV-2 in 81 sewage water samples collected between September 2021 and April 2023 from different regions of north and southeast Romania, at the border with Ukraine. We used, for the molecular detection of the pathogens, the multiplex real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay produced for respiratory samples and the Respiratory 2.1 Plus panel Biofire Film array. The isolation of enteroviruses was performed on cell culture lines, in accordance with the World Health Organization (WHO) recommendations. By molecular investigations, we detected the SARS-CoV-2 in 22 (27%) samples, and the human rhinovirus/enterovirus in 64 (79%) samples. By isolation on cell culture lines, 27 samples (33,33%) were positive for non-polio enteroviruses, and no poliovirus strains were isolated, proving the maintenance of the polio-free status in Romania. In an emergency situation, the molecular detection of the pathogens in sewage water using a PCR system integrating sample preparation, amplification, detection, and analysis in 1 h could be implemented.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits copying and redistribution for non-commercial purposes with no derivatives, provided the original work is properly cited (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anda</LastName><ForeName>Baicus</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4929-6493</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Viral Infections, Laboratory 'Cantacuzino' Medico Military National Institute of Research and Development, 050096 Bucharest, Romania; Department of Microbiology III - Emergency University Hospital Bucharest, Faculty of Medicine, 'Carol Davila' University of Medicine and Pharmacy, 050098 Bucharest, Romania E-mail: baicus.anda@cantacuzino.ro.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>National Authority of Scientific Research and Innovation, Romania, Core Project PN 19 14 02 07.</GrantID><Agency>Autoritatea Natională pentru Cercetare Stiintifică</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Water Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101185420</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1477-8920</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012722">Sewage</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012722" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sewage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012383" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Romania</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliomyelitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sewage water</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author declares there is no conflict.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38678424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/wh.2024.327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">wh_2024_327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Băicuș A., Joffret M. L., Bessaud M., Delpeyroux F. &amp; Oprisan G. 2020 Reinforced poliovirus and enterovirus surveillance in Romania, 2015–2016. Archives of Virology 165 (11), 2627–2632.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Băicuș A., Cherciu C. M. &amp; Lazăr M. 2021 Identification of SARS-CoV-2 and enteroviruses in sewage water-A pilot study. Viruses 13 (5), 844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8148526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barril P. A., Pianciola L. A., Mazzeo M., Ousset M. J., Jaureguiberry M. V., Alessandrello M., Sánchez G. &amp; Oteiza J. M. 2021 Evaluation of viral concentration methods for SARS-CoV-2 recovery from wastewaters. Science of the Total Environment 756, 144105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7700007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33302076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi P. M., Bowes D. A., O'Brien J. W., Li J., Halden R. U., Jiang G., Thomas K. V. &amp; Mueller J. F. 2020 Do food and stress biomarkers work for wastewater-based epidemiology? a critical evaluation. Science of the Total Environment 736, 139654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32497888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Canada 2023 Polio (Poliomyelitis): Wastewater Surveillance. Available from: https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/diseases/poliomyelitis-polio/wastewater-surveillance.html (accessed 7 January 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J., Han B. &amp; Wang J. 2020 COVID-19: Gastrointestinal manifestations and potential fecal-oral transmission. Gastroenterology 158, 1518–1519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7130192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadj Hassine I. 2022 COVID-19 vaccines and variants of concern: A review. Reviews in Medical Virology 32 (4), e2313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34755408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill M. &amp; Pollard A. J. 2022 Detection of poliovirus in London highlights the value of sewage surveillance. Lancet 400, 1491–1492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36243023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krzysztoszek A., Gad B., Diedrich S., Böttcher S. &amp; Wieczorek M. 2022 Investigation of airport sewage to detect importation of poliovirus. Poland, 2017 to 2020. Euro Surveillance 27 (24), 2100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Link-Gelles R., Lutterloh E., Schnabel Ruppert P., Backenson P. B., St George K., Rosenberg E. S., Anderson B. J., Fuschino M., Popowich M., Punjabi C., Souto M., McKay K., Rulli S., Insaf T., Hill D., Kumar J., Gelman I., Jorba J., Ng T. F. F., Gerloff N., Masters N. B., Lopez A., Dooling K., Stokley S., Kidd S., Oberste M. S. &amp; Routh J. 2022 Public health response to a case of paralytic poliomyelitis in an unvaccinated person and detection of poliovirus in wastewater – New York, June-August 2022. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 71 (33), 1065–1068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9400530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35980868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medema G., Heijnen L., Elsinga G., Italiaander R. &amp; Brouwer A. 2020 Presence of SARS-Coronavirus-2 RNA in sewage and correlation with reported COVID-19 prevalence in the early stage of the epidemic in the Netherlands. Environmental Sciency and Technology Letters 7 (7), 511–516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melnick J. L. 1947 Poliomyelitis virus in urban sewage in epidemic and in nonepidemic times. American Journal of Epidemiology 45 (2), 240–253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parkins M. D., Lee B. E., Acosta N., Bautista M., Hubert C. R. J., Hrudey S. E., Frankowski K. &amp; Pang X.-L. 2023 Wastewater-based surveillance as a tool for public health action: SARS-CoV-2 and beyond. Clinical Microbiology Review e0010322. doi:10.1128/cmr.00103-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10938902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryerson A. B., Lang D., Alazawi M. A., Neyra M., Hill D. T., St George K., Fuschino M., Lutterloh E., Backenson B., Rulli S., Ruppert P. S., Lawler J., McGraw N., Knecht A., Gelman I., Zucker J. R., Omoregie E., Kidd S., Sugerman D. E., Jorba J., Gerloff N., Ng T. F. F., Lopez A., Masters N. B., Leung J., Burns C. C., Routh J., Bialek S. R., Oberste M. S. &amp; Rosenberg E. S. 2022 Wastewater testing and detection of poliovirus type 2 genetically linked to virus isolated from a paralytic polio case – New York, March 9-October 11, 2022. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 71, 1418–1424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9639435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36327157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Termansen M. B. &amp; Frische S. 2023 Fecal-oral transmission of SARS-CoV-2: A systematic review of evidence from epidemiological and experimental studies. American Journal of Infection Control 51 (12), 1430–1437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10141930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37121473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson K. M., Kalkowska D. A., Routh J. A., Brenner I. R., Rosenberg E. S., Zucker J. R., Langdon-Embry M., Sugerman D. E., Burns C. C. &amp; Badizadegan K. 2023 Modeling poliovirus transmission and responses in New York state. Journal of Infectious Diseases 19, jiad355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO 2003 Guidelines for Environmental Surveillance of Poliovirus Circulation. World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland. Available from: https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/67854 (accessed 2 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO 2004 Polio Laboratory Manual, 4th edn. World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland. Available from: https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/68762 (accessed 2 November 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO 2022 Circulating Vaccine-Derived Poliovirus Type 3 – Israel. 2022. World Health Organization. Available from: https://www.who.int/europe/news/item/10-03-2022-circulating-vaccine-derived-poliovirus-confirmed-in-israel-and-the-occupied-palestinian-territory (accessed 7 January 2024).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>