<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38618381</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Infant Appendicitis: A Case Presentation of Appendicitis in a Nine-Month-Old Infant With Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV) and Otitis Media and Review of Literature.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e56059</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e56059</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e56059</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.56059</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Appendicitis in children &lt; 5 years old is uncommon and even less common in children &lt; 1 year old. Symptoms of appendicitis can be non-specific and mimic other common pediatric diseases, causing delays in diagnosis. Without a timely diagnosis, young children with appendicitis are at risk of developing worsening disease, intra-abdominal abscess, perforation, and bacteremia.  We submit a case of a nine-month-old male infant presenting with fever, vomiting, and irritability seen the day prior and treated for otitis media, who was ultimately diagnosed with appendicitis with concomitant viral infection (respiratory syncytial virus and human rhinovirus/enterovirus) and treated with intravenous antibiotics and laparoscopic appendectomy.  This case illustrates how easy it is to misdiagnose infant appendicitis due to factors including normal developmental speech barriers, nonspecific presentations, and overlap of symptoms with many other common childhood illnesses, along with a challenging abdominal examination. Delay in diagnosis leads to increased rates of perforation and complications. Providers should trust abnormal physical examination findings, especially abdominal guarding against palpation, and keep a wide differential diagnosis in order to diagnose appendicitis in young children.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Hueschen et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hueschen</LastName><ForeName>Leslie A</ForeName><Initials>LA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Emergency Medicine, Children's Mercy Hospital/University of Missouri-Kansas City, Kansas City, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McNeill-Johnson</LastName><ForeName>April</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Emergency Medicine, Children's Mercy Hospital/University of Missouri-Kansas City, Kansas City, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">appendicitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">complications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pediatric</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38618381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11009476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.56059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in children less than 3 years of age: a 28-year review. Alloo J, Gerstle T, Shilyansky J, Ein SH. Pediatr Surg Int. 2004;19:777–779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14730382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in preschool aged children: Regression analysis of factors associated with perforation outcome. Bonadio W, Peloquin P, Brazg J, Scheinbach I, Saunders J, Okpalaji C, Homel P. J Pediatr Surg. 2015;50:1569–1573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25783356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neonatal and infant appendicitis. Bence CM, Densmore JC. Clin Perinatol. 2020;47:183–196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32000925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in children less than 5 years old: influence of age on presentation and outcome. Bansal S, Banever GT, Karrer FM, Partrick DA. Am J Surg. 2012;204:1031–1035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23231939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical features and preventability of delayed diagnosis of pediatric appendicitis. Michelson KA, Reeves SD, Grubenhoff JA, et al. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8408667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34463745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neonatal appendicitis (Part 1): A review of 52 cases with abdominal manifestation. Raveenthiran V. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4420402/ J Neonatal Surg. 2015;4:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4420402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26023528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in children less than five years old: A challenge for the general practitioner. Marzuillo P, Germani C, Krauss BS, Barbi E. World J Clin Pediatr. 2015;4:19–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4438437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26015876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in the young child: a continuing diagnostic challenge. Nance ML, Adamson WT, Hedrick HL. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2000;16:160–162.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10888451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in an infant with atypical features. Sayyahfar S, Jahangiri F, Zarei E. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27376232/ J Coll Physicians Surg Pak. 2016;26:0–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27376232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usefulness of ultrasonography in acute appendicitis in early childhood. Chang YJ, Kong MS, Hsia SH, et al. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2007;44:592–595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17460492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Importance of diarrhea as a presenting symptom of appendicitis in very young children. Horwitz JR, Gursoy M, Jaksic T, Lally KP. Am J Surg. 1997;173:80–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9074368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in a 14-month-old infant with respiratory symptoms. Brisighelli G, Morandi A, Parolini F, Leva E. Afr J Paediatr Surg. 2012;9:148–151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22878766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute appendicitis in children: emergency department diagnosis and management. Rothrock SG, Pagane J. Ann Emerg Med. 2000;36:39–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10874234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical features and outcome of appendicitis in children younger than three years of age. Huang CB, Yu HR, Hung GC, Huang SC, Chuang JH. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11299974/ Chang Gung Med J. 2001;24:27–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11299974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute appendicitis in children younger than five years of age: diagnostic challenge for pediatric surgeons. Pogorelić Z, Domjanović J, Jukić M, Poklepović Peričić T. Surg Infect (Larchmt) 2020;21:239–245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31618143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Systematic review and meta-analysis of the diagnostic accuracy of procalcitonin, C-reactive protein and white blood cell count for suspected acute appendicitis. Yu CW, Juan LI, Wu MH, Shen CJ, Wu JY, Lee CC. Br J Surg. 2013;100:322–329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23203918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic value of serum procalcitonin in appendicitis in infants and young children: retrospective cohort study. Pian P, Chang Q, Zhou G, Li L, Wang W, Mu Y. Clin Lab. 2021;67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34758216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Value of fibrinogen to discriminate appendicitis from nonspecific abdominal pain in preschool children. Prada-Arias M, Gómez-Veiras J, Salgado-Barreira Á, Vázquez JL, Montero-Sánchez M, Fernández-Lorenzo JR. Eur J Pediatr Surg. 2020;30:357–363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31189186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnostic value of clinical prediction scores for acute appendicitis in children younger than 4 years. Rassi R, Muse F, Sánchez-Martínez J, Cuestas E. Eur J Pediatr Surg. 2022;32:198–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appendicitis in young children: imaging experience and clinical outcomes. Rodriguez DP, Vargas S, Callahan MJ, Zurakowski D, Taylor GA. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2006;186:1158–1164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16554597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>