<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38798735</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2352-7714</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>One health (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>One Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bioinformatics-based screening tool identifies a wide variety of human and zoonotic viruses in Trujillo-Peru wastewater.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100756</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100756</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100756</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.onehlt.2024.100756</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Peru was one of the most affected countries during the COVID-19 pandemic. Moreover, multiple other viral diseases (enteric, respiratory, bloodborne, and vector-borne) are endemic and rising. According to Peru's Ministry of Health, various health facilities in the country were reallocated for the COVID-19 pandemic, thereby leading to reduced action to curb other diseases. Many viral diseases in the area are under-reported and not recognized. The One Health approach, in addition to clinical testing, incorporates environmental surveillance for detection of infectious disease outbreaks. The purpose of this work is to use a screening tool that is based on molecular methods, high throughput sequencing and bioinformatics analysis of wastewater samples to identify virus-related diseases circulating in Trujillo-Peru. To demonstrate the effectiveness of the tool, we collected nine untreated wastewater samples from the Covicorti wastewater utility in Trujillo-Peru on October 22, 2022. High throughput metagenomic sequencing followed by bioinformatic analysis was used to assess the viral diversity of the samples. Our results revealed the presence of sequences associated with multiple human and zoonotic viruses including Orthopoxvirus, Hepatovirus, Rhadinovirus, Parechovirus, Mamastrovirus, Enterovirus, Varicellovirus, Norovirus, Kobuvirus, Bocaparvovirus, Simplexvirus, Spumavirus, Orthohepevirus, Cardiovirus, Molliscipoxvirus, Salivirus, Parapoxvirus, Gammaretrovirus, Alphavirus, Lymphocryptovirus, Erythroparvovirus, Sapovirus, Cosavirus, Deltaretrovirus, Roseolovirus, Flavivirus, Betacoronavirus, Rubivirus, Lentivirus, Betapolyomavirus, Rotavirus, Hepacivirus, Alphacoronavirus, Mastadenovirus, Cytomegalovirus and Alphapapillomavirus. For confirmation purposes, we tested the samples for the presence of selective viruses belonging to the genera detected above. PCR based molecular methods confirmed the presence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), monkeypox virus (MPXV), noroviruses GI and GII (NoVGI and NoVGII), and rotavirus A (RoA) in our samples. Furthermore, publicly available clinical data for selected viruses confirm our findings. Wastewater or other environmental media surveillance, combined with bioinformatics methods, has the potential to serve as a systematic screening tool for the identification of human or zoonotic viruses that may cause disease. The results of this method can guide further clinical surveillance efforts and allocation of resources. Incorporation of this bioinformatic-based screening tool by public health officials in Peru and other Latin American countries will help manage endemic and emerging diseases that could save human lives and resources.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miyani</LastName><ForeName>Brijen</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yabing</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guzman</LastName><ForeName>Heidy Peidro</ForeName><Initials>HP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Briceno</LastName><ForeName>Ruben Kenny</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vieyra</LastName><ForeName>Sabrina</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hinojosa</LastName><ForeName>Rene</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xagoraraki</LastName><ForeName>Irene</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>One Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101660501</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2352-7714</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioinformatics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Trujillo-Peru</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viral diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viral pathogen screening</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38798735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11127556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.onehlt.2024.100756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2352-7714(24)00082-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>“Peru - National geographic kids.” https://kids.nationalgeographic.com/geography/countries/article/peru [Online]. Available. [Accessed: 09-Dec-2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uhart M., Pérez A., Rostal M., Robles E.A., Mendoza A.P., Nava A., de Paula C.D., Miranda F., Iñiguez V., Zambrana C., Durigon E. A ‘One Health’approach to predict emerging zoonoses in the Amazon. Saúde Silvestre e Humana: Experiências e Perspectivas. Rio de Janeiro. FIOCRUZ. 2013:65–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones K.E., Patel N.G., Levy M.A., Storeygard A., Balk D., Gittleman J.L., Daszak P. Global trends in emerging infectious diseases. Nature. 2008 Feb;451(7181):990–993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5960580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18288193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolhouse M., Gaunt E. Ecological origins of novel human pathogens. Crit. Rev. Microbiol. 2007 Jan 1;33(4):231–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18033594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karesh W.B., Cook R.A. The human-animal link. Foreign Aff. 2005;84:38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanagan M.L., Parrish C.R., Cobey S., Glass G.E., Bush R.M., Leighton T.J. Anticipating the species jump: surveillance for emerging viral threats. Zoonoses Public Health. 2012 May;59(3):155–163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4948863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21914152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien E., Xagoraraki I. A water-focused one-health approach for early detection and prevention of viral outbreaks. One Health. 2019 Jun;1(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6501061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31080867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xagoraraki I., O’Brien E. Wastewater-based epidemiology for early detection of viral outbreaks. Women in water quality: Investigations by prominent female engineers. 2020:75–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xagoraraki I. Can we predict viral outbreaks using wastewater surveillance? J. Environ. Eng. 2020 Nov 1;146(11):01820003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Miyani B., Zhao L., Spooner M., Gentry Z., Zou Y., Rhodes G., Li H., Kaye A., Norton J., Xagoraraki I. Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 in nine neighborhood sewersheds in Detroit Tri-County area, United States: assessing per capita SARS-CoV-2 estimations and COVID-19 incidence. Sci. Total Environ. 2022 Dec;10(851)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9419442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36041621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao L., Zou Y., Li Y., Miyani B., Spooner M., Gentry Z., Jacobi S., David R.E., Withington S., McFarlane S., Faust R. Five-week warning of COVID-19 peaks prior to the omicron surge in Detroit, Michigan using wastewater surveillance. Sci. Total Environ. 2022 Oct;20(844)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9239917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35779714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyani B., Zhao L., Spooner M., Buch S., Gentry Z., Mehrotra A., Norton J., Xagoraraki I. Early warnings of COVID-19 second wave in Detroit. J. Environ. Eng. 2021 Aug;147(8):06021004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCall C., Wu H., Miyani B., Xagoraraki I. Identification of multiple potential viral diseases in a large urban center using wastewater surveillance. Water Res. 2020 Oct;1(184)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7342010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32738707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyani B., McCall C., Xagoraraki I. High abundance of human herpesvirus 8 in wastewater from a large urban area. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2021 May;130(5):1402–1411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33058412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Miyani B., Childs K.L., Shiu S.H., Xagoraraki I. Effect of wastewater collection and concentration methods on assessment of viral diversity. Sci. Total Environ. 2024 Jan;15(908)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37918732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Miyani B., Faust R.A., David R.E., Xagoraraki I. A broad wastewater screening and clinical data surveillance for virus-related diseases in the metropolitan Detroit area in Michigan. Hum. Genomics. 2024 Dec;18(1):1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10845806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38321488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru WHO Mortality Database Leading causes of death per year.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru: WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan M.M., Hernández-Yépez P.J., de los Angeles Rivera-Cabrera M, Sarkar A, dos Santos Costa AC, Essar MY. Concurrent epidemics of dengue and COVID-19 in Peru: which way forward? The Lancet Regional Health–Americas. 2022 Aug:12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9903762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36776431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centro Nacional de Epidemiologia Prevencion y control de enfermedades, “Incremento de incidencia de casos y ocurrencia de brotes por Dengue y otras arbovirosis en el país,”Minist. Salud. 2021;19(2):6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>“Instituto Nacional de Estadistica e Informatica, INEI, Republica del Peru (2017). La Libertad: Resultados Definitivos, Censo Nacional, 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avila Calderón SL. Caracterización físico-química del efluente final de uso agrícola de la Planta de Tratamiento El Cortijo, Trujillo, Perú.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. D. E. C. Profesional . 2006. ca lio te de In g ie ría uí m ica ca lio te de Bi In g en ie ría m.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flood M.T., D’Souza N., Rose J.B., Aw T.G. Methods evaluation for rapid concentration and quantification of SARS-CoV-2 in raw wastewater using droplet digital and quantitative RT-PCR. Food Environ. Virol. 2021 Sep;13:303–315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34296387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D., Coscoy L., Zylberberg M., Avila P.C., Boushey H.A., Ganem D., DeRisi J.L. Microarray-based detection and genotyping of viral pathogens. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2002 Nov;99(24):15687–15692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC137777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12429852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D., Urisman A., Liu Y.T., Springer M., Ksiazek T.G., Erdman D.D., Mardis E.R., Hickenbotham M., Magrini V., Eldred J., Latreille J.P. Viral discovery and sequence recovery using DNA microarrays. PLoS Biol. 2003 Nov;1(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC261870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14624234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews S. FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data.2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolger A.M., Lohse M., Usadel B. Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data. Bioinformatics. 2014 Aug;30(15):2114–2120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4103590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24695404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menzel P., Ng K.L., Krogh A. Fast and sensitive taxonomic classification for metagenomics with kaiju. Nat. Commun. 2016 Apr;7(1):11257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4833860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27071849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibby K., Viau E., Peccia J. Viral metagenome analysis to guide human pathogen monitoring in environmental samples. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 2011 Apr;52(4):386–392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3055918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21272046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bağcı C., Patz S., Huson D.H. DIAMOND+ MEGAN: fast and easy taxonomic and functional analysis of short and long microbiome sequences. Current protocols. 2021 Mar;1(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33656283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huson D.H., Beier S., Flade I., Górska A., El-Hadidi M., Mitra S., Ruscheweyh H.J., Tappu R. MEGAN community edition-interactive exploration and analysis of large-scale microbiome sequencing data. PLoS Comput. Biol. 2016 Jun;12(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4915700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27327495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for disease control and prevention., “centers for disease control &amp; Prevention Poxvirus &amp; Rabies Branch (PRB),”. 2022;01(01)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y., Zhao H., Wilkins K., Hughes C., Damon I.K. Real-time PCR assays for the specific detection of monkeypox virus west African and Congo Basin strain DNA. J. Virol. Methods. 2010 Oct;169(1):223–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9628942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20643162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thongprachum A., Fujimoto T., Takanashi S., Saito H., Okitsu S., Shimizu H., Khamrin P., Maneekarn N., Hayakawa S., Ushijima H. Detection of nineteen enteric viruses in raw sewage in Japan. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2018 Sep;1(63):17–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29753903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura K., Stecher G., Kumar S. MEGA11: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 11. Mol. Biol. Evol. 2021 Jul;38(7):3022–3027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8233496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33892491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hospital Regional Docente De Trujillo - Epidemiological Bulletins [Online]. Available: https://www.hrdt.gob.pe/site/index.php/servicios-linea/publicaciones/boletines-epidemiologicos. [Accessed: 01-Dec-2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru Ministerio de Salud. National Center for Epidemiology, Disease Prevention and Control [Online]. Available: https://www.dge.gob.pe/portalnuevo/publicaciones/boletines-epidemiologicos/. [Accessed: 01-Dec-2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru Ministerio de Salud National Center for Epidemiology, Disease Prevention and Control - Cumulative Incident Cases. [Online] https://www.dge.gob.pe/portalnuevo/informacion-publica/casos-de-incidencias-acumuladas/ Available. [Accessed: 01-Dec-2023]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>“Unique digital platform of the Peruvian State - Ministry of Health.” [Online]. Available: https://www.gob.pe/minsa. [Accessed: 01-Dec-2023].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds E.M., Nguyen K.H., Harwood V.J., Breitbart M. Pepper mild mottle virus: a plant pathogen with a greater purpose in (waste) water treatment development and public health management. Water Res. 2018 Nov;1(144):1–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6162155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30005176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutilh B.E., Cassman N., McNair K., Sanchez S.E., Silva G.G., Boling L., Barr J.J., Speth D.R., Seguritan V., Aziz R.K., Felts B. A highly abundant bacteriophage discovered in the unknown sequences of human faecal metagenomes. Nat. Commun. 2014 Jul;5(1):4498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4111155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25058116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stachler E., Bibby K. Metagenomic evaluation of the highly abundant human gut bacteriophage CrAssphage for source tracking of human fecal pollution. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2014 Oct;1(10):405–409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malla B., Ghaju Shrestha R., Tandukar S., Sherchand J.B., Haramoto E. Performance evaluation of human-specific viral markers and application of pepper mild mottle virus and crAssphage to environmental water samples as fecal pollution markers in the Kathmandu Valley, Nepal. Food and Environ. Virology. 2019 Sep;1(11):274–287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31087275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandukar S., Sherchan S.P., Haramoto E. Applicability of crAssphage, pepper mild mottle virus, and tobacco mosaic virus as indicators of reduction of enteric viruses during wastewater treatment. Sci. Rep. 2020 Feb;10(1):3616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7046655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32107444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm R.H., Nagarkar M., Yeager R.A., Talley D., Chaney A.C., Rai J.P., Mukherjee A., Rai S.N., Bhatnagar A., Smith T. Surveillance of RNase P, PMMoV, and CrAssphage in wastewater as indicators of human fecal concentration across urban sewer neighborhoods, Kentucky. FEMS microbes. 2022;3:xtac003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10117713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37228897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meuchi Y., Nakada M., Kuroda K., Hanamoto S., Hata A. Applicability of F-specific bacteriophage subgroups, PMMoV and crAssphage as indicators of source specific fecal contamination and viral inactivation in rivers in Japan. PLoS One. 2023 Jul;18(7)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10348522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37450468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyani B., Fonoll X., Norton J., Mehrotra A., Xagoraraki I. SARS-CoV-2 in Detroit wastewater. J. Environ. Eng. 2020 Nov;146(11):06020004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randazzo W., Truchado P., Cuevas-Ferrando E., Simón P., Allende A., Sánchez G. SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater anticipated COVID-19 occurrence in a low prevalence area. Water Res. 2020 Aug;15(181)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7229723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32425251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girón-Guzmán I., Díaz-Reolid A., Truchado P., Carcereny A., García-Pedemonte D., Hernáez B., Bosch A., Pintó R.M., Guix S., Allende A., Alcamí A. Spanish wastewater reveals the current spread of Monkeypox virus. Water Res. 2023 Mar;1(231)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9845017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36693290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jonge E.F., Peterse C.M., Koelewijn J.M., van der Drift A.M., van der Beek R.F., Nagelkerke E., Lodder W.J. The detection of monkeypox virus DNA in wastewater samples in the Netherlands. Sci. Total Environ. 2022 Dec;15(852)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9558568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36057309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wurtzer S., Levert M., Dhenain E., Boni M., Tournier J.N., Londinsky N., Lefranc A., OBEPINE SIG, Ferraris O, Moulin L. First detection of monkeypox virus genome in sewersheds in France: the potential of wastewater-based epidemiology for monitoring emerging disease. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett. 2022 Oct;9(11):991–996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCall C., Wu H., O’Brien E., Xagoraraki I. Assessment of enteric viruses during a hepatitis outbreak in Detroit MI using wastewater surveillance and metagenomic analysis. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2021 Sep;131(3):1539–1554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33550682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) World Health Organization (WHO) - Peru Responds to Monkeypox by Engaging Affected Communities [Online]. Available: https://www.paho.org/en/stories/peru-responds-monkeypox-engaging-affected-communities. [Accessed: 07-Feb-2024].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ampuero M., Martínez-Valdebenito C., Ferrés M., Soto-Rifo R., Gaggero A. Monkeypox virus in wastewater samples from Santiago metropolitan region, Chile. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2023 Nov;29(11):2358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10617339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37877805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peres M.G., Bacchiega T.S., Appolinário C.M., Vicente A.F., Allendorf S.D., Antunes J.M., Moreira S.A., Legatti E., Fonseca C.R., Pituco E.M., Okuda L.H. Serological study of vaccinia virus reservoirs in areas with and without official reports of outbreaks in cattle and humans in São Paulo, Brazil. Archiv. Virol. 2013 Dec;158:2433–2441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3830743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23760628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abrahão J.S., Campos R.K., de Souza Trindade G., Da Fonseca F.G., Ferreira P.C., Kroon E.G. Outbreak of severe zoonotic vaccinia virus infection, southeastern Brazil. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2015 Apr;21(4):695.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4378504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25811411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroon E.G., Mota B.E., Abrahão J.S., da Fonseca F.G., de Souza Trindade G. Zoonotic Brazilian vaccinia virus: from field to therapy. Antivir. Res. 2011 Nov;92(2):150–163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21896287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Styczynski A., Burgado J., Walteros D., Usme-Ciro J., Laiton K., Farias A.P., Nakazawa Y., Chapman C., Davidson W., Mauldin M., Morgan C. Seroprevalence and risk factors possibly associated with emerging zoonotic vaccinia virus in a farming community, Colombia. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2019 Dec;25(12):2169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6874243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31743085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prado T., Fumian T.M., Miagostovich M.P., Gaspar A.M. Monitoring the hepatitis A virus in urban wastewater from Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Trans. R. Soc. Trop. Med. Hyg. 2012 Feb;106(2):104–109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22100367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez-Díaz J., Querales L., Caraballo L., Vizzi E., Liprandi F., Takiff H., Betancourt W.Q. Detection and characterization of waterborne gastroenteritis viruses in urban sewage and sewage-polluted river waters in Caracas, Venezuela. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2009 Jan;75(2):387–394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2620703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19028907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanez L.A., Lucero N.S., Barril P.A., Díaz M.D., Tenaglia M.M., Spinsanti L.I., Nates S.V., Isa M.B., Ré V.E. Evidence of hepatitis A virus circulation in Central Argentina: seroprevalence and environmental surveillance. J. Clin. Virol. 2014 Jan;59(1):38–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24332411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baez P.A., Lopez M.C., Duque-Jaramillo A., Pelaez D., Molina F., Navas M.C. First evidence of the hepatitis E virus in environmental waters in Colombia. PLoS One. 2017 May;12(5)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5433737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28520759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro I.L., Espul C., Paula V.S., Altabert N.R., Gonzalez J.E., Lago B.V., Villar L.M. High prevalence of hepatitis A and E viruses in environmental and clinical samples from West Argentina. Braz. J. Infect. Dis. 2023 May;19(27)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9926214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36603828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero-Latorre L., Romero B., Bonifaz E., Timoneda N., Rusiñol M., Girones R., Rios-Touma B. Quito’s virome: metagenomic analysis of viral diversity in urban streams of Ecuador’s capital city. Sci. Total Environ. 2018 Dec;15(645):1334–1343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30248857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pardo-Figueroa B., Mindreau-Ganoza E., Reyes-Calderon A., Yufra S.P., Solorzano-Ortiz I.M., Donayre-Torres A.J., Antonini C., Renom J.M., Quispe A.M., Mota C.R., Chernicharo C.A. Spatiotemporal surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 in the sewage of three major urban areas in Peru: generating valuable data where clinical testing is extremely limited. Acs Es&amp;T Water. 2022 May;2(11):2144–2157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37552743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes-Calderón A., Mindreau-Ganoza E., Pardo-Figueroa B., Garcia-Luquillas K.R., Yufra S.P., Romero P.E., Antonini C., Renom J.M., Mota C., Santa-Maria M.C. 2022 Dec 23. Evaluation of Low-Cost SARS-CoV-2 Purification Methods for Viral Quantification and NGS Analysis: Implications for Wider Wastewater-Based Epidemiology Adoption. Available at SSRN 4308586.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10188194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37228686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fongaro G., Stoco P.H., Souza D.S., Grisard E.C., Magri M.E., Rogovski P., Schörner M.A., Barazzetti F.H., Christoff A.P., de Oliveira L.F., Bazzo M.L. The presence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in human sewage in Santa Catarina, Brazil, November 2019. Sci. Total Environ. 2021 Jul;15(778)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7938741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero-Latorre L., Ballesteros I., Villacrés-Granda I., Granda M.G., Freire-Paspuel B., Ríos-Touma B. SARS-CoV-2 in river water: implications in low sanitation countries. Sci. Total Environ. 2020 Nov;15(743)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7343659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32679506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López G.R., Martinez L.M., Freyre L., Freire M.C., Vladimirsky S., Rabossi A., Cisterna D.M. Persistent detection of cosavirus and saffold cardiovirus in Riachuelo River, Argentina. Food and Environ. Virol. 2021 Mar;13:64–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33165867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamora-Figueroa A., Rosales R.E., Fernández R., Ramírez V., Bastardo M., Farías A., Vizzi E. Detection and diversity of gastrointestinal viruses in wastewater from Caracas, Venezuela, 2021-2022. Virology. 2024 Jan;1(589)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37924728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burutarán L., Lizasoain A., García M., Tort L.F., Colina R., Victoria M. Detection and molecular characterization of Aichivirus 1 in wastewater samples from Uruguay. Food Environ. Virol. 2016 Mar;8:13–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26456918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimarães F.R., Ferreira F.F., Vieira C.B., Fumian T.M., Shubo T., Leite J.P., Miagostovich M.P. Molecular detection of human astrovirus in an urban sewage treatment plant in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz. 2008;103:819–823.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19148423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lizasoain A., Tort L.F., García M., Gómez M.M., Cristina J., Leite J.P., Miagostovich M.P., Victoria M., Colina R. Environmental assessment of classical human astrovirus in Uruguay. Food Environ. Virol. 2015 Jun;7:142–148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25680829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fumian T.M., Fioretti J.M., Lun J.H., Dos Santos I.A., White P.A., Miagostovich M.P. Detection of norovirus epidemic genotypes in raw sewage using next generation sequencing. Environ. Int. 2019 Feb;1(123):282–291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30553201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díaz J., Solari V., Cáceres O., Mena J., Baeza S., Muñoz X., O’Ryan M., Galeno H., Maldonado A., Mamani N. Brote de gastroenteritis aguda en la Región de Antofagasta, Chile: 2010. Rev. Chil. Infectol. 2012 Feb;29(1):19–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22552506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández M.D., Torres C., Martínez L.C., Giordano M.O., Masachessi G., Barril P.A., Isa M.B., Campos R.H., Nates S.V., Mbayed V.A. Genetic and evolutionary characterization of norovirus from sewage and surface waters in Cordoba City, Argentina. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2011 Oct;11(7):1631–1637.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21703365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bucardo F., Lindgren P.E., Svensson L., Nordgren J. Low prevalence of rotavirus and high prevalence of norovirus in hospital and community wastewater after introduction of rotavirus vaccine in Nicaragua. PLoS One. 2011 Oct;6(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3189239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22016794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Victoria M., Tort L.L., García M., Lizasoain A., Maya L., Leite J.P., Miagostovich M.P., Cristina J., Colina R. Assessment of gastroenteric viruses from wastewater directly discharged into Uruguay River. Uruguay. Food and Environmental Virology. 2014 Jun;6:116–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24777819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tort L.F., Victoria M., Lizasoain A., García M., Berois M., Cristina J., Leite J.P., Gómez M.M., Miagostovich M.P., Colina R. Detection of common, emerging and uncommon VP4, and VP7 human group A rotavirus genotypes from urban sewage samples in Uruguay. Food Environ. Virol. 2015 Dec;7:342–353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26267835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehnert D.U., Stewien K.E. Detection and distribution of rotavirus in raw sewage and creeks in São Paulo, Brazil. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1993 Jan;59(1):140–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC202068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8382461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barril P.A., Giordano M.O., Isa M.B., Masachessi G., Ferreyra L.J., Castello A.A., Glikmann G., Nates S.V. Correlation between rotavirus A genotypes detected in hospitalized children and sewage samples in 2006, Córdoba, Argentina. J. Med. Virol. 2010 Jul;82(7):1277–1281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20513096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calgua B., Fumian T., Rusinol M., Rodriguez-Manzano J., Mbayed V.A., Bofill-Mas S., Miagostovich M., Girones R. Detection and quantification of classic and emerging viruses by skimmed-milk flocculation and PCR in river water from two geographical areas. Water Res. 2013 May;47(8):2797–2810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23535378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fioretti J.M., Rocha M.S., Fumian T.M., Ginuino A., da Silva T.P., de Assis M.R., Rodrigues J.D., Carvalho-Costa F.A., Miagostovich M.P. Occurrence of human sapoviruses in wastewater and stool samples in Rio De Janeiro, Brazil. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2016 Sep;121(3):855–862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27306455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvo M., Lizasoain A., Castells M., Bortagaray V., Castro S., Colina R., Tort F.L., Victoria M. Human bocavirus: detection, quantification and molecular characterization in sewage and surface waters in Uruguay. Food Environ. Virol. 2018 Jun;10:193–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29299861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvo M., Mir D., Tort L.F., Lizasoain A., Colina R., Victoria M. Description of a human Bocavirus recombinant strain in the Americas. Mem. Inst. Oswaldo Cruz. 2019 Oct;21:114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6804322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31644704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos F.M., Vieira M.J., Garrafa P., Monezi T.A., Pellizari V.H., Hársi C.M., Mehnert D.U. Discrimination of adenovirus types circulating in urban sewage and surface polluted waters in São Paulo city, Brazil. Water Sci. Technol. Water Supply. 2004 Apr;4(2):79–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreyra L.J., Giordano M.O., Martinez L.C., Barril P.A., Masachessi G., Isa M.B., Poma R., Rajal V., Biganzoli P., Nates S.V., Pavan J.V. Tracking novel adenovirus in environmental and human clinical samples: no evidence of endemic human adenovirus type 58 circulation in Cordoba city, Argentina. Epidemiol. Infect. 2015 May;143(7):1427–1431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25165987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres C., Barrios M.E., Cammarata R.V., Cisterna D.M., Estrada T., Novas S.M., Cahn P., Fernández M.D., Mbayed V.A. High diversity of human polyomaviruses in environmental and clinical samples in Argentina: detection of JC, BK, Merkel-cell, Malawi, and human 6 and 7 polyomaviruses. Sci. Total Environ. 2016 Jan;15(542):192–202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26519580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fumian T.M., Guimarães F.R., Pereira Vaz B.J., da Silva M.T., Muylaert F.F., Bofill-Mas S., Gironés R., Leite J.P., Miagostovich M.P. Molecular detection, quantification and characterization of human polyomavirus JC from waste water in Rio De Janeiro, Brazil. J. Water and Health. 2010 Sep;8(3):438–445.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20375473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levican J., Levican A., Ampuero M., Gaggero A. JC polyomavirus circulation in one-year surveillance in wastewater in Santiago, Chile. Infect. Genet. Evol. 2019 Jul;1(71):151–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30905776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation (IHME) Covid-19 (https://covid19.healthdata.org/global?view=cumulative-deaths&amp;tab=trend).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru Covid-19 statistics worldometer (https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/peru/).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peru has the world's highest COVID death rate. Here's why NPR WAMU 88.5 (https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2021/11/27/1057387896/peru-has-the-worlds-highest-covid-death-rate-heres-why).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johns Hopkins University &amp; Medicine CORONAVIRUS RESEARCH CENTER (https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/data/mortality).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Disease Outbreak News; Multi-country monkeypox outbreak in non-endemic countries 2022. https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2022-DON390</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antinori A., Mazzotta V., Vita S., Carletti F., Tacconi D., Lapini L.E., D’Abramo A., Cicalini S., Lapa D., Pittalis S., Puro V. Epidemiological, clinical and virological characteristics of four cases of monkeypox support transmission through sexual contact, Italy, may 2022. Eurosurveillance. 2022 Jun;27(22):2200421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9164671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35656836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jonge E.F., Peterse C.M., Koelewijn J.M., van der Drift A.M., van der Beek R.F., Nagelkerke E., Lodder W.J. The detection of monkeypox virus DNA in wastewater samples in the Netherlands. Sci. Total Environ. 2022 Dec;15(852)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9558568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36057309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>