<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38754002</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>43</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Neurodevelopmental Outcomes Following Childhood Viral Meningitis in Canterbury New Zealand.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>924</StartPage><EndPage>930</EndPage><MedlinePgn>924-930</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004398</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Most childhood meningitis is viral in countries with widespread conjugate vaccine use. This study assessed clinical features and neurodevelopmental outcomes in preschool children following enteroviral and parechoviral meningitis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Children 18-42 months of age in Canterbury, New Zealand were included, who had enterovirus (EV) or parechovirus (HPEV) meningitis from 2015 to 2021. Comprehensive neurodevelopmental assessments were completed by a psychologist using the Bayley Scale for Infant Development-3 (BSID-3). Mean composite and scaled scores and proportion below the cutoff were assessed in each domain. Clinical data was analyzed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">There were 79 children 18-42 months old with previous EV or HPEV meningitis. BSID assessments were completed for 33 children (55% male), median age 32 months, from 2019 to 2022 including 23 with EV and 10 HPEV meningitis. At diagnosis, 32 (97%) received intravenous/intramuscular antibiotics, and 6 received a fluid bolus. Parents reported developmental speech concerns in 6 children, and delayed motor milestones in 1 child. There was no reported sensorineural hearing loss. BSID mean composite scores were in the expected range for cognition 102 (confidence interval: 98-106), language 96 (93-100) and motor 102 (98-106) domains. Overall, 12/33 (36%) children had below expected scores in 1 developmental domain, including scores 1-2 SD below the normative mean for cognition (2/33; 6%), receptive language (6/33; 18%), expressive language (5/33; 15%) and gross motor (6/33; 18%). There were no differences between scores in EV and HPEV meningitis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Following viral meningitis, more than a third of preschool children had a mild developmental delay with comprehensive neurodevelopmental assessment, suggesting targeted follow-up should be considered.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin</LastName><ForeName>Natalie G</ForeName><Initials>NG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1150-4602</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Paediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Williman</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health, University of Otago Christchurch, Christchurch, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walls</LastName><ForeName>Tony</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Paediatrics.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sadarangani</LastName><ForeName>Manish</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vaccine Evaluation Center, BC Children's Hospital Research Institute.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grant</LastName><ForeName>Cameron C</ForeName><Initials>CC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics: Child and Youth Health, University of Auckland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, General Paediatrics, Starship Children's Hospital, Auckland, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>University of Otago Research Grant</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009520" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">New Zealand</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008587" MajorTopicYN="Y">Meningitis, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065886" MajorTopicYN="N">Neurodevelopmental Disorders</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010850" MajorTopicYN="N">Picornaviridae Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002657" MajorTopicYN="N">Child Development</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030061" MajorTopicYN="N">Parechovirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002658" MajorTopicYN="N">Developmental Disabilities</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>M.S. has been an investigator on projects funded by GlaxoSmithKline, Merck, Moderna, Pfizer and Sanofi-Pasteur. All funds have been paid to his institute, and he has not received any personal payments. C.C.G. has been an investigator on projects funded by GlaxoSmithKline. All funds have been paid to his institute, and he has not received any personal payments. The other authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38754002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202410000-00002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Heath PT, McVernon J. The UK Hib vaccine experience. Arch Dis Child. 2002;86:396–399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ladhani SN, Slack MP, Andrews NJ, et al. Invasive pneumococcal disease after routine pneumococcal conjugate vaccination in children, England and Wales. Emerg Infect Dis. 2013;19:61–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell H, Borrow R, Salisbury D, et al. Meningococcal C conjugate vaccine: the experience in England and Wales. Vaccine. 2009;27:B20–B29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nigrovic LE, Kuppermann N, Macias CG, et al.; Pediatric Emergency Medicine Collaborative Research Committee of the American Academy of Pediatrics. Clinical prediction rule for identifying children with cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis at very low risk of bacterial meningitis. JAMA. 2007;297:52–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Sadarangani M, Pollard AJ, et al. Hospital admission rates for meningitis and septicaemia caused by Haemophilus influenzae , Neisseria meningitidis , and Streptococcus pneumoniae in children in England over five decades: a population-based observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:397–405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubos F, Lamotte B, Bibi-Triki F, et al. Clinical decision rules to distinguish between bacterial and aseptic meningitis. Arch Dis Child. 2006;91:647–650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuerlinckx D, El Hayeck J, Van der Linden D, et al. External validation of the bacterial meningitis score in children hospitalized with meningitis. Acta Clin Belg. 2012;67:282–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadarangani M, Willis L, Kadambari S, et al. Childhood meningitis in the conjugate vaccine era: a prospective cohort study. Arch Dis Child. 2015;100:292–294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Defres S, Willis L, et al.; on behalf of the UK-ChiMES and ENCEPH-UK study groups. Paediatric meningitis in the conjugate vaccine era and a novel clinical decision model to predict bacterial aetiology. J Infect. 2024;88:106145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson LD, Viner RM, Christie D. Long-term sequelae of childhood bacterial meningitis. Curr Infect Dis Rep. 2013;15:236–241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edmond K, Clark A, Korczak VS, et al. Global and regional risk of disabling sequelae from bacterial meningitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10:317–328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viner RM, Booy R, Johnson H, et al. Outcomes of invasive meningococcal serogroup B disease in children and adolescents (MOSAIC): a case-control study. Lancet Neurol. 2012;11:774–783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadarangani M, Scheifele DW, Halperin SA, et al.; investigators of the Canadian Immunization Monitoring Program, ACTive (IMPACT). Outcomes of invasive meningococcal disease in adults and children in Canada between 2002 and 2011: a prospective cohort study. Clin Infect Dis. 2015;60:e27–e35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergman I, Painter MJ, Wald ER, et al. Outcome in children with enteroviral meningitis during the first year of life. J Pediatr. 1987;110:705–709.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rorabaugh ML, Berlin LE, Heldrich F, et al. Aseptic meningitis in infants younger than 2 years of age: acute illness and neurologic complications. Pediatrics. 1993;92:206–211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilfert CM, Thompson RJ Jr, Sunder TR, et al. Longitudinal assessment of children with enteroviral meningitis during the first three months of life. Pediatrics. 1981;67:811–815.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee KY, Burgner D, Lee HS, et al. The changing epidemiology of pediatric aseptic meningitis in Daejeon, Korea from 1987 to 2003. BMC Infect Dis. 2005;5:97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatami A, McMullan BJ, Webber M, et al. Sepsis-like disease in infants due to human parechovirus type 3 during an outbreak in Australia. Clin Infect Dis. 2015;60:228–236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker RC, Kummer AW, Schultz JR, et al. Neurodevelopmental outcome of infants with viral meningitis in the first three months of life. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 1996;35:295–301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farmer K, MacArthur BA, Clay MM. A follow-up study of 15 cases of neonatal meningoencephalitis due to Coxsackie virus B5. J Pediatr. 1975;87:568–571.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sells CJ, Carpenter RL, Ray CG. Sequelae of central-nervous-system enterovirus infections. N Engl J Med. 1975;293:1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Dale RC, Nissen MD, et al.; on behalf of the PAEDS-ACE Investigators. Parechovirus encephalitis and neurodevelopmental outcomes. Pediatrics. 2016;137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Ory F, Avellon A, Echevarria JE, et al. Viral infections of the central nervous system in Spain: a prospective study. J Med Virol. 2013;85:554–562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Okike I, Ribeiro S, et al. Seven-fold increase in viral meningo-encephalitis reports in England and Wales during 2004-2013. J Infect. 2014;69:326–332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waespe N, Steffen I, Heininger U. Etiology of aseptic meningitis, peripheral facial nerve palsy, and a combination of both in children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2010;29:453–456.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyypia T, Horsnell C, Maaronen M, et al. A distinct picornavirus group identified by sequence analysis. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1992;89:8847–8851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton PN, Khandaker G, Khatami A, et al. High prevalence of developmental concern amongst infants at 12 months following hospitalised parechovirus infection. J Paediatr Child Health. 2018;54:289–295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph L, May M, Thomas M, et al. Human parechovirus 3 in infants: expanding our knowledge of adverse outcomes. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2019;38:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vergnano S, Kadambari S, Whalley K, et al. Characteristics and outcomes of human parechovirus infection in infants (2008-2012). Eur J Pediatr. 2015;174:919–924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albers CA, Grieve AJ. Test review: Bayley, N. (2006). Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development– third edition. San Antonio, TX: Harcourt Assessment. J Psychoeduc Assess. 2007;25:180–190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinta S, Walker K, Halliday R, et al. A comparison of the performance of healthy Australian 3-year-olds with the standardised norms of the Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (version-III). Arch Dis Child. 2014;99:621–624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darlow BA, Horwood LJ, Wynn-Williams MB, et al. Admissions of all gestations to a regional neonatal unit versus controls: 2-year outcome. J Paediatr Child Health. 2009;45:187–193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The National Institute for Health and Care Excellence Guideline Development Group. Bacterial meningitis and meningococcal septicaemia in children, NICE Clinical Guidance: full guideline. 2010. https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg102/evidence/full-guideline-134564941 . Accessed September 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss L, Oakland T, Aylward G. Bayley-III Clinical Use and Interpretation. 1st ed. Academic Press, Elsevier; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldsworthy M, Franich-Ray C, Kinney S, et al. Relationship between social-emotional and neurodevelopment of 2-year-old children with congenital heart disease. Congenit Heart Dis. 2016;11:378–385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson JA, Broad J, Martin NG, et al. Outcomes beyond hospital discharge in infants and children with viral meningitis: a systematic review. Rev Med Virol. 2019;30:e2083.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang L-Y, Huang L-M, Gau SS-F, et al. Neurodevelopment and cognition in children after enterovirus 71 infection. N Engl J Med. 2007;356:1226–1234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Jiang L, Peng H-l. Clinical analysis of 134 children with nervous system damage caused by enterovirus 71 infection. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2015;34:718–723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramanian H, Wagh D, Rao S, et al. Developmental outcomes in cerebrospinal fluid proven enteroviral meningitis in neonates &gt; 32 weeks of gestation. J Paediatr Child Health. 2016;52:327–332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hristeva L, Booy R, Bowler I, et al. Prospective surveillance of neonatal meningitis. Arch Dis Child. 1993;69(1 Spec No):14–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gau SS, Chang LY, Huang LM, et al. Attention-deficit/hyperactivity-related symptoms among children with enterovirus 71 infection of the central nervous system. Pediatrics. 2008;122:e452–e458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biaukula VL, Tikoduadua L, Azzopardi K, et al. Meningitis in children in Fiji: etiology, epidemiology, and neurological sequelae. Int J Infect Dis. 2012;16:e289–e295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao X, Wong V. Brainstem auditory-evoked potential evaluation in children with meningitis. Pediatr Neurol. 1998;19:109–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choong CT, Lee EY, Tan HKK, et al. Good hearing outcome in children recovering from non-polio enteroviral meningitis. J Paediatr Child Health. 2021;57:1438–1441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimberlin DW, Jester PM, Sanchez PJ, et al.; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases Collaborative Antiviral Study Group. Valganciclovir for symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus disease. N Engl J Med. 2015;372:933–943.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei X, Franke N, Alsweiler J, et al. Dextrose gel prophylaxis for neonatal hypoglycaemia and neurocognitive function at early school age: a randomised dosage trial [published online ahead of print February 12, 2024]. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2024:fetalneonatal-2023. doi:10.1136/archdischild-2023-326452.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin NG, Sadarangani M, Kelly DF, Pollard AJ. Childhood meningitis: current and previous UK epidemiology, clinical and laboratory characteristics and outcomes. DPhil thesis. University of Oxford; 2017. https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:16d3f55f-e3dd-45e1-8fec-2552bdf78cd6 . Accessed September 4, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landgraf JM. ITQOL: Infant toddler quality of life questionnaire™. 2007. Available at: https://www.qualitymetric.com/health-surveys/itqol-infant-toddler-quality-of-life-questionnaire/ . Accessed March 6, 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huizing KM, Swanink CM, Landstra AM, et al. Rapid enterovirus molecular testing in cerebrospinal fluid reduces length of hospitalization and duration of antibiotic therapy in children with aseptic meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2011;30:1107–1109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King RL, Lorch SA, Cohen DM, et al. Routine cerebrospinal fluid enterovirus polymerase chain reaction testing reduces hospitalization and antibiotic use for infants 90 days of age or younger. Pediatrics. 2007;120:489–496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyons TW, McAdam AJ, Cohn KA, et al. Impact of in-hospital enteroviral polymerase chain reaction testing on the clinical management of children with meningitis. J Hosp Med. 2012;7:517–520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson CC, Willis M, Meagher A, et al. Impact of rapid polymerase chain reaction results on management of pediatric patients with enteroviral meningitis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2002;21:283–286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffery KJ, Read SJ, Peto TE, et al. Diagnosis of viral infections of the central nervous system: clinical interpretation of PCR results. Lancet. 1997;349:313–317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seiden JA, Zorc JJ, Hodinka RL, et al. Lack of cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis in young infants with enterovirus infections of the central nervous system. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2010;26:77–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun KW, Choi EH, Cheon DS, et al. Enteroviral meningitis without pleocytosis in children. Arch Dis Child. 2012;97:874–878.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Griffiths M, Solomon T, et al. Distinct systemic and central nervous system disease patterns in enterovirus and parechovirus infected children. J Infect. 2014;69:69–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulford WS, Buller RS, Arens MQ, et al. Correlation of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) cell counts and elevated CSF protein levels with enterovirus reverse transcription-PCR results in pediatric and adult patients. J Clin Microbiol. 2004;42:4199–4203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadwick DR. Viral meningitis. Br Med Bull. 2005;75-76:1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negrini B, Kelleher KJ, Wald ER. Cerebrospinal fluid findings in aseptic versus bacterial meningitis. Pediatrics. 2000;105:316–319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaker OG, Abdelhamid N. Detection of enteroviruses in pediatric patients with aseptic meningitis. Clin Neurol Neurosurg. 2015;129:67–71.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>