<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38779280</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemiological and Clinical Profile of Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in Children in a Tertiary Care Center in Jammu.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e58704</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e58704</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e58704</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.58704</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) is a viral illness commonly seen in children under five years of age, characterized by typical manifestations such as oral lesions and rashes on the hands and feet. Coxsackievirus A-16 (CV-A16) and Enterovirus A-71 (EV-A71) are the major etiological agents of this disease. Over the past two decades, there have been several outbreaks of HFMD all across India. As there is no chemoprophylaxis available for the disease, it becomes even more significant to conduct regular research and surveillance for HFMD. Aim and objective To observe the clinico-epidemiological profile along with constitutional symptoms in HFMD patients attending pediatric OPD. Methods This hospital-based prospective observational study was conducted in the Post Graduate Department of Pediatrics, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital (ASCOMS &amp; H), Sidra, Jammu and Kashmir, India, over six months from April to September 2023. A total of 132 children with symptoms of HFMD visited the pediatric OPD. After using inclusive and exclusive criteria, we selected a sample size of 112 children with HFMD. The descriptive data were expressed in terms of percentages and proportions, and their graphical representation was done using MS Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington, United States). Results Among the 112 HFMD patients examined, the highest peak was seen in August, followed by another one in September. Most of the cases were seen in the age group of zero to three years, and it was observed that there was a linear fall in the number of cases with the increase in age. Nearly 61% of cases were male, showing a slight male preponderance. Vesiculopapular rash on the hand and foot was the most common clinical characteristic, whereas painful deglutition was noted to be the most common constitutional symptom in HFMD patients. About 27% had a positive family history, and nail changes post-recovery were present in 1.79% of cases during their regular follow-ups. Conclusions This study reveals that HFMD cases surged in August and September, with a history of contact in one-fourth of cases. Disease is seen more commonly in children under three years of age, and the incidence of cases decreases with the increase in age. The illness is usually contagious and can spread quickly; therefore, more awareness programs should be done to educate parents and promote hygiene to prevent contact cases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Khajuria et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khajuria</LastName><ForeName>Aakriti</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital, Jammu, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saini</LastName><ForeName>Divyanshu</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital, Jammu, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gupta</LastName><ForeName>Ravinder K</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital, Jammu, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Amber</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital, Jammu, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Babber</LastName><ForeName>Sunny</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Acharya Shri Chander College of Medical Sciences and Hospital, Jammu, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinico-epidemiological profile</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus a-16</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus a-71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hand-foot-and-mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vesiculopapular rash</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38779280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11109520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.58704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Singhal T, Lodha R, Kabra SK. Ghai Essential Pediatrics 10th Edition. New Delhi, India: CBS Publishers &amp; Distributors Pvt Ltd; Infections and Infestations; pp. 220–293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot, and mouth disease: identifying and managing an acute viral syndrome. Repass GL, Palmer WC, Stancampiano FF. Cleve Clin J Med. 2014;81:537–543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25183845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot, and mouth disease in adults. Afonso C, Almeida A. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10699830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38060762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Current status of hand-foot-and-mouth disease. Zhu P, Ji W, Li D, et al. J Biomed Sci. 2023;30:15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9951172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36829162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD): emerging epidemiology and the need for a vaccine strategy. Aswathyraj S, Arunkumar G, Alidjinou EK, Hober D. Med Microbiol Immunol. 2016;205:397–407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27406374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot and mouth disease: changing Indian scenario. Rao PK, Veena K, Jagadishchandra H, Bhat SS, Shetty SR. Int J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2012;5:220–222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4155884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25206173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot and mouth disease: a single centre retrospective study of 403 new cases and brief review of relevant Indian literature to understand clinical, epidemiological, and virological attributes of a long-lasting Indian epidemic. Sharma A, Mahajan VK, Mehta KS, Chauhan PS, Manvi S, Chauhan A. Indian Dermatol Online J. 2022;13:310–320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9549533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36226004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical profile and molecular typing of viral etiological agents associated with Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease (HFMD): a study from Udhampur, Northern India. Aggarwal M, Bansal N, Naresh A, et al. Indian J Med Microbiol. 2023;41:97–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36470773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand, foot and mouth disease in children: a clinico epidemiological study. Kumar KB, Kiran AG, Kumar BU. Indian Journal of Paediatric Dermatology. 2016;17:7–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Age patterns and transmission characteristics of hand, foot and mouth disease in China. Zhao J, Jiang F, Zhong L, Sun J, Ding J. BMC Infect Dis. 2016;16:691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5117511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27871252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An epidemiological surveillance of hand foot and mouth disease in paediatric patients and in community: a Singapore retrospective cohort study, 2013-2018. Min N, Ong YH, Han AX, et al. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2021;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7901731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33566802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hand foot mouth disease during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic: a multicentric study. Mohta A, Pareek S, Sharma MK, Aggrwal A, Vyas K, Pandey H, Jain SK. Indian Pediatr. 2023;60:394–396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10185946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36814120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemic of hand, foot and mouth disease in West Bengal, India in August, 2007: a multicentric study. Sarma N, Sarkar A, Mukherjee A, Ghosh A, Dhar S, Malakar R. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20049265/ Indian J Dermatol. 2009;54:26–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2800866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20049265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology and clinical characteristics of hand foot, and mouth disease in a Shenzhen sentinel hospital from 2009 to 2011. Wang YR, Sun LL, Xiao WL, Chen LY, Wang XF, Pan DM. BMC Infect Dis. 2013;13:539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3829808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24225231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinico-epidemiological profile and complications of hand foot mouth disease among cases attending tertiary care centre in Northern Kerala, India. Linu M, Thomas R, Kumaran JA. International Journal Of Community Medicine And Public Health. 2023;10:2849–2853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiological research on hand, foot, and mouth disease in mainland China. Zhuang ZC, Kou ZQ, Bai YJ, et al.  https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4690870/ Viruses. 2015;7:6400–6411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4690870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26690202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical profile of hand, foot, and mouth disease and its associated complications among children in Shimoga City, southern Karnataka: a hospital-based study. Kumar VS, Budur SV, Odappa GH, Bankolli SY, Rao AP. Indian J Public Health. 2015;59:141–144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26021653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mucocutaneous features of hand, foot, and mouth disease: a reappraisal from an outbreak in the city of Kolkata. Ghosh SK, Bandyopadhyay D, Ghosh A, Dutta A, Biswas S, Mandal RK, Jamadar NS. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol. 2010;76:564–566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20827002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Udaipur. Agarwal N, Mittal A, Kayal A, Khare AK, Kuldeep C, Gupta LK. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4318054/#:~:text=Thirty%2Deight%20patients%2C%2020%20males,skin%2C%20predominantly%20over%20distal%20extremities. Indian J Dermatol. 2015;60:108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4318054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25657448</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical profile and virology analysis of hand, foot and mouth disease cases from North Kerala, India in 2015-2016: a tertiary care hospital-based cross-sectional study. Sabitha S, Sasidharanpillai S, Sanjay RE, et al. Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol. 2018;84:328–331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29620046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The history of enterovirus A71 outbreaks and molecular epidemiology in the Asia-Pacific region. Puenpa J, Wanlapakorn N, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y. J Biomed Sci. 2019;26:75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6798416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31627753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nail changes in hand-foot-and-mouth disease (HFMD) Verma S, Singal A. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8354413/#:~:text=Characteristic%20nail%20changes%2C%20onychomadesis%2C%20Beau's,weeks%20after%20the%20disease%20onset. Indian Dermatol Online J. 2021;12:656–657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8354413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34430491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onychomadesis and Beau’s line following hand-foot-and-mouth disease in a seven-year-old male. Alghamdi A, Mazraani N, Alghamdi Y, Albugami SM. Cureus. 2022;14:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9069175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35530819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>