<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38752008</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2287-3651</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical and experimental vaccine research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Exp Vaccine Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Inferring B-cell derived T-cell receptor induced multi-epitope-based vaccine candidate against enterovirus 71: a reverse vaccinology approach.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>132</StartPage><EndPage>145</EndPage><MedlinePgn>132-145</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7774/cevr.2024.13.2.132</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Enterovirus 71, a pathogen that causes hand-foot and mouth disease (HFMD) is currently regarded as an increasing neurotropic virus in Asia and can cause severe complications in pediatric patients with blister-like sores or rashes on the hand, feet, and mouth. Notwithstanding the significant burden of the disease, no authorized vaccine is available. Previously identified attenuated and inactivated vaccines are worthless over time owing to changes in the viral genome.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A novel vaccine construct using B-cell derived T-cell epitopes from the virulent polyprotein found the induction of possible immune response. In order to boost the immune system, a beta-defensin 1 preproprotein adjuvant with EAAAK linker was added at the N-terminal end of the vaccine sequence.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The immunogenicity of the designed, refined, and verified prospective three-dimensional-structure of the multi-epitope vaccine was found to be quite high, exhibiting non-allergenic and antigenic properties. The vaccine candidates bound to toll-like receptor 3 in a molecular docking analysis, and the efficacy of the potential vaccine to generate a strong immune response was assessed through <i>in silico</i> immunological simulation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Computational analysis has shown that the proposed multi-epitope vaccine is possibly safe for use in humans and can elicit an immune response.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Korean Vaccine Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Swain</LastName><ForeName>Subrat Kumar</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9173-1727</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Research, IMS and SUM Hospital, Siksha "O" Anusandhan Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Panda</LastName><ForeName>Subhasmita</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2813-9931</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, IMS and SUM Hospital, Siksha "O" Anusandhan Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sahu</LastName><ForeName>Basanta Pravas</ForeName><Initials>BP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6454-0976</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biological Science, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Decipline of Biosciences and Biomedical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology, Indore, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahapatra</LastName><ForeName>Soumya Ranjan</ForeName><Initials>SR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8927-458X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biotechnology, Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology (KIIT), Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dey</LastName><ForeName>Jyotirmayee</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5543-7109</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biotechnology, Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology (KIIT), Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarangi</LastName><ForeName>Rachita</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1204-5746</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, IMS and SUM Hospital, Siksha "O" Anusandhan Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Misra</LastName><ForeName>Namrata</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1813-6478</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biotechnology, Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology (KIIT), Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>KIIT-Technology Business Incubator (KIIT-TBI), Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology (KIIT), Deemed to be University, Bhubaneswar, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Exp Vaccine Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101592344</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2287-3651</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus 71</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ligand-receptor docking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reverse vaccinology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38752008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11091429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7774/cevr.2024.13.2.132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Poland GA, Ovsyannikova IG, Jacobson RM. Application of pharmacogenomics to vaccines. Pharmacogenomics. 2009;10:837–852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2722448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19450131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flower DR. Bioinformatics for vaccinology. Hoboken (NJ): John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourdette DN, Edmonds E, Smith C, et al. A highly immunogenic trivalent T cell receptor peptide vaccine for multiple sclerosis. Mult Scler. 2005;11:552–561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16193893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez JA, Weilenman C, Audran R, et al. A synthetic malaria vaccine elicits a potent CD8(+) and CD4(+) T lymphocyte immune response in humans: implications for vaccination strategies. Eur J Immunol. 2001;31:1989–1998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11449351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knutson KL, Schiffman K, Disis ML. Immunization with a HER-2/neu helper peptide vaccine generates HER-2/neu CD8 T-cell immunity in cancer patients. J Clin Invest. 2001;107:477–484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC199268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11181647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W, Liao Q, Viboud C, et al. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008-12: an epidemiological study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:308–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4035015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24485991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox JA, Hiscox JA, Solomon T, Ooi MH, Ng LF. Immunopathogenesis and virus-host interactions of enterovirus 71 in patients with hand, foot and mouth disease. Front Microbiol. 2017;8:2249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5713468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29238324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei X, Cui S, Zhao Z, Wang J. Etiology, pathogenesis, antivirals and vaccines of hand, foot, and mouth disease. Natl Sci Rev. 2015;2:268–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bello AM, Roshorm YM. Recent progress and advances towards developing enterovirus 71 vaccines for effective protection against human hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) Biologicals. 2022;79:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36089444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi EJ, Shin YJ, Kim JH, Kim TG, Chang SY. Enterovirus 71 infection and vaccines. Clin Exp Vaccine Res. 2017;6:4–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5292356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28168168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu IN, Farinelle S, Sausy A, Muller CP. Identification of a CD4 T-cell epitope in the hemagglutinin stalk domain of pandemic H1N1 influenza virus and its antigen-driven TCR usage signature in BALB/c mice. Cell Mol Immunol. 2017;14:511–520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5518815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27157498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He R, Yang X, Liu C, et al. Efficient control of chronic LCMV infection by a CD4 T cell epitope-based heterologous prime-boost vaccination in a murine model. Cell Mol Immunol. 2018;15:815–826.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6203753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28287115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsen MV, Lundegaard C, Lamberth K, Buus S, Lund O, Nielsen M. Large-scale validation of methods for cytotoxic T-lymphocyte epitope prediction. BMC Bioinformatics. 2007;8:424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2194739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17973982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reynisson B, Alvarez B, Paul S, Peters B, Nielsen M. NetMHCpan-4.1 and NetMHCIIpan-4.0: improved predictions of MHC antigen presentation by concurrent motif deconvolution and integration of MS MHC eluted ligand data. Nucleic Acids Res. 2020;48:W449–W454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7319546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32406916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Raghava GP. Prediction methods for B-cell epitopes. Methods Mol Biol. 2007;409:387–394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18450017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimitrov I, Bangov I, Flower DR, Doytchinova I. AllerTOP v.2: a server for in silico prediction of allergens. J Mol Model. 2014;20:2278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24878803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doytchinova IA, Flower DR. VaxiJen: a server for prediction of protective antigens, tumour antigens and subunit vaccines. BMC Bioinformatics. 2007;8:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1780059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17207271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng J, Randall AZ, Sweredoski MJ, Baldi P. SCRATCH: a protein structure and structural feature prediction server. Nucleic Acids Res. 2005;33:W72–W76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1160157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15980571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta S, Kapoor P, Chaudhary K, et al. In silico approach for predicting toxicity of peptides and proteins. PLoS One. 2013;8:e73957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3772798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24058508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vita R, Mahajan S, Overton JA, et al. The Immune Epitope Database (IEDB): 2018 update. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47(D1):D339–D343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6324067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30357391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bui HH, Sidney J, Dinh K, Southwood S, Newman MJ, Sette A. Predicting population coverage of T-cell epitope-based diagnostics and vaccines. BMC Bioinformatics. 2006;7:153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1513259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16545123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasteiger E, Hoogland C, Gattiker A, et al. In: The proteomics protocols handbook. Walker JM, editor. New York (NY): Humana Press; 2005. Protein identification and analysis tools on the Expasy server; pp. 571–607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGuffin LJ, Bryson K, Jones DT. The PSIPRED protein structure prediction server. Bioinformatics. 2000;16:404–405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10869041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GR, Won J, Heo L, Seok C. GalaxyRefine2: simultaneous refinement of inaccurate local regions and overall protein structure. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47:W451–W455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6602442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31001635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laskowski RA, MacArthur MW, Moss DS, Thornton JM. PROCHECK: a program to check the stereochemical quality of protein structures. J Appl Crystallogr. 1993;26:283–291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craig DB, Dombkowski AA. Disulfide by Design 2.0: a web-based tool for disulfide engineering in proteins. BMC Bioinformatics. 2013;14:346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3898251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24289175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozakov D, Hall DR, Xia B, et al. The ClusPro web server for protein-protein docking. Nat Protoc. 2017;12:255–278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5540229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28079879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Sanden S, Koopmans M, Uslu G, van der Avoort H Dutch Working Group for Clinical Virology. Epidemiology of enterovirus 71 in the Netherlands, 1963 to 2008. J Clin Microbiol. 2009;47:2826–2833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2738086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19625480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rapin N, Lund O, Bernaschi M, Castiglione F. Computational immunology meets bioinformatics: the use of prediction tools for molecular binding in the simulation of the immune system. PLoS One. 2010;5:e9862.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2855701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20419125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Nagata N, Iwata N, et al. An attenuated strain of enterovirus 71 belonging to genotype a showed a broad spectrum of antigenicity with attenuated neurovirulence in cynomolgus monkeys. J Virol. 2007;81:9386–9395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1951441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17567701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi EE, Phoon MC, Ishak B, Chan SH. Seroepidemiology of human enterovirus 71, Singapore. Emerg Infect Dis. 2002;8:995–997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2732542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12194783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Tu P, Thao NT, Perera D, et al. Epidemiologic and virologic investigation of hand, foot, and mouth disease, southern Vietnam, 2005. Emerg Infect Dis. 2007;13:1733–1741.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3375788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18217559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bible JM, Pantelidis P, Chan PK, Tong CY. Genetic evolution of enterovirus 71: epidemiological and pathological implications. Rev Med Virol. 2007;17:371–379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17487831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan YF, Sam IC, AbuBakar S. Phylogenetic designation of enterovirus 71 genotypes and subgenotypes using complete genome sequences. Infect Genet Evol. 2010;10:404–412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19465162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu SC, Liu CC, Lian WC. Optimization of microcarrier cell culture process for the inactivated enterovirus type 71 vaccine development. Vaccine. 2004;22:3858–3864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15364432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tung WS, Bakar SA, Sekawi Z, Rosli R. DNA vaccine constructs against enterovirus 71 elicit immune response in mice. Genet Vaccines Ther. 2007;5:6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3225814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17445254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray KA, Allen T, Loh E, Machalaba C, Daszak P. In: Food safety risks from wildlife: challenges in agriculture, conservation, and public health. Jay-Russell M, Doyle M, editors. Cham: Springer; 2016. Emerging viral zoonoses from wildlife associated with animal-based food systems: risks and opportunities; pp. 31–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojha R, Nandani R, Prajapati VK. Contriving multiepitope subunit vaccine by exploiting structural and nonstructural viral proteins to prevent Epstein-Barr virus-associated malignancy. J Cell Physiol. 2019;234:6437–6448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30362500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma A, Sanduja P, Anand A, et al. Advanced strategies for development of vaccines against human bacterial pathogens. World J Microbiol Biotechnol. 2021;37:67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7982316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33748926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moise L, Gutierrez A, Kibria F, et al. iVAX: an integrated toolkit for the selection and optimization of antigens and the design of epitope-driven vaccines. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2015;11:2312–2321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4635942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26155959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>