<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38792848</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2076-2607</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microorganisms</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microorganisms</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficiency of Virucidal Disinfectants on Wood Surfaces in Animal Husbandry.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1019</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/microorganisms12051019</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The aim of this study was to test the inactivation of viruses on germ carriers of different types of wood using a disinfectant in order to assess the biosafety of wood as a building material in animal husbandry. The laboratory disinfectant efficacy tests were based on German testing guidelines and current European standards. Five different types of wood germ carriers, i.e., spruce (<i>Picea abies</i>), pine (<i>Pinus sylvestris</i>), poplar (<i>Populus</i> sp.), beech (<i>Fagus sylvatica</i>) and Douglas fir (<i>Pseudotsuga menziesii</i>), were inoculated with enveloped or non-enveloped viruses and then treated with one of three different disinfectants. The results revealed that intact, fine-sawn timber with a low roughness depth can be effectively inactivated. Peracetic acid proved to be the most effective disinfectant across all tests. Regardless of the pathogen and the type of wood, a concentration of 0.1% of the pure substance at a temperature of 10 °C and an exposure time of one hour can be recommended. At a temperature of -10 °C, a concentration of 0.75% is recommended. The basic chemicals formic acid and glutaraldehyde demonstrated only limited effectiveness overall. The synergistic effects of various wood components on the inactivation of viruses offer potential for further investigation. Disinfectant tests should also be conclusively verified in field trials to ensure that the results from standardised laboratory tests can be transferred to real stable conditions.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oettler</LastName><ForeName>Martin J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-8596-1211</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, 17493 Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Conraths</LastName><ForeName>Franz J</ForeName><Initials>FJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7400-9409</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, 17493 Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roesler</LastName><ForeName>Uwe</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6268-5207</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Animal Hygiene and Environmental Health, Freie Universität Berlin, 14163 Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reiche</LastName><ForeName>Sven</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7575-2483</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Experimental Animal Facilities and Biorisk Management, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, 17493 Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Homeier-Bachmann</LastName><ForeName>Timo</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8135-3814</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, 17493 Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Denzin</LastName><ForeName>Nicolai</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4705-6792</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Federal Research Institute for Animal Health, 17493 Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2220HV036E</GrantID><Agency>Fachagentur Nachwachsende Rohstoffe</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Microorganisms</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101625893</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2076-2607</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus E</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Newcastle disease virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disinfection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">formic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">glutaraldehyde</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inactivation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">peracetic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">wood</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38792848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11124466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12051019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">microorganisms12051019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Federal Ministry of Food and Agriculture of Germany  Charta für Holz 2.0.  [(accessed on 11 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.bmel.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/DE/Broschueren/ChartafuerHolz20.pdf?__blob=publicationFile&amp;v=7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Statistical Office of Germany  Baufertigstellungen von Wohn- und Nichtwohngebäuden (Neubau) nach Überwiegend Verwendetem Baustoff.  [(accessed on 11 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.destatis.de/DE/Themen/Branchen-Unternehmen/Bauen/Publikationen/Downloads-Bautaetigkeit/baufertigstellungen-baustoff-pdf-5311202.pdf?__blob=publicationFile.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Statistical Office of Germany  Baugenehmigungen von Wohn- und Nichtwohngebäuden nach Überwiegend Verwendetem Baustoff.  [(accessed on 11 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.destatis.de/DE/Themen/Branchen-Unternehmen/Bauen/Publikationen/Downloads-Bautaetigkeit/baugenehmigungen-baustoff-pdf-5311107.pdf?__blob=publicationFile.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Statistical Office of Germany  Land- und Forstwirtschaft, Fischerei: Bodennutzung der Betriebe.  [(accessed on 11 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.destatis.de/DE/Themen/Branchen-Unternehmen/Landwirtschaft-Forstwirtschaft-Fischerei/Publikationen/Bodennutzung/bodennutzung-2030212227004.pdf?__blob=publicationFile.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bär K. Auf die Planung kommt es an—Landwirtschaftliches Bauen mit Holz. Bauernzeitung. 2022;63:19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittrach B. Dauerhaft mit Holz bauen. BLW. 1979;8:53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engler K. Ein Schweinestall aus Holz?!! Landwirt. 2021;11:32–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dauermann A., Enneking U. Einstellungen deutscher LandwirtInnen zum Holzeinsatz beim Stallbau. Austrian J. Agric. Econ. Rural. Stud. 2019;29:177–183. doi: 10.15203/OEGA_29.21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15203/OEGA_29.21</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y., Dietsch P., Winter S. Landwirtschaftliche Nutzgebäude aus Holz. LWF Aktuell. 2019;25:53–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dietsch P., Jiang Y., Winter S. Landwirtschaftliches Bauen mit Holz—Vorbeugender chemischer Holzschutz zwangsläufig notwendig? Int. Holzbau-Forum. 2018;24:325–338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dederich L., Witzel E. Beispielhafte Betriebsgebäude mit Holz gebaut. Landtechnik. 2006;61:394–396. doi: 10.15150/LT.2006.1146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15150/LT.2006.1146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Parliament. Council of the European Union . Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 on the hygiene of foodstuffs, last amended by Commission Regulation (EU) 2021/382 of 3 March 2021. Official Journal of the European Union; Luxembourg: 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Parliament. Council of the European Union . Regulation (EU) 2016/429 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 March 2016 on Transmissible Animal Diseases and Amending and Repealing Certain Acts in the Area of Animal Health (‘Animal Health Law’), Last Amended by Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2018/1629 of 25 July 2018. Official Journal of the European Union; Luxembourg: 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böhm R. Reinigung und Desinfektion im Tierseuchenfall.  [(accessed on 3 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://umwelthygiene-tierhygiene.uni-hohenheim.de/fileadmin/einrichtungen/umwelthygiene-tierhygiene/April_2009/Nutztiersystmanagm_schwein/Gesetzestexte/Skriptum_Reinigung_und_Desinfektipon_im_Tierseuchenfall.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schönwälder A., Kehr R., Wulf A., Smalla K. Wooden boards affecting the survival of bacteria? Holz Roh Werkst. 2002;60:249–257. doi: 10.1007/s00107-002-0300-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00107-002-0300-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gehrig M., Schnell G., Zürcher E., Kucera L.J. Hygienische Eigenschaften von Holz- und Kunststoffbrettern in der Nahrungsmittelverarbeitung und -präsentation: Ein Vergleich. Holz Roh Werkst. 2000;58:265–269. doi: 10.1007/s001070050423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s001070050423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böhm R. Grundlagen der Reinigung und Desinfektion. In: Strauch D., Böhm R., editors. Reinigung und Desinfektion in der Nutztierhaltung und Veredlungswirtschaft. 2nd ed. Enke Verlag; Stuttgart, Germany: 2002. pp. 19–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böhm R. Reinigung und Desinfektion in der Haltung von Wiederkäuern und Schweinen. In: Strauch D., Böhm R., editors. Reinigung und Desinfektion in der Nutztierhaltung und Veredlungswirtschaft. 2nd ed. Enke Verlag; Stuttgart, Germany: 2002. pp. 65–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schliesser T. Desinfektionsmaßnahmen in der Veterinärmedizin. In: Bodenschatz W., editor. Kompaktwissen Desinfektion. 3rd ed. Behr’s Verlag; Hamburg, Germany: 2022. pp. 390–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoy S. Reinigung und Desinfektion. In: Hoy S., Gauly M., Krieter J., editors. Nutztierhaltung und -Hygiene. 2nd ed. Verlag Eugen Ulmer; Stuttgart, Germany: 2016. pp. 256–268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Committee for Standardization . EN 14675: Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics—Quantitative Suspension Test for the Evaluation of Virucidal Activity of Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics Used in the Veterinary Area—Test Method and Requirements (Phase 2, Step 1) Beuth Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Committee for Standardization . EN 17122: Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics—Quantitative Non-Porous Surface Test for the Evaluation of Virucidal Activity of Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics Used in the Veterinary Area—Test Method and Requirements—Phase 2, Step 2. Beuth Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deutsche Veterinärmedizinische Gesellschaft  Methoden der Prüfung von Chemischen Desinfektionsmitteln für die Tierhaltung, Viruzidie.  [(accessed on 3 August 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.desinfektion-dvg.de/fileadmin/FG_Desinfektion/Dokumente/Fuer_Gutachter/Pruefrichtlinien/V.4_Viruzidie_7Nov2017.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bremer P. Untersuchungen zur Viruziden Wirksamkeit von Chemischen Desinfektionsmitteln bei Verschiedenen Temperaturen. Justus-Liebig-Universität Gießen; Gießen, Germany: 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pirschel J.C. Untersuchungen zur Eignung Verschiedener Animaler Viren zur Prüfung der Viruzidie Chemischer Desinfektionsmittel in der Nutztierhaltung. Universität Leipzig; Leipzig, Germany: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Köhler C. Untersuchungen zur Änderung der DVG-Desinfektionsmittelrichtlinien (Viruzidie) Universität Leipzig; Leipzig, Germany: 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt F. Etablierung Neuer Richtlinien für Die Desinfektionsmittelprüfung im Bereich Tierhaltung Sowie für Die Tierärztliche Praxis. Universität Leipzig; Leipzig, Germany: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karnath C. Etablierung eines Keimträgermodells zur Prüfung der Viruziden Wirksamkeit von Desinfektionsmitteln. Universität Leipzig; Leipzig, Germany: 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Committee for Standardization . EN 12353: Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics—Preservation of Test Organisms Used for the Determination of Bactericidal (Including Legionella), Mycobactericidal, Sporicidal, Fungicidal and Virucidal (Including Bacteriophages) Activity. Beuth Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schubert G.F. Leitfaden Desinfektion, Sterilisation und Entwesung. 10th ed. Behr’s Verlag; Hamburg, Germany: 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ticháček B. Peressigsäure. In: Horn H., Přívora M., Weuffen W., editors. Handbuch der Desinfektion und Sterilisation, Band 1. 1st ed. VEB Verlag Volk und Gesundheit; Berlin, Germany: 1972. pp. 162–177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A., Reichenwagen S., Widulle H., Nürnberg W., Heldt P. Organische Carbonsäuren. In: Kramer A., Assadian O., editors. Wallhäußers Praxis der Sterilisation, Desinfektion, Antiseptik und Konservierung. 6th ed. Georg Thieme Verlag; Stuttgart, Germany: 2008. pp. 690–710.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Parliament. Council of the European Union . Regulation (EU) No 528/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 May 2012 Concerning the Making Available on the Market and Use of Biocidal Products, Last Amended by Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2021/807 of 10 March 2021. Official Journal of the European Union; Luxembourg: 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Committee for Standardization . EN 16437: Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics—Quantitative Surface Test for the Evaluation of Bactericidal Activity of Chemical Disinfectants and Antiseptics Used in Veterinary Area on Porous Surfaces without Mechanical Action—Test Method and Requirements (Phase 2, Step 2) Beuth Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deutsches Institut für Normung . DIN 68365: Sawn Timber for Carpentry—Appearance Grading—Softwood. Beuth Verlag GmbH; Berlin, Germany: 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kärber G. Beitrag zur kollektiven Behandlung pharmakologischer Reihenversuche. Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch. Exp. Pathol. Pharmakol. 1931;162:480–483. doi: 10.1007/BF01863914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF01863914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spearman C. The method of ‘right and wrong cases’ (‘constant stimuli’) without Gauss’s formulae. Br. J. Psychol. 1908;2:227–242. doi: 10.1111/j.2044-8295.1908.tb00176.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8295.1908.tb00176.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team  R: A language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. 2024.  [(accessed on 30 January 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.R-project.org/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Khleif A. Entwicklung Eines Quantitativen Keimträgertests zur Prüfung der Wirksamkeit von Desinfektionsmitteln Gegen Animale Viren im Lebensmittelbereich. Justus-Liebig-Universität Gießen; Gießen, Germany: 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin H., Soumet C., Fresnel R., Morin T., Lamaudière S., Le Sauvage A.L., Deleurme K., Maris P. Comparison of the virucidal efficiency of peracetic acid, potassium monopersulfate and sodium hypochlorite on hepatitis A and enteric cytopathogenic bovine orphan virus. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2013;115:955–968. doi: 10.1111/jam.12297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.12297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23906424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Von Rheinbaben F., Wolff M.H. Handbuch der viruswirksamen Desinfektionen. 1st ed. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A., Reichenwagen S., Heldt P., Widulle H., Nürnberg W. Oxidantien. In: Kramer A., Assadian O., editors. Wallhäußers Praxis der Sterilisation, Desinfektion, Antiseptik und Konservierung. 6th ed. Georg Thieme Verlag; Stuttgart, Germany: 2008. pp. 713–745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wekerle J. Untersuchungen zur Wirkung organischer Säuren auf Viren. Tierarztl. Umsch. 1988;43:646–654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz A., Kaleta E.F. Evaluation of virucidal activity of three commercial disinfectants and formic acid using bovine enterovirus type 1 (ECBO virus), mammalian orthoreovirus type 1 and bovine adenovirus type 1. Vet. J. 2003;166:67–78. doi: 10.1016/S1090-0233(02)00269-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1090-0233(02)00269-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12788019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhee C.H., Park S.-C., Her M., Jeong W. Surrogate Selection for Foot-and-Mouth Disease Virus in Disinfectant Efficacy Tests by Simultaneous Comparison of Bacteriophage MS2 and Bovine Enterovirus Type 1. Viruses. 2022;14:2590. doi: 10.3390/v14122590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v14122590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9782237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahnel H. Resistenzunterschiede zwischen Viren verschiedener Gruppen gegenüber einigen chemisch-physikalischen Dekontaminationsverfahren. Infection. 1979;7:240–246. doi: 10.1007/BF01648934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF01648934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">511342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michels I., Menge C., Philipp W., Chemische Desinfektionsmittel: Aldehyde  In Richtlinie über Mittel und Verfahren für Die Durchführung der Desinfektion bei Bestimmten Tierseuchen; Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems.  [(accessed on 22 September 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.openagrar.de/servlets/MCRFileNodeServlet/openagrar_derivate_00052132/FLI-5-3-3-5-Chemische-Desinfektionsmittel-Aldehyde-RL-Desinfektion-V1-0.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhee C.H., Her M., Jeong W. Virucidal efficacy of potassium peroxymonosulfate, sodium dichloroisocyanurate, glutaraldehyde, and quaternary ammonium compounds against Newcastle disease virus. J. Prev. Vet. Med. 2022;46:16–21. doi: 10.13041/jpvm.2022.46.1.16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13041/jpvm.2022.46.1.16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schliesser T. Grundlagen der Desinfektion. In: Schliesser T., Strauch D., editors. Desinfektion in Tierhaltung, Fleisch- und Milchwirtschaft. 1st ed. Enke; Stuttgart, Germany: 1981. pp. 1–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones L.A., Hoffman R.K., Phillips C.R. Sporicidal activity of peracetic acid and beta-propiolactone at subzero temperatures. Appl. Microbiol. 1967;15:357–362. doi: 10.1128/am.15.2.357-362.1967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/am.15.2.357-362.1967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC546905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4963043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lächele R. Untersuchungen über Die Bakterizide Wirkung Einiger Stalldesinfektionsmittel im Suspensionsversuch und praxisnahen Sprühdesinfektionsmodell Unter Berücksichtigung der Faktoren Temperatur und Wasserhärte. Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München; München, Germany: 1990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hölzle L.E., Philipp W., Michels I., Menge C., Chemische Desinfektionsmittel: Ameisensäure, Zitronensäure und andere organische Säuren  In Richtlinie über Mittel und Verfahren für Die Durchführung der Desinfektion bei Bestimmten Tierseuchen; Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems.  [(accessed on 21 September 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.openagrar.de/servlets/MCRFileNodeServlet/openagrar_derivate_00052134/FLI-5-3-3-7-Chemische-Desinfektionsmittel-organische-Saeuren-RL-Desinfektion-V1-0.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A. Chemische Desinfektion. In: Bodenschatz W., editor. Kompaktwissen Desinfektion. 3rd ed. Behr’s Verlag; Hamburg, Germany: 2022. pp. 155–211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheinemann H.A., Michels I., Menge C., Chemische Desinfektionsmittel: Peressigsäure  In Richtlinie über Mittel und Verfahren für die Durchführung der Desinfektion bei Bestimmten Tierseuchen; Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems.  [(accessed on 23 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.openagrar.de/servlets/MCRFileNodeServlet/openagrar_derivate_00052133/FLI-5-3-3-6-Chemische-Desinfektionsmittel-Peressigsaeure-RL-Desinfektion-V1-0.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer A., Reichenwagen S., Widulle H., Heldt P., Nürnberg W. Aldehyde. In: Kramer A., Assadian O., editors. Wallhäußers Praxis der Sterilisation, Desinfektion, Antiseptik und Konservierung. 6th ed. Georg Thieme Verlag; Stuttgart, Germany: 2008. pp. 670–686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steiger A. Desinfektion: Tierärztliche Praxis. 1st ed. VEB Gustav Fischer; Jena, Germany: 1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grosser D., Teetz W. Einheimische Nutzhölzer (Loseblattsammlung) 1st ed. Centrale Marketing-Gesellschaft der deutschen Agrarwirtschaft; Bonn, Germany: 1998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoy F.-J. Über Die Auswirkung der Hochdruckreinigung und -Desinfektion mit Unterschiedlichen Temperaturen auf den Keimgehalt von Stalloberflächen. Universität Hohenheim; Hohenheim, Germany: 1983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Ministry of Food and Agriculture of Germany  Der Wald in Deutschland: Ausgewählte Ergebnisse der Dritten Bundeswaldinventur.  [(accessed on 11 October 2023)].  Available online:  https://www.bmel.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/DE/Broschueren/bundeswaldinventur3.pdf?__blob=publicationFile&amp;v=6.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>