<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38896609</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2375-2548</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>25</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Science advances</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Adv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Structure and dynamics of enterovirus genotype networks.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>eado1693</StartPage><MedlinePgn>eado1693</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">eado1693</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1126/sciadv.ado1693</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Like all biological populations, viral populations exist as networks of genotypes connected through mutation. Mapping the topology of these networks and quantifying population dynamics across them is crucial to understanding how populations adapt to changes in their selective environment. The influence of mutational networks is especially profound in viral populations that rapidly explore their mutational neighborhoods via high mutation rates. Using a single-cell sequencing method, scRNA-seq-enabled acquisition of mRNA and consensus haplotypes linking individual genotypes and host transcriptomes (SEARCHLIGHT), we captured and assembled viral haplotypes from hundreds of individual infected cells, revealing the complexity of viral population structures. We obtained these genotypes in parallel with host cell transcriptome information, enabling us to link host cell transcriptional phenotypes to the genetic structures underlying virus adaptation. Our examination of these structures reveals the common evolutionary dynamics of enterovirus populations and illustrates how viral populations reach through mutational "tunnels" to span evolutionary landscapes and maintain connection with multiple adaptive genotypes simultaneously.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dábilla</LastName><ForeName>Nathânia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5664-5797</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Quantitative Virology and Evolution Unit, Laboratory of Viral Diseases, NIAID, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dolan</LastName><ForeName>Patrick T</ForeName><Initials>PT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4169-0058</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Quantitative Virology and Evolution Unit, Laboratory of Viral Diseases, NIAID, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Adv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101653440</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2375-2548</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="Y">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009154" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mutation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019143" MajorTopicYN="N">Evolution, Molecular</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059467" MajorTopicYN="N">Transcriptome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006239" MajorTopicYN="N">Haplotypes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059010" MajorTopicYN="N">Single-Cell Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054884" MajorTopicYN="N">Host-Pathogen Interactions</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38896609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11186490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.ado1693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hein M. Y., Weissman J. S., Functional single-cell genomics of human cytomegalovirus infection. Nat. Biotechnol. 40, 391–401 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34697476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantri M., Hinchman M. M., McKellar D. W., Wang M. F. Z., Cross S. T., Parker J. S. L., De Vlaminck I., Spatiotemporal transcriptomics reveals pathogenesis of viral myocarditis. Nat. Cardiovasc. Res. 1, 946–960 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10035375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36970396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanini F., Robinson M. L., Croote D., Sahoo M. K., Sanz A. M., Ortiz-Lasso E., Albornoz L. L., Rosso F., Montoya J. G., Goo L., Pinsky B. A., Quake S. R., Einav S., Virus-inclusive single-cell RNA sequencing reveals the molecular signature of progression to severe dengue. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 115, E12363–E12369 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6310786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30530648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell A. B., Trapnell C., Bloom J. D., Extreme heterogeneity of influenza virus infection in single cells. eLife 7, e32303 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5826275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29451492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell A. B., Elshina E., Kowalsky J. R., Te Velthuis A. J. W., Bloom J. D., Single-cell virus sequencing of influenza infections that trigger innate immunity. J. Virol. 93, e00500-19 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6600203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31068418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saikia M., Burnham P., Keshavjee S. H., Wang M. F. Z., Heyang M., Moral-Lopez P., Hinchman M. M., Danko C. G., Parker J. S. L., De Vlaminck I., Simultaneous multiplexed amplicon sequencing and transcriptome profiling in single cells. Nat. Methods 16, 59–62 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6378878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30559431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bacsik D. J., Dadonaite B., Butler A., Greaney A. J., Heaton N. S., Bloom J. D., Influenza virus transcription and progeny production are poorly correlated in single cells. eLife 12, RP86852 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10484525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37675839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanini F., Pu S.-Y., Bekerman E., Einav S., Quake S. R., Single-cell transcriptional dynamics of flavivirus infection. eLife 7, e32942 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5826272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29451494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouvier N. M., Palese P., The biology of influenza viruses. Vaccine 26 (Suppl. 4), D49–D53 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3074182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19230160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McWilliam Leitch E. C., McLauchlan J., Determining the cellular diversity of hepatitis C virus quasispecies by single-cell viral sequencing. J. Virol. 87, 12648–12655 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3838117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24049174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J., Vera J. C., Drnevich J., Lin Y. T., Ke R., Brooke C. B., Single cell heterogeneity in influenza A virus gene expression shapes the innate antiviral response to infection. PLOS Pathog. 16, e1008671 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7363107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32614923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak M., Schuster P., Error thresholds of replication in finite populations mutation frequencies and the onset of Muller’s ratchet. J. Theor. Biol. 137, 375–395 (1989).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2626057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eigen M., Viral quasispecies. Sci. Am. 269, 42–49 (1993).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8337597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Domingo, “Quasispecies” in Encyclopedia of Virology, A. Granoff, R. G. Webster, Eds. (Elsevier, ed. 2, 1999), pp. 1431–1436.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou D., Zhao Y., Kotecha A., Fry E. E., Kelly J. T., Wang X., Rao Z., Rowlands D. J., Ren J., Stuart D. I., Unexpected mode of engagement between enterovirus 71 and its receptor SCARB2. Nat. Microbiol. 4, 414–419 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30531980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lane T. R., Fu J., Sherry B., Tarbet B., Hurst B. L., Riabova O., Kazakova E., Egorova A., Clarke P., Leser J. S., Frost J., Rudy M., Tyler K. L., Klose T., Volobueva A. S., Belyaevskaya S. V., Zarubaev V. V., Kuhn R. J., Makarov V., Ekins S., Efficacy of an isoxazole-3-carboxamide analog of pleconaril in mouse models of Enterovirus-D68 and Coxsackie B5. Antiviral Res. 216, 105654 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10527014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37327878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai W., Li X., Liu Z., Zhang C., Identification of four neutralizing antigenic sites on the enterovirus D68 capsid. J. Virol. 97, e0160023 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10734511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38047678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeiffer J. K., Kirkegaard K., A single mutation in poliovirus RNA-dependent RNA polymerase confers resistance to mutagenic nucleotide analogs via increased fidelity. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 100, 7289–7294 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC165868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12754380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vignuzzi M., Stone J. K., Arnold J. J., Cameron C. E., Andino R., Quasispecies diversity determines pathogenesis through cooperative interactions in a viral population. Nature 439, 344–348 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1569948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16327776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acevedo A., Brodsky L., Andino R., Mutational and fitness landscapes of an RNA virus revealed through population sequencing. Nature 505, 686–690 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4111796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24284629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C., Forst C. V., Chou T.-W., Geber A., Wang M., Hamou W., Smith M., Sebra R., Zhang B., Zhou B., Ghedin E., Cell-to-cell variation in defective virus expression and effects on host responses during influenza virus infection. mBio 11, e02880-19 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6960286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31937643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen K.-R., Ling P., Interplays between Enterovirus A71 and the innate immune system. J. Biomed. Sci. 26, 95 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6886175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31787104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang H. Y., Kim J.-Y., Lim J.-Y., Chung S.-K., Nam J.-H., Park S. I., Coxsackievirus B3 modulates cell death by downregulating activating transcription factor 3 in HeLa cells. Virus Res. 130, 10–17 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17599613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sood V., Sharma K. B., Gupta V., Saha D., Dhapola P., Sharma M., Sen U., Kitajima S., Chowdhury S., Kalia M., Vrati S., ATF3 negatively regulates cellular antiviral signaling and autophagy in the absence of type I interferons. Sci. Rep. 7, 8789 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5562757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28821775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Badu, C. T. Pager, Activation of ATF3 via the integrated stress response pathway regulates innate immune and autophagy processes to restrict zika virus. bioRxiv 550716 [Preprint] (2023). 10.1101/2023.07.26.550716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2023.07.26.550716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hetz C., Zhang K., Kaufman R. J., Mechanisms, regulation and functions of the unfolded protein response. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 21, 421–438 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8867924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32457508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwasa Y., Michor F., Nowak M. A., Stochastic tunnels in evolutionary dynamics. Genetics 166, 1571–1579 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1470783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15082570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weissman D. B., Desai M. M., Fisher D. S., Feldman M. W., The rate at which asexual populations cross fitness valleys. Theor. Popul. Biol. 75, 286–300 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2992471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19285994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villa Martín P., Muñoz M. A., Pigolotti S., Bet-hedging strategies in expanding populations. PLOS Comput. Biol. 15, e1006529 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6490941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30998676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overton C. E., Sharkey K. J., Evolutionary bet-hedging in structured populations. J. Math. Biol. 82, 43 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8016807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33796960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morawska L. P., Hernandez-Valdes J. A., Kuipers O. P., Diversity of bet-hedging strategies in microbial communities-Recent cases and insights. WIREs Mech. Dis. 14, e1544 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9286555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35266649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotem A., Serohijos A. W. R., Chang C. B., Wolfe J. T., Fischer A. E., Mehoke T. S., Zhang H., Tao Y., Lloyd Ung W., Choi J.-M., Rodrigues J. V., Kolawole A. O., Koehler S. A., Wu S., Thielen P. M., Cui N., Demirev P. A., Giacobbi N. S., Julian T. R., Schwab K., Lin J. S., Smith T. J., Pipas J. M., Wobus C. E., Feldman A. B., Weitz D. A., Shakhnovich E. I., Evolution on the biophysical fitness landscape of an RNA virus. Mol. Biol. Evol. 35, 2390–2400 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6188569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29955873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi K., Mizuta K., Koike S., Heparan sulfate attachment receptor is a major selection factor for attenuated enterovirus 71 mutants during cell culture adaptation. PLOS Pathog. 16, e1008428 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7105141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32187235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeh M. T., Capponi S., Catching A., Bianco S., Andino R., Mapping attenuation determinants in enterovirus-D68. Viruses 12, 867 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7472100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32784424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Replogle J. M., Norman T. M., Xu A., Hussmann J. A., Chen J., Cogan J. Z., Meer E. J., Terry J. M., Riordan D. P., Srinivas N., Fiddes I. T., Arthur J. G., Alvarado L. J., Pfeiffer K. A., Mikkelsen T. S., Weissman J. S., Adamson B., Combinatorial single-cell CRISPR screens by direct guide RNA capture and targeted sequencing. Nat. Biotechnol. 38, 954–961 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7416462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32231336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quick J., Grubaugh N. D., Pullan S. T., Claro I. M., Smith A. D., Gangavarapu K., Oliveira G., Robles-Sikisaka R., Rogers T. F., Beutler N. A., Burton D. R., Lewis-Ximenez L. L., de Jesus J. G., Giovanetti M., Hill S. C., Black A., Bedford T., Carroll M. W., Nunes M., Alcantara L. C. Jr., Sabino E. C., Baylis S. A., Faria N. R., Loose M., Simpson J. T., Pybus O. G., Andersen K. G., Loman N. J., Multiplex PCR method for MinION and Illumina sequencing of Zika and other virus genomes directly from clinical samples. Nat. Protoc. 12, 1261–1276 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5902022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28538739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Li, Minimap2: Pairwise alignment for nucleotide sequences. arXiv:1708.01492 [q-bio.GN] (2017). http://arxiv.org/abs/1708.01492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6137996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29750242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. M. Ortiz, sam2consensus: Get the Consensus Sequences from SAM (and BAM) Files, Ignoring the Reference, Github (2019); https://github.com/edgardomortiz/sam2consensus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon P., Markiel A., Ozier O., Baliga N. S., Wang J. T., Ramage D., Amin N., Schwikowski B., Ideker T., Cytoscape: A software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome Res. 13, 2498–2504 (2003).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC403769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14597658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng G. X. Y., Terry J. M., Belgrader P., Ryvkin P., Bent Z. W., Wilson R., Ziraldo S. B., Wheeler T. D., McDermott G. P., Zhu J., Gregory M. T., Shuga J., Montesclaros L., Underwood J. G., Masquelier D. A., Nishimura S. Y., Schnall-Levin M., Wyatt P. W., Hindson C. M., Bharadwaj R., Wong A., Ness K. D., Beppu L. W., Deeg H. J., McFarland C., Loeb K. R., Valente W. J., Ericson N. G., Stevens E. A., Radich J. P., Mikkelsen T. S., Hindson B. J., Bielas J. H., Massively parallel digital transcriptional profiling of single cells. Nat. Commun. 8, 14049 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5241818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28091601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao Y., Hao S., Andersen-Nissen E., Mauck W. M. III, Zheng S., Butler A., Lee M. J., Wilk A. J., Darby C., Zager M., Hoffman P., Stoeckius M., Papalexi E., Mimitou E. P., Jain J., Srivastava A., Stuart T., Fleming L. M., Yeung B., Rogers A. J., McElrath J. M., Blish C. A., Gottardo R., Smibert P., Satija R., Integrated analysis of multimodal single-cell data. Cell 184, 3573–3587.e29 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8238499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34062119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang D. W., Sherman B. T., Lempicki R. A., Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nat. Protoc. 4, 44–57 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19131956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherman B. T., Hao M., Qiu J., Jiao X., Baseler M. W., Lane H. C., Imamichi T., Chang W., DAVID: A web server for functional enrichment analysis and functional annotation of gene lists (2021 update). Nucleic Acids Res. 50, W216–W221 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9252805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35325185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>