<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38872674</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Virological Profile of Asthma Exacerbation in Children: A Hospital-Based Retrospective Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e60261</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e60261</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e60261</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.60261</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Introduction Viruses are the most common triggering factors for asthma exacerbation during the autumn and winter seasons. Viruses, such as influenza A and rhinovirus, play a major role in the occurrence of severe exacerbation of asthma. This association between viral infection and asthma exacerbation in children is a result of the antiviral response of the immune system and various anti-inflammatory phenomena. In this work, we aimed to identify the virological profile of asthma exacerbation in children and analyze the correlation between viral infection type and the severity of exacerbation. Materials and methods This retrospective study was conducted from January 2016 to January 2024. The study included children hospitalized for asthma exacerbation associated with signs of viral-like respiratory infection with positive virological testing by multiplex real-time polymerase chain reaction or rapid test in the case of influenza A or respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). Data analysis was performed with Microsoft Excel and SPSS software using a previously established data collection sheet Results Thirty cases were collected for the study period. The mean age of the patients was 4 years and 8 months, with a male-to-female ratio of 3.3. Eighteen patients were known to have asthma, of which nine had uncontrolled asthma, and exacerbation was inaugural in 12 patients. Viral shedding was found in 14 patients. A viral agent was found in all patients, with coinfection of two or more viruses in three patients. The viruses found were influenza A (18 cases), coupled rhinovirus/enterovirus (eight cases), RSV (eight cases), human metapneumovirus (three patients), and parainfluenza type IV in only one inaugural patient. Asthma exacerbation was severe in 20 patients, moderate in eight patients, and two patients had severe acute asthma requiring intensive care management. We noted a higher frequency of severe exacerbation among those with an influenza A viral infection. All patients with RSV infection exhibited moderate exacerbation. No other significant correlation between asthma severity and other types of viruses was found. Conclusions Our results demonstrate the major role played by viruses in triggering asthma exacerbation, primarily influenza virus, followed by enterovirus, rhinovirus, RSV, and metapneumovirus. Larger-scale studies should be carried out to establish a more complete virological profile and further investigate the viral factor in the management of asthma in children.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ennadif et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ennadif</LastName><ForeName>Basma</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Pneumo-Allergology Unit, Pediatric Department 2, Hôpital Mère-Enfants Abderrahim Harouchi, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alaoui-Inboui</LastName><ForeName>Fatima Zahra</ForeName><Initials>FZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Pneumo-Allergology Unit, Pediatric Department 2, Hôpital Mère-Enfants Abderrahim Harouchi, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Benmoussa</LastName><ForeName>AbdelHakim Youssef</ForeName><Initials>AY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Pneumo-Allergology Unit, Pediatric Department 2, Hôpital Mère-Enfants Abderrahim Harouchi, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El Kettani</LastName><ForeName>Assiya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elmdaghri</LastName><ForeName>Naima</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Slaoui</LastName><ForeName>Bouchra</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Faculté de Médecine et de Pharmacie, Université Hassan II, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Pneumo-Allergology Unit, Pediatric Department 2, Hôpital Mère-Enfants Abderrahim Harouchi, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Ibn Rochd, Casablanca, MAR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">asthma exacerbation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coinfections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory syncytial virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rhinovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38872674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11170309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.60261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Viral identification, Chlamydia pneumoniae and Mycoplasma pneumoniae during asthma exacerbation: comparative epidemiology between infants and children (Article in French) Brouard J, Freymuth F, Toutain F, et al. Rev Fr Allergol Immunol Clin. 2001;41:389–395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7144065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32287957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of viruses and atypical bacteria in exacerbations of asthma in hospitalized children: a prospective study in the Nord-Pas de Calais region (France) Thumerelle C, Deschildre A, Bouquillon C, et al. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2003;35:75–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7168026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12526066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhinovirus and asthma: challenges and opportunities. Ortega H, Nickle D, Carter L. Rev Med Virol. 2021;31:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8365703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33217098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Detection of pathogenic bacteria during rhinovirus infection is associated with increased respiratory symptoms and asthma exacerbations. Kloepfer KM, Lee WM, Pappas TE, et al. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2014;133:1301-7, 1307.e1-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4047978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24698319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regional, age and respiratory-secretion-specific prevalence of respiratory viruses associated with asthma exacerbation: a literature review. Zheng XY, Xu YJ, Guan WJ, Lin LF. Arch Virol. 2018;163:845–853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7087223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29327237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Severe asthma exacerbations: what are the seasonal actors? Viral infections (Article in French) Mordacq C, Lejeune S, Deschildre A. Rev Fr Allergol (2009) 2016;56:205–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32288890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of viral respiratory tract infections in children with asthma. Khetsuriani N, Kazerouni NN, Erdman DD, Lu X, Redd SC, Anderson LJ, Teague WG. J Allergy Clin Immunol . 2007;119:314–321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17140648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of viruses and atypical bacteria in asthma exacerbations among children in Oporto (Portugal) João Silva M, Ferraz C, Pissarra S, Cardoso MJ, Simões J, Bonito Vítor A. Allergol Immunopathol (Madr) 2007;35:4–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17338895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viruses and atypical bacteria associated with asthma exacerbations in hospitalized children. Maffey AF, Barrero PR, Venialgo C, et al. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2010;45:619–625.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20503289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The association between seasonal asthma exacerbations and viral respiratory infections in a pediatric population receiving inhaled corticosteroid therapy with or without long-acting beta-adrenoceptor agonist: a randomized study. Prazma CM, Gern JE, Weinstein SF, Prillaman BA, Stempel DA. Respir Med. 2015;109:1280–1286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7125883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26289742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multi-season analyses of causative pathogens in children hospitalized with asthma exacerbation. Abe N, Yasudo H, Fukano R, et al. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. 2019;30:724–731.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31251831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asthmatic exacerbations: specific features in children (Article in French) Carsin A, Pham-Thi N. Rev Mal Respir. 2011;28:1322–1328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7135330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22152939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of respiratory viral infection in children hospitalized for acute lower respiratory tract diseases, and association of rhinovirus and influenza virus with asthma exacerbations. Kwon JM, Shim JW, Kim DS, Jung HL, Park MS, Shim JY. Korean J Pediatr. 2014;57:29–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3935110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24578714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Double-stranded RNA exacerbates pulmonary allergic reaction through TLR3: implication of airway epithelium and dendritic cells. Torres D, Dieudonné A, Ryffel B, et al. J Immunol. 2010;185:451–459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20505141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interactions between innate antiviral and atopic immunoinflammatory pathways precipitate and sustain asthma exacerbations in children. Subrata LS, Bizzintino J, Mamessier E, et al. J Immunol. 2009;183:2793–2800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19620293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asthmatic bronchial epithelial cells have a deficient innate immune response to infection with rhinovirus. Wark PA, Johnston SL, Bucchieri F, et al. J Exp Med. 2005;201:937–947.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2213100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15781584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global, regional, and national disease burden estimates of acute lower respiratory infections due to respiratory syncytial virus in young children in 2015: a systematic review and modelling study. Shi T, McAllister DA, O'Brien KL, et al. Lancet. 2017;390:946–958.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5592248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28689664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modeling of the human rhinovirus C capsid suggests possible causes for antiviral drug resistance. Basta HA, Ashraf S, Sgro JY, Bochkov YA, Gern JE, Palmenberg AC. Virology. 2014;448:82–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3878079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24314639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The effect of inhaled IFN-β on worsening of asthma symptoms caused by viral infections. A randomized trial. Djukanović R, Harrison T, Johnston SL, et al. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014;190:145–154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4226052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24937476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dynamics of IFN‐β responses during respiratory viral infection: Insights for therapeutic strategies. Watson A, Spalluto CM, McCrae C, et al. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2020;201:83–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31461630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>