<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38973067</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1600-0560</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of cutaneous pathology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Cutan Pathol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Immunophenotyping and viral studies in pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta lesions.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/cup.14679</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The underlying pathogenesis of pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta (PLEVA) remains unclear, although immunologic injury and viral etiology have been suggested.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate and expand the immunophenotype of PLEVA and to search for possible viral pathogens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded specimens of 20 patients with PLEVA and 9 patients with common inflammatory dermatoses (ID) were studied for immunophenotyping and for human herpesvirus (HHV) 1 and 2, cytomegalovirus (CMV), HHV-8, parvovirus B19, and Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) immunohistochemistry. The presence of HHV-6, HHV-7, and enteroviruses was assayed molecularly.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The numbers of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and T-cell intracellular antigen-1 (TIA-1)<sup>+</sup> cells were statistically significantly higher in PLEVA compared to the ID group. Immunohistochemistry for human HHV-1 and HHV-2, CMV and HHV-8, parvovirus B19, and in situ hybridization for EBV were all negative. There was molecular evidence for HHV-7 in only one PLEVA case (5%). Molecular studies for HHV-6 and enterovirus involvement were negative in all the PLEVA specimens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The predominant T-cell infiltrate in PLEVA is dominated by CD8<sup>+</sup> cells, and by increased numbers of TIA1<sup>+</sup> cells, which may indicate a cytotoxic T-cell damage to the epidermis. Viral presence was not detected.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons A/S. Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mishlab</LastName><ForeName>Salih</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9422-3584</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Avitan-Hersh</LastName><ForeName>Emily</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zohar</LastName><ForeName>Yaniv</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szwarcwort-Cohen</LastName><ForeName>Moran</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bergman</LastName><ForeName>Reuven</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Rambam Health Care Campus and The Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Cutan Pathol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0425124</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0303-6987</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acuta</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunophenotyping</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lichenoides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pityriasis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">varioliformis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viruses</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38973067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cup.14679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Bowers S, Warshaw EM. Pityriasis lichenoides and its subtypes. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2006;55(4):557‐572. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2005.07.058</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes NF, Rozdeba PJ, Schwartz RA, Kihiczak G, Lambert WC. Pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta: a disease spectrum. Int J Dermatol. 2010;49(3):257‐261. doi:10.1111/j.1365‐4632.2008.03915</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ersoy‐Evans S, Greco MF, Mancini AJ, Subaşı N, Paller AS. Pityriasis lichenoides in childhood: a retrospective review of 124 patients. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2007;56(2):205‐210. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2006.08.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahie S, Hiscutt E, Natarajan S, Taylor A. Pityriasis lichenoides: the differences between children and adults. Br J Dermatol. 2007;157(5):941‐945. doi:10.1111/j.1365‐2133.2007.08163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood GS, Strickler JG, Abel EA, Deneau DG, Warnke RA. Immunohistology of pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta and pityriasis lichenoides chronica. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1987;16(3):559‐570. doi:10.1016/s0190‐9622(87)70074‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss LM, Wood GS, Ellisen LW, Reynolds TC, Sklar J. Clonal T‐cell populations in pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta (Mucha‐Habermann disease). Am J Pathol. 1987;126(3):417‐421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhlbauer JE, Bhan AK, Harrist TJ, et al. Immunopathology of pityriasis lichenoides acuta. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1984;10(5):783‐795. doi:10.1016/s0190‐9622(84)70094‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JE, Yun WJ, Mun SK, et al. Pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta and pityriasis lichenoides chronica: comparison of lesional T‐cell subsets and investigation of viral associations. J Cutan Pathol. 2011;38(8):649‐656. doi:10.1111/j.1600‐0560.2011.01717</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ackerman AB. Histologic Diagnosis of Inflammatory Skin Diseases. 2nd ed. Wiliams &amp; Wilkins; 1997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mobini N, Toussaint S, Kamino H. Noninfectious erythematous, papular, and squamous diseases. In: Elder DE, ed. Lever's Histopathology of the Skin. 10th ed. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2009:169‐204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavakoli NP, Nattanmai S, Hull R, et al. Detection and typing of human herpesvirus 6 by molecular methods in specimens from patients diagnosed with encephalitis or meningitis. J Clin Microbiol. 2007;45(12):3972‐3978. doi:10.1128/jcm.01692‐07</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto K, Yoshikawa T, Okamoto S, Yamaki K, Shimokata K, Nishiyama Y. HHV‐6 and 7 DNA loads in lung tissues collected from patients with interstitial pneumonia. J Med Virol. 2004;75(1):70‐75. doi:10.1002/jmv.20239</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verstrepen WA, Kuhn S, Kockx MM, Van De Vyvere ME, Mertens AH. Rapid detection of enterovirus RNA in cerebrospinal fluid specimens with a novel single‐tube real‐time reverse transcription‐PCR assay. J Clin Microbiol. 2001;39(11):4093‐4096. doi:10.1128/jcm.39.11.4093‐4096.2001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jang K, Choi JC, Choi JH. Expression of cutaneous lymphocyte‐associated antigen and TIA‐1 by lymphocytes in pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta and lymphomatoid papulosis: immunohistochemical study. J Cutan Pathol. 2001;28(9):453‐459. doi:10.1034/j.1600‐0560.2001.028009453</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvell JD, Nowfar‐Rad M, Sundram U. An immunohistochemical study of CD4, CD8, TIA‐1 and CD56 subsets in inflammatory skin disease. J Cutan Pathol. 2003;30(2):108‐113. doi:10.1034/j.1600‐0560.2002.00038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenzel J, Gütgemann I, Distelmaier M, et al. The role of cytotoxic skin‐homing CD8+ lymphocytes in cutaneous cytotoxic T‐cell lymphoma and pityriasis lichenoides. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2005;53(3):422‐427. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2005.05.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velasco BR, Izquierdo JM. T‐cell intracellular antigen 1‐like protein in physiology and pathology. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23(14):7836. doi:10.3390/ijms23147836</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roediger B, Schlapbach C. T cells in the skin: lymphoma and inflammatory skin disease. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2022;149(4):1172‐1184. doi:10.1016/j.jaci.2022.02.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon GJ, Magro CM. Foxp3 expression in cutaneous T‐cell lymphocytic infiltrates. J Cutan Pathol. 2008;35(11):1032‐1039. doi:10.1111/j.1600‐0560.2007.00969</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burkett PR, Pawlak M, Peters A, Kuchroo VK. Chapter 6—T cells and their subsets in autoimmunity. In: Noel R, Mackay IR, eds. The Autoimmune Diseases. 5th ed. Academic Press; 2014:69‐86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenger S, Modlin RL. T cell mediated immunity to Mycobacterium tuberculosis. Curr Opin Microbiol. 1999;2(1):89‐93. doi:10.1016/s1369‐5274(99)80015‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez‐Escala ME, Sidiropoulos M, Deonizio J, Gerami P, Kadin ME, Guitart J. γδ T‐cell‐rich variants of pityriasis lichenoides and lymphomatoid papulosis: benign cutaneous disorders to be distinguished from aggressive cutaneous γδ T‐cell lymphomas. Br J Dermatol. 2014;172(2):372‐379. doi:10.1111/bjd.13364</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempf W, Kazakov DV, Palmedo G, Fraitag S, Schaerer L, Kutzner H. Pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta with numerous CD30+ cells: a variant mimicking lymphomatoid papulosis and other cutaneous lymphomas. A clinicopathologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular biological study of 13 cases. Am J Surg Pathol. 2012;36(7):1021‐1029. doi:10.1097/PAS.0b013e31824f4f66</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karouni M, Rahal JA, Kurban M, Kibbi AG, Abbas O. Possible role of plasmacytoid dendritic cells in pityriasis lichenoides. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2018;43(4):404‐409. doi:10.1111/ced.13351</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa‐Silva M, Calistru A, Sobrinho‐Simões J, Lisboa C, Azevedo F. Pitiryasis lichenoides et varioliformis aacuta associated with human herpesvirus 7. Actas Dermosifiliogr. 2018;109(7):e6‐e10. doi:10.1016/j.ad.2017.03.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomasini D, Tomasini CF, Cerri A, et al. Pityriasis lichenoides: a cytotoxic T‐cell‐mediated skin disorder. Evidence of human parvovirus B19 DNA in nine cases. J Cutan Pathol. 2004;31(8):531‐538. doi:10.1111/j.0303‐6987.2004.00186</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>