<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38986004</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Emerging and Re-Emerging Enterovirus Infections: The Known Unknowns.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004472</ELocationID><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cottrell</LastName><ForeName>Simon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Communicable Disease Surveillance Centre and Vaccine Preventable Disease Programme, Public Health Wales, Cardiff, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moore</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8934-0930</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wales Specialist Virology Centre, Public Health Wales Microbiology Cardiff, University Hospital of Wales, Cardiff, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38986004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-990000000-00941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zell R, Delwart E, Gorbalenya AE, et al.; Ictv Report Consortium. ICTV virus taxonomy profile: picornaviridae. J Gen Virol. 2017;98:2421–2422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165:793–797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bubba L, Broberg EK, Jasir A, et al. Circulation of non-polio enteroviruses in 24 EU and EEA countries between 2015 and 2017: a retrospective surveillance study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:350–361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumdar M, Sharif S, Klapsa D, et al. Environmental surveillance reveals complex enterovirus circulation patterns in human populations. Open Forum Infectious Diseases. 2018;5:ofy250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Broberg E, Benschop K, et al. Recommendations for enterovirus diagnostics and characterisation within and beyond Europe. J Clin Virol. 2018;101:11–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulholm T, Yeang M, Nguyen I, et al. Molecular typing of enteroviruses: comparing 5′ UTR, VP1 and whole genome sequencing methods. Pathology (Phila). 2022;54:779–783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian L, Wang Y, Yao X, et al. Coxsackievirus A6: a new emerging pathogen causing hand, foot and mouth disease outbreaks worldwide. Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther. 2015;13:1061–1071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimmis BD, Downing C, Tyring S. Hand-foot-and-mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6 on the rise. Cutis. 2018;102:353–356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Liu F, Liao Q, et al. Epidemiology of hand, foot and mouth disease in China, 2008 to 2015 prior to the introduction of EV-A71 vaccine. Euro Surveill. 2017;22:16–00824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Zhou Y, Cheng Y, et al. Effectiveness of EV-A71 vaccination in prevention of paediatric hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with EV-A71 virus infection requiring hospitalisation in Henan, China, 2017–18: a test-negative case-control study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2019;3:697–704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Sanz R, Casas-Alba D, Launes C, et al. Molecular epidemiology of an enterovirus A71 outbreak associated with severe neurological disease, Spain, 2016. Euro Surveill. 2019;24:1800089.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew O, Pallansch M. Breaking the last chains of poliovirus transmission: progress and challenges in global polio eradication. Annu Rev Virol. 2018;5:427–451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam MM, Ikram A, Mahmood N, et al. Conserved antigenic structure of contemporary wild poliovirus Type 1 strains endemic in Pakistan. J Infect Dis. 2022;226:843–851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klapsa D, Wilton T, Zealand A, et al. Sustained detection of type 2 poliovirus in London sewage between February and July, 2022, by enhanced environmental surveillance. Lancet. 2022;400:1531–1538.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Abzug MJ, Dominguez SR. 2014 outbreak of enterovirus D68 in North America. J Med Virol. 2016;88:739–745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hixon AM, Yu G, Leser JS, et al. A mouse model of paralytic myelitis caused by enterovirus D68. PLoS Pathog. 2017;13:e1006199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cottrell S, Moore C, Perry M, et al. Prospective enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) surveillance from September 2015 to November 2018 indicates a current wave of activity in Wales. Euro Surveill. 2018;23:1800578.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassidy H, Lizarazo-Forero E, Schuele L, et al. Off-season circulation and characterization of enterovirus D68 with respiratory and neurological presentation using whole-genome sequencing. Front Microbiol. 2023;13:1088770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simoes MP, Hodcroft EB, Simmonds P, et al. Epidemiological and clinical insights into the enterovirus D68 upsurge in Europe 2021/22 and the emergence of novel B3-derived lineages, ENPEN multicentre study. J Infect Dis. 2024:jiae154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grapin M, Mirand A, Pinquier D, et al. Severe and fatal neonatal infections linked to a new variant of echovirus 11, France, July 2022 to April 2023. Euro Surveill. 2023;28:2300253–2300253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng KF, Gibb J, Struik S, et al.; Neonatal Enteroviral Myocarditis Consortium. Remember the heart: neonatal myocarditis. Arch Dis Child. 2023;108:417–419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singanayagam A, Moore C, Froude S, et al. Increased reports of severe myocarditis associated with enterovirus infection in neonates, United Kingdom, 27 June 2022 to 26 April 2023. Euro Surveill. 2023;28:2300313–2300313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morfopoulou S, Buddle S, Torres Montaguth OE, et al.; DIAMONDS Consortium. Genomic investigations of unexplained acute hepatitis in children. Nature. 2023;617:564–573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chetty K, Cheng I, Kaliakatsos M, et al. Case report: novel treatment regimen for enterovirus encephalitis in SCID. Front Immunol. 2022;13:930031–930031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LC, Tsai HP, Chen SH, et al. Therapeutics for fulminant hepatitis caused by enteroviruses in neonates. Front Pharmacol. 2022;13:1014823.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis D, Taylor K. Acute flaccid myelitis. Point-of-Care Quick Reference. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer TK, Simmonds P, Harvala H. The importance of enterovirus surveillance in a post-polio world. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22:e35–e40.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>