<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">38955545</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3468</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>598</Volume><Issue>15</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>FEBS letters</Title><ISOAbbreviation>FEBS Lett</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Poliovirus capsid protein VP3 can penetrate vascular endothelial cells.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1909</StartPage><EndPage>1918</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1909-1918</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/1873-3468.14974</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The poliovirus (PV) enters the central nervous system (CNS) via the bloodstream, suggesting the existence of a mechanism to cross the blood-brain barrier. Here, we report that PV capsid proteins (VP1 and VP3) can penetrate cells, with VP3 being more invasive. Two independent parts of VP3 are responsible for this function. Both peptides can penetrate human umbilical cord vascular endothelial cells, and one peptide of VP3 could also penetrate peripheral blood mononuclear cells. In an in vitro blood-brain barrier model using rat-derived astrocytes, pericytes, and endothelial cells, both peptides were observed to traverse from the blood side to the brain side at 6 h after administration. These results provide insights into the molecular mechanisms underlying PV invasion into the CNS.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). FEBS Letters published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Federation of European Biochemical Societies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mizutani</LastName><ForeName>Taketoshi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1329-6512</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computational Biology and Medical Sciences, Graduate School of Frontier Sciences, The University of Tokyo, Chiba, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ishizaka</LastName><ForeName>Aya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Advanced Clinical Research Center, The Institute of Medical Science, The University of Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>JP223fa627001</GrantID><Agency>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>21K11592</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>22K20926</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>24K11630</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Taiju Life Social Welfare Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016422">Letter</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>FEBS Lett</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0155157</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0014-5793</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D036022">Capsid Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036022" MajorTopicYN="Y">Capsid Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051381" MajorTopicYN="N">Rats</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001812" MajorTopicYN="Y">Blood-Brain Barrier</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D042783" MajorTopicYN="N">Endothelial Cells</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061307" MajorTopicYN="N">Human Umbilical Vein Endothelial Cells</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007963" MajorTopicYN="N">Leukocytes, Mononuclear</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000166" MajorTopicYN="N">cytology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001253" MajorTopicYN="N">Astrocytes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood–brain barrier (BBB)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cell‐penetrating peptide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">central nervous system (CNS)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">drug delivery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">poliovirus</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38955545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/1873-3468.14974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Bordin ES (1955) Ambiguity as a therapeutic variable. J Consult Psychol 19, 9–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB (1956) Pathogenesis of poliomyelitis; reappraisal in the light of new data. Science 123, 1151–1157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohka S, Nihei C, Yamazaki M and Nomoto A (2012) Poliovirus trafficking toward central nervous system via human poliovirus receptor‐dependent and ‐independent pathway. Front Microbiol 3, 147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koyuncu OO, Hogue IB and Enquist LW (2013) Virus infections in the nervous system. Cell Host Microbe 13, 379–393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohka S, Yang WX, Terada E, Iwasaki K and Nomoto A (1998) Retrograde transport of intact poliovirus through the axon via the fast transport system. Virology 250, 67–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohka S, Sakai M, Bohnert S, Igarashi H, Deinhardt K, Schiavo G and Nomoto A (2009) Receptor‐dependent and ‐independent axonal retrograde transport of poliovirus in motor neurons. J Virol 83, 4995–5004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang WX, Terasaki T, Shiroki K, Ohka S, Aoki J, Tanabe S, Nomura T, Terada E, Sugiyama Y and Nomoto A (1997) Efficient delivery of circulating poliovirus to the central nervous system independently of poliovirus receptor. Virology 229, 421–428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballabh P, Braun A and Nedergaard M (2004) The blood‐brain barrier: an overview: structure, regulation, and clinical implications. Neurobiol Dis 16, 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brightman MW (1977) Morphology of blood‐brain interfaces. Exp Eye Res 25, 1–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reese TS and Karnovsky MJ (1967) Fine structural localization of a blood‐brain barrier to exogenous peroxidase. J Cell Biol 34, 207–217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadry H, Noorani B and Cucullo L (2020) A blood‐brain barrier overview on structure, function, impairment, and biomarkers of integrity. Fluids Barriers CNS 17, 69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koepsell H (2020) Glucose transporters in brain in health and disease. Pflugers Arch 472, 1299–1343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fishman JB, Rubin JB, Handrahan JV, Connor JR and Fine RE (1987) Receptor‐mediated transcytosis of transferrin across the blood‐brain barrier. J Neurosci Res 18, 299–304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pardridge WM, Eisenberg J and Yang J (1987) Human blood‐brain barrier transferrin receptor. Metabolism 36, 892–895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wessling‐Resnick M (2018) Crossing the iron gate: why and how transferrin receptors mediate viral entry. Annu Rev Nutr 38, 431–458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Obaidi MMJ, Bahadoran A, Wang SM, Manikam R, Raju CS and Sekaran SD (2018) Disruption of the blood brain barrier is vital property of neurotropic viral infection of the central nervous system. Acta Virol 62, 16–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal T, Sharvani V, Nair D and Medigeshi GR (2013) Japanese encephalitis virus disrupts cell‐cell junctions and affects the epithelial permeability barrier functions. PLoS ONE 8, e69465.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bramley JC, Drummond CG, Lennemann NJ, Good CA, Kim KS and Coyne CB (2017) A three‐dimensional cell culture system to model RNA virus infections at the blood‐brain barrier. mSphere 2, e00206‐17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Nan X, Zhou D, Wang X, Zhu S, Li Q, Jia F, Zhu B, Si Y, Cao S et al. (2024) Japanese encephalitis virus NS1 and NS1' protein disrupts the blood‐brain barrier through macrophage migration inhibitory factor‐mediated autophagy. J Virol 98, e0011624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mladinich MC, Schwedes J and Mackow ER (2017) Zika virus persistently infects and is Basolaterally released from primary human brain microvascular endothelial cells. MBio 8, e00952‐17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papa MP, Meuren LM, Coelho SVA, Lucas CGO, Mustafa YM, Lemos Matassoli F, Silveira PP, Frost PS, Pezzuto P, Ribeiro MR et al. (2017) Zika virus infects, activates, and crosses brain microvascular endothelial cells, without barrier disruption. Front Microbiol 8, 2557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mizutani T, Ishizaka A and Nihei C (2016) Transferrin receptor 1 facilitates poliovirus permeation of mouse brain capillary endothelial cells. J Biol Chem 291, 2829–2836.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roe K, Kumar M, Lum S, Orillo B, Nerurkar VR and Verma S (2012) West Nile virus‐induced disruption of the blood‐brain barrier in mice is characterized by the degradation of the junctional complex proteins and increase in multiple matrix metalloproteinases. J Gen Virol 93, 1193–1203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiong V, Shu MH, Wong WF, AbuBakar S and Chang LY (2018) Nipah virus infection of immature dendritic cells increases its Transendothelial migration across human brain microvascular endothelial cells. Front Microbiol 9, 2747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galea I (2021) The blood‐brain barrier in systemic infection and inflammation. Cell Mol Immunol 18, 2489–2501.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varga Z, Flammer AJ, Steiger P, Haberecker M, Andermatt R, Zinkernagel AS, Mehra MR, Schuepbach RA, Ruschitzka F and Moch H (2020) Endothelial cell infection and endotheliitis in COVID‐19. Lancet 395, 1417–1418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene C, Connolly R, Brennan D, Laffan A, O'Keeffe E, Zaporojan L, O'Callaghan J, Thomson B, Connolly E, Argue R et al. (2024) Blood‐brain barrier disruption and sustained systemic inflammation in individuals with long COVID‐associated cognitive impairment. Nat Neurosci 27, 421–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuthill TJ, Groppelli E, Hogle JM and Rowlands DJ (2010) Picornaviruses. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol 343, 43–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann DA and Frankel AD (1991) Endocytosis and targeting of exogenous HIV‐1 tat protein. EMBO J 10, 1733–1739.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hogle JM, Chow M and Filman DJ (1985) Three‐dimensional structure of poliovirus at 2.9 a resolution. Science 229, 1358–1365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volle R, Archimbaud C, Couraud PO, Romero IA, Weksler B, Mirand A, Pereira B, Henquell C, Peigue‐Lafeuille H and Bailly JL (2015) Differential permissivity of human cerebrovascular endothelial cells to enterovirus infection and specificities of serotype EV‐A71 in crossing an in vitro model of the human blood‐brain barrier. J Gen Virol 96, 1682–1695.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirchhausen T, Macia E and Pelish HE (2008) Use of dynasore, the small molecule inhibitor of dynamin, in the regulation of endocytosis. Methods Enzymol 438, 77–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meier O, Boucke K, Hammer SV, Keller S, Stidwill RP, Hemmi S and Greber UF (2002) Adenovirus triggers macropinocytosis and endosomal leakage together with its clathrin‐mediated uptake. J Cell Biol 158, 1119–1131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swanson JA and Watts C (1995) Macropinocytosis. Trends Cell Biol 5, 424–428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson SM and De Camilli P (2012) Dynamin, a membrane‐remodelling GTPase. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 13, 75–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zidaric T, Gradisnik L and Velnar T (2022) Astrocytes and human artificial blood‐brain barrier models. Bosn J Basic Med Sci 22, 651–672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eberle KE, Nguyen VT and Freistadt MS (1995) Low levels of poliovirus replication in primary human monocytes: possible interactions with lymphocytes. Arch Virol 140, 2135–2150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haddad A, Nokhbeh MR, Alexander DA, Dawe SJ, Grise C, Gulzar N and Dimock K (2004) Binding to decay‐accelerating factor is not required for infection of human leukocyte cell lines by enterovirus 70. J Virol 78, 2674–2681.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabor‐Godwin JM, Ruller CM, Bagalso N, An N, Pagarigan RR, Harkins S, Gilbert PE, Kiosses WB, Gude NA, Cornell CT et al. (2010) A novel population of myeloid cells responding to coxsackievirus infection assists in the dissemination of virus within the neonatal CNS. J Neurosci 30, 8676–8691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Vainionpaa R, Vanharanta R and Hyypia T (1996) Susceptibility of human bone marrow cells and hematopoietic cell lines to coxsackievirus B3 infection. J Virol 70, 9018–9023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid R, Cannon MJ and Chow M (2005) Dendritic cells and macrophages are productively infected by poliovirus. J Virol 79, 401–409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coyne CB, Kim KS and Bergelson JM (2007) Poliovirus entry into human brain microvascular cells requires receptor‐induced activation of SHP‐2. EMBO J 26, 4016–4028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markowicz‐Piasecka M, Darlak P, Markiewicz A, Sikora J, Kumar Adla S, Bagina S and Huttunen KM (2022) Current approaches to facilitate improved drug delivery to the central nervous system. Eur J Pharm Biopharm 181, 249–262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pardridge WM (2007) Drug targeting to the brain. Pharm Res 24, 1733–1744.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren M, Wang Y, Luo Y, Yao X, Yang Z, Zhang P, Zhao W and Jiang D (2021) Functionalized nanoparticles in prevention and targeted therapy of viral diseases with Neurotropism properties, special insight on COVID‐19. Front Microbiol 12, 767104.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>