<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39037255</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>43</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Progresses Toward Polio Eradication in Asian Countries: Its History and Japan's Contributions.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e347</StartPage><EndPage>e353</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e347-e353</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004478</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Japan experienced a large outbreak of wild poliovirus in the 1960s. The government made an exceptional decision to import oral polio vaccines (OPVs) from the Soviet Union and Canada while bypassing the usual approval process for medical products. Mass vaccination and subsequent, routine immunization successfully contained the wild poliovirus; the last case in Japan was reported in 1980. Domestic OPV had been used to sustain Japan's polio-free state. In 2012, the world's first inactivated polio vaccine developed from the Sabin vaccine replaced OPVs. Domestic vaccines combined with Sabin-derived inactivated polio vaccine are currently used in Japan. When the World Health Assembly announced the Global Polio Eradication Initiative in 1988, the Japanese government made a commitment to support endemic countries. The Japan International Cooperation Agency supported the establishment of microbiological laboratories, surveillance, distribution of polio vaccines and capacity building. Vaccine-derived poliovirus emerged as a new, international risk in the early 2000s. Vaccine-derived poliovirus was also detected in several Asian countries and required an outbreak response with additional vaccinations and strengthened surveillance. Genetically stable, novel, oral polio vaccine type 2 became available for use in outbreak responses and was used in Indonesia. Japan maintains its commitment to work toward the eradication of the poliovirus.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toizumi</LastName><ForeName>Michiko</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8401-9344</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Institute of Tropical Medicine, Nagasaki University, Nagasaki, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takamatsu</LastName><ForeName>Masamitsu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-2565-7234</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>World Health Organization Papua New Guinea, Port Moresby, Papua New Guinea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health and Global Policy Institute, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toda</LastName><ForeName>Kohei</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunization Center, Akita Red Cross Hospital, Akita, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Horikoshi</LastName><ForeName>Yuho</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5875-1024</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Tokyo Metropolitan Children's Medical Center, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>001</GrantID><Acronym>WHO_</Acronym><Agency>World Health Organization</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016456">Historical Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011055">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011054">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011051" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poliomyelitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060740" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Eradication</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007564" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Japan</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049673" MajorTopicYN="N">History, 20th Century</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011055" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Oral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017955" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049674" MajorTopicYN="N">History, 21st Century</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001208" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Asia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011054" MajorTopicYN="N">Poliovirus Vaccine, Inactivated</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. Y.H. is a principal investigator for COVID-19 vaccine trial of Shionogi Pharma. The other authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39037255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-202410000-00017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare. White paper of Ministry of Health and Welfare 1961 (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei_hakusho/hakusho/kousei/1961/ . Accessed February 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infection Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Poliomyelitis (Japanese). Available at: http://idsc.nih.go.jp/disease/polio/yobou.html . Accessed February 26, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare. White paper of Ministry of Health and Welfare 1959 (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei_hakusho/hakusho/kousei/1959/ . Accessed February 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidor E, Plotkin SA. Poliovirus vaccine-inactivated. In: Plotkin SA, Orenstein WA, Offit PA, eds. Vaccines. 6 ed. Elsevier Saunders; 2013:573–597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutter RW, Kew OM, Cochi SL, Aylward RB. Poliovirus vaccine-live. In: Plotkin SA, Orenstein WA, Offit PA, eds. Vaccines. 6 ed. Elsevier Saunders; 2013:598–645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare. White paper of Ministry of Health and Welfare 1960 (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/toukei_hakusho/hakusho/kousei/1960/ . Accessed February 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirayama M. Progress on urgent introduction of live polio vaccine in Japan and poliomyelitis thereafter. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc. 2007;19:186–196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamanouchi K. Eradication of viral infections by vaccines (4): polio. The corporation for production and research of laboratory primates. Available at: https://primate.or.jp/serialization/31%ef%bc%8e%e3%83%af%e3%82%af%e3%83%81%e3%83%b3%e3%81%ab%e3%82%88%e3%82%8b%e3%82%a6%e3%82%a4%e3%83%ab%e3%82%b9%e6%84%9f%e6%9f%93%e7%97%87%e3%81%ae%e6%a0%b9%e7%b5%b6%ef%bc%884%ef%bc%89%ef%bc%9a/ . Accessed February 29, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishizawa I. Social significance observed in the campaign to acquire a live polio vaccine. Report Issued by Research Center for Ars Vivendi of Ritsumeikan University. 2009;10:83–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishio O. Prevention countermeasure and the national administrative training about eradication on poliomyelitis. J Natl Inst Public Health. 2000;49:33–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infectious Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Polio in Japan: 1952-1995 (Japanese). Infectious Agents Surveillance Report. 18 (1). Available at: http://idsc.nih.go.jp/iasr/18/203/tpc203-j.html . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satoh H, Tanaka-Taya K, Shimizu H, et al. Polio vaccination coverage and seroprevalence of poliovirus antibodies after the introduction of inactivated poliovirus vaccines for routine immunization in Japan. Vaccine. 2019;37:1964–1971.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hara M, Hagiwara A, Yoneyama T, et al. Antigenic and biochemical characterization of poliovirus type 1 isolates of non-vaccine origin. Microbiol Immunol. 1983;27:1057–1065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health Labour and Welfare. Poliomyelitis and polio vaccine (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/bunya/kenkou/polio/index.html . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu H. Development and introduction of inactivated poliovirus vaccines derived from Sabin strains in Japan. Vaccine. 2016;34:1975–1985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infectious Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Blood antibody persistence after polio vaccine (OPV, cIPV, sIPV) immunisation: from the National Epidemiological Surveillance of Vaccine-Preventable Diseases (NESVPD) from 1974 to 2022 (Japanese). Infectious Agents Surveillance Report. 44:146–148. Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/ja/polio-m/polio-iasrd/12282-523d01.html . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Polio (Pol3) immunization coverage among 1-year-olds (%). Available at: https://www.who.int/data/gho/data/indicators/indicator-details/GHO/polio-(pol3)-immunization-coverage-among-1-year-olds-(-) . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health Labour and Welfare of Japan. Pentacomponent antigens vaccine (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/10900000/001139473.pdf . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health Labour and Welfare. National Epidemiological Surveillance of Infectious Diseases (NESID) (Japanese). Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/stf/seisakunitsuite/bunya/0000115283.html . Accessed February 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Research Group for Clinical Epidemiological Studies Contributing to the Identification of the Causes of Acute Flaccid Paralysis, Acute Encephalitis and Encephalopathy, Including Enterovirus and Other Infectious Diseases. Guide for Surveillance, Diagnosis, Examination, and Treatment of Diseases With Acute Flaccid Paralysis (Japanese). 2nd ed. Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/images/idsc/disease/AFP/AFP-guide.pdf . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infectious Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Polio source surveillance. Infectious Agents Surveillance Report; 30:176–178. Available at: http://idsc.nih.go.jp/iasr/30/353/dj3533.html . Accessed February 27, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida H, Horie H, Matsuura K, et al. Characterisation of vaccine-derived polioviruses isolated from sewage and river water in Japan. Lancet. 2000;356:1461–1463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitakawa K, Kitamura K, Yoshida H. Monitoring enteroviruses and SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater using the polio environmental surveillance system in Japan. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2023;89:e0185322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyamura K, Yamashita K, Yamadera S, et al. Poliovirus surveillance: isolation of polioviruses in Japan, 1980-1991. a report of the national epidemiological surveillance of infectious agents in Japan. Jpn J Med Sci Biol. 1992;45:203–214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Polio: Annual report of the National Epidemiological Surveillance of Vaccine-Preventable Diseases (NESVPD) 2014 (Japanese). Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/images/epi/yosoku/AnnReport/2014-02.pdf . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Polio: Annual report of the National Epidemiological Surveillance of Vaccine-Preventable Diseases (NESVPD) 2016. (Japanese) Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/images/epi/yosoku/AnnReport/2016-02.pdf . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infectious Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Polio as of 2023. Infectious Agents Surveillance Report (Japanese). 44:113–114. Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/ja/polio-m/polio-iasrtpc/12211-522t.html . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Infectious Disease Surveillance Center National Institute of Infectious Diseases. Vaccine strain of poliovirus detected in stool samples from children who received oral polio vaccine overseas - Kumamoto City. Infectious Agents Surveillance Report (Japanese). 36: 86–87. Available at: https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/ja/polio-m/polio-iasrs/5559-pr4223.html . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Iwai M, Wakita T, et al. Development of a poliovirus neutralization test with poliovirus pseudovirus for measurement of neutralizing antibody titer in human serum. Clin Vaccine Immunol. 2011;18:1889–1894.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita M, Iwai-Itamochi M. Evaluation of antigenic differences between wild and Sabin vaccine strains of poliovirus using the pseudovirus neutralization test. Sci Rep. 2019;9:11970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Forty-first World Health Assembly Resolutions and Decisions. WHA41.28 Global eradication of poliomyelitis by the year 2000. In: Geneva. World Health Organization; 1988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization. Poliomyelitis Eradication Field Guide. 1st ed.: 1987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu WZ, Wen N, Zhang Y, et al. Poliomyelitis eradication in China: 1953–2012. J Infect Dis. 2014;210:S268–S274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tangermann RH, Bilous J, Maher C, et al. Poliomyelitis eradication in the western Pacific region. J Infect Dis. 1997;175(Supplement_1):S97–104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita I, Nakane M, Fenner F. Is polio eradication realistic? Science. 2006;312:852–854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arita I, Nakane M. Road map for polio eradication--establishing the link with millennium development goal no. 4 for child survival. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2008;61:169–174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Historical Contributions 1988-2022. Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/financing/donors/historical-contributions/ . Accessed June 15, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Health Policy Division Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Japan. Global Initiative for Polio Eradication and Contribution of Government of Japan (unpublished internal document provided and agreed to be published by Japan International Cooperation Agency); 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toda K, Ha BK, Van TTB, et al. The progress of polio eradication in the Mekong Delta area in the south Vietnam. Clin Virol. 1995;23:133–140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication -- Socialist Republic of Vietnam, 1991-1993. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 1994;43:387–391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>John TJ, Vashishtha VM. Eradicating poliomyelitis: India’s journey from hyperendemic to polio-free status. Indian J Med Res. 2013;137:881–894.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication --- India, 2003. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2004;53:238–241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication --- India, January 2010--September 2011. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2011;60:1482–1486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BBC. How India managed to defeat polio. Available at: https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-25709362#:~:text=The%20introduction%20of%20bivalent%20oral,was%20causing%20repeated%20disease%20outbreaks . Accessed March 29, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. History of Polio Vaccine. Available at: https://www.who.int/news-room/spotlight/history-of-vaccination/history-of-polio-vaccination . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Variant Poliovirus (cVDPV). Available at: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/polio-prevention/the-virus/variant-poliovirus-cvdpv/ . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohanty A, Rohilla R, Zaman K, et al. Vaccine derived poliovirus (VDPV). Infez Med. 2023;31:174–185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Reporting and classification of vaccine-derived polioviruses: GPEI guidelines. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/VDPV_ReportingClassification.pdf . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kew O, Morris-Glasgow V, Landaverde M, et al. Outbreak of poliomyelitis in hispaniola associated with circulating type 1 vaccine-derived poliovirus. Science. 2002;296:356–359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai YA, Chen X, Kunasekaran M, et al. Global epidemiology of vaccine-derived poliovirus 2016–2021: a descriptive analysis and retrospective case-control study. EClinicalMedicine. 2022;50:101508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Polio Today. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/polio-today/ . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Standard Operating Procedures: Responding to a Poliovirus Event or Outbreak, Version 4. Available at: https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/363627/9789240049154-eng.pdf . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurji FD, Bandyopadhyay AS, Zipursky S, et al. Novel oral polio vaccine type 2 use for polio outbreak response: a global effort for a global health emergency. Pathogens. 2024;13:273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stehling-Ariza T, Wilkinson AL, Diop OM, et al. Surveillance to track progress toward polio eradication — worldwide, 2021–2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2023;72:613–620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SE, Greene SA, Burns CC, et al. Progress toward poliomyelitis eradication — worldwide, January 2021–March 2023. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2023;72:517–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Outbreak Countries. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/where-we-work/polio-outbreak-countries/ . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitamura K, Shimizu H. Outbreaks of circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus in the world health organization western Pacific Region, 2000–2021. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2022;75:431–444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the South-East Asia. Poliomyelitis (polio). Available at: https://www.who.int/southeastasia/health-topics/poliomyelitis-(polio) . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Poliomyelitis (polio). Available at: https://www.who.int/westernpacific/health-topics/poliomyelitis . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin. 2018, Issue no. 25 (Week 50). Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/277362 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2019. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/279730 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2020. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/330696 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2021. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/338522 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2022. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/350978 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2023. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/365558 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific. Polio Bulletin 2024. Available at: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/375482 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. Polio eradication and endgame midterm review. 2015. Available at: http://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/GPEI-MTR_July2015.pdf . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 - Indonesia (Disease Outbreak News 19 December 2022). Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2022-DON430 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 - Indonesia (Disease Outbreak News 17 April 2023). Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2023-DON458 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Report of the Indonesia Polio Outbreak Response Assessment Report of the Indonesia Polio Outbreak Response Assessment-July 2023. Available at: https://www.who.int/indonesia/news/publications/other-documents/report-of-the-indonesia-polio-outbreak-response-assessment---july-2023 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 - Indonesia (Disease Outbreak News 11 January 2024). Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2024-DON500 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snider CJ, Boualam L, Tallis G, et al. Concurrent outbreaks of circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus types 1 and 2 affecting the Republic of the Philippines and Malaysia, 2019–2021. Vaccine. 2023;41:A58–A69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alipon SB, Takashima Y, Avagyan T, et al. Emergence of vaccine-derived poliovirus type 2 after using monovalent type 2 oral poliovirus vaccine in an outbreak response, Philippines. Western Pac Surveill Response J. 2022;13:1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H, Ma X, Tang H, et al. Circulation of type 2 vaccine-derived poliovirus in China in 2018-2019. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2021;8:ofab535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Wen N, Zhang Y, et al. Detection and initial response to a type 2 vaccine-derived Poliovirus-Sichuan Province, China, 2019. China CDC Wkly. 2020;2:172–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauri M, Wilkinson AL, Ropa B, et al. Circulating vaccine-derived poliovirus type 1 and outbreak response — Papua New Guinea, 2018. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2019;68;119–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pomat W, Lopez Cavestany R, Jeyaseelan V, et al. Poliovirus serological assay after the cVDPV1 outbreak in Papua New Guinea: a cross-sectional study from 2020 to 2021. Lancet Reg Health West Pac. 2024;44. doi:10.1016/j.lanwpc.2023.100986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2023.100986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Statement of the Twenty-Third IHR Emergency Committee Regarding the International Spread of Poliovirus. Available at: https://www.who.int/news/item/07-01-2020-statement-o-the-twenty-third-ihr-emergency-committee-regarding-the-international-spread-of-poliovirus . Accessed April 24, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Polio Eradication Strategy 2022-2026: Delivering on a promise. Available at: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240031937 . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Polio Eradication Initiative. nOPV2. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/nopv2/ . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay AS, Cooper LV, Zipursky S. One billion doses and WHO prequalification of nOPV2: implications for the global polio situation and beyond. PLOS Glob Public Health. 2024;4. doi:10.1371/journal.pgph.0002920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0002920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Global Polio Surveillance Action Plan, 2022-2024. Available at: https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/GPSAP-2022-2024-EN.pdf . Accessed April 2, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diop OM, Kew OM, De Gourville EM, et al. The global polio laboratory network as a platform for the viral vaccine-preventable and emerging diseases laboratory networks. J Infect Dis. 2017;216:S299–S307.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>