<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39056240</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Molecular epidemiology and characterization of enteroviruses detected in cerebrospinal fluid and respiratory samples in Slovenia, 2014-2023.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29827</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29827</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29827</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enterovirus (EV) infections have various symptoms and severe complications, including death. To determine EV prevalence and EV types in Slovenia, data on over 25 000 EV RNA tests for diagnostics and surveillance from 2014 to 2023 were analyzed. Altogether, 3733 cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and 21 297 respiratory (sentinel and clinical) samples were tested for EV RNA. EV typing was performed on all residual EV-positive CSF samples and on subset of respiratory specimens. Altogether, 1238 samples tested positive for EV RNA: 238 (6.4%) CSF and 1000 (4.7%) respiratory samples. EV-positive patients were predominantly male (p &lt; 0.001). Many EV-positive CSF samples were from infants under 3 months (33.1%), whereas most EV-positive respiratory samples were from children 1 to 2 years old (49.2%). Echovirus 30 (E-30) was most frequent in CSF (33.0%), followed by CV-B5 (13.8%) and E-6 (13.8%). CV-A6 was most frequent in respiratory samples (16.0%), followed by EV-D68 (7.6%) and CV-A5 (7.4%). EV types in CSF and respiratory samples show diverse dynamics, with some outbreaks indicated. A significant difference was found in the EV detection rate between CSF and respiratory samples by age. Various EV types were characterized, showing that some EV types are more neurotropic or cause more severe infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berginc</LastName><ForeName>Nataša</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-9949-8230</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Microbiology, National Laboratory for Health, Environment, and Food, Maribor, Slovenia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lunar</LastName><ForeName>Maja M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1262-338X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Šramel</LastName><ForeName>Nina</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3451-6497</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poljak</LastName><ForeName>Mario</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3216-7564</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Institute of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ljubljana</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P3-0083</GrantID><Agency>Slovenian Research and Innovation Agency</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017524" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Slovenia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004769" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000134" MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017720" MajorTopicYN="Y">Molecular Epidemiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000134" MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="N">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000134" MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002555" MajorTopicYN="N">Cerebrospinal Fluid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="N">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CSF</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cerebrospinal fluid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enteroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory samples</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">typing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39056240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Henquell C, Archimbaud C, et al. Prospective identification of enteroviruses involved in meningitis in 2006 through direct genotyping in cerebrospinal fluid. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46:87‐96. doi:10.1128/JCM.01020-07</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalwai A, Ahmad S, Al‐Nakib W. Echoviruses are a major cause of aseptic meningitis in infants and young children in Kuwait. Virol J. 2010;7:236. doi:10.1186/1743-422X-7-236</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M, Trallero G, Echevarría JE, et al. Molecular characterization of enteroviruses associated with neurological infections in Spain, 2008. J Med Virol. 2013;85:1975‐1977. doi:10.1002/jmv.23693</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milia MG, Cerutti F, Gregori G, et al. Recent outbreak of aseptic meningitis in Italy due to echovirus 30 and phylogenetic relationship with other European circulating strains. J Clin Virol. 2013;58:579‐583. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2013.08.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadakis G, Chibo D, Druce J, Catton M, Birch C. Detection and genotyping of enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid in patients in Victoria, Australia, 2007‒2013. J Med Virol. 2014;86:1609‐1613. doi:10.1002/jmv.23885</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volle R, Bailly JL, Mirand A, et al. Variations in cerebrospinal fluid viral loads among enterovirus genotypes in patients hospitalized with laboratory‐confirmed meningitis due to enterovirus. J Infect Dis. 2014;210:576‐584. doi:10.1093/infdis/jiu178</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vollbach S, Müller A, Drexler JF, et al. Prevalence, type and concentration of human enterovirus and parechovirus in cerebrospinal fluid samples of pediatric patients over a 10‐year period: a retrospective study. Virol J. 2015;12:199. doi:10.1186/s12985-015-0427-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krasota A, Loginovskih N, Ivanova O, Lipskaya G. Direct identification of enteroviruses in cerebrospinal fluid of patients with suspected meningitis by nested PCR amplification. Viruses. 2016;8:10. doi:10.3390/v8010010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Othman I, Volle R, Elargoubi A, et al. Enterovirus meningitis in Tunisia (Monastir, Mahdia, 2011‒2013): identification of virus variants cocirculating in France. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2016;84:116‐122. doi:10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.10.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordey S, Schibler M, L'Huillier AG, et al. Comparative analysis of viral shedding in pediatric and adult subjects with central nervous system‐associated enterovirus infections from 2013 to 2015 in Switzerland. J Clin Virol. 2017;89:22‐29. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2017.01.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerra JA, Waters A, Kelly A, et al. Seroepidemiological and phylogenetic characterization of neurotropic enteroviruses in Ireland, 2005‒2014. J Med Virol. 2017;89:1550‐1558. doi:10.1002/jmv.24765</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumaidi K, Al‐Jawabreh A, Samarah F, Zraiqi A, Yaseen D. Genetic diversity of the enteroviruses detected from cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) samples of patients with suspected aseptic meningitis in northern West Bank, Palestine in 2017. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0202243. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0202243</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smuts H, Cronje S, Thomas J, Brink D, Korsman S, Hardie D. Molecular characterization of an outbreak of enterovirus‐associated meningitis in Mossel Bay, South Africa, December 2015‒January 2016. BMC Infect Dis. 2018;18:709. doi:10.1186/s12879-018-3641-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gámbaro F, Pérez AB, Agüera E, et al. Genomic surveillance of enterovirus associated with aseptic meningitis cases in southern Spain, 2015‒2018. Sci Rep. 2021;11:21523. doi:10.1038/s41598-021-01053-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nkosi N, Preiser W, van Zyl G, et al. Molecular characterisation and epidemiology of enterovirus‐associated aseptic meningitis in the Western and Eastern Cape Provinces, South Africa 2018‒2019. J Clin Virol. 2021;139:104845. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2021.104845</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posnakoglou L, Tatsi EB, Chatzichristou P, et al. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus in children with central nervous system infections. Viruses. 2021;13:100. doi:10.3390/v13010100</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bucci S, Coltella L, Martini L, et al. Clinical and neurodevelopmental characteristics of enterovirus and parechovirus meningitis in neonates. Front Pediatr. 2022;10:881516. doi:10.3389/fped.2022.881516</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rmadi Y, Elargoubi A, González‐Sanz R, Mastouri M, Cabrerizo M, Aouni M. Molecular characterization of enterovirus detected in cerebrospinal fluid and wastewater samples in Monastir, Tunisia, 2014‒2017. Virol J. 2022;19:45. doi:10.1186/s12985-022-01770-w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fall A, Forman M, Morris CP, et al. Enterovirus characterized from cerebrospinal fluid in a cohort from the Eastern United States. J Clin Virol. 2023;161:105401. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2023.105401</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kriger O, Weil M, Fratty IS, et al. Separating the wheat from the chaff—optimizing the diagnosis of enterovirus‐associated meningitis. J Clin Virol. 2023;165:105522. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2023.105522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvala H, Broberg E, Benschop K, et al. Recommendations for enterovirus diagnostics and characterisation within and beyond Europe. J Clin Virol. 2018;101:11‐17. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2018.01.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolay B, Cauchemez S. Enterovirus outbreak dynamics. Science. 2018;361:755‐756. doi:10.1126/science.aau6932</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Abzug MJ, Dominguez SR. 2014 outbreak of enterovirus D68 in North America. J Med Virol. 2016;88:739‐745. doi:10.1002/jmv.24410</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltola V, Österback R, Waris M, et al. Enterovirus D68 outbreak in children, Finland, August‒September 2022. Emerging Infect Dis. 2023;29:1258‐1261. doi:10.3201/eid2906.221795</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González‐Sanz R, Casas‐Alba D, Launes C, et al. Molecular epidemiology of an enterovirus A71 outbreak associated with severe neurological disease, Spain, 2016. Euro Surveill. 2019;24:1800089. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2019.24.7.1800089</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanh TH, Sabanathan S, Thanh TT, et al. Enterovirus 71‐associated hand, foot, and mouth disease, Southern Vietnam, 2011. Emerging Infect Dis. 2012;18:2002‐2005. doi:10.3201/eid1812.120929</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons‐Salort M, Grassly NC. Serotype‐specific immunity explains the incidence of diseases caused by human enteroviruses. Science. 2018;361:800‐803. doi:10.1126/science.aat6777</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auburn H, Zuckerman M, Broughton S, Greenough A, Smith M. Detection of nine respiratory RNA viruses using three multiplex RT‐PCR assays incorporating a novel RNA internal control transcript. J Virol Methods. 2011;176:9‐13. doi:10.1016/j.jviromet.2011.05.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bezerra PGM, Britto MCA, Correia JB, et al. Viral and atypical bacterial detection in acute respiratory infection in children under five years. PLoS One. 2011;6:e18928. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0018928</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Cui D, Zheng S, et al. Simultaneous detection of influenza A, influenza B, and respiratory syncytial viruses and subtyping of influenza A H3N2 virus and H1N1 (2009) virus by multiplex real‐time PCR. J Clin Microbiol. 2011;49:1653‐1656. doi:10.1128/JCM.02184-10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vos N, Vankeerberghen A, Vaeyens F, Vaerenbergh K, Boel A, Beenhouwer H. Simultaneous detection of human bocavirus and adenovirus by multiplex real‐time PCR in a Belgian paediatric population. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2009;28:1305‐1310. doi:10.1007/s10096-009-0780-y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierssen U, Rehren F, Henke‐Gendo C, Harste G, Heim A. Rapid routine detection of enterovirus RNA in cerebrospinal fluid by a one‐step real‐time RT‐PCR assay. J Clin Virol. 2008;42:58‐64. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2007.11.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klemenc J, Asad Ali S, Johnson M, et al. Real‐time reverse transcriptase PCR assay for improved detection of human metapneumovirus. J Clin Virol. 2012;54:371‐375. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2012.05.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nix WA, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA. Sensitive, seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all enterovirus serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44:2698‐2704. doi:10.1128/JCM.00542-06</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroneman A, Vennema H, Deforche K, et al. An automated genotyping tool for enteroviruses and noroviruses. J Clin Virol. 2011;51:121‐125. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2011.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Girello A, Premoli M, Baldanti F. A new real‐time reverse transcription‐PCR assay for detection of human enterovirus 68 in respiratory samples. J Clin Microbiol. 2015;53:1725‐1726. doi:10.1128/JCM.03691-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poelman R, Schölvinck EH, Borger R, Niesters HGM, van Leer‐Buter C. The emergence of enterovirus D68 in a Dutch university medical center and the necessity for routinely screening for respiratory viruses. J Clin Virol. 2015;62:1‐5. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2014.11.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bubba L, Broberg EK, Jasir A, et al. Circulation of non‐polio enteroviruses in 24 EU and EEA countries between 2015 and 2017: a retrospective surveillance study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:350‐361. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30566-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh DY, Buda S, Biere B, et al. Trends in respiratory virus circulation following COVID‐19‐targeted nonpharmaceutical interventions in Germany, January‒September 2020: analysis of national surveillance data. Lancet Region Health ‐ Europe. 2021;6:100112. doi:10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin DA, Spieker AJ, Perez A, et al. Circulation of rhinoviruses and/or enteroviruses in pediatric patients with acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2254909. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.54909</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow EJ, Uyeki TM, Chu HY. The effects of the COVID‐19 pandemic on community respiratory virus activity. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2022;21:195‐210. doi:10.1038/s41579-022-00807-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nougairede A, Bessaud M, Thiberville SD, et al. Widespread circulation of a new echovirus 30 variant causing aseptic meningitis and non‐specific viral illness, south‐east France, 2013. J Clin Virol. 2014;61:118‐124. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2014.05.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benschop KSM, Broberg EK, Hodcroft E, et al. Molecular epidemiology and evolutionary trajectory of emerging echovirus 30, Europe. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27:1616‐1626. doi:10.3201/eid2706.203096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McWilliam Leitch EC, Cabrerizo M, Cardosa J, et al. Evolutionary dynamics and temporal/geographical correlates of recombination in the human enterovirus echovirus types 9, 11, and 30. J Virol. 2010;84:9292‐9300. doi:10.1128/JVI.00783-10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forero EL, Knoester M, Gard L, et al. Changes in enterovirus epidemiology after easing of lockdown measures. J Clin Virol. 2023;169:105617. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2023.105617</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes A, Nguyen D, Andersson M, et al. A European multicentre evaluation of detection and typing methods for human enteroviruses and parechoviruses using RNA transcripts. J Med Virol. 2020;92:1065‐1074. doi:10.1002/jmv.25659</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandoni M, Ciardo L, Tamburini C, et al. Enteroviral infections in the first three months of life. Pathogens. 2022;11:60. doi:10.3390/pathogens11010060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamau E, Nguyen D, Celma C, et al. Seroprevalence and virologic surveillance of enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A6, United Kingdom, 2006‒2017. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27:2261‐2268. doi:10.3201/eid2709.204915</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadeharju K, Knip M, Virtanen SM, et al. Maternal antibodies in breast milk protect the child from enterovirus infections. Pediatrics. 2007;119:941‐946. doi:10.1542/peds.2006-0780</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowal C, Athanassiou A, Chen H, Diamond B. Maternal antibodies and developing blood‐brain barrier. Immunol Res. 2015;63:18‐25. doi:10.1007/s12026-015-8714-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rueca M, Lanini S, Giombini E, et al. Detection of recombinant breakpoint in the genome of human enterovirus E11 strain associated with a fatal nosocomial outbreak. Virol J. 2022;19:97. doi:10.1186/s12985-022-01821-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muslin C, Mac Kain A, Bessaud M, Blondel B, Delpeyroux F. Recombination in enteroviruses, a multi‐step modular evolutionary process. Viruses. 2019;11:859. doi:10.3390/v11090859</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirand A, Schuffenecker I, Henquell C, et al. Phylogenetic evidence for a recent spread of two populations of human enterovirus 71 in European countries. J Gen Virol. 2010;91:2263‐2277. doi:10.1099/vir.0.021741-0</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>