<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39078431</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-8798</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>169</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Archives of virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arch Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>In vitro synergistic antiviral activity of repurposed drugs against enterovirus 71.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>169</StartPage><MedlinePgn>169</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00705-024-06097-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviruses cause viral diseases that are harmful to children. Hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) with neurological complications is mainly caused by enterovirus 71 (EV71). Despite its clinical importance, there is no effective antiviral drug against EV71. However, several repurposed drugs have been shown to have antiviral activity against related viruses. Treatments with single drugs and two-drug combinations were performed in vitro to assess anti-EV71 activity. Three repurposed drug candidates with broad-spectrum antiviral activity were found to demonstrate potent anti-EV71 activity: prochlorperazine, niclosamide, and itraconazole. To improve antiviral activity, combinations of two drugs were tested. Niclosamide and itraconazole showed synergistic antiviral activity in Vero cells, whereas combinations of niclosamide-prochlorperazine and itraconazole-prochlorperazine showed only additive effects. Furthermore, the combination of itraconazole and prochlorperazine showed an additive effect in neuroblastoma cells. Itraconazole and prochlorperazine exert their antiviral activities by inhibiting Akt phosphorylation. Repurposing of drugs can provide a treatment solution for HFMD, and our data suggest that combining these drugs can enhance that efficacy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Austria, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jitobaom</LastName><ForeName>Kunlakanya</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, 10700, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boonarkart</LastName><ForeName>Chompunuch</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, 10700, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thongon</LastName><ForeName>Songkran</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, 10700, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sirihongthong</LastName><ForeName>Thanyaporn</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, 10700, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sornwong</LastName><ForeName>Arpakorn</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Central instrument and Research Laboratory, Virology and Immunology Laboratory, Chulabhorn Royal Academy, Bangkok, 10210, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Auewarakul</LastName><ForeName>Prasert</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, 10700, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suptawiwat</LastName><ForeName>Ornpreya</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0832-0079</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Central instrument and Research Laboratory, Virology and Immunology Laboratory, Chulabhorn Royal Academy, Bangkok, 10210, Thailand. ornpreya.sup@cra.ac.th.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Princess Srisavangavadhana College of Medicine, Chulabhorn Royal Academy, Bangkok, 10210, Thailand. ornpreya.sup@cra.ac.th.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>SI-09/2562</GrantID><Agency>National Research Council of Thailand</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</GrantID><Agency>Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</GrantID><Agency>Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Austria</Country><MedlineTA>Arch Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7506870</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0304-8608</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000998">Antiviral Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>304NUG5GF4</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D017964">Itraconazole</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>8KK8CQ2K8G</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009534">Niclosamide</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000998" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antiviral Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004357" MajorTopicYN="Y">Drug Synergism</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002522" MajorTopicYN="N">Chlorocebus aethiops</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058492" MajorTopicYN="Y">Drug Repositioning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014709" MajorTopicYN="N">Vero Cells</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017964" MajorTopicYN="Y">Itraconazole</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009534" MajorTopicYN="N">Niclosamide</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="N">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39078431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-024-06097-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00705-024-06097-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>AASLD (2021) HCV Guidance: Recommendations for testing, managing, and treating Hepatitis C Virus infection. Infectious Diseases Society of America</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Backer V, Sjöbring U, Sonne J, Weiss A, Hostrup M, Johansen HK, Becker V, Sonne DP, Balchen T, Jellingsø M, Sommer MOA (2021) A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 1 trial of inhaled and intranasal niclosamide: A broad spectrum antiviral candidate for treatment of COVID-19. Lancet Reg Health Eur 4:100084</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33842908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8021896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrows NJ, Campos RK, Powell ST, Prasanth KR, Schott-Lerner G, Soto-Acosta R, Galarza-Muñoz G, McGrath EL, Urrabaz-Garza R, Gao J, Wu P, Menon R, Saade G, Fernandez-Salas I, Rossi SL, Vasilakis N, Routh A, Bradrick SS, Garcia-Blanco MA (2016) A screen of FDA-approved drugs for inhibitors of Zika virus infection. Cell Host Microbe 20:259–270</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27476412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4993926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnet R, Nebout M, Brousse C, Reinier F, Imbert V, Rohrlich PS, Peyron J-F (2020) New Drug Repositioning Candidates for T-ALL Identified Via Human/Murine Gene Signature Comparison. 10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M, Tarragó D, Muñoz-Almagro C, del Amo E, Domínguez-Gil M, Eiros JM, López-Miragaya I, Pérez C, Reina J, Otero A, González I, Echevarría JE, Trallero G (2014) Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus 71, coxsackievirus A16 and A6 associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Spain. Clin Microbiol Infect 20:O150–O156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24033818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamoun-Emanuelli AM, Pecheur E-I, Simeon RL, Huang D, Cremer PS, Chen Z (2013) Phenothiazines inhibit hepatitis C virus entry, likely by increasing the fluidity of cholesterol-rich membranes. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 57:2571–2581</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23529728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3716126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M, Ju Y, Chen M, Xie Z, Zhou K, Tan Y, Mo J (2017) Epidemiological and genetic characteristics of EV71 in hand, foot, and mouth disease in Guangxi, southern China, from 2010 to 2015. PLoS ONE 12:e0188640</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29216216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5720782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Gu F, Guan J-L (2018) Metformin Might Inhibit Virus through Increasing Insulin Sensitivity. Chin Med J 131:376–377</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29363663</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5798069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng B, Morales LD, Zhang Y, Mito S, Tsin A (2017) Niclosamide induces protein ubiquitination and inhibits multiple pro-survival signaling pathways in the human glioblastoma U-87 MG cell line. PLoS ONE 12:e0184324–e0184324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28877265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5587337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho J, Yi H, Jang EY, Lee MS, Lee JY, Kang C, Lee CH, Kim K (2017) Mycophenolic mofetil, an alternative antiviral and immunomodulator for the highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 virus infection. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 494:298–304</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29017920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coll B, van Wijk JP, Parra S, Castro Cabezas M, Hoepelman IM, Alonso-Villaverde C, de Koning EJ, Camps J, Ferre N, Rabelink TJ, Tous M, Joven J (2006) Effects of rosiglitazone and metformin on postprandial paraoxonase-1 and monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 in human immunodeficiency virus-infected patients with lipodystrophy. Eur J Pharmacol 544:104–110</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16843455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang J, Sun L, Peng G, Xu J, Zhou R, Cao S, Chen H, Song Y (2013) Identification of three antiviral inhibitors against Japanese encephalitis virus from library of pharmacologically active compounds 1280. PLoS ONE 8:e78425</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24348901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3857149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser JE, Watanabe S, Wang C, Chan WK, Maher B, Lopez-Denman A, Hick C, Wagstaff KM, Mackenzie JM, Sexton PM, Vasudevan SG, Jans DA (2014) A nuclear transport inhibitor that modulates the unfolded protein response and provides in vivo protection against lethal dengue virus infection. J Infect Dis 210:1780–1791</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24903662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman BW, Irizarry E, Solorzano C, Latev A, Rosa K, Zias E, Vinson DR, Bijur PE, Gallagher EJ (2017) Randomized study of IV prochlorperazine plus diphenhydramine vs IV hydromorphone for migraine. Neurology 89:2075–2082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29046364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5711508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Q, Yuan S, Zhang C, Wang Y, Wang Y, He G, Zhang S, Altmeyer R, Zou G (2015) Discovery of Itraconazole with boad-sectrum i vtro antienterovirus activity that targets nonstrutural protein 3A. 59:2654–2665</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Serradilla M, Risco C, Pacheco B (2019) Drug repurposing for new, efficient, broad spectrum antivirals. Virus Res 264:22–31</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30794895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastaminza P, Whitten-Bauer C, Chisari FV (2010) Unbiased probing of the entire hepatitis C virus life cycle identifies clinical compounds that target multiple aspects of the infection. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107:291–296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19995961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hart BJ, Dyall J, Postnikova E, Zhou H, Kindrachuk J, Johnson RF, Olinger GG, Frieman MB, Holbrook MR, Jahrling PB, Hensley L (2014) Interferon-β and mycophenolic acid are potent inhibitors of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus in cell-based assays. J Gen Virol 95:571–577</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24323636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3929173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hewitt RG, Yiannoutsos CT, Higgs ES, Carey JT, Geiseler PJ, Soave R, Rosenberg R, Vazquez GJ, Wheat LJ, Fass RJ, Antoninievic Z, Walawander AL, Flanigan TP, Bender JF (2000) Paromomycin: no more effective than placebo for treatment of cryptosporidiosis in patients with advanced human immunodeficiency virus infection. AIDS Clinical Trial Group. Clin Infect Dis 31:1084–1092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11049793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hickson SE, Margineantu D, Hockenbery DM, Simon JA, Geballe AP (2018) Inhibition of vaccinia virus replication by nitazoxanide. Virology 518:398–405</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29625403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho M-R, Tsai T-T, Chen C-L, Jhan M-K, Tsai C-C, Lee Y-C, Chen C-H, Lin C-F (2017) Blockade of dengue virus infection and viral cytotoxicity in neuronal cells in vitro and in vivo by targeting endocytic pathways. Sci Rep 7:6910</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28761128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5537343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong J, Liu F, Qi H, Tu W, Ward MP, Ren M, Zhao Z, Su Q, Huang J, Chen X, Le J, Ren X, Hu Y, Cowling B, Li Z, Chang Z, Zhang Z (2022) Changing epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2013−2019: a population-based study. The Lancet Regional Health – Western Pacific 20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L, Yang M, Yuan Y, Li X, Kuang E (2017) Niclosamide inhibits lytic replication of Epstein-Barr virus by disrupting mTOR activation. Antiviral Res 138:68–78</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27939840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon S, Ko M, Lee J, Choi I, Byun SY, Park S, Shum D, Kim S (2020) Identification of Antiviral Drug Candidates against SARS-CoV-2 from FDA-Approved Drugs. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 64</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung E, Nam S, Oh H, Jun S, Ro HJ, Kim B, Kim M, Go YY (2019) Neutralization of Acidic Intracellular Vesicles by Niclosamide Inhibits Multiple Steps of the Dengue Virus Life Cycle In Vitro. Sci Rep 9:8682</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31213630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6582152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jurgeit A, McDowell R, Moese S, Meldrum E, Schwendener R, Greber UF (2012) Niclosamide is a proton carrier and targets acidic endosomes with broad antiviral effects. PLoS Pathog 8:e1002976</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23133371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3486884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kao J-C, HuangFu W-C, Tsai T-T, Ho M-R, Jhan M-K, Shen T-J, Tseng P-C, Wang Y-T, Lin C-F (2018) The antiparasitic drug niclosamide inhibits dengue virus infection by interfering with endosomal acidification independent of mTOR. PLOS Negl Trop Dis 12:e0006715–e0006715</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30125275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6117097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo R-L, Shih S-R (2013) Strategies to develop antivirals against enterovirus 71. Virol J 10:28–28</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23339605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3614426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee KY (2016) Enterovirus 71 infection and neurological complications. Korean J Pediatr 59:395–401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27826325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5099286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei D, Griffiths E, Martin J (2020) WHO working group meeting to develop WHO Recommendations to assure the quality, safety and efficacy of enterovirus 71 vaccines. Vaccine 38:4917–4923</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32418797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7327506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Peng T (2021) Strategy, progress, and challenges of drug repurposing for efficient antiviral discovery. Front Pharmacol 12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Li PK, Roberts MJ, Arend RC, Samant RS, Buchsbaum DJ (2014) Multi-targeted therapy of cancer by niclosamide: A new application for an old drug. Cancer Lett 349:8–14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24732808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4166407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Brecher M, Deng YQ, Zhang J, Sakamuru S, Liu B, Huang R, Koetzner CA, Allen CA, Jones SA, Chen H, Zhang NN, Tian M, Gao F, Lin Q, Banavali N, Zhou J, Boles N, Xia M, Kramer LD, Qin CF, Li H (2017) Existing drugs as broad-spectrum and potent inhibitors for Zika virus by targeting NS2B-NS3 interaction. Cell Res 27:1046–1064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28685770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5539352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J-Y, Kung Y-A, Shih S-R (2019) Antivirals and vaccines for Enterovirus A71. J Biomed Sci 26:65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31481071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6720414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y-W, Lin H-Y, Tsou Y-L, Chitra E, Hsiao K-N, Shao H-Y, Liu C-C, Sia C, Chong P, Chow Y-H (2012) Human SCARB2-mediated entry and endocytosis of EV71. PLoS ONE 7:e30507–e30507</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22272359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3260287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzon M, Ortega-Prieto AM, Imrie D, Luft C, Hess L, Czieso S, Grove J, Skelton JK, Farleigh L, Bugert JJ, Wright E, Temperton N, Angell R, Oxenford S, Jacobs M, Ketteler R, Dorner M, Marsh M (2019) Identification of broad-spectrum antiviral compounds by targeting viral entry. Viruses 11:176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30791609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6410080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niyomdecha N, Suptawiwat O, Boonarkart C, Jitobaom K, Auewarakul P (2020) Inhibition of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 by niclosamide through mTORC1 inhibition. Heliyon 6:e04050–e04050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32529067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7276449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noisumdaeng P, Sangsiriwut K, Prasertsopon J, Klinmalai C, Payungporn S, Mungaomklang A, Chokephaibulkit K, Buathong R, Thitithanyanont A, Puthavathana P (2018) Complete genome analysis demonstrates multiple introductions of enterovirus 71 and coxsackievirus A16 recombinant strains into Thailand during the past decade. Emerg Microbes Infect 7:214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30552334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6294798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otreba M, Kosmider L (2021) In vitro anticancer activity of fluphenazine, perphenazine and prochlorperazine. A review. J Appl Toxicol 41:82–94</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32852120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pantziarka Pan SV, Bouche Gauthier M, Lydie, Sukhatme Vikas P (2015) Repurposing Drugs in Oncology (ReDO)—itraconazole as an anti-cancer agent. ecancer 9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paplomata E, O'Regan R (2014) The PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway in breast cancer: targets, trials and biomarkers. Ther Adv Med Oncol 6:154–166</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25057302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4107712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perelygina L, Hautala T, Seppänen M, Adebayo A, Sullivan KE, Icenogle J (2017) Inhibition of rubella virus replication by the broad-spectrum drug nitazoxanide in cell culture and in a patient with a primary immune deficiency. Antiviral Res 147:58–66</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28974385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7127570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phougat N, Khatri S, Singh A, Dangi M, Kumar M, Dabur R, Chhillar AK (2014) Combination therapy: the propitious rationale for drug development. Comb Chem High Throughput Screen 17:53–67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24138510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puenpa J, Wanlapakorn N, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y (2019) The History of Enterovirus A71 Outbreaks and Molecular Epidemiology in the Asia-Pacific Region. J Biomed Sci 26:75</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31627753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6798416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero-Gómez M, Diago M, Andrade RJ, Calleja JL, Salmerón J, Fernández-Rodríguez CM, Solà R, García-Samaniego J, Herrerías JM, De la Mata M, Moreno-Otero R, Nuñez O, Olveira A, Durán S, Planas R (2009) Treatment of insulin resistance with metformin in naïve genotype 1 chronic hepatitis C patients receiving peginterferon alfa-2a plus ribavirin. Hepatology 50:1702–1708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19845037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossignol JF (2014) Nitazoxanide: a first-in-class broad-spectrum antiviral agent. Antiviral Res 110:94–103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25108173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7113776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossignol JF (2016) Nitazoxanide, a new drug candidate for the treatment of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus. J Infect Public Health 9:227–230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27095301</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7102735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sacramento CQ, de Melo GR, de Freitas CS, Rocha N, Hoelz LV, Miranda M, Fintelman-Rodrigues N, Marttorelli A, Ferreira AC, Barbosa-Lima G, Abrantes JL, Vieira YR, Bastos MM, de Mello Volotão E, Nunes EP, Tschoeke DA, Leomil L, Loiola EC, Trindade P, Rehen SK, Bozza FA, Bozza PT, Boechat N, Thompson FL, de Filippis AM, Brüning K, Souza TM (2017) The clinically approved antiviral drug sofosbuvir inhibits Zika virus replication. Sci Rep 7:40920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28098253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5241873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahoo M, Jena L, Daf S, Kumar S (2016) Virtual Screening for Potential Inhibitors of NS3 Protein of Zika Virus. Genomics Inf 14:104–111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Z, Wei J, Deng X, Li S, Qiu Y, Shao D, Li B, Zhang K, Xue F, Wang X, Ma Z (2014) Nitazoxanide inhibits the replication of Japanese encephalitis virus in cultured cells and in a mouse model. Virol J 11:10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24456815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3927656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simanjuntak Y, Liang JJ, Lee YL, Lin YL (2015) Repurposing of prochlorperazine for use against dengue virus infection. J Infect Dis 211:394–404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25028694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon T, Lewthwaite P, Perera D, Cardosa MJ, McMinn P, Ooi MH (2010) Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of enterovirus 71. Lancet Infect Dis 10:778–790</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20961813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strating JRPM, van der Linden L, Albulescu L, Bigay J, Arita M, Delang L, Leyssen P, van der Schaar HM, Lanke KHW, Thibaut HJ, Ulferts R, Drin G, Schlinck N, Wubbolts RW, Sever N, Head SA, Liu JO, Beachy PA, De Matteis MA, Shair MD, Olkkonen VM, Neyts J, van Kuppeveld FJM (2015) Itraconazole inhibits enterovirus replication by targeting the oxysterol-binding protein. Cell Rep 10:600–615</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25640182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4383725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Yogarajah T, Lee RCH, Kaur P, Inoue M, Tan YW, Chu JJH (2020) Drug repurposing of pyrimidine analogs as potent antiviral compounds against human enterovirus A71 infection with potential clinical applications. Sci Rep 10:8159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32424333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7235037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takatsuki A, Tamura G, Arima K (1969) Antiviral and Antitumor Antibiotics. XIV. Effects of Ascochlorin and Other Respiration Inhibitors on Multiplication of Newcastle Disease Virus in Cultured Cells. 17:825–829</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tariq A, Mateen RM, Afzal MS, Saleem M (2020) Paromomycin: A potential dual targeted drug effectively inhibits both spike (S1) and main protease of COVID-19. Int J Infect Dis 98:166–175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32579907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7306207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thammasonthijarern N, Kosoltanapiwat N, Nuprasert W, Sittikul P, Sriburin P, Pan-ngum W, Maneekan P, Hataiyusuk S, Hattasingh W, Thaipadungpanit J, Chatchen S (2021) Molecular Epidemiological Study of Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease in a Kindergarten-Based Setting in Bangkok. Thail Pathogens 10:576</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsubamoto H, Inoue K, Sakata K, Ueda T, Takeyama R, Shibahara H, Sonoda T (2017) Itraconazole Inhibits AKT/mTOR Signaling and Proliferation in Endometrial Cancer Cells. Anticancer Res 37:515–519</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28179296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanden Bossche H, Marichal P, Le Jeune L, Coene MC, Gorrens J, Cools W (1993) Effects of itraconazole on cytochrome P-450-dependent sterol 14 alpha-demethylation and reduction of 3-ketosteroids in Cryptococcus neoformans. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 37:2101–2105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8257130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">192235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Hu Y, Zheng M (2022) Enterovirus A71 antivirals: Past, present, and future. Acta Pharm Sin B 12:1542–1566</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35847514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang YM, Lu JW, Lin CC, Chin YF, Wu TY, Lin LI, Lai ZZ, Kuo SC, Ho YJ (2016) Antiviral activities of niclosamide and nitazoxanide against chikungunya virus entry and transmission. Antiviral Res 135:81–90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27742486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7126800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2018) Updated recommendations on first-line and second-line antiretroviral regimens and post-exposure prophylaxis and. recommendations on early infant diagnosis of HIV</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong WR, Chen YY, Yang SM, Chen YL, Horng JT (2005) Phosphorylation of PI3K/Akt and MAPK/ERK in an early entry step of enterovirus 71. Life Sci 78:82–90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16150462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7094582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu CJ, Jan JT, Chen CM, Hsieh HP, Hwang DR, Liu HW, Liu CY, Huang HW, Chen SC, Hong CF, Lin RK, Chao YS, Hsu JT (2004) Inhibition of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus replication by niclosamide. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 48:2693–2696</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15215127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">434198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Shi P-Y, Li H, Zhou J (2020) Broad Spectrum Antiviral Agent Niclosamide and Its Therapeutic Potential. ACS Infect Dis 6:909–915</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32125140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7098069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xun YH, Zhang YJ, Pan QC, Mao RC, Qin YL, Liu HY, Zhang YM, Yu YS, Tang ZH, Lu MJ, Zang GQ, Zhang JM (2014) Metformin inhibits hepatitis B virus protein production and replication in human hepatoma cells. J Viral Hepat 21:597–603</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24164660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav B, Wennerberg K, Aittokallio T, Tang J (2015) Searching for drug synergy in complex dose–response landscapes using an interaction potency model. Comput Struct Biotechnol 13:504–513</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi L, Lu J, Kung HF, He ML (2011) The virology and developments toward control of human enterovirus 71. Crit Rev Microbiol 37:313–327</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21651436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng S, Meng X, Huang Q, Lei N, Zeng L, Jiang X, Guo X (2019) Spiramycin and azithromycin, safe for administration to children, exert antiviral activity against enterovirus A71 in vitro and in vivo. Int J Antimicrob Agents 53:362–369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30599241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Li F, Pan Z, Wu Z, Wang Y, Cui Y (2014) Activation of PI3K/Akt pathway limits JNK-mediated apoptosis during EV71 infection. Virus Res 192:74–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25116390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T, Huang J, Yi Y, Zhang X, Loor JJ, Cao Y, Shi H, Luo J (2018) Akt Serine/Threonine Kinase 1 Regulates de Novo Fatty Acid Synthesis through the Mammalian Target of Rapamycin/Sterol Regulatory Element Binding Protein 1 Axis in Dairy Goat Mammary Epithelial Cells. J Agric Food Chem 66:1197–1205</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29323924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Bhagwath AS, Ramzan Z, Williams TA, Subramaniyan I, Edpuganti V, Kallem RR, Dunbar KB, Ding P, Gong K, Geurkink SA, Beg MS, Kim J, Zhang Q, Habib AA, Choi SH, Lapsiwala R, Bhagwath G, Dowell JE, Melton SD, Jie C, Putnam WC, Pham TH, Wang DH (2021) Itraconazole Exerts Its Antitumor Effect in Esophageal Cancer By Suppressing the HER2/AKT Signaling Pathway. Mol Cancer Ther 20:1904–1915</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34376577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8492513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X-N, Song Z-G, Jiang T, Shi B-S, Hu Y-W, Yuan Z-H (2010) Rupintrivir is a promising candidate for treating severe cases of Enterovirus-71 infection. World J Gastroenterol 16:201–209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20066739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2806558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Han H, Sun L, Qiu H, Lin H, Yu L, Zhu W, Qi J, Yang R, Pang Y, Wang X, Lu G, Yang Y (2017) Antiviral activity of shikonin ester derivative PMM-034 against enterovirus 71 in vitro. Braz J Med Biol Res 50:e6586</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28832767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5561812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Q, Xiong Y, Xu J, Chen S, Li P, Huang Y, Wang Y, Chen W-X, Wang B (2018) Host MicroRNA hsa-miR-494-3p Promotes EV71 Replication by Directly Targeting PTEN. Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology 8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu YZ, Wu DG, Ren H, Xu QQ, Zheng KC, Chen W, Chen SL, Qian XJ, Tao QY, Wang Y, Zhao P, Qi ZT (2015) The Role of Lipid Rafts in the Early Stage of Enterovirus 71 Infection. Cell Physiol Biochem 35:1347–1359</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25720437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>