<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39170726</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2057-1577</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virus evolution</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virus Evol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Opening a 60-year time capsule: sequences of historical poliovirus cold variants shed a new light on a contemporary strain.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>veae063</StartPage><MedlinePgn>veae063</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">veae063</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/ve/veae063</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Polioviruses (PVs) are positive strand RNA viruses responsible for poliomyelitis. Many PVs have been isolated and phenotypically characterized in the 1940s-50s for the purpose of identifying attenuated strains that could be used as vaccine strains. Among these historical PVs, only few are genetically characterized. We report here the sequencing of four PV strains stored for more than 60 years in a sealed box. These PVs are cold variants that were selected by Albert Sabin based on their capacity to multiply at relatively low temperatures. Inoculation of permissive cells at 25°C showed that two of the four historical virus stocks still contained infectious particles. Both viruses reached titres that were higher at 25°C than at 37°C, thus demonstrating that they were genuine cold variants. We obtained sequences that span virtually all the genome for three out of the four strains; a short sequence that partly covers the 5' untranslated region was recovered for the last one. Unexpectedly, the genome of one historical cold variant (which derives from PV-3 Glenn) displayed a very high nucleotide identity (above 95%) with that of a PV strain (PV-3 strain WIV14) sampled in China in 2014 and then classified as a highly evolved vaccine-derived PV. Our analyses made this hypothesis very unlikely and strongly suggested that Glenn and WIV14 shared a very recent common ancestor with one another. Some strains used to produce the inactivated polio vaccine were also very close to Glenn and WIV14 in the capsid-encoding region, but they had not been sequenced beyond the capsid. We therefore sequenced one of these strains, Saukett A, which was available in our collection. Saukett A and WIV14 featured an identity higher than 99% at the nucleotide level. This work provides original data on cold variants that were produced and studied decades ago. It also highlights that sequences of historical PV strains could be crucial to reliably characterize contemporary PVs in case of release from a natural reservoir or from a facility, which is of highest importance for the PV eradication program.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chesnais</LastName><ForeName>Morgane</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire associé au Centre national de référence pour les entérovirus &amp; paréchovirus, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bujaki</LastName><ForeName>Erika</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vaccines, National Institute for Biological Standards and Control, Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency, Blanche Lane, South Mimms, Potters Bar, Hertfordshire EN6 3QG, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Filhol</LastName><ForeName>Typhaine</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Caval</LastName><ForeName>Vincent</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Joffret</LastName><ForeName>Marie-Line</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5244-5429</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire associé au Centre national de référence pour les entérovirus &amp; paréchovirus, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vaccines, National Institute for Biological Standards and Control, Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency, Blanche Lane, South Mimms, Potters Bar, Hertfordshire EN6 3QG, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jouvenet</LastName><ForeName>Nolwenn</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bessaud</LastName><ForeName>Maël</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6758-9591</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris Cité, CNRS UMR 3569, Virus sensing and signaling Unit, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire associé au Centre national de référence pour les entérovirus &amp; paréchovirus, 28 rue du Dr Roux, Paris 75 015, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Virus Evol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664675</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2057-1577</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Saukett</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cold mutants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cold variants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">containment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polioviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine-derived polioviruses</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39170726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11336667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ve/veae063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">veae063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
Anonymous . WHO Global Action Plan to minimize poliovirus facility-associated risk after type-specific eradication of wild polioviruses and sequential cessation of oral polio vaccine use. 2022. https://polioeradication.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/GAPIII_2014.pdf (7 September 2023, date last accessed).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes JM, Heymann CS, Galbraith NS. et al. A clinical trial of Glenn type 3 attenuated poliovirus vacine. Arch Gesamte Virusforsch 1967;20:296–304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4299730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Jegouic S, Joffret M-L. et al. Characterization of the genome of human enteroviruses: design of generic primers for amplification and sequencing of different regions of the viral genome. J Virol Methods 2008;149:277–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18329732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Razafindratsimandresy R, Nougairède A. et al. Molecular comparison and evolutionary analyses of VP1 nucleotide sequences of new African human enterovirus 71 isolates reveal a wide genetic diversity. PLoS One 2014;9:e90624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3944068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24598878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessaud M, Sadeuh-Mba SA, Joffret M-L. et al. Whole genome sequencing of enterovirus species C isolates by high-throughput sequencing: development of generic primers. Front Microbiol 2016;7:1294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4999429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27617004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouchard MJ, Lam DH, Racaniello VR. Determinants of attenuation and temperature sensitivity in the type 1 poliovirus Sabin vaccine. J Virol 1995;69:4972–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC189313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7609067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Benschop KSM, Nguyen D. et al. Recombination analysis of non-poliovirus members of the enterovirus C species; restriction of recombination events to members of the same 3DPol cluster. Viruses 2020;12:E706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7412211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32629843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burns CC, Diop OM, Sutter RW. et al. Vaccine-derived polioviruses. J Infect Dis 2014;210:S283–293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25316847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cann AJ, Stanway G, Hughes PJ. et al. Reversion to neurovirulence of the live-attenuated Sabin type 3 oral poliovirus vaccine. Nucleic Acids Res 1984;12:7787–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC320200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6093054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combelas N, Holmblat B, Joffret M-L. et al. Recombination between poliovirus and coxsackie A viruses of species C: a model of viral genetic plasticity and emergence. Viruses 2011;3:1460–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3185806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21994791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dove AW, Racaniello VR. Cold-adapted poliovirus mutants bypass a postentry replication block. J Virol 1997;71:4728–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC191694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9151866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duizer E, Ruijs WL, Putri Hintaran AD. et al. Wild poliovirus type 3 (WPV3)-shedding event following detection in environmental surveillance of poliovirus essential facilities, the Netherlands, November 2022 to January 2023. Euro Surveill 2023;28:2300049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9896605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36729115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duizer E, Ruijs WL, van der Weijden CP. et al. Response to a wild poliovirus type 2 (WPV2)-shedding event following accidental exposure to WPV2, the Netherlands, April 2017. Euro Surveill 2017;22:30542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5479986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28597830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duizer E, Rutjes S, de Roda Husman AM. et al. Risk assessment, risk management and risk-based monitoring following a reported accidental release of poliovirus in Belgium, September to November 2014. Euro Surveill 2016;21:30169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27020766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn G. Quality assurance in the polio laboratory. Cell sensitivity and cell authentication assays. Methods Mol Biol 2016;1387:109–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26983732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson M, Evans DM, Magrath DI. et al. Induction by synthetic peptides of broadly reactive, type-specific neutralizing antibody to poliovirus type 3. Virology 1985;143:505–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2414909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavrilin GV, Cherkasova EA, Lipskaya GY. et al. Evolution of circulating wild poliovirus and of vaccine-derived poliovirus in an immunodeficient patient: a unifying model. J Virol 2000;74:7381–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC112258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10906191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Georgescu MM, Tardy-Panit M, Guillot S. et al. Mapping of mutations contributing to the temperature sensitivity of the Sabin 1 vaccine strain of poliovirus. J Virol 1995;69:5278–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC189363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7636970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horaud F. An historical outline of the development of live poliovaccine and its non-target effects. Dev Biol Stand 1995;84:117–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7796943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houwenhuyse S, Macke E, Reyserhove L. et al. Back to the future in a petri dish: origin and impact of resurrected microbes in natural populations. Evol Appl 2018;11:29–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5748525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29302270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huovilainen A, Kinnunen L, Pöyry T. et al. Poliovirus type 3/Saukett: antigenic and structural correlates of sequence variation in the capsid proteins. Virology 1994;199:228–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8116248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeannoël M, Antona D, Lazarus C. et al. Risk assessment and virological monitoring following an accidental exposure to concentrated sabin poliovirus type 3 in France, November 2018. Vaccines (Basel) 2020;8:331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32580378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joffret M-L, Polston PM, Razafindratsimandresy R. et al. Whole genome sequencing of enteroviruses species A to D by high-throughput sequencing: application for viral mixtures. Front Microbiol 2018;9:2339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6172331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30323802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jorba J, Campagnoli R, De L. et al. Calibration of multiple poliovirus molecular clocks covering an extended evolutionary range. J Virol 2008;82:4429–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2293050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18287242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinnunen L, Hovi T. Partial RNA sequencing of eight supposed derivatives of type 3 poliovirus/USA/Saukett/50 reveals remarkable differences between three apparent substrains. Virology 1989;170:316–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2541551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klapsa D, Wilton T, Zealand A. et al. Sustained detection of type 2 poliovirus in London sewage between February and July, 2022, by enhanced environmental surveillance. Lancet 2022;400:1531–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9627700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36243024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koprowski H. Sabin: Attenuated Polioviruses in Humans - Discussion. Cellular Biology: Nucleic Acids and Viruses. New York: New York Academy of Sciences, 1957, 128–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Stecher G, Li M. et al. MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. Mol Biol Evol 2018;35:1547–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5967553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29722887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyriakopoulou Z, Pliaka V, Amoutzias GD. et al. Recombination among human non-polio enteroviruses: implications for epidemiology and evolution. Virus Genes 2015;50:177–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25537948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lole KS, Bollinger RC, Paranjape RS. et al. Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination. J Virol 1999;73:152–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC103818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9847317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lwoff A. Factors influencing the evolution of viral diseases at the cellular level and in the organism. Bacteriol Rev 1959;23:109–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC181026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14419105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lwoff A. The thermosensitive critical event of the viral cycle. Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol 1962;27:159–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13931896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lwoff A. Death and transfiguration of a problem. Bacteriol Rev 1969;33:390–403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC378331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4313270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lwoff A, Lwoff M. Remarques sur quelques caractères du développement du virus de la poliomyélite. C R Hebd Seances Acad Sci 1959;248:1725–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13639370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macadam AJ, Pollard SR, Ferguson G. et al. The 5ʹ noncoding region of the type 2 poliovirus vaccine strain contains determinants of attenuation and temperature sensitivity. Virology 1991;181:451–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1707566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macadam AJ, Pollard SR, Ferguson G. et al. Genetic basis of attenuation of the Sabin type 2 vaccine strain of poliovirus in primates. Virology 1993;192:18–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8390752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mee ET, Minor PD, Martin J. High resolution identity testing of inactivated poliovirus vaccines. Vaccine 2015;33:3533–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4504004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26049003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minor PD, Dunn G, Evans DM. et al. The temperature sensitivity of the Sabin type 3 vaccine strain of poliovirus: molecular and structural effects of a mutation in the capsid protein VP3. J Gen Virol 1989;70:1117–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2543771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minor PD, Schild GC, Ferguson M. et al. Genetic and antigenic variation in type 3 polioviruses: characterization of strains by monoclonal antibodies and T1 oligonucleotide mapping. J Gen Virol 1982;61:167–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6181190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monpoeho S, Dehée A, Mignotte B. et al. Quantification of enterovirus RNA in sludge samples using single tube real-time RT-PCR. Biotechniques 2000;29:88–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10907082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muslin C, Mac Kain A, Bessaud M. et al. Recombination in enteroviruses, a multi-step modular evolutionary process. Viruses 2019;11:E859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6784155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31540135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nomoto A, Omata T, Toyoda H. et al. Complete nucleotide sequence of the attenuated poliovirus Sabin 1 strain genome. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 1982;79:5793–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC346996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6310545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS. Comparative genomics of the coxsackie B viruses and related enteroviruses. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol 2008;323:33–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18357764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS. Progress of polio eradication and containment requirements after eradication. Transfusion 2018;58:3078–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8963859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30536438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Offit Paul A. The cutter incident, 50 years later. N Engl J Med 2005;352:1411–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15814877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omata T, Kohara M, Kuge S. et al. Genetic analysis of the attenuation phenotype of poliovirus type 1. J Virol 1986;58:348–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC252919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3009852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul AV, Mugavero J, Yin J. et al. Studies on the attenuation phenotype of polio vaccines: poliovirus RNA polymerase derived from Sabin type 1 sequence is temperature sensitive in the uridylylation of VPg. Virology 2000;272:72–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10873750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeiffer JK, Rall GF. The importance of model systems: why we study a virus on the brink of global eradication. PLoS Pathog 2017;13:e1006330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5398706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28426821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezapkin GV, Fan L, Asher DM. et al. Mutations in Sabin 2 strain of poliovirus and stability of attenuation phenotype. Virology 1999;258:152–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10329577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB. Present status of attenuated live-virus poliomyelitis vaccine. J Am Med Assoc 1956;162:1589–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13376323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB. Behavior of Cold Mutants of Poliovirus in Human Beings. Washington, D. C: Pan American Health Organization, 1960, 101–08.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB. Chapter 8. Reproductive capacity of polioviruses of diverse origins at various temperatures. In: The Gustav Stern Symposium on Perspectives on Virology, Volume II. Morris Pollard, p. 90–110. Minneapolis: Burgess Publishing Co; 1961.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB. Oral poliovirus vaccine: history of its development and use and current challenge to eliminate poliomyelitis from the world. J Infect Dis 1985;151:420–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2982959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabin AB, Boulger LR. History of Sabin attenuated poliovirus oral live vaccine strains. J Biol Stand 1973;1:115–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders BP, Liu Y, Brandjes A. et al. Brunenders: a partially attenuated historic poliovirus type I vaccine strain. J Gen Virol 2015;96:2614–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26018960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanders BP, Rios Oakes I de L, van Hoek V. et al. Cold-Adapted Viral Attenuation (CAVA): highly temperature sensitive polioviruses as novel vaccine strains for a next generation inactivated poliovirus vaccine. PLoS Pathog 2016;12:e1005483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4816566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27032093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shulman LM, Laassri M, Handsher R. et al. Epidemiology of type 3 poliovirus AFP cases in Israel between 1973 and 1988: whole genome sequencing of RNA extracted directly from archived stocks to avoid re-culturing neurovirulent wild poliovirus. Vaccines (Basel) 2022;10:2154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9781118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simonen M-L, Roivainen M, Iber J. et al. Outbreak of poliomyelitis in Finland in 1984–85 - re-analysis of viral sequences using the current standard approach. Virus Res 2010;147:91–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19883702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tardy-Panit M, Blondel B, Martin A. et al. A mutation in the RNA polymerase of poliovirus type 1 contributes to attenuation in mice. J Virol 1993;67:4630–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC237848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8392604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavares FN, da Costa EV, Kew OM. et al. Complete genome sequence of the last representative genotype of wild indigenous poliovirus type 1, which circulated in Brazil. Genome Announc 2013;1:e00811–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3814633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24179117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorley BR, Roberts JA. Isolation and characterization of poliovirus in cell culture systems. Methods Mol Biol 2016;1387:29–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26983730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wildi N, Bagatella S, Koch M. et al. Archival wild-type poliovirus 1 infected central nervous system tissues of the pre-vaccination era in Switzerland reveal a distinct virus genotype. Acta Neuropathol 2023;145:357–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9888746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36719503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Chen W, Chang H. et al. Genetic analysis of the VP1 region of enterovirus 71 reveals the emergence of genotype A in central China in 2008. Virus Genes 2010;41:1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20306124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Qin C, Li W. et al. Isolation and characterization of a highly evolved type 3 vaccine-derived poliovirus in China. Virus Res 2017;238:179–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28669764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu J, Luo Z, Wang J. et al. Phylogenetic analysis of enterovirus 71 circulating in Beijing, China from 2007 to 2009. PLoS One 2013;8:e56318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3572022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23418551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>