<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39150641</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1439-0973</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infection</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Disseminated Echovirus 11 infection in a newborn in the Province of Bolzano, Italy.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s15010-024-02315-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Recently, cases of serious illness in newborns infected with Echovirus 11 have been reported in Europe, including Italy. Here, we report the case of a newborn diagnosed with disseminated Echovirus 11 infection, which occurred in October 2023 in the Province of Bolzano, Italy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A molecular screening, by Real-Time RT-PCR, was employed to analyse the cerebrospinal fluid, blood and stool samples, and nasal swabs. The entire viral genome was sequenced using both Illumina and Nanopore technologies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The patient was admitted to hospital due to fever. Molecular testing revealed the presence of enterovirus RNA. Typing confirmed the presence of Echovirus 11. The patient was initially treated with antibiotic therapy and, following the diagnosis of enterovirus infection, also with human immunoglobulins. Over the following days, the patient remained afebrile, with decreasing inflammation indices and in excellent general condition. Genomic and phylogenetic characterization suggested that the strain was similar to strains from severe cases reported in Europe.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Despite the low overall risk for the neonatal population in Europe, recent cases of Echovirus 11 have highlighted the importance of surveillance and complete genome sequencing is fundamental to understanding the phylogenetic relationships of Echovirus 11 variants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bianconi</LastName><ForeName>Irene</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Microbiology and Virology, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy. irene.bianconi@sabes.it.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Battisti</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Paediatrics, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Staffler</LastName><ForeName>Alex</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Neonatology/NICU, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giacobazzi</LastName><ForeName>Elisabetta</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Microbiology and Virology, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Masi</LastName><ForeName>Elisa</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Microbiology and Virology, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Incrocci</LastName><ForeName>Elisabetta</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Microbiology and Virology, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bellutti</LastName><ForeName>Marion</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Paediatrics, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fontana</LastName><ForeName>Stefano</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Istituto Superiore di Sanità, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stefanelli</LastName><ForeName>Paola</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Istituto Superiore di Sanità, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Buttinelli</LastName><ForeName>Gabriele</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Istituto Superiore di Sanità, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pagani</LastName><ForeName>Elisabetta</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Microbiology and Virology, Hospital of Bolzano (SABES-ASDAA), Teaching Hospital of Paracelsus Medical University (PMU), Bolzano-Bozen, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Infection</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0365307</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0300-8126</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Echovirus 11</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Illumina</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanopore</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Newborn</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-polio Enteroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">WGS</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39150641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s15010-024-02315-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s15010-024-02315-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bubba L, Broberg EK, Jasir A, Simmonds P, Harvala H, Redlberger-Fritz M, Nikolaeva-Glomb L, Havlíčková M, Rainetova P, Fischer TK, et al. Circulation of Non-polio enteroviruses in 24 EU and EEA Countries between 2015 and 2017: a Retrospective Surveillance Study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(19)30566-3 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L, Moreni G, Wolthers KC, Pajkrt D. World-Wide Prevalence and Genotype Distribution of Enteroviruses. Viruses 2021, 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Wang H, Tang J, He Y, Xiong T, Li W, Qu Y, Mu D. Clinical characteristics of severe neonatal enterovirus infection: a systematic review. BMC Pediatr. 2021;21. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12887-021-02599-y .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freund MW, Kleinveld G, Krediet TG, Van Loon AM, Verboon-Maciolek MA. Prognosis for neonates with Enterovirus Myocarditis. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2010;95. https://doi.org/10.1136/adc.2009.165183 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grapin M, Mirand A, Pinquier D, Basset A, Bendavid M, Bisseux M, Jeannoel M, Kireche B, Kossorotoff M, L’Honneur AS, et al. Severe and Fatal Neonatal Infections Linked to a new variant of Echovirus 11, France, July 2022 to April 2023. Eurosurveillance. 2023;28. https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2023.28.22.2300253 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Borghesi A, Di Comite A, Giardina F, Ferrari G, Zanette S, Figar TA, Angelini M, Pisoni C, Pitrolo AMG, et al. Fulminant Echovirus 11 Hepatitis in Male Non-identical Twins in Northern Italy, April 2023. Eurosurveillance. 2023;28. https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2023.28.24.2300289 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang P, Xu Y, Liu M, Li H, Wang H, Liu Y, Wang B, Xia S, Su H, Wei M, et al. Risk factors and early markers for Echovirus Type 11 Associated Haemorrhage-Hepatitis Syndrome in neonates, a Retrospective Cohort Study. Front Pediatr. 2023;11. https://doi.org/10.3389/fped.2023.1063558 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sandoni M, Ciardo L, Tamburini C, Boncompagni A, Rossi C, Guidotti I, Garetti E, Lugli L, Iughetti L, Berardi A. Enteroviral Infections in the First Three Months of Life. Pathogens 2022, 11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allan Nix W, Oberste MS, Pallansch MA, Sensitive. Seminested PCR amplification of VP1 sequences for direct identification of all Enterovirus Serotypes from original clinical specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2006;44. https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.00542-06 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isaacs SR, Kim KW, Cheng JX, Bull RA, Stelzer-Braid S, Luciani F, Rawlinson WD, Craig ME. Amplification and next generation sequencing of near full-length human enteroviruses for identification and characterisation from clinical samples. Sci Rep. 2018;8. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-30322-y .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H. Minimap2: pairwise alignment for nucleotide sequences. Bioinformatics. 2018;34. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty191 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castellano S, Cestari F, Faglioni G, Tenedini E, Marino M, Artuso L, Manfredini R, Luppi M, Trenti T, Tagliafico E. Ivar, an interpretation-oriented Tool to manage the update and revision of variant annotation and classification. Genes (Basel). 2021;12. https://doi.org/10.3390/genes12030384 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sayers EW, Cavanaugh M, Clark K, Pruitt KD, Schoch CL, Sherry ST, Karsch-Mizrachi I, GenBank. Nucleic Acids Res. 2022;50. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkab1135 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura K, Stecher G, Kumar S. MEGA11: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis Version 11. Mol Biol Evol. 2021;38. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msab120 .</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>