<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39106854</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1476-1645</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>111</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Trop Med Hyg</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Changing Epidemiology of Hand, Foot, and Mouth Disease Causative Agents and Contributing Factors.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>740</StartPage><EndPage>755</EndPage><MedlinePgn>740-755</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4269/ajtmh.23-0852</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) is a common viral infection primarily affecting children. It causes vesicles on the skin and inside the mouth. Although most cases get better on their own, severe cases can lead to complications such as brain stem encephalitis, meningoencephalitis, acute flaccid paralysis, and pulmonary edema. Hand, foot, and mouth disease is caused by various enteroviruses, with enterovirus A71 (EV-A71) and coxsackievirus A16 being the most common. However, recent studies have shown a shift in the molecular epidemiology of HFMD-causing pathogens, with coxsackievirus A6 and coxsackievirus A10 causing more infections. In addition, extensive recombination events have been identified among enterovirus strains, which may have a role in faster evolution and extinction of dominant enterovirus serotypes. Other strains of enterovirus can also cause severe complications, and there has been an increase in mortality associated with brain stem encephalitis in children under 3 years of age and teenagers. Currently, there are no effective antiviral therapies available to treat enterovirus infections. Vaccines against EV-A71 have been approved and are now used in mainland China. Studying the changing epidemiology of HFMD pathogens and the evolution patterns of its causative agents is crucial in developing effective prevention and control strategies. Increased interest in the molecular epidemiology of HFMD causative agents has led to a better understanding of the critical drivers of HFMD outbreaks, which can inform efforts to prevent and control the disease.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kalam</LastName><ForeName>Nida</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jeffrey Cheah School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Monash University Malaysia, Bandar Sunway, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Balasubramaniam</LastName><ForeName>Vinod</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jeffrey Cheah School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Monash University Malaysia, Bandar Sunway, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Trop Med Hyg</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370507</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0002-9637</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006232" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hand, Foot and Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029821" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus A, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Authors’ contributions: V. Balasubramaniam conceptualized and designed the manuscript. N. Kalam wrote and prepared the manuscript and the figure. V. Balasubramaniam critically revised the manuscript. Both authors approved the final version. Both authors significantly contributed to the development and the writing of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39106854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11448535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.23-0852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">tpmd230852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Robinson CR, Doane FW, Rhodes AJ, 1958. Report of an outbreak of febrile illness with pharyngeal lesions and exanthem: Toronto, summer 1957; isolation of group A Coxsackie virus. Can Med Assoc J 79: 615–621.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1830188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13585281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y-F, Hu L, Xu F, Liu C-J, Li J, 2019. A case report of a teenager with severe hand, foot, and mouth disease with brainstem encephalitis caused by enterovirus 71. BMC Pediatr 19: 59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6373151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30760232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao K, Duan L, Peng Y, Wu M, Mai G, Yan Z, Chen S, Lu Y, 2019. Epidemiologic features of enterovirus associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in 2013 and 2014 in Shenzhen, China. Sci Rep 9: 3856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6405776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30846756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Jiang L, Peng HL, 2015. Clinical analysis of 134 children with nervous system damage caused by enterovirus 71 infection. Pediatr Infect Dis J 34: 718–723.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25860536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMinn P, Stratov I, Nagarajan L, Davis S, 2001. Neurological manifestations of enterovirus 71 infection in children during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Western Australia. Clin Infect Dis 32: 236–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11170913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahmahmoodi S. et al., 2008. First detection of enterovirus 71 from an acute flaccid paralysis case with residual paralysis in Iran. J Clin Virol 42: 409–411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18403258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan PH, Dau HV, Chu ST, Phung TB, Van Pham T, Van Nguyen T, Nguyen LT, 2012. Continuous veno-venous hemofiltration for treatment of enterovirus 71-induced fulminant cardiopulmonary failure: A case report. J Med Case Rep 6: 159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3464731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22734721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang MG, Sun HM, Liu XM, Deng XQ, 2017. Clinical analysis of 59 children with hand foot and mouth diseases due to enterovirus EV71 and concomitant viral encephalitis. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci 21: 43–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29165766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nhu LNT. et al., 2021. Coxsackievirus A16 in Southern Vietnam. Front Microbiol 12: 689658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8265502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34248913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayak G, Bhuyan SK, Bhuyan R, Sahu A, Kar D, Kuanar A, 2022. Global emergence of enterovirus 71: A systematic review. Beni Suef Univ J Basic Appl Sci 11: 78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9188855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35730010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blomqvist S, Klemola P, Kaijalainen S, Paananen A, Simonen ML, Vuorinen T, Roivainen M, 2010. Co-circulation of coxsackieviruses A6 and A10 in hand, foot and mouth disease outbreak in Finland. J Clin Virol 48: 49–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20189452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracho MA, González-Candelas F, Valero A, Córdoba J, Salazar A, 2011. Enterovirus co-infections and onychomadesis after hand, foot, and mouth disease, Spain, 2008. Emerg Infect Dis 17: 2223–2231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3311182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22172227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He YQ. et al., 2013. Emergence, circulation, and spatiotemporal phylogenetic analysis of coxsackievirus A6- and coxsackievirus A10-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease infections from 2008 to 2012 in Shenzhen, China. J Clin Microbiol 51: 3560–3566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3889734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23966496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Q-B. et al., 2012. Circulation of coxsackievirus A10 and A6 in hand-foot-mouth disease in China, 2009–2011. PLoS One 7: e52073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3525556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23272213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lizasoain A, Mir D, Martínez N, Colina R, 2020. Coxsackievirus A10 causing hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Uruguay. Int J Infect Dis 94: 1–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32081777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J. et al., 2018. An outbreak of coxsackievirus A6-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease in a kindergarten in Beijing in 2015. BMC Pediatr 18: 277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6103857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30131060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H, Zhang M, Feng C, Cong S, Xu D, Sun H, Yang Z, Ma S, 2021. Characterization of coxsackievirus A6 strains isolated from children with hand, foot, and mouth disease. Front Cell Infect Microbiol 11: 700191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8418080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34490141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie J. et al., 2020. Co-circulation of coxsackieviruses A-6, A-10, and A-16 causes hand, foot, and mouth disease in Guangzhou city, China. BMC Infect Dis 20: 271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7137261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32264839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu MY, Liu J, Lai W, Luo J, Liu Y, Vu G-P, Yang Z, Trang P, Li H, Wu J, 2016. Characterization of enterovirus 71 infection and associated outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Shawo of China in 2012. Sci Rep 6: 38451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5150535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27941929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng Y. et al., 2023. Factors related to the mortality risk of severe hand, foot, and mouth diseases (HFMD): A 5-year hospital-based survey in Guangxi, Southern China. BMC Infect Dis 23: 144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9993373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36890462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng D, Ma Y, Liu Y, Lv Q, Yin F, 2020. Epidemiological and aetiological characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Sichuan Province, China, 2011–2017. Sci Rep 10: 6117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7145801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32273569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Wang T, Zhao M, Dong S, Wang S, Shi J, 2022. Spatiotemporal cluster patterns of hand, foot, and mouth disease at the province level in mainland China, 2011–2018. PLoS One 17: e0270061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9394824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35994464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li XW. et al., 2018. Chinese guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of hand, foot and mouth disease (2018 edition). World J Pediatr 14: 437–447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30280313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox B, Levent F, 2018. Hand, foot, and mouth disease. JAMA 320: 2492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30561482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao J, Jiang F, Zhong L, Sun J, Ding J, 2016. Age patterns and transmission characteristics of hand, foot and mouth disease in China. BMC Infect Dis 16: 691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5117511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27871252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bo YC, Song C, Wang JF, Li XW, 2014. Using an autologistic regression model to identify spatial risk factors and spatial risk patterns of hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) in Mainland China. BMC Public Health 14: 358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4022446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24731248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knöpfel N, Noguera-Morel L, Latour I, Torrelo A, 2019. Viral exanthems in children: A great imitator. Clin Dermatol 37: 213–226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31178104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro MCR, Ramos ESM, 2020. The rash with mucosal ulceration. Clin Dermatol 38: 35–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32197747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-López N. et al., 2021. Surveillance for enteroviruses associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease, and other mucocutaneous symptoms in Spain, 2006–2020. Viruses 13: 781.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8146579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33924875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long L. et al., 2016. Neurological complications and risk factors of cardiopulmonary failure of EV-A71-related hand, foot and mouth disease. Sci Rep 6: 23444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4802311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27001010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsia SH, Lin JJ, Chan OW, Lin TY, 2020. Cardiopulmonary failure in children infected with enterovirus A71. J Biomed Sci 27: 53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7161201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32299443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justino MCA, da S Mesquita D, Souza MF, Farias FP, dos S Alves JC, Ferreira JL, Lopes DP, Tavares FN, 2020. Atypical hand-foot-mouth disease in Belém, Amazon region, northern Brazil, with detection of coxsackievirus A6. J Clin Virol 126: 104307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruning AHL, van der Sanden SMG, ten Hoedt AE, Wolthers KC, van Kaam AH, Pajkrt D, 2015. An atypical course of coxsackievirus A6 associated hand, foot and mouth disease in extremely low birth weight preterm twins. J Clin Virol 65: 20–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25766981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez-Fort MK, Downing C, Doan HQ, Benoist F, Oberste MS, Khan F, Tyring SK, 2014. Coxsackievirus A6 associated hand, foot and mouth disease in adults: Clinical presentation and review of the literature. J Clin Virol 60: 381–386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24932735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapadia RK, Gill CM, Baca C, McMenamin C, Kannappan A, Niehaus WN, Tyler KL, Pastula DM, Piquet AL, 2021. Enterovirus A71 causing meningoencephalitis and acute flaccid myelitis in a patient receiving rituximab. J Neuroimmunol 358: 577639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34214953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zare M, Jamalidoust M, Pouladfar GR, Amanati A, Shafaati M, Namayandeh M, Ziyaeyan M, 2022. A case report of severe systemic infection with neurological HFMD symptoms followed by an accidental puncture of thumb during HFMD sample collection. IDCases 27: e01434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8819104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35145864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Jiang C, Cheng X, Ma L, Xin Y, Liu T, Sun R, 2022. Secondary hypogonadism following hand, foot, and mouth disease in an adult: A case report and review of literature. BMC Infect Dis 22: 56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8760742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35033020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crabol Y. et al., 2017. A prospective, comparative study of severe neurological and uncomplicated hand, foot and mouth forms of paediatric enterovirus 71 infections. Int J Infect Dis 59: 69–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28438677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Su L, Zhang T, He F, Yin Y, 2019. MRI reveals segmental distribution of enterovirus lesions in the central nervous system: A probable clinical evidence of retrograde axonal transport of EV-A71. J Neurovirol 25: 354–362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30734196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akuzawa N, Harada N, Hatori T, Imai K, Kitahara Y, Sakurai S, Kurabayashi M, 2014. Myocarditis, hepatitis, and pancreatitis in a patient with coxsackievirus A4 infection: A case report. Virol J 11: 3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3895747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24410962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen F, Liu T, Li J, Xing Z, Huang S, Wen G, 2014. MRI characteristics and follow-up findings in patients with neurological complications of enterovirus 71-related hand, foot, and mouth disease. Int J Clin Exp Med 7: 2696–2704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4211777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25356127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Second J, Velter C, Calès S, Truchetet F, Lipsker D, Cribier B, 2017. Clinicopathologic analysis of atypical hand, foot, and mouth disease in adult patients. J Am Acad Dermatol 76: 722–729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28027826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okada H, Wada M, Sato H, Yamaguchi Y, Tanji H, Kurokawa K, Kawanami T, Takahashi T, Kato T, 2013. Neuromyelitis optica preceded by hyperCKemia and a possible association with coxsackie virus group A10 infection. Intern Med 52: 2665–2668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24292760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stewart CL, Chu EY, Introcaso CE, Schaffer A, James WD, 2013. Coxsackievirus A6-induced hand-foot-mouth disease. JAMA Dermatol 149: 1419–1421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24172861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin X-G, Yi H-X, Shu J, Wang X-J, Wu X-J, Yu L-H, 2014. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics of adult hand, foot, and mouth disease in northern Zhejiang, China, May 2008–November 2013. BMC Infect Dis 14: 251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4026826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24885052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu L, He J, Wang L, Yi H, 2019. Incidence, aetiology, and serotype spectrum analysis of adult hand, foot, and mouth disease patients: A retrospective observational cohort study in northern Zhejiang, China. Int J Infect Dis 85: 28–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31100417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing J, Wang K, Wei H, Wei D, 2018. Pathologic and molecular studies of enterovirus 71 infection in a fatal case from a recent epidemic in China. Case Rep Med 97: e13447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6283094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30508963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi R, Omar E, Tuan Soh TS, Mohd Nawi SFA, Md Noor S, 2017. A sudden paediatric death due to hand, foot and mouth disease: The importance of vigilance. Malays J Pathol 39: 167–170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28866699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lao Q, Guo C-P, Weng T, Xu Z-F, Li H-G, 2019. MRI and CT characteristics of the complications of hand-foot-mouth disease in central nervous system in children: Summary of 15 cases. Radiol Infect Dis 6: 26–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H-G, Lao Q, 2017. The pulmonary complications associated with EV71-infected hand–foot–mouth disease. Radiol Infect Dis 4: 137–142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Sousa IP, Jr., Giamberardino HI, Raboni SM, Debur MC, de Lourdes Aguiar Oliveira M, Burlandy FM, da Silva EE, 2021. Simultaneous enterovirus EV-D68 and CVA6 infections causing acute respiratory distress syndrome and hand, foot and mouth disease. Virol J 18: 88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8085469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33931064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goto K, Sanefuji M, Kusuhara K, Nishimura Y, Shimizu H, Kira R, Torisu H, Hara T, 2009. Rhombencephalitis and coxsackievirus A16. Emerg Infect Dis 15: 1689–1691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2866411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19861078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richter J, Tryfonos C, Christodoulou C, 2019. Molecular epidemiology of enteroviruses in Cyprus 2008–2017. PLoS One 14: e0220938.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6687182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31393960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pogka V, Emmanouil M, Labropoulou S, Voulgari-Kokota A, Angelakis E, Mentis AF, 2020. Molecular characterization of enteroviruses among hospitalized patients in Greece, 2013–2015. J Clin Virol 127: 104349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32339946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Sanz R. et al., 2019. Molecular epidemiology of an enterovirus A71 outbreak associated with severe neurological disease, Spain, 2016. Euro Surveill 24: 1800089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6381658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30782267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrinelli L, Galli C, Primache V, Bubba L, Buttinelli G, Stefanelli P, Pariani E, Binda S, 2021. Emerging non-polio enteroviruses recognized in the framework of the Acute Flaccid Paralyses (AFP) Surveillance system in Northern Italy, 2016–2018. Int J Infect Dis 106: 36–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33771675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böttcher S, Diedrich S, Keeren K, Laboratory Network for Enterovirus Diagnostic (LaNED) , 2019. Increased detection of enterovirus A71 infections, Germany, 2019. Euro Surveill 24: 1900556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6774229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31576805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casas-Alba D. et al., 2017. Outbreak of brainstem encephalitis associated with enterovirus-A71 in Catalonia, Spain (2016): A clinical observational study in a children’s reference centre in Catalonia. Clin Microbiol Infect 23: 874–881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28344164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broccolo F. et al., 2019. Severe atypical hand-foot-and-mouth disease in adults due to coxsackievirus A6: Clinical presentation and phylogenesis of CV-A6 strains. J Clin Virol 110: 1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30472520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieczorek M, Purzyńska M, Krzysztoszek A, Ciąćka A, Figas A, Szenborn L, 2018. Genetic characterization of enterovirus A71 isolates from severe neurological cases in Poland. J Med Virol 90: 372–376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28960454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrés C. et al., 2019. Surveillance of enteroviruses from paediatric patients attended at a tertiary hospital in Catalonia from 2014 to 2017. J Clin Virol 110: 29–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30530096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M. et al., 2014. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus 71, coxsackievirus A16 and A6 associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Spain. Clin Microbiol Infect 20: O150–O156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24033818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bible Jon M, Iturriza-Gomara M, Megson B, Brown D, Pantelidis P, Earl P, Bendig J, Tong CYW, 2008. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus 71 in the United Kingdom from 1998 to 2006. J Clin Microbiol 46: 3192–3200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2566106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18650362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Shi Y, Miao L, Zhang C, Liu Y, 2021. Molecular epidemiology and recombination of enterovirus A71 in mainland China from 1987 to 2017. Int Microbiol 24: 291–299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7895512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33608776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan X, Li L, Zhang B, Jorba J, Su X, Ji T, Yang D, Lv L, Li J, Xu W, 2015. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A6 associated with outbreaks of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Tianjin, China, in 2013. Arch Virol 160: 1097–1104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4629805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25680566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duong V. et al., 2016. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus 71 at the origin of an epidemic of fatal hand, foot and mouth disease cases in Cambodia. Emerg Microbes Infect 5: e104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5113052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27651091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng H. et al., 2021. Emergence of a non vaccine-cognate enterovirus A71 genotype C1 in mainland China. J Infect 82: 407–413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33373653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q, Ding J, Cao J, Huang Q, Hong C, Yang B, 2015. Epidemiological and etiological characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Wuhan, China from 2012 to 2013: Outbreaks of coxsackieviruses A10. J Med Virol 87: 954–960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25754274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upala P, Apidechkul T, Suttana W, Kullawong N, Tamornpark R, Inta C, 2018. Molecular epidemiology and clinical features of hand, foot and mouth disease in northern Thailand in 2016: A prospective cohort study. BMC Infect Dis 18: 630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30522440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y. et al., 2017. Persistent circulation of coxsackievirus A6 of genotype D3 in mainland of China between 2008 and 2015. Sci Rep 7: 5491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5511160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28710474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan D. et al., 2012. Population dynamics and genetic diversity of C4 strains of human enterovirus 71 in Mainland China, 1998–2010. PLoS One 7: e44386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3440427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22984501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thammasonthijarern N. et al., 2021. Molecular epidemiological study of hand, foot, and mouth disease in a kindergarten-based setting in Bangkok, Thailand. Pathogens 10: 576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8150733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34068676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mizuta K, Aoki Y, Matoba Y, Yahagi K, Itagaki T, Katsushima F, Katsushima Y, Ito S, Hongo S, Matsuzaki Y, 2014. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus 71 strains isolated from children in Yamagata, Japan, between 1990 and 2013. J Med Microbiol 63: 1356–1362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25053796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z. et al., 2014. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus associated with aseptic meningitis in Shandong Province, China, 2006–2012. PLoS One 9: e89766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3931826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24587020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Li C, Liu L, Liu X, Shang S, Mao H, Zhang Y, 2019. Molecular epidemiology of enterovirus from children with herpangina or hand, foot, and mouth disease in Hangzhou, 2016. Arch Virol 164: 2565–2571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31321585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Su L, Cao L, Zhong H, Dong N, Xu J, 2013. Enterovirus genotypes causing hand foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, China: A molecular epidemiological analysis. BMC Infect Dis 13: 489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24148902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastasina M, Domanska A, Palm K, Butcher S, 2017. Human picornaviruses associated with neurological diseases and their neutralization by antibodies. J Gen Virol 98: 1145–1158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28631594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen CS, Yao YC, Lin SC, Lee YP, Wang YF, Wang JR, Liu CC, Lei HY, Yu CK, 2007. Retrograde axonal transport: A major transmission route of enterovirus 71 in mice. J Virol 81: 8996–9003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1951457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17567704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong KC, Wong KT, 2015. Understanding enterovirus 71 neuropathogenesis and its impact on other neurotropic enteroviruses. Brain Pathol 25: 614–624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8029433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26276025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong KC, Badmanathan M, Devi S, Leong KL, Cardosa MJ, Wong KT, 2008. Pathologic characterization of a murine model of human enterovirus 71 encephalomyelitis. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 67: 532–542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18520772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniels BP, Holman DW, Cruz-Orengo L, Jujjavarapu H, Durrant DM, Klein RS, 2014. Viral pathogen-associated molecular patterns regulate blood-brain barrier integrity via competing innate cytokine signals. mBio 5: e01476-e14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4173776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25161189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Vainionpää R, Vanharanta R, Hyypiä T, 1996. Susceptibility of human bone marrow cells and hematopoietic cell lines to coxsackievirus B3 infection. J Virol 70: 9018–9023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC191003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8971035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabor-Godwin JM. et al., 2010. A novel population of myeloid cells responding to coxsackievirus infection assists in the dissemination of virus within the neonatal CNS. J Neurosci 30: 8676–8691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2902258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20573913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phyu WK, Ong KC, Wong KT, 2016. A consistent orally-infected hamster model for enterovirus A71 encephalomyelitis demonstrates squamous lesions in the paws, skin and oral cavity reminiscent of hand-foot-and-mouth disease. PLoS One 11: e0147463.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4729525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26815859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phyu WK, Ong KC, Kong CK, Alizan AK, Ramanujam TM, Wong KT, 2017. Squamous epitheliotropism of enterovirus A71 in human epidermis and oral mucosa. Sci Rep 7: 45069.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5359612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28322333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo-Cao E, Hall S, Parsell R, Dandie G, Fahlström A, 2021. Neurogenic pulmonary edema. Am J Emerg Med 45: 678.e3–678.e5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33308892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lum LC, Wong KT, Lam SK, Chua KB, Goh AY, 1998. Neurogenic pulmonary oedema and enterovirus 71 encephalomyelitis. Lancet 352: 1391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9802304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>West JB, Mathieu-Costello O, 1992. Stress failure of pulmonary capillaries in the intensive care setting. Schweiz Med Wochenschr 122: 751–757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1604280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finsterer J, 2019. Neurological perspectives of neurogenic pulmonary edema. Eur Neurol 81: 94–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31117074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SM, Lei HY, Huang KJ, Wu JM, Wang JR, Yu CK, Su IJ, Liu CC, 2003. Pathogenesis of enterovirus 71 brainstem encephalitis in pediatric patients: Roles of cytokines and cellular immune activation in patients with pulmonary edema. J Infect Dis 188: 564–570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12898444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste MS, Peñaranda S, Maher K, Pallansch MA, 2004. Complete genome sequences of all members of the species Human enterovirus A. J Gen Virol 85: 1597–1607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15166444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osterback R, Vuorinen T, Linna M, Susi P, Hyypiä T, Waris M, 2009. Coxsackievirus A6 and hand, foot, and mouth disease, Finland. Emerg Infect Dis 15: 1485–1488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2819858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19788821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anh NT. et al., 2018. Emerging coxsackievirus A6 causing hand, foot and mouth disease, Vietnam. Emerg Infect Dis 24: 654–662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5875260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29553326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu J. et al., 2014. Hand, foot and mouth disease in Guangdong, China, in 2013: New trends in the continuing epidemic. Clin Microbiol Infect 20: O442–O445.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24428125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui P. et al., 2019. Clinical analysis of 555 outpatients with hand, foot and mouth diseases caused by different enteroviruses. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi 57: 445–451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31216802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ai Y. et al., 2021. Molecular epidemiology and clinical features of enteroviruses-associated hand, foot, and mouth disease and herpangina outbreak in Zunyi, China, 2019. Front Med (Lausanne) 8: 656699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8109248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33981716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing W. et al., 2014. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2008–12: An epidemiological study. Lancet Infect Dis 14: 308–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4035015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24485991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong J. et al., 2022. Changing epidemiology of hand, foot, and mouth disease in China, 2013–2019: A population-based study. Lancet Reg Health West Pac 20: 100370.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8743221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35036978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Z, Wang J, 2014. EV71 vaccine, an invaluable gift for children. Clin Transl Immunol 3: e28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4237031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25505956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang L, Jiang H, Tian X, Xia X, Huang T, 2021. Epidemiological characteristics of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Yunnan Province, China, 2008–2019. BMC Infect Dis 21: 751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8336324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34348655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi S. et al., 2016. Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China: Modeling epidemic dynamics of enterovirus serotypes and implications for vaccination. PLoS Med 13: e1001958.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4755668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26882540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh WM, Bogich T, Siegel K, Jin J, Chong EY, Tan CY, Chen MI, Horby P, Cook AR, 2016. The epidemiology of hand, foot and mouth disease in Asia: A systematic review and analysis. Pediatr Infect Dis J 35: e285–e300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5130063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27273688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu H, Xue M, Wu C, Lu Q, Ding Z, Wang X, Fu T, Yang K, Lin J, 2022. Trend of hand, foot, and mouth disease from 2010 to 2021 and estimation of the reduction in enterovirus 71 infection after vaccine use in Zhejiang Province, China. PLoS One 17: e0274421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9488823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36126038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang B, Wu P, Wu JT, Lau EH, Leung GM, Yu H, Cowling BJ, 2015. Seroprevalence of enterovirus 71 antibody among children in China: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Pediatr Infect Dis J 34: 1399–1406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4718881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26368058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chou AH. et al., 2012. Immunological evaluation and comparison of different EV71 vaccine candidates. Clin Dev Immunol 2012: 831282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3447357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23008736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng X. et al., 2015. A novel recombinant lineage’s contribution to the outbreak of coxsackievirus A6-associated hand, foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, China, 2012–2013. Sci Rep 5: 11700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4485158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26121916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu Y, Sun Q, Liu B, Xu H, Wang Y, Zhu W, Pan L, Zhu L, 2016. Epidemiological characteristics and pathogens attributable to hand, foot, and mouth disease in Shanghai, 2008–2013. J Infect Dev Ctries 10: 612–618.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27367010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge Y, Zheng Y, Pan H, Mao S, Li Y, Xia A, Zhu Q, Hu J, Zeng M, 2015. Epidemiological surveillance of hand, foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, 2010–2014. Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi 53: 676–683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26757968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J. et al., 2018. Epidemiological and serological surveillance of hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Shanghai, China, 2012–2016. Emerg Microbes Infect 7: 8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5837173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29362406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo SH, Huang YC, Huang CG, Tsao KC, Li WC, Hsieh YC, Chiu CH, Lin TY, 2011. Clinical and epidemiologic features of coxsackievirus A6 infection in children in northern Taiwan between 2004 and 2009. J Microbiol Immunol Infect 44: 252–257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21524960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben-Chetrit E, Wiener-Well Y, Shulman LM, Cohen MJ, Elinav H, Sofer D, Feldman I, Marva E, Wolf DG, 2014. Coxsackievirus A6-related hand foot and mouth disease: Skin manifestations in a cluster of adult patients. J Clin Virol 59: 201–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24457116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dowell SF, 2001. Seasonal variation in host susceptibility and cycles of certain infectious diseases. Emerg Infect Dis 7: 369–374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2631809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11384511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang LY, Tsao KC, Hsia SH, Shih SR, Huang CG, Chan WK, Hsu KH, Fang TY, Huang YC, Lin TY, 2004. Transmission and clinical features of enterovirus 71 infections in household contacts in Taiwan. JAMA 291: 222–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14722149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang HL. et al., 2012. The association between enterovirus 71 infections and meteorological parameters in Taiwan. PLoS One 7: e46845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3465260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23071650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei S-H, Huang Y-P, Liu M-C, Tsou T-P, Lin H-C, Lin T-L, Tsai C-Y, Chao Y-N, Chang L-Y, Hsu C-M, 2011. An outbreak of coxsackievirus A6 hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with onychomadesis in Taiwan, 2010. BMC Infect Dis 11: 346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3297538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22168544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flett K. et al., 2012. Hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus a6. Emerg Infect Dis 18: 1702–1704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3471644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23017893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di B. et al., 2014. Circulation of coxsackievirus A6 in hand-foot-mouth disease in Guangzhou, 2010–2012. Virol J 11: 157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4169826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25178398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Losada M, Arenas M, Galán JC, Palero F, González-Candelas F, 2015. Recombination in viruses: Mechanisms, methods of study, and evolutionary consequences. Infect Genet Evol 30: 296–307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7106159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25541518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cobbin JCA, Britton PN, Burrell R, Thosar D, Selvakumar K, Eden J-S, Jones CA, Holmes EC, 2018. A complex mosaic of enteroviruses shapes community-acquired hand, foot and mouth disease transmission and evolution within a single hospital. Virus Evol 4: vey020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6047454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30026965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaidis M, Mimouli K, Kyriakopoulou Z, Tsimpidis M, Tsakogiannis D, Markoulatos P, Amoutzias GD, 2019. Large-scale genomic analysis reveals recurrent patterns of intertypic recombination in human enteroviruses. Virology 526: 72–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30366300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minor P, 2009. Vaccine-derived poliovirus (VDPV): Impact on poliomyelitis eradication. Vaccine 27: 2649–2652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19428874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y. et al., 2009. An outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease associated with subgenotype C4 of human enterovirus 71 in Shandong, China. J Clin Virol 44: 262–267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19269888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Y. et al., 2020. Genetic recombination in fast-spreading coxsackievirus A6 variants: A potential role in evolution and pathogenicity. Virus Evol 6: veaa048.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8597624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34804589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempf BJ, Peersen OB, Barton DJ, 2016. Poliovirus polymerase Leu420 facilitates RNA recombination and ribavirin resistance. J Virol 90: 8410–8421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5021434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27412593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodman A, Lee KM, Janissen R, Gong YN, Dekker NH, Shih SR, Cameron CE, 2019. Predicting intraserotypic recombination in enterovirus 71. J Virol 93: e02057-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6364027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30487277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau SKP. et al., 2018. Molecular epidemiology of coxsackievirus A6 circulating in Hong Kong reveals common neurological manifestations and emergence of novel recombinant groups. J Clin Virol 108: 43–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30237097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W-P. et al., 2015. Fourteen types of co-circulating recombinant enterovirus were associated with hand, foot, and mouth disease in children from Wenzhou, China. J Clin Virol 70: 29–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26305816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S-H. et al., 2018. Divergent pathogenic properties of circulating coxsackievirus A6 associated with emerging hand, foot, and mouth disease. J Virol 92: e00303-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5952127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29563294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puenpa J. et al., 2016. Molecular epidemiology and the evolution of human coxsackievirus A6. J Gen Virol 97: 3225–3231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27692044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Z. et al., 2018. Genetic characterization and molecular epidemiological analysis of novel enterovirus EV-B80 in China. Emerg Microbes Infect 7: 193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6258725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30482903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muslin C, Mac Kain A, Bessaud M, Blondel B, Delpeyroux F, 2019. Recombination in enteroviruses, a multi-step modular evolutionary process. Viruses 11: 859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6784155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31540135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volle R. et al., 2019. High permissiveness for genetic exchanges between enteroviruses of species A, including enterovirus 71, favors evolution through intertypic recombination in Madagascar. J Virol 93: e01667-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6401452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30602612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu H. et al., 2020. A novel interspecies recombinant enterovirus (enterovirus A120) isolated from a case of acute flaccid paralysis in China. Emerg Microbes Infect 9: 1733–1743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32672504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujimoto T. et al., 2012. Hand, foot, and mouth disease caused by coxsackievirus A6, Japan, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis 18: 337–339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3310456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22304983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan H, Wang J, Wang C, Yang M, Liu L, Yang G, Ma X, 2015. Etiology of multiple non-EV71 and non-CVA16 enteroviruses associated with hand, foot and mouth disease in Jinan, China, 2009–June 2013. PLoS One 10: e0142733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4642993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26562154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao X. et al., 2015. Enterovirus spectrum from the active surveillance of hand foot and mouth disease patients under the clinical trial of inactivated enterovirus A71 vaccine in Jiangsu, China, 2012–2013. J Med Virol 87: 2009–2017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26010334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji H, Fan H, Lu PX, Zhang XF, Ai J, Shi C, Huo X, Bao CJ, Shan J, Jin Y, 2019. Surveillance for severe hand, foot, and mouth disease from 2009 to 2015 in Jiangsu province: Epidemiology, etiology, and disease burden. BMC Infect Dis 19: 79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6341624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30669973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M, Su L, Cao L, Zhong H, Dong N, Dong Z, Xu J, 2015. Genotypes of the enterovirus causing hand foot and mouth disease in Shanghai, China, 2012–2013. PLoS One 10: e0138514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4580587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26398767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu PY. et al., 2011. Spatiotemporal phylogenetic analysis and molecular characterization of coxsackievirus A4. Infect Genet Evol 11: 1426–1435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21635970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu YF, Yang F, Du J, Dong J, Zhang T, Wu ZQ, Xue Y, Jin Q, 2011. Complete genome analysis of coxsackievirus A2, A4, A5, and A10 strains isolated from hand, foot, and mouth disease patients in China revealing frequent recombination of human enterovirus A. J Clin Microbiol 49: 2426–2434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3147834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21543560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F, Zhang T, Hu Y, Wang X, Du J, Li Y, Sun S, Sun X, Li Z, Jin Q, 2011. Survey of enterovirus infections from hand, foot and mouth disease outbreak in China, 2009. Virol J 8: 508.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3227625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22054534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li JS, Dong XG, Qin M, Xie ZP, Gao HC, Yang JY, Yang XX, Li DD, Li J, Duan ZJ, 2015. Outbreak of febrile illness caused by coxsackievirus A4 in a nursery school in Beijing, China. Virol J 12: 92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4495935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26084565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puenpa J, Mauleekoonphairoj J, Linsuwanon P, Suwannakarn K, Chieochansin T, Korkong S, Theamboonlers A, Poovorawan Y, 2014. Prevalence and characterization of enterovirus infections among pediatric patients with hand foot mouth disease, herpangina and influenza like illness in Thailand, 2012. PLoS One 9: e98888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4041783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24887237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen P, Wang H, Tao Z, Xu A, Lin X, Zhou N, Wang P, Wang Q, 2018. Multiple transmission chains of coxsackievirus A4 co-circulating in China and neighboring countries in recent years: Phylogenetic and spatiotemporal analyses based on virological surveillance. Mol Phylogenet Evol 118: 23–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28942015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji T. et al., 2019. Emerging recombination of the C2 sub-genotype of HFMD-associated CV-A4 is persistently and extensively circulating in China. Sci Rep 9: 13668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6754396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31541120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y. et al., 2013. Complete genome analysis of the C4 subgenotype strains of enterovirus 71: Predominant recombination C4 viruses persistently circulating in China for 14 years. PLoS One 8: e56341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3575343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23441179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin CH, Wang YB, Chen SH, Hsiung CA, Lin CY, 2015. Precise genotyping and recombination detection of enterovirus. BMC Genomics 16 (Suppl 12): S8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4682392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26678286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Wu S, Xiong Y, Li T, Wen Z, Yan M, Qin K, Liu Y, Wu J, 2014. Co-circulation and genomic recombination of coxsackievirus A16 and enterovirus 71 during a large outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Central China. PLoS One 9: e96051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4002479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24776922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>