<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39117819</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0065-2598</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>1448</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advances in experimental medicine and biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Exp Med Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cytokine Storm Syndrome Associated with Hemorrhagic Fever and Other Viruses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>249</StartPage><EndPage>267</EndPage><MedlinePgn>249-267</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/978-3-031-59815-9_17</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A wide variety of infections can trigger cytokine storm syndromes including those caused by bacteria, viruses, fungi and parasites. The most frequent viral trigger is Epstein-.Barr virus which is covered in Chapter 16. CSS associated with COVID-19 is also discussed separately (Chapter 22). This chapter will focus on other viruses including the hemorrhagic fever viruses, influenza, parainfluenza, adenovirus, parvovirus, hepatitis viruses, measles, mumps, rubella, enterovirus, parechovirus, rotavirus, human metapneumovirus and human T-lymphotropic virus. The published literature consists of many single case reports and moderate-sized case series reporting CSS, in most circumstances meeting the 2004 diagnostic criteria for hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis (HLH). There is no published clinical trial evidence specifically for management of HLH associated with these viruses. In some situations, patients received supportive therapy and blood product transfusions only but in most cases, they were treated with one or more of intravenous corticosteroids, intravenous immunoglobulin and/or etoposide. These were successful in many patients although in significant numbers progression of infection to CSS was associated with mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sen</LastName><ForeName>Ethan S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Consultant in Paediatric Rheumatology, Great North Children's Hospital, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramanan</LastName><ForeName>A V</ForeName><Initials>AV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Consultant in Paediatric Rheumatology, Bristol Royal Hospital for Children, Bristol, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Exp Med Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0121103</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0065-2598</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000080424" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cytokine Release Syndrome</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051359" MajorTopicYN="N">Lymphohistiocytosis, Hemophagocytic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006482" MajorTopicYN="N">Hemorrhagic Fevers, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adenovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Congo hemorrhagic fever</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Crimean</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dengue fever</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hepatitis viruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human T-lymphotropic virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human metapneumovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Measles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mumps</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parainfluenza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parechovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parvovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rotavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rubella</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viral hemorrhagic fever</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39117819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-59815-9_17</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sen ES, Clarke SL, Ramanan AV. Macrophage activation syndrome. Indian J Pediatr. 2016;83:248–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26400031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-015-1877-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen ES, Steward CG, Ramanan AV. Diagnosing haemophagocytic syndrome. Arch Dis Child. 2017;102:279–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27831908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2016-310772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janka G, Imashuku S, Elinder G, Schneider M, Henter JI. Infection- and malignancy-associated hemophagocytic syndromes. Secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. 1998;12:435–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9561911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0889-8588(05)70521-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maakaroun NR, Moanna A, Jacob JT, Albrecht H. Viral infections associated with haemophagocytic syndrome. Rev Med Virol. 2010;20:93–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20127750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7169125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Viral Hemorrhagic Fevers (VHFs). (2021). https://www.cdc.gov/vhf/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. Haemorrhagic fevers, Viral. (2022). http://www.emro.who.int/health-topics/haemorrhagic-fevers-viral/introduction.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. Health topics. (2022). https://www.who.int/health-topics/ .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cascio A, Pernice LM, Barberi G, Delfino D, Biondo C, Beninati C, Mancuso G, Rodriguez-Morales AJ, Iaria C. Secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in zoonoses. A systematic review. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2012;16:1324–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23104648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Update on emerging infections from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Fatal hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with locally acquired dengue virus infection-New Mexico and Texas, 2012. Ann Emerg Med. 2014;64:55–7; discussion 58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ab-Rahman HA, Wong PF, Rahim H, Abd-Jamil J, Tan KK, Sulaiman S, Lum CS, Syed-Omar SF, AbuBakar S. Dengue death with evidence of hemophagocytic syndrome and dengue virus infection in the bone marrow. Springerplus. 2015;4:665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26558168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4630261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40064-015-1463-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ab-Rahman HA, Rahim H, AbuBakar S, Wong PF. Macrophage activation syndrome-associated markers in severe dengue. Int J Med Sci. 2016;13:179–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26941578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4773282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7150/ijms.13680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arshad U, Ahmad SQ, Khan F. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with dengue infection. Hematol Oncol Stem Cell Ther. 2015;8:189–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25921404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hemonc.2015.03.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung SM, Song JY, Kim W, Choi MJ, Jeon JH, Kang S, Jung E, Noh JY, Cheong HJ, Kim WJ. Dengue-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in an adult: a case report and literature review. Medicine. 2017;96:e6159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28225498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5569431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000006159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Koninck AS, Dierick J, Steyaert S, Taelman P. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis and dengue infection: rare case report. Acta Clin Belg. 2014;69:210–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24820925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1179/2295333714Y.0000000019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray S, Kundu S, Saha M, Chakrabarti P. Hemophagocytic syndrome in classic dengue Fever. J Global Infect Dis. 2011;3:399–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0974-777X.91068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellis EM, Sharp TM, Perez-Padilla J, Gonzalez L, Poole-Smith BK, Lebo E, Baker C, Delorey MJ, Torres-Velasquez B, Ochoa E, Rivera-Garcia B, Diaz-Pinto H, Clavell L, Puig-Ramos A, Janka GE, Tomashek KM. Incidence and risk factors for developing dengue-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in Puerto Rico, 2008–2013. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2016;10:e0004939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27556807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4996422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain D, Singh T. Dengue virus related hemophagocytosis: a rare case report. Hematology (Amsterdam, Netherlands). 2008;13:286–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18854091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jasmine YS, Lee SL, Kan FK. Infection associated haemophagocytic syndrome in severe dengue infection – a case series in a district hospital. Med J Malaysia. 2017;72:62–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28255145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi R, Phatarpekar A, Currimbhoy Z, Desai M. Haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: a case series from Mumbai. Ann Trop Paediatr. 2011;31:135–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21575318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1179/1465328111Y.0000000009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapdi M, Shah I. Dengue and haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Scand J Infect Dis. 2012;44:708–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22264033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/00365548.2011.652667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kobayashi K, Hikone M, Sakamoto N, Iwabuchi S, Kashiura M, Takasaki T, Fujita H, Ohnishi K. Dengue-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in a Japanese traveler: a case report. J Travel Med. 2015;22:64–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25159130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jtm.12158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koshy M, Mishra AK, Agrawal B, Kurup AR, Hansdak SG. Dengue fever complicated by hemophagocytosis. Oxf Med Case Rep. 2016;2016:121–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/omcr/omw043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krithika MV, Amboiram P, Latha SM, Ninan B, Suman FR, Scott J. Neonate with haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis secondary to dengue infection: a case report. Trop Dr. 2017;47:253–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakhotia M, Pahadiya HR, Gandhi R, Prajapati GR, Choudhary A. Stuck with pancytopenia in dengue fever: evoke for hemophagocytic syndrome. Indian J Crit Care Med. 2016;20:55–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26955219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4759997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0972-5229.173695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu PL, Hsiao HH, Tsai JJ, Chen TC, Feng MC, Chen TP, Lin SF. Dengue virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome and dyserythropoiesis: a case report. Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2005;21:34–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15754587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1607-551X(09)70274-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra S, Bhattacharyya R. Hemophagocytic syndrome in severe dengue fever: a rare presentation. Indian J Hematol Blood Transfus. 2014;30:97–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25332549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12288-013-0273-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>My LT, le Lien B, Hsieh WC, Imamura T, Anh TN, Anh PN, Hung NT, Tseng FC, Chi CY, Dao NT, Le DT, le Thinh Q, Tung TT, Imashuku S, Thuong TC, Su IJ. Comprehensive analyses and characterization of haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in Vietnamese children. Br J Haematol. 2010;148:301–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19863536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.2009.07957.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal P, Giri PP, Ramanan AV. Dengue associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: a case series. Indian Pediatr. 2014;51:496–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24986293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pongtanakul B, Narkbunnam N, Veerakul G, Sanpakit K, Viprakasit V, Tanphaichitr VT, Suvatte V. Dengue hemorrhagic fever in patients with thalassemia. J Med Assoc Thailand = Chotmaihet Thangphaet. 2005;88(Suppl 8):S80–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raju S, Kalyanaraman S, Swaminathan K, Nisha A, Praisid S. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis syndrome in dengue hemorrhagic fever. Indian J Pediatr. 2014;81:1381–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24728701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-014-1425-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramanathan M, Duraisamy G. Haemophagocytosis in dengue haemorrhagic fever: a case report. Ann Acad Med Singap. 1991;20:803–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1803975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray U, Dutta S, Mondal S, Bandyopadhyay S. Severe dengue due to secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: a case study. IDCases. 2017;8:50–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28409119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5388930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.idcr.2017.03.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribeiro E, Kassab S, Pistone T, Receveur MC, Fialon P, Malvy D. Primary dengue fever associated with hemophagocytic syndrome: a report of three imported cases, Bordeaux, France. Intern Med (Tokyo, Japan). 2014;53:899–902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.53.1108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharp TM, Gaul L, Muehlenbachs A, Hunsperger E, Bhatnagar J, Lueptow R, Santiago GA, Munoz-Jordan JL, Blau DM, Ettestad P, Bissett JD, Ledet SC, Zaki SR, Tomashek KM. Fatal hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with locally acquired dengue virus infection – New Mexico and Texas, 2012. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2014;63:49–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24452132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5779429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soler Rosario Y, Garcia R, Fernandez Sein A. Dengue virus associated hemophagocytic syndrome in children: a case report. Boletin de la Asociacion Medica de Puerto Rico. 2010;102:49–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20853575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srichaikul T, Punyagupta S, Kanchanapoom T, Chanokovat C, Likittanasombat K, Leelasiri A. Hemophagocytic syndrome in Dengue hemorrhagic fever with severe multiorgan complications. J Med Assoc Thailand = Chotmaihet Thangphaet. 2008;91:104–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan LH, Lum LC, Omar SF, Kan FK. Hemophagocytosis in dengue: comprehensive report of six cases. J Clin Virol. 2012;55:79–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22789140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2012.06.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan Jamaludin WF, Periyasamy P, Wan Mat WR, Abdul Wahid SF. Dengue infection associated hemophagocytic syndrome: therapeutic interventions and outcome. J Clin Virol. 2015;69:91–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26209387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2015.06.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshifuji K, Oshina T, Sonokawa S, Noguchi Y, Suzuki S, Tanaka K, Kumagai T. Domestic dengue infection with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis successfully treated by early steroid therapy. [Rinsho ketsueki] Jpn J Clin Hematol. 2016;57:864–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hein N, Bergara GH, Moura NB, Cardoso DM, Hirose M, Ferronato AE, Pastorino AC, Lo DS, Gilio AE. Dengue fever as a cause of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Autopsy Case Rep. 2015;5:33–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4322/acr.2015.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal G, Wazir S, Sachdeva A, Kumar S. Primary dengue infection triggered haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a neonate. BMJ Case Rep. 2020;13:e236881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33384343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7780535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bcr-2020-236881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takkinsatian P, Sowithayasakul P, Prommalikit O. Dengue associated haemophagocytic lymphohystiocytosis: an often-missed complication of a common infection. Med J Malaysia. 2020;75:588–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32918433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnappa A, Munusamy J, Ray S, Rameshbabu M, Bhatia P, Roy PS, Sundaram V, Kumar P. Neonatal dengue with HLH: perks of early diagnosis and management. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2021;43:e770–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32675555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0000000000001881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaitanya K, Karanam S, Kumar K. Dengue Associated Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis. Indian J Pediatr. 2020;87:237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31900851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-019-03158-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharya D, Angurana SK, Nallasamy K, Iyer R, Jayashree M. Severe dengue and associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in PICU. Indian J Pediatr. 2019;86:1094–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31353429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-019-03040-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan FK, Tan CC, Von Bahr Greenwood T, Khalid KE, Supramaniam P, Hed Myrberg I, Tan LH, Henter JI. Dengue infection complicated by Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis: experiences from 180 patients with severe dengue. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;70:2247–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31188423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciz499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giang HTN, Banno K, Minh LHN, Trinh LT, Loc LT, Eltobgy A, Tai LLT, Khan A, Tuan NH, Reda Y, Samsom M, Nam NT, Huy NT, Hirayama K. Dengue hemophagocytic syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis on epidemiology, clinical signs, outcomes, and risk factors. Rev Med Virol. 2018;28:e2005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30109914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.2005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betancur JF, Navarro EP, Echeverry A, Moncada PA, Canas CA, Tobon GJ. Hyperferritinemic syndrome: still’s disease and catastrophic antiphospholipid syndrome triggered by fulminant Chikungunya infection: a case report of two patients. Clin Rheumatol. 2015;34:1989–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26233722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-015-3040-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bicakci Z, Tavil B, Tezer H, Olcay L. Hemophagocytosis in a case with Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever and an overview of possible pathogenesis with current evidence. Turk J Pediatr. 2013;55:344–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24217086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erduran E, Cakir M. Reactive hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis and Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever. Int J Infect Dis. 2010;14:e349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20034830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2009.08.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tasdelen Fisgin N, Fisgin T, Tanyel E, Doganci L, Tulek N, Guler N, Duru F. Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever: five patients with hemophagocytic syndrome. Am J Hematol. 2008;83:73–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17597475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajh.20969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gayretli Aydin ZG, Yesilbas O, Reis GP, Guven B. The first pediatric case of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis secondary to Crimean-Congo haemorrhagic fever successfully treated with therapeutic plasma exchange accompanying ribavirin and intravenous immunoglobulin. J Clin Apher. 2021;36:780–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34061376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jca.21915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakut N, Kepenekli E, Dogru O. Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Rev Soc Bras Med Trop. 2021;54:e0438-2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33681917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8008853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0037-8682-0438-2020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JJ, Chung IJ, Shin DH, Cho SH, Cho D, Ryang DW, Khan AS, Kim HJ. Hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome presenting with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Emerg Infect Dis. 2002;8:209–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11897077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2732452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid0802.010299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao Q, Luo L, Gao L, Xiong W, Nie Q, Wu D. Hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome presenting as leukemoid reaction and hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. J Med Virol. 2022;94:433–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34491571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Wang C, Wu L, Jiang X, Zhang S, Jing F. Hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome with secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in West China: a case report. BMC Infect Dis. 2019;19:492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31164087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6549348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4122-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shastri B, Kofman A, Hennenfent A, Klena JD, Nicol S, Graziano JC, Morales-Betoulle M, Cannon D, Maradiaga A, Tran A, Ramdeen SK. Domestically acquired Seoul virus causing hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis-Washington, DC, 2018. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2019;6:ofz404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31660366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6790396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofz404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Jeong G, Lim JH, Kim H, Park SW, Lee WJ, Jun JB. Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome presenting with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Infect Chemother. 2016;48:338–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27883371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5204015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3947/ic.2016.48.4.338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L, Xu YZ, Wu XM, Ge HF, Feng JX, Chen MF, Lv DQ, Li BL, Lin J. A rare fatal case of a novel bunyavirus-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. J Infect Dev Ctries. 2016;10:533–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27249531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3855/jidc.7268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakano A, Ogawa H, Nakanishi Y, Fujita H, Mahara F, Shiogama K, Tsutsumi Y, Takeichi T. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a fatal case of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome. Intern Med (Tokyo, Japan). 2017;56:1597–602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.56.6904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawaguchi T, Umekita K, Yamanaka A, Hara S, Yamaguchi T, Inoue E, Okayama A. Corticosteroids may have negative effects on the management of patients with severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome: a case-control study. Viruses. 2021;13:785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33925061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8145003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v13050785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzman MG, Harris E. Dengue. Lancet. 2015;385:453–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25230594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60572-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan S, Jamdar SF, Alalowi M, Al Ageel Al Beaiji SM. Dengue virus: a global human threat: review of literature. J Int Soc Prev Community Dent. 2016;6:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27011925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4784057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2231-0762.175416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kularatne SA. Dengue fever. BMJ. 2015;351:h4661.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26374064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.h4661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajapakse S, Ranasinghe C, Rodrigo C. Corticosteroid therapy in dengue infection- opinions of junior doctors. J Global Infect Dis. 2010;2:199–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0974-777X.62861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tam DT, Ngoc TV, Tien NT, Kieu NT, Thuy TT, Thanh LT, Tam CT, Truong NT, Dung NT, Qui PT, Hien TT, Farrar JJ, Simmons CP, Wolbers M, Wills BA. Effects of short-course oral corticosteroid therapy in early dengue infection in Vietnamese patients: a randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;55:1216–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22865871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3466094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cis655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F, Kramer CV. Corticosteroids for dengue infection. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;2016:CD003488.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajapakse S, Rodrigo C, Maduranga S, Rajapakse AC. Corticosteroids in the treatment of dengue shock syndrome. Infect Drug Resist. 2014;7:137–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24899817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4038529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S55380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Premaratna R, Jayasinghe KG, Liyanaarachchi EW, Weerasinghe OM, Pathmeswaran A, de Silva HJ. Effect of a single dose of methyl prednisolone as rescue medication for patients who develop hypotensive dengue shock syndrome during the febrile phase: a retrospective observational study. Int J Infect Dis. 2011;15:e433–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21530348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2011.03.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandara SMR, Herath HMMT. Effectiveness of corticosteroid in the treatment of dengue – a systemic review. Heliyon. 2018;4:e00816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30258999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6151849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2018.e00816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiwanitkit V. Haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis and dengue. Acta Clin Belg. 2015;70:72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25649532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1179/2295333714Y.0000000040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramachandran B, Balasubramanian S, Abhishek N, Ravikumar KG, Ramanan AV. Profile of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in children in a tertiary care hospital in India. Indian Pediatr. 2011;48:31–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20972297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13312-011-0020-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van de Weg CA, Huits RM, Pannuti CS, Brouns RM, van den Berg RW, van den Ham HJ, Martina BE, Osterhaus AD, Netea MG, Meijers JC, van Gorp EC, Kallas EG. Hyperferritinaemia in dengue virus infected patients is associated with immune activation and coagulation disturbances. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014;8:e3214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25299654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4191960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martina BE, Koraka P, Osterhaus AD. Dengue virus pathogenesis: an integrated view. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2009;22:564–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19822889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2772360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00035-09</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhat CS, Shetty R, Sundaram B, Ramanan AV. Immunomodulatory therapy in dengue: need for clinical trials and evidence base. Arch Dis Child. 2022;108:451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35680407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2022-324100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBride A, Mehta P, Rivino L, Ramanan AV, Yacoub S. Targeting hyperinflammation in infection: can we harness the COVID-19 therapeutics momentum to end the dengue drugs drought? Lancet Microbe. 2021;2:e277–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33899037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8057720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00087-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dilber E, Cakir M, Erduran E, Koksal I, Bahat E, Mutlu M, Celtik AY, Okten A. High-dose methylprednisolone in children with Crimean-Congo haemorrhagic fever. Trop Dr. 2010;40:27–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erduran E, Bahadir A, Palanci N, Gedik Y. The treatment of crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever with high-dose methylprednisolone, intravenous immunoglobulin, and fresh frozen plasma. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2013;35:e19–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23018575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0b013e3182706444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McElroy AK, Erickson BR, Flietstra TD, Rollin PE, Nichol ST, Towner JS, Spiropoulou CF. Ebola hemorrhagic fever: novel biomarker correlates of clinical outcome. J Infect Dis. 2014;210:558–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24526742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4172044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Ven AJ, Netea MG, van der Meer JW, de Mast Q. Ebola virus disease has features of Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis syndrome. Front Med (Lausanne). 2015;2:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25699258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cron RQ, Behrens EM, Shakoory B, Ramanan AV, Chatham WW. Does viral hemorrhagic fever represent reactive hemophagocytic syndrome? J Rheumatol. 2015;42:1078–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26136549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3899/jrheum.150108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samransamruajkit R, Hiranrat T, Chieochansin T, Sritippayawan S, Deerojanawong J, Prapphal N, Poovorawan Y. Prevalence, clinical presentations and complications among hospitalized children with influenza pneumonia. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2008;61:446–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19050351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7883/yoken.JJID.2008.446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beutel G, Wiesner O, Eder M, Hafer C, Schneider AS, Kielstein JT, Kuhn C, Heim A, Ganzenmuller T, Kreipe HH, Haverich A, Tecklenburg A, Ganser A, Welte T, Hoeper MM. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome as a major contributor to death in patients with 2009 influenza A (H1N1) infection. Crit Care (London, England). 2011;15:R80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/cc10073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Influenza (Flu). (2022). https://www.cdc.gov/flu</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Human Parainfluenza viruses (HPIVs). (2019).. https://www.cdc.gov/parainfluenza</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Adenoviruses. (2019). https://www.cdc.gov/adenovirus</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Echavarría M. Adenoviruses in immunocompromised hosts. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2008;21:704–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18854488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2570151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00052-07</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu J, Söderlund-Venermo M, Young NS. Human Parvoviruses. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2017;30:43–113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27806994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.00040-16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Viral hepatitis. (2021). https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inman RD, Hodge M, Johnston ME, Wright J, Heathcote J. Arthritis, vasculitis, and cryoglobulinemia associated with relapsing hepatitis A virus infection. Ann Intern Med. 1986;105:700–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3021038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-105-5-700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schiff ER. Atypical clinical manifestations of hepatitis A. Vaccine. 1992;10(Suppl 1):S18–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1475999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0264-410X(92)90534-Q</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iaria C, Leonardi MS, Buda A, Toro ML, Cascio A. Measles and secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012;18:1529. author reply 1529-1530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22931858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3437716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1809.120235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komatsuda A, Chubachi A, Miura AB. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome due to measles accompanied by acute respiratory failure. Intern Med (Tokyo, Japan). 1995;34:203–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.34.203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Measles (Rubeola). (2020). https://www.cdc.gov/measles</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiraiwa K, Obara K, Sato A. Mumps virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome. Emerg Infect Dis. 2005;11:343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15759337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3320431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1102.040993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Mumps. (2021). https://www.cdc.gov/mumps</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Rubella (German measles, three day measles). (2020). https://www.cdc.gov/rubella</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom SC, Rossen JW, van Furth AM, Obihara CC. Enterovirus and parechovirus infection in children: a brief overview. Eur J Pediatr. 2016;175:1023–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27156106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4930465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-016-2725-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuzurihara SS, Ao K, Hara T, Tanaka F, Mori M, Kikuchi N, Kai S, Yokota S. Human parechovirus-3 infection in nine neonates and infants presenting symptoms of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. J Infect Chemother. 2013;19:144–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22569793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-012-0420-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vergnano S, Kadambari S, Whalley K, Menson EN, Martinez-Alier N, Cooper M, Sanchez E, Heath PT, Lyall H. Characteristics and outcomes of human parechovirus infection in infants (2008-2012). Eur J Pediatr. 2015;174:919–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25573462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-014-2483-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford SE, Ramani S, Tate JE, Parashar UD, Svensson L, Hagbom M, Franco MA, Greenberg HB, O’Ryan M, Kang G, Desselberger U, Estes MK. Rotavirus infection. Nat Rev Dis Prim. 2017;3:17083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29119972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2017.83</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafagati N, Williams J. Human metapneumovirus – what we know now. F1000Research. 2018;7:135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29744035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5795268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12688/f1000research.12625.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura D, Inoue S, Kawahara Y, Mori M, Yamagata T. Hypercytokinemia with hemophagocytic syndrome due to human metapneumovirus. Pediatr Int. 2018;60:974–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30345702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ped.13665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quaresma JA, Yoshikawa GT, Koyama RV, Dias GA, Fujihara S, Fuzii HT. HTLV-1, immune response and autoimmunity. Viruses. 2015;8:5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26712781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4728565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v8010005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potter MN, Foot AB, Oakhill A. Influenza A and the virus associated haemophagocytic syndrome: cluster of three cases in children with acute leukaemia. J Clin Pathol. 1991;44:297–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2030147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">496902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jcp.44.4.297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ando M, Miyazaki E, Hiroshige S, Ashihara Y, Okubo T, Ueo M, Fukami T, Sugisaki K, Tsuda T, Ohishi K, Yoshitake S, Noguchi T, Kumamoto T. Virus associated hemophagocytic syndrome accompanied by acute respiratory failure caused by influenza A (H3N2). Intern Med (Tokyo, Japan). 2006;45:1183–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.45.1736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe T, Okazaki E, Shibuya H. Influenza A virus-associated encephalopathy with haemophagocytic syndrome. Eur J Pediatr. 2003;162:799–800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12937973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-003-1288-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mou SS, Nakagawa TA, Riemer EC, McLean TW, Hines MH, Shetty AK. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis complicating influenza A infection. Pediatrics. 2006;118:e216–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16785288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2005-1861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Zhang J, Huang K, Li KS, Yuen KY, Guan Y, Chen H, Ng WF. Systemic infection of avian influenza A virus H5N1 subtype in humans. Hum Pathol. 2009;40:735–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19121843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7112124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2008.08.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>To KF, Chan PK, Chan KF, Lee WK, Lam WY, Wong KF, Tang NL, Tsang DN, Sung RY, Buckley TA, Tam JS, Cheng AF. Pathology of fatal human infection associated with avian influenza A H5N1 virus. J Med Virol. 2001;63:242–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11170064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/1096-9071(200103)63:3&lt;242::AID-JMV1007&gt;3.0.CO;2-N</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harms PW, Schmidt LA, Smith LB, Newton DW, Pletneva MA, Walters LL, Tomlins SA, Fisher-Hubbard A, Napolitano LM, Park PK, Blaivas M, Fantone J, Myers JL, Jentzen JM. Autopsy findings in eight patients with fatal H1N1 influenza. Am J Clin Pathol. 2010;134:27–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20551263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1309/AJCP35KOZSAVNQZW</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsumi A, Nishida T, Murata M, Terakura S, Shimada K, Saito S, Kobayashi M, Kodaira A, Shibata S, Oda I, Yagi T, Kiyoi H, Matsushita T, Kojima T, Naoe T. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome caused by pandemic swine-origin influenza A (H1N1) in a patient after unrelated bone marrow transplantation. J Clin Exp Hematopathol, Japan. 2011;51:63–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3960/jslrt.51.63</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozdemir H, Ciftci E, Ince EU, Ertem M, Ince E, Dogru U. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus infection. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2011;33:135–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21285906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0b013e3181f46baf</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willekens C, Cornelius A, Guerry MJ, Wacrenier A, Fourrier F. Fulminant hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis induced by pandemic A (H1N1) influenza: a case report. J Med Case Rep. 2011;5:280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21722406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3141719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-5-280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang XY, Ye XW, Feng DX, Han J, Li D, Zhang C. Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis induced by severe pandemic Influenza A (H1N1) 2009 virus infection: a case report. Case Rep Med. 2011;2011:951910.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21559246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3087486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2011/951910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai S, Merritt BY, Chen L, Zhou X, Green LK. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with influenza A (H1N1) infection in a patient with chronic lymphocytic leukemia: an autopsy case report and review of the literature. Ann Diagn Pathol. 2012;16:477–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21724431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anndiagpath.2011.03.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yontem Y, Ilker D, Yesim O, Aysen T, Gulcihan O, Ozgur C, Meral AC, Burcak TG, Bengu D, Esin A, Selim B, Canan V. Analysis of fatal cases of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus infections in pediatric patients with leukemia. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2013;30:437–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23697998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/08880018.2013.796025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casciaro R, Cresta F, Favilli F, Naselli A, De Alessandri A, Minicucci L. Macrophage activation syndrome induced by A/H1N1 influenza in cystic fibrosis. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2014;49:E10–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23401277</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ppul.22778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha B, Omran A, Rong P, Wang W. Report of a fatal pediatric case of Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis associated with pandemic influenza A (H1N1) infection in 2009. Pediatrics and Neonatology. 2015;56:189–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23602384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pedneo.2013.03.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Bahr Greenwood T, Holzgraefe B, Chiang SCC, Wang Y, Tesi B, Bryceson YT, Henter JI. Clinical and laboratory signs of haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with pandemic influenza A (H1N1) infection in patients needing extracorporeal membrane oxygenation: a retrospective observational study. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2021;38:692–701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EJA.0000000000001386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dlela M, Turki O, Bahloul M, Kallel H, Jedidi I, Bouaziz M. Haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis induced by A/H1N1 influenza. Presse Med. 2019;48:576–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31003733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lpm.2019.02.034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulert GS, Zhang M, Fall N, Husami A, Kissell D, Hanosh A, Zhang K, Davis K, Jentzen JM, Napolitano L, Siddiqui J, Smith LB, Harms PW, Grom AA, Cron RQ. Whole-exome sequencing reveals mutations in genes linked to hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis and macrophage activation syndrome in fatal cases of H1N1 influenza. J Infect Dis. 2016;213:1180–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26597256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiv550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong MD, Bach VC, Phan TQ, Vo MH, Tran TT, Nguyen BH, Beld M, Le TP, Truong HK, Nguyen VV, Tran TH, Do QH, Farrar J. Fatal avian influenza A (H5N1) in a child presenting with diarrhea followed by coma. N Engl J Med. 2005;352:686–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15716562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa044307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikebe T, Takata H, Sasaki H, Miyazaki Y, Ohtsuka E, Saburi Y, Ogata M, Shirao K. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis following influenza vaccination in a patient with aplastic anemia undergoing allogeneic bone marrow stem cell transplantation. Int J Hematol, Japan. 2017;105:389–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12185-016-2177-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soliman S, Bakulina A. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis after inactivated influenza vaccination in a Young man complicated by severe rhabdomyolysis. Cureus. 2022;14:e23334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35475089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9018019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chokephaibulkit K, Uiprasertkul M, Puthavathana P, Chearskul P, Auewarakul P, Dowell SF, Vanprapar N. A child with avian influenza A (H5N1) infection. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:162–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15702046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.inf.0000151037.25237.1e</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan PK. Outbreak of avian influenza A(H5N1) virus infection in Hong Kong in 1997. Clin Infect Dis. 2002;34(Suppl 2):S58–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11938498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/338820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng WF, To KF, Lam WW, Ng TK, Lee KC. The comparative pathology of severe acute respiratory syndrome and avian influenza A subtype H5N1–A review. Hum Pathol. 2006;37:381–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16564911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7112039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2006.01.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh SM, Chang SC. Insufficient perforin expression in CD8+ T cells in response to hemagglutinin from avian influenza (H5N1) virus. J Immunol. 2006;176:4530–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16585542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.176.8.4530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peiris JS, Yu WC, Leung CW, Cheung CY, Ng WF, Nicholls JM, Ng TK, Chan KH, Lai ST, Lim WL, Yuen KY, Guan Y. Re-emergence of fatal human influenza A subtype H5N1 disease. Lancet. 2004;363:617–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14987888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7112424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(04)15595-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henter JI, Chow CB, Leung CW, Lau YL. Cytotoxic therapy for severe avian influenza A (H5N1) infection. Lancet. 2006;367:870–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16530581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68232-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henter JI, Samuelsson-Horne A, Aricò M, Egeler RM, Elinder G, Filipovich AH, Gadner H, Imashuku S, Komp D, Ladisch S, Webb D, Janka G, Society H. Treatment of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis with HLH-94 immunochemotherapy and bone marrow transplantation. Blood. 2002;100:2367–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12239144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/blood-2002-01-0172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horai Y, Miyamura T, Takahama S, Sonomoto K, Nakamura M, Ando H, Minami R, Yamamoto M, Suematsu E. Influenza virus B-associated hemophagocytic syndrome and recurrent pericarditis in a patient with systemic lupus erythematosus. Modern Rheumatol/Jpn Rheum Assoc. 2010;20:178–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/s10165-009-0241-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayashree K, Rao S, Kamath N. Influenza B virus triggering macrophage activation syndrome in an infant. Indian J Crit Care Med. 2017;21:802–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29279647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5699014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0972-5229.218137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao J, Pasion J, Sanchez-Petitto G, Law J. Influenza virus B-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Hematol Rep. 2019;11:8268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31579142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6761467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4081/hr.2019.8268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beffermann N, Pilcante J, Sarmiento M. Acquired hemophagocytic syndrome related to parainfluenza virus infection: case report. J Med Case Rep. 2015;9:78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25886447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4422322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13256-015-0552-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy J, Wodell RA, August CS, Bayever E. Adenovirus-related hemophagocytic syndrome after bone marrow transplantation. Bone Marrow Transplant. 1990;6:349–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2291998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seidel MG, Kastner U, Minkov M, Gadner H. IVIG treatment of adenovirus infection-associated macrophage activation syndrome in a two-year-old boy: case report and review of the literature. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2003;20:445–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14631618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08880010390220162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morimoto A, Teramura T, Asazuma Y, Mukoyama A, Imashuku S. Hemophagocytic syndrome associated with severe adenoviral pneumonia: usefulness of real-time polymerase chain reaction for diagnosis. Int J Hematol. 2003;77:295–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12731675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02983789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imashuku S, Ueda I, Teramura T, Mori K, Morimoto A, Sako M, Ishii E. Occurrence of haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis at less than 1 year of age: analysis of 96 patients. Eur J Pediatr. 2005;164:315–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15731905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-005-1636-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klein A, Corazza F, Demulder A, Van Beers D, Ferster A. Recurrent viral associated hemophagocytic syndrome in a child with Langerhans cell histiocytosis. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 1999;21:554–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10598673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00043426-199911000-00022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyama S, Matsunaga T, Fujimi A, Murase K, Kuribayasi K, Sato T, Hirayama Y, Sakamaki S, Kohda K, Niitsu Y. Successful treatment with oral ribavirin of adenovirus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in a stem cell transplantation recipient. [Rinsho ketsueki] Jpn J Clin Hematol. 2005;46:363–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin CI, Yu HH, Lee JH, Wang LC, Lin YT, Yang YH, Chiang BL. Clinical analysis of macrophage activation syndrome in pediatric patients with autoimmune diseases. Clin Rheumatol. 2012;31:1223–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22615046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-012-1998-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosnut FO, Ozcay F, Malbora B, Hizli S, Ozbek N. Severe adenovirus infection associated with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Turk J Haematol. 2014;31:103–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24764742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3996635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4274/Tjh.2013.0218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mellon G, Henry B, Aoun O, Boutolleau D, Laparra A, Mayaux J, Sanson M, Caumes E. Adenovirus related lymphohistiocytic hemophagocytosis: case report and literature review. J Clin Virol. 2016;78:53–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26985594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2016.03.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reardon DA, Roskos R, Hanson CA, Castle V. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome following bone marrow transplantation. Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 1991;13:305–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1665315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00043426-199123000-00010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risdall RJ, McKenna RW, Nesbit ME, Krivit W, Balfour HH, Simmons RL, Brunning RD. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome: a benign histiocytic proliferation distinct from malignant histiocytosis. Cancer. 1979;44:993–1002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">225008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/1097-0142(197909)44:3&lt;993::AID-CNCR2820440329&gt;3.0.CO;2-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz KA, Neglia JP, Smith AR, Ochs HD, Torgerson TR, Kumar A. Familial hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in two brothers with X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2008;51:293–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18421721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pbc.21573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang HY, Xiao M, Yan F, Zhang MR, Zhang Y. Risk factors for the development of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in children with severe adenovirus pneumonia: a single-center retrospective study. Front Pediatr. 2021;9:654002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34660470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8517263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2021.654002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagamatsu K, Takano K, Sakata M, Yanai Y, Katayama O, Honda S, Yoshida N, Kawano R, Imamura T, Ogata M. Successful treatment with cidofovir for disseminated adenovirus infection accompanied by hemophagocytic syndrome and meningitis in an allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation recipient. [Rinsho ketsueki] Jpn J Clin Hematol. 2021;62:251–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demey B, Brault C, Maizel J, Francois C. From upper respiratory symptoms to hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: case report of a human adenovirus infection in haploidentical hematopoietic stem cell transplant recipient. Pathogens. 2021;10:340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33804012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8001405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10030340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otto WR, Behrens EM, Teachey DT, Lamson DM, Barrett DM, Bassiri H, Lambert MP, Mount S, Petrosa WL, Romberg N, Sullivan KE, Topjian AA, Fisher BT, Kajon AE. Human adenovirus 7-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis-like illness: clinical and Virological characteristics in a cluster of five pediatric cases. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;73:e1532–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32866230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa1277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Fay C, Bosdure E, Baravalle-Einaudi M, Stremler-Le Bel N, Dubus JC, Mazenq J. Severe adenovirus pneumonia with hemophagocytic syndrome and respiratory failure. Arch Pediatr. 2020;27:383–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32811705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arcped.2020.07.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Chen X, Tan XR, Liu DH, Li XF, Zhang XX. Adenovirus pneumonia with hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in children: a clinical analysis of 7 children. Zhongguo dang dai er ke za zhi = Chin J Contemp Pediatr. 2020;22:749–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang HY, Li CJ, Long Y, Sun DM, Wang RG, Zhang Y. Clinical features of children with severe adenovirus pneumonia and hemophagocytic syndrome: an analysis of 30 cases. Zhongguo dang dai er ke za zhi = Chin J Contemp Pediatr. 2020;22:744–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal P, Bose N, Poddar A, Chowdhury K, Saha A. Experience with Cidofovir as an adjunctive therapy in a patient of adenovirus-induced macrophage activation syndrome in systemic arthritis. Clin Rheumatol. 2020;39:2449–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32418043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7230034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10067-020-05133-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang FZ, Cai YQ, Tang LF. Adenovirus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in a young child. World J Pediatr. 2020;16:215–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31502024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12519-019-00300-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Censoplano N, Gorga S, Waldeck K, Stillwell T, Rabah-Hammad R, Flori H. Neonatal adenovirus infection complicated by hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis syndrome. Pediatrics. 2018;141:S475–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29610175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2017-2061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lev R, Haim A, Greenberg D, Fruchtman Y. Adenovirus infection as an imitator of hemophagocytic lymphocytosis. Clin Pediatr. 2018;57:600–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0009922817728703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya Z, Ozturk G, Gursel T, Bozdayi G. Spontaneous resolution of hemophagocytic syndrome and disseminated intravascular coagulation associated with parvovirus b19 infection in a previously healthy child. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2005;58:149–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15973005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7883/yoken.JJID.2005.149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larroche C, Scieux C, Honderlick P, Piette AM, Morinet F, Bletry O. Spontaneous resolution of hemophagocytic syndrome associated with acute parvovirus B19 infection and concomitant Epstein-Barr virus reactivation in an otherwise healthy adult. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2002;21:739–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12415473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-002-0793-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutta U, Mittal S, Ratho RK, Das A. Acute liver failure and severe hemophagocytosis secondary to parvovirus B19 infection. Indian J Gastroenterol. 2005;24:118–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16041107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz S, Oren H, Demircioglu F, Firinci F, Korkmaz A, Irken G. Parvovirus B19: a cause for aplastic crisis and hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2006;47:861.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16514614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pbc.20807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermann J, Steinbach D, Lengemann J, Zintl F. Parvovirus B 19 associated hemophagocytic syndrome in a patient with hereditary sperocytosis. Klin Padiatr. 2003;215:270–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14520589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-2003-42662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syruckova Z, Stary J, Sedlacek P, Smisek P, Vavrinec J, Komrska V, Roubalova K, Vandasova J, Sintakova B, Houskova J, Hassan M. Infection-associated hemophagocytic syndrome complicated by infectious lymphoproliferation: a case report. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 1996;13:143–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8721028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/08880019609030804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan C, Asad-Ur-Rahman F, Abusaada K. A rare case of Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis associated with parvovirus B19 infection. Cureus. 2016;8:e897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28018767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5178984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yufu Y, Matsumoto M, Miyamura T, Nishimura J, Nawata H, Ohshima K. Parvovirus B19-associated haemophagocytic syndrome with lymphadenopathy resembling histiocytic necrotizing lymphadenitis (Kikuchi’s disease). Br J Haematol. 1997;96:868–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9074434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2141.1997.d01-2099.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debels L, Reynders M, Cauwelier B, Willandt B, Selleslag D, Snauwaert C. Parvovirus B19-triggered hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with Crohn’s disease. Acta Gastroenterol Belg. 2022;85:1–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cefai E, Caruana D, Sillato MG, Mercieca C. Haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis secondary to parvovirus B19 infection: an unexpected case of multiorgan failure. Br J Hosp Med (London, England). 2022;83:1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12968/hmed.2021.0619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orth HM, Fuchs A, Lübke N, Jensen BO, Luedde T. Recurrent parvovirus B19 viremia resulting in two episodes of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Virol J. 2022;19:107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35752863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9233783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-022-01841-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KT, Hong KT, Kim BK, An HY, Choi JY, Chang YH, Kang HJ. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with parvovirus B19-induced aplastic crisis in a hereditary spherocytosis patient: a case report and literature review. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2022;39:158–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34369269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08880018.2021.1949082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalmuk J, Matar S, Feng G, Kilb E, Lim MY. Parvovirus B19-induced hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: case report and review of the literature. Clin Case Rep. 2019;7:2076–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31788255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6878072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ccr3.2401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aravamudan VM, Er C, Hussain I, Cheong NWW, Chern Hao C, Kuthah N, En-Xian Tan E, Fan BE. A case of parvovirus-related haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with HbH disease. Case Rep Med. 2018;2018:8057045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30675165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6323427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/8057045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zečkanović A, Perovnik M, Jazbec J, Petrovec M, Pokorn M, Kavčič M. Parvovirus B19-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2018;40:e550–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29432306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0000000000001109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirono K, Tsuda H. Parvovirus B19-associated haemophagocytic syndrome in healthy adults. Br J Haematol. 1995;89:923–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7772537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.1995.tb08440.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ardalan MR, Shoja MM, Tubbs RS, Esmaili H, Keyvani H. Postrenal transplant hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis and thrombotic microangiopathy associated with parvovirus b19 infection. Am J Transplant. 2008;8:1340–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18522549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2008.02244.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavera M, Petroni J, Leon L, Minue E, Casadei D. Reactive haemophagocytic syndrome associated with parvovirus B19 in a kidney-pancreas transplant patient. Nefrologia. 2012;32:125–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22294016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsubara K, Uchida Y, Wada T, Iwata A, Yura K, Kamimura K, Nigami H, Fukaya T. Parvovirus B19-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a child with precursor B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia under maintenance chemotherapy. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2011;33:565–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21617562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0b013e3182099a54</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekiguchi Y, Shimada A, Imai H, Wakabayashi M, Sugimoto K, Nakamura N, Sawada T, Komatsu N, Noguchi M. A case of recurrent autoimmune hemolytic anemia during remission associated with acute pure red cell aplasia and hemophagocytic syndrome due to human parvovirus B19 infection successfully treated by steroid pulse therapy with a review of the literature. Int J Clin Exp Pathol. 2014;7:2624–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24966977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4069955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uike N, Miyamura T, Obama K, Takahira H, Sato H, Kozuru M. Parvovirus B19-associated haemophagocytosis in Evans syndrome: aplastic crisis accompanied by severe thrombocytopenia. Br J Haematol. 1993;84:530–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8217805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.1993.tb03113.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayama M, Yoshihara M, Kokabu T, Oguchi H. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with a parvovirus B19 infection during pregnancy. Obstet Gynecol. 2014;124:438–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25004318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/AOG.0000000000000385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishore J, Kishore D. Fatal missed case of hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis co-infected with parvovirus B19 and Epstein-Barr virus in an infant: test hyperferritinaemia early. Indian J Med Microbiol. 2014;32:181–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24713910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0255-0857.129819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sood N, Yadav P. Hemophagocytic syndrome associated with concomitant Klebsiella and Parvovirus B-19 infection. Indian J Pathol Microbiol, India. 2012;55:124–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0377-4929.94886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouphael NG, Talati NJ, Vaughan C, Cunningham K, Moreira R, Gould C. Infections associated with haemophagocytic syndrome. Lancet Infect Dis. 2007;7:814–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18045564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7185531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(07)70290-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramachandra G, Shields L, Brown K, Ramnarayan P. The challenges of prompt identification and resuscitation in children with acute fulminant myocarditis: case series and review of the literature. J Paediatr Child Health. 2010;46:579–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20626579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1754.2010.01799.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsuda H, Maeda Y, Nakagawa K, Nakayama M, Nishimura H, Ishihara A, Miyayama H. Parvovirus B19-associated haemophagocytic syndrome with prominent neutrophilia. Br J Haematol. 1994;86:413–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8199040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.1994.tb04756.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butin M, Mekki Y, Phan A, Billaud G, Di Filippo S, Javouhey E, Cochat P, Belot A. Successful immunotherapy in life-threatening parvovirus B19 infection in a child. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2013;32:789–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23429554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e31828df4d1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe M, Shibuya A, Okuno J, Maeda T, Tamama S, Saigenji K. Hepatitis A virus infection associated with hemophagocytic syndrome: report of two cases. Intern Med (Tokyo, Japan). 2002;41:1188–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.41.1188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuon FF, Gomes VS, Amato VS, Graf ME, Fonseca GH, Lazari C, Nicodemo AC. Hemophagocytic syndrome associated with hepatitis A: case report and literature review. Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo. 2008;50:123–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18488094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S0036-46652008000200012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo RA, Rosenzweig SD, Katsicas MM. Hepatitis A-associated macrophage activation syndrome in children with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis: report of 2 cases. J Rheumatol. 2008;35:166–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18050365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bay A, Bosnak V, Leblebisatan G, Yavuz S, Yilmaz F, Hizli S. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in 2 pediatric patients secondary to hepatitis A virus infection. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2012;29:211–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22475296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/08880018.2012.666783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canoz PY, Afat E, Temiz F, Azizoglu NO, Citilcioglu HB, Tumgor G, Leblebisatan G, Turgut M. Reactive hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis after hepatitis a infection. Indian J Hematol Blood Transfus. 2014;30:46–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25332533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12288-013-0241-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho E, Cha I, Yoon K, Yang HN, Kim HW, Kim MG, Jo SK, Cho WY, Kim HK. Hemophagocytic syndrome in a patient with acute tubulointerstitial nephritis secondary to hepatitis A virus infection. J Korean Med Sci. 2010;25:1529–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20890439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2946668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3346/jkms.2010.25.10.1529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishii H, Yamagishi Y, Okamoto S, Saito H, Kikuchi H, Kodama T. Hemophagocytic syndrome associated with fulminant hepatitis A: a case report. Keio J Med. 2003;52:38–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12713021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyoda K, Nakamura S, Machi T, Kitagawa S, Ohtake S, Matsuda T. Acute hepatitis A virus infection-associated hemophagocytic syndrome. Am J Gastroenterol. 1998;93:1187–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9672368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.1998.1187a.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navamani K, Natarajan MM, Lionel AP, Kumar S. Hepatitis a virus infection-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in two children. Indian J Hematol Blood Transfus. 2014;30:239–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25332588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4192162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12288-014-0341-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onaga M, Hayashi K, Nishimagi T, Nagata K, Uto H, Kubuki Y, Hirono S, Tsubouchi H. A case of acute hepatitis A with marked hemophagocytosis in bone marrow. Hepatol Res. 2000;17:205–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10794974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1386-6346(99)00076-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tai CM, Liu CJ, Yao M. Successful treatment of acute hepatitis A-associated hemophagocytic syndrome by intravenous immunoglobulin. J Formos Med Assoc = Taiwan yi zhi. 2005;104:507–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16091828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McPeake JR, Hirst WJ, Brind AM, Williams R. Hepatitis A causing a second episode of virus-associated haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a patient with Still’s disease. J Med Virol. 1993;39:173–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8487038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.1890390216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Termsinsuk P, Sirisanthiti P. Acute hepatitis A infection-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in adult presenting as impending acute liver failure: a case report and literature review. Clin Case Rep. 2022;10:e05334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35154712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8819581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ccr3.5334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallick B, Daniel P, Dutta U. Hepatitis A infection related haemophagocytic syndrome: a case report and systematic review. Trop Dr. 2019;49:234–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aleem A, Al Amoudi S, Al-Mashhadani S, Siddiqui N. Haemophagocytic syndrome associated with hepatitis-B virus infection responding to etoposide. Clin Lab Haematol. 2005;27:395–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16307542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2257.2005.00728.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu MG, Chua J. Virus-associated haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in a young Filipino man. BMJ Case Rep. 2016;2016:bcr2016214655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27284096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4904420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bcr-2016-214655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaney H, Thotakura D, Sisco L. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with hepatitis B and HIV coinfection with resultant liver failure. ACG Case Rep J. 2021;8:e00532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33553464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7862042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14309/crj.0000000000000532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faurschou M, Nielsen OJ, Hansen PB, Juhl BR, Hasselbalch H. Fatal virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome associated with coexistent chronic active hepatitis B and acute hepatitis C virus infection. Am J Hematol. 1999;61:135–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10367794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-8652(199906)61:2&lt;135::AID-AJH11&gt;3.0.CO;2-E</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tierney LM, Thabet A, Nishino H. Case records of the Massachusetts General Hospital. Case 10-2011. A woman with fever, confusion, liver failure, anemia, and thrombocytopenia. N Engl J Med. 2011;364:1259–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21449790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMcpc1013924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerra JAAA, Kampa KC, Morsoletto DGB, Junior AP, Ivantes CAP. Hepatitis E: a literature review. J Clin Transl Hepatol. 2017;5:376–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29226104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5719195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamihira T, Yano K, Tamada Y, Matsumoto T, Miyazato M, Nagaoka S, Ohata K, Abiru S, Komori A, Daikoku M, Yatsuhashi H, Ishibashi H. Case of domestically infected hepatitis E with marked thrombocytopenia. Nihon Shokakibyo Gakkai Zasshi. 2008;105:841–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18525191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leroy M, Coiffier G, Pronier C, Triquet L, Perdriger A, Guggenbuhl P. Macrophage activation syndrome with acute hepatitis E during tocilizumab treatment for rheumatoid arthritis. Joint Bone Spine. 2015;82:278–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25791259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbspin.2015.01.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary SK, Agarwal A, Mandal RN, Grover R. Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis associated with Hepatitis A and Hepatitis E co-infection. Indian J Pediatr. 2016;83:607–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26821545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-015-2021-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muyldermans A, Van Droogenbroeck J, Descheemaeker P, Reynders M. Hepatitis E virus-associated haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Acta Clin Belg. 2021;76:314–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32089126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/17843286.2020.1733179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjan A, Mokta J, Thakur S, Bhawani R, Joshi I, Vohra S. Hemophagocytic Lymphohistiocytosis secondary to acute hepatitis E Infection: a rare association. J Assoc Physicians, India. 2018;66:96–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31325278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsunemi Y, Matsushita T, Nagayama T, Takahashi T, Tamaki T. A case of virus-associated Hemophagocytic syndrome due to measles. Jpn J Dermatol. 2001;111:1591–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lagousi T, Korovessi P, Panagouli E, Tsagris V, Kostaridou S. A rare case of measles-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis in an infant. Cureus. 2020;12:e8246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32596066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7308916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otagiri T, Mitsui T, Kawakami T, Katsuura M, Maeda K, Ikegami T, Sendo D, Hayasaka K. Haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis following measles vaccination. Eur J Pediatr. 2002;161:494–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12200609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-002-1027-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buda P, Gietka P, Wieteska-Klimczak A, Smorczewska-Kiljan A, Książyk J. Autoimmune/inflammatory syndrome leading to macrophage activation syndrome: an example of autoinflammatory spectrum disorder? Isr Med Assoc J. 2016;18:571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28681590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing Q, Xing P. Mumps caused hemophagocytic syndrome: a rare case report. Am J Emerg Med. 2013;31:1000.e1001-1002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2013.02.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takenaka H, Kishimoto S, Ichikawa R, Shibagaki R, Kubota Y, Yamagata N, Gotoh H, Fujita N, Yasuno H. Virus-associated haemophagocytic syndrome caused by rubella in an adult. Br J Dermatol. 1998;139:877–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9892958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2133.1998.02517.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takeoka Y, Hino M, Oiso N, Nishi S, Koh KR, Yamane T, Ohta K, Nakamae H, Aoyama Y, Hirose A, Fujino H, Takubo T, Inoue T, Tatsumi N. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome due to rubella virus and varicella-zoster virus dual infection in patient with adult idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura. Ann Hematol. 2001;80:361–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11475151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s002770000282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baykan A, Akcakus M, Deniz K. Rubella-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in an infant. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2005;27:430–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16096525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.mph.0000177427.94164.df</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koubaa M, Marrakchi C, Maaloul I, Makni S, Berrajah L, Elloumi M, Hammami B, Lahiani D, Boudawara T, Ben Jemaa M. Rubella associated with hemophagocytic syndrome. First report in a male and review of the literature. Mediterranean J Hematol Infect Dis. 2012;4:e2012050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4084/mjhid.2012.050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerin C, Pozzetto B, Berthoux F. Hemophagocytic syndrome associated with coxsackie virus A 9 infection in a non-immunosuppressed adult. Intensive Care Med. 1989;15:547–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2558130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barre V, Marret S, Mendel I, Lesesve JF, Fessard CI. Enterovirus-associated haemophagocytic syndrome in a neonate. Acta paediatr (Oslo, Norway: 1992). 1998;87:469–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1651-2227.1998.tb01482.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashiwagi Y, Kawashima H, Sato S, Ioi H, Amaha M, Takekuma K, Hoshika A, Oshiro H, Matsubayashi J, Mukai K. Virological and immunological characteristics of fatal virus-associated haemophagocytic syndrome (VAHS). Microbiol Immunol. 2007;51:53–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17237599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1348-0421.2007.tb03890.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Letsas KP, Filippatos GS, Delimpasi S, Spanakis N, Kounas SP, Efremidis M, Tsakris A, Kardaras F. Enterovirus-induced fulminant myocarditis and hemophagocytic syndrome. J Infect. 2007;54:e75–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16733067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2006.04.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsibardi K, Moschovi MA, Theodoridou M, Spanakis N, Kalabalikis P, Tsakris A, Tzortzatou-Stathopoulou F. Enterovirus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in children with malignancy: report of three cases and review of the literature. Eur J Pediatr. 2008;167:97–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17318619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-007-0436-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindamood KE, Fleck P, Narla A, Vergilio JA, Degar BA, Baldwin M, Wintermark P. Neonatal enteroviral sepsis/meningoencephalitis and hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis: diagnostic challenges. Am J Perinatol. 2011;28:337–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21089006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1268710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukazawa M, Hoshina T, Nanishi E, Nishio H, Doi T, Ohga S, Hara T. Neonatal hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with a vertical transmission of coxsackievirus B1. J Infect Chemother. 2013;19:1210–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23757031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10156-013-0629-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hara S, Kawada J, Kawano Y, Yamashita T, Minagawa H, Okumura N, Ito Y. Hyperferritinemia in neonatal and infantile human parechovirus-3 infection in comparison with other infectious diseases. J Infect Chemother. 2014;20:15–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24462418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2013.11.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Wang H, Tang J, He Y, Xiong T, Li W, Qu Y, Mu D. Clinical characteristics of severe neonatal enterovirus infection: a systematic review. BMC Pediatr. 2021;21:127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33722228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7958388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12887-021-02599-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramani A, Sudhakaran S, Rahimi RS, Guileyardo J, Sandkovsky US. Enterovirus-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis with multiorgan failure. Proc (Baylor Univ Med Cent). 2020;33:248–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08998280.2020.1731051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardman SJ, Tukur G, Waruiru C. Enterovirus-associated HLH: addition of Anakinra to IVIG and corticosteroids. J Clin Immunol. 2019;39:373–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31104275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10875-019-00639-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aviner S, Sofer D, Shulman LM, Bibi H, Weitzman S. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis associated with parechovirus 3 infection. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2014;36:e251–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24072243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MPH.0000000000000015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nanmoku K, Yamamoto T, Tsujita M, Hiramitsu T, Goto N, Katayama A, Narumi S, Watarai Y, Kobayashi T, Uchida K. Virus-associated hemophagocytic syndrome in renal transplant recipients: report of 2 cases from a single center. Case Rep Hematol. 2015;2015:876301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25838952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4369932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park M, Yun YJ, Woo SI, Lee JW, Chung NG, Cho B. Rotavirus-associated hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis (HLH) after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for familial HLH. Pediatr Int. 2015;57:e77–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25712613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ped.12567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi S, Oki J, Miyamoto A, Koyano S, Ito K, Azuma H, Okuno A. Encephalopathy associated with haemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis following rotavirus infection. Eur J Pediatr. 1999;158:133–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10048610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s004310051033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagao T, Takahashi N, Saitoh H, Noguchi S, Guo YM, Ito M, Watanabe A, Fujishima N, Kameoka Y, Tagawa H, Hirokawa M, Sawada K. Adult T-cell leukemia-lymphoma developed from an HTLV-1 carrier during treatment of B-cell lymphoma-associated hemophagocytic syndrome. [Rinsho ketsueki] Jpn J Clin Hematol. 2012;53:2008–12.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>