<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39192960</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2008-9872</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>79</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Archives of Razi Institute</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arch Razi Inst</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Presence of Enteric Viruses in Shellfish Samples from the Persian Gulf.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>129</StartPage><EndPage>137</EndPage><MedlinePgn>129-137</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.32592/ARI.2024.79.1.129</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Shellfishes are a significant economic and nutritious seafood amongst people in different countries. Seafood products, particularly shellfish, are potential reservoirs of enteric viruses. This research investigated the incidence of rotavirus (RoV), norovirus (NoV) GI and GII, hepatitis A virus (HAV), and hepatitis E virus (HEV) in shellfish samples from the Persian Gulf, Iran. One hundred and fifty shellfish samples were collected. RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis were performed using commercial kits. The real-time polymerase chain reaction assessed the presence of enteric viruses in extracted cDNA samples. Thirty-two out of 150 (21.33%) shellfish samples were contaminated with enteric viruses. Prevalence rates of NoV GI, NoV GII, HAV, and RoV amongst shellfish samples were 8.00%, 11.33%, 1.33%, and 0.66%, respectively. There were no contaminated shellfish samples with HEV. Simultaneous prevalence of HAV and NoV GI, and HAV and NoV GII viruses were 0.66% and 0.66%, respectively. Examined viruses had a higher prevalence in shellfish samples collected in the winter season (<i>P</i>&lt;0.05). Prevalence of HAV, RoV, NoV GI, and NoV GII amongst shellfish samples gathered in the winter season was 2.85%, 9.09%, 11.90%, and 20%, respectively. To the best of our knowledge, this was the first report of the incidence of enteric viruses, particularly HAV, NoV GI, NoV GII, and RoV, in shellfish samples from the Persian Gulf, Iran. Shellfish samples may serve as a potential source of enteric viruses for the human population. Therefore, routine viral assessments should be conducted. The consumption of fully cooked shellfish can significantly reduce the risk of HAV, RoV, NoV GI, and NoV GII infections. Furthermore, given the export value and importance of shellfish samples, their microbial quality and safety should be routinely monitored.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alipoor Amroabadi</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Hygiene, Shahrekord Branch, Islamic Azad University, Shahrekord, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahimi</LastName><ForeName>E</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center of Nutrition and Organic Products (RCNOP), Shahrekord Branch, Islamic Azad University, Shahrekord, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shakerian</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center of Nutrition and Organic Products (RCNOP), Shahrekord Branch, Islamic Azad University, Shahrekord, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Iran</Country><MedlineTA>Arch Razi Inst</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101549567</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0365-3439</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012758" MajorTopicYN="Y">Shellfish</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019156" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Indian Ocean</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004770" MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030041" MajorTopicYN="N">Hepatitis A virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029322" MajorTopicYN="N">Norovirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hepatitis A Virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Noroviruses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Persian Gulf</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rota Virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Shellfish</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39192960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11345468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32592/ARI.2024.79.1.129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ARI-79-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alipour Amroabadi M, Rahimi E, Shakerian A, Momtaz H. Incidence of hepatitis A and hepatitis E viruses and norovirus and rotavirus in fish and shrimp samples caught from the Persian Gulf. Arquivo Brasileiro de Medicina Veterinaria e Zootecnia. 2021;73(1):169–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittman RJ, Flick GJ. Microbial contamination of shellfish: prevalence, risk to human health, and control strategies.  Annual Review of Public Health. 1995;16:123–140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7639867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>La Bella G, Martella V, Basanisi MG, Nobili G, Terio V, La Salandra G. Food-Borne Viruses in shellfish: investigation on norovirus and HAV presence in Apulia (SE Italy) .  Food Environ Virol. 2017;9(2):179–186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5429374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27943110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goyal SM, Cannon JL. Shellfish-Associated Enteric Virus Illness: Virus Localization, Disease Outbreaks and Prevention. Viruses in Foods. 2016: 185–207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thebault A, Teunis PF, Le Pendu J, Le Guyader FS, Denis JB. Infectivity of GI and GII noroviruses established from oyster related outbreaks.  Epidemics. 2013;5(2):98–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23746803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority (EFSA). Analysis of the European baseline survey of norovirus in oysters.  EFSA Journal. 2019;17(7):5762.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32626378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford SE, Ramani S, Tate JE. Rotavirus infection. Nature Reviews Disease Primers. 2017;3:17083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5858916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29119972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemon SM, Walker CM. Hepatitis A Virus and Hepatitis E Virus: Emerging and Re-Emerging Enterically Transmitted Hepatitis Viruses.  Cold Spring Harbor perspectives in medicine. 2019;9(6):31823.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6531368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29735577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randazzo W, Sánchez G. Hepatitis A infections from food.  Journal of Applied Microbiology. 2020;10:1111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32471014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahk H, Lee KB, Lee MH. Development of Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay for the Detection of Hepatitis a Virus in Vegetables. Food Control. 2012;23:210–214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suffredini E, Lanni L, Arcangeli G. Qualitative and quantitative assessment of viral contamination in bivalve molluscs harvested in Italy.  International Journal of Food Microbiology. 2014;184:21–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24666883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joo Seo D, Hwa Lee M, Ry Son N, Seo S, Bum Lee K, Wang X, Choi C. Seasonal and regional prevalence of norovirus, hepatitis A virus, hepatitis E virus, and rotavirus in shellfish harvested from South Korea. Food Control. 2014;41:178–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momtaz H, Rahimi E, Hajian S, Momeni M. Prevalence of hepatitis A virus in sea food in Iran. Arquivo Brasileiro de Medicina Veterinarian e Zootecnia. 2012;64(4):887–890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesquita JR, Vaz L, Cerqueira S. Norovirus, hepatitis a virus and enterovirus presence in shellfish from high quality harvesting areas in Portugal. Food Microbiology. 2011;28:936–941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21569936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kittigul L, Thamjaroen A, Chiawchan S, Chavalitshewinkoon-Petmitr P, Pombubpa K, Diraphat P. Prevalence and molecular genotyping of noroviruses in market oysters, mussels, and cockles in Bangkok, Thailand.  Food Environ Virol. 2016;8(2):133–140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26872638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao J, Chunhui H, Fanning S, Nan L, Jiahui W, Hongyuan Z, et al. Norovirus contamination in retail oysters from Beijing and Qingdao, China. Food Control. 2018;86:415–419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anbazhagi S, Kamatchiammal S. Contamination of Seafood by Norovirus in India.  International Journal of Virology. 2010;6:138–149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loutreul J, Cazeaux C, Levert D, Nicolas A, Vautier S, Sauvage AL, et al. Prevalence of Human Noroviruses in Frozen Marketed Shellfish, Red Fruits and Fresh Vegetables. Food Environ Virol. 2014;6:157–168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24923255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Manzano J, Hundesa A, Calgua B, Carratala A, Maluquer de Motes C, Rusin˜ol M, et al. Adenovirus in commercially distributed and norovirus contaminants shellfish. Food and Environmental Virology. 2013;6(1):31–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24293153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sdiri‐Loulizi K, Hassine M, Aouni Z, Gharbi‐Khelifi H, Chouchane S, Sakly N, et al. Detection and molecular characterization of enteric viruses in environmental samples in Monastir. Journal of Applied Microbiology. 2010;109:1093–1104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20553345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DePaola A, Jones JL, Woods J, Burkhardt W, Calci KR, Krantz JA. Bacterial and viral pathogens in live oysters. Applied and Environmental Microbiology. 2010;76(9):2754–2768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2863423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20190085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torok V, Hodgson K, McLeod C, Tan J, Malhi N, Turnbull A. National survey of foodborne viruses in Australian oysters at production. Food Microbiology. 2018;69:196–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28941902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suffredini E, Le QH, Di Pasquale S, Pham TD, Vicenza T, Losardo M, De Medici D. Occurrence and molecular characterization of enteric viruses in bivalve shellfish marketed in Vietnam. Food Control. 2020;108:106828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chironna M, Germinario C, De Medici D, Fiore A, Di Pasquale S, Quarto M, Barbuti S. Detection of hepatitis a in mussels from different sources marketed in Puglia region (South Italy) . International Journal Food Microbiology. 2002;75(1-2):11–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11999106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohan V, Rawat S, Lokesh KM, Mohan HV, Avinash Reddy D, Kumar A, Bhilegaonkar KN. Prevalence of Rotavirus in shellfish from Southern Kerala. Veterinary World. 2014;7(10):821–824.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Guyader F, Haugarreau L, Miossec L, Dubois E, Pommepuy M. Three-year study to assess human enteric viruses in shellfish.  Applied and Environmental Microbiology.  2000;66:3241–3248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC92140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10919776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park K, Yeo S, Jeong H. Updates on the genetic variations of norovirus in sporadic gastroenteritis in Chungnam Korea. Virology Journal. 2012;9(1):29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3312829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22273062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fusco G, Anastasio A, Kingsley D, Amoroso MG, Pepe T, Fratamico PM, et al. Detection of hepatitis a virus and other enteric viruses in shellfish collected in the gulf of naples, Italy. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. 2019;16(4):2588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6678136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31331104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purpari G, Macaluso G, Gucciardi F. Molecular characterization of human enteric viruses in food, water samples, and surface swabs in Sicily. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2019;80:66–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30639406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>