<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39163309</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-0987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pediatric infectious disease journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Infect Dis J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical Presentation of Enterovirus D68 in a Swiss Pediatric University Center.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/INF.0000000000004503</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) is responsible for millions of infections. In the last decade, there has been an increase in the number of children requiring hospital or critical care admission due to severe respiratory illness. Nevertheless, the epidemiological and clinical importance of EV-D68 infections remains unclear.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">We aimed to determine the local prevalence of EV-D68 infection in pediatric patients and to characterize its clinical presentation and disease burden compared with non-EV-D68 enterovirus and human rhinovirus (RV) infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">We performed a retrospective single-center study of children presenting with respiratory symptoms and positive respiratory panel polymerase chain reaction for EV/RV from November 2018 to December 2019. We tested EV/RV positive specimens with an EV-D68-specific polymerase chain reaction to discriminate EV-D68, non-EV-D68 and RV and compared their respective clinical presentation, outcomes and treatment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We identified 224 patients (median age 21 months), of which 16 (7%) were EV-D68 positive. They presented with cough (88%), wheezing (62%) and dyspnea (75%). EV-D68 infection had an odds ratio regarding pediatric respiratory severity-score of 11.6 relative to non-EV-D68 [confidence intervals (CI): 3.51-41.14], and of 9.9 (CI: 3.75-27.95) relative to RV. The fitted logistic regression showed that the odds of intensive care were 5 times more likely with EV-D68 than RV infection (CI: 1.32-19.28; P = 0.001). Patients with EV-D68 infections were more likely to receive medical support in the form of supplementary oxygen, antibiotics and steroids.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">EV-D68 infection is associated with higher morbidity and a higher likelihood of intensive care treatment than non-EV-D68 and RV infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ott</LastName><ForeName>Chantal</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Applied Microbiology Research, Department of Biomedicine, University of Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatric infectious diseases, Children University Hospital Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dutilh</LastName><ForeName>Gilles</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Research, University of Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reist</LastName><ForeName>Josiane</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Applied Microbiology Research, Department of Biomedicine, University of Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bingisser</LastName><ForeName>Roland</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Department, University Hospital Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Egli</LastName><ForeName>Adrian</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Applied Microbiology Research, Department of Biomedicine, University of Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Bacteriology and Microbiology, University Hospital Basel, Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Microbiology, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heininger</LastName><ForeName>Ulrich</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatric infectious diseases, Children University Hospital Basel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Infect Dis J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8701858</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-3668</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39163309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00006454-990000000-00981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N, Lamonte-Fowlkes A, Oberst S, et al.; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Enterovirus surveillance--United States, 1970-2005. MMWR Surveill Summ. 2006;55:1–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rankin DA, Spieker AJ, Perez A, et al.; NVSN Network Investigators. Circulation of rhinoviruses and/or enteroviruses in pediatric patients with acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2254909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royston L, Tapparel C. Rhinoviruses and respiratory enteroviruses: not as simple as ABC. Viruses. 2016;8:16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lugo D, Krogstad P. Enteroviruses in the early 21st century. Curr Opin Pediatr. 2016;28:107–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schieble JH, Fox VL, Lennette EH. A probable new human picornavirus associated with respiratory diseases. Am J Epidemiol. 1967;85:297–310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Abzug MJ, Dominguez SR. 2014 outbreak of enterovirus D68 in North America. J Med Virol. 2016;88:739–745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poelman R, Schuffenecker I, Van Leer-Buter C, et al.; ESCV-ECDC EV-D68 study group. European surveillance for enterovirus D68 during the emerging North-American outbreak in 2014. J Clin Virol. 2015;71:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drews SJ, Simmonds K, Usman HR, et al. Characterization of enterovirus activity, including that of enterovirus D68, in pediatric patients in Alberta, Canada, in 2014. J Clin Microbiol. 2015;53:1042–1045.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karelehto E, Koen G, Benschop K, et al. van der Klis F, Pajkrt D, Wolthers K: enterovirus D68 serosurvey: evidence for endemic circulation in the Netherlands, 2006 to 2016. Euro Surveill. 2019;24:1800671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao S, Messacar K, Torok MR, et al. Enterovirus D68 in critically Ill children: a comparison with pandemic H1N1 influenza. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2016;17:1023–1031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fall A, Kenmoe S, Ebogo-Belobo JT, et al. Global prevalence and case fatality rate of enterovirus D68 infections, a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS NeglTrop Dis. 2022;16:e0010073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Schreiner TL, Maloney JA, et al. A cluster of acute flaccid paralysis and cranial nerve dysfunction temporally associated with an outbreak of enterovirus D68 in children in Colorado, USA. Lancet. 2015;385:1662–1671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyda A, Stelzer-Braid S, Adam D, et al. The association between acute flaccid myelitis (AFM) and enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) - what is the evidence for causation? Euro Surveill. 2018;23:17–00310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aliabadi N, Messacar K, Pastula DM, et al. Dominguez SR: enterovirus D68 infection in children with acute flaccid myelitis, Colorado, USA, 2014. Emerg Infect Dis. 2016;22:1387–1394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm-Hansen CC, Midgley SE, Fischer TK. Global emergence of enterovirus D68: a systematic review. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16:e64–e75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Principi N, Ruggiero L, et al. Enterovirus-D68 (EV-D68) in pediatric patients with respiratory infection: the circulation of a new B3 clade in Italy. J Clin Virol. 2018;99-100:91–96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sooksawasdi Na Ayudhya S, Laksono BM, van Riel D. The pathogenesis and virulence of enterovirus-D68 infection. Virulence. 2021;12:2060–2072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Hu XY, Yu XF. Current understanding of human enterovirus D68. Viruses. 2019;11:490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyrdak R, Grabbe M, Hammas B, et al. Outbreak of enterovirus D68 of the new B3 lineage in Stockholm, Sweden, August to September 2016. Euro Surveill. 2016;21:30403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodcroft EB, Dyrdak R, Andres C, et al. Evolution, geographic spreading, and demographic distribution of enterovirus D68. PLoS Pathog. 2022;18:e1010515.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelmann I, Fatoux M, Lazrek M, et al. Enterovirus D68 detection in respiratory specimens: association with severe disease. J Med Virol. 2017;89:1201–1207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Girello A, Premoli M, et al. A new real-time reverse transcription-PCR assay for detection of human enterovirus 68 in respiratory samples. J Clin Microbiol. 2015;53:1725–1726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyaji Y, Sugai K, Nozawa A, et al. Pediatric Respiratory Severity Score (PRESS) for respiratory tract infections in children. Austin Virol Retrovirol. 2015;2:1009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagalamarri V, Balleda L, Kolla S, et al. Utility of PRESS score in predicting the outcomes of children admitted with respiratory distress: a prospective study. Pediatr Respirol Crit Care Med. 2021;5:57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nayani K, Naeem R, Munir O, et al. The clinical respiratory score predicts paediatric critical care disposition in children with respiratory distress presenting to the emergency department. BMC Pediatr. 2018;18:339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thokngaen J, Karoonboonyanan W. Pediatric respiratory severity score evaluates disease severity of respiratory tract infection in children. Chula Med J. 2019;63:41–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin PC. Balance diagnostics for comparing the distribution of baseline covariates between treatment groups in propensity-score matched samples. Stat Med. 2009;28:3083–3107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang D, Dalton JE. A unified approach to measuring the effect size between two groups using SAS®. SAS Glob Forum. 2012;12:335–2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faraone SV. Interpreting estimates of treatment effects: implications for managed care. P t. 2008;33:700–711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai HP, Kuo PH, Liu CC, et al. Respiratory viral infections among pediatric inpatients and outpatients in Taiwan from 1997 to 1999. J Clin Microbiol. 2001;39:111–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muenchhoff M, Goulder PJ. Sex differences in pediatric infectious diseases. J Infect Dis. 2014;209(Suppl 3):S120–S126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marriott I, Huet-Hudson YM. Sexual dimorphism in innate immune responses to infectious organisms. Immunol Res. 2006;34:177–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgley CM, Jackson MA, Selvarangan R, et al. Severe respiratory illness associated with enterovirus D68 - Missouri and Illinois, 2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2014;63:798–799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggs HM, Nix WA, Zhang J, et al. Enterovirus D68 infection among hospitalized children with severe acute respiratory illness in El Salvador and Panama, 2012-2013. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15:181–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reina J, Cabrerizo M. Distribución etaria de las infecciones respiratorias agudas causadas por los enterovirus en la población infantil. Enferme Infec Microbiol Clín. 2017;35:608–609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itagaki T, Aoki Y, Matoba Y, et al. Clinical characteristics of children infected with enterovirus D68 in an outpatient clinic and the association with bronchial asthma. Infect Dis (Lond). 2018;50:303–312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calvo C, Cuevas MT, Pozo F, et al. Respiratory infections by enterovirus D68 in outpatients and inpatients Spanish children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2016;35:45–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Funakoshi Y, Ito K, Morino S, et al. Enterovirus D68 respiratory infection in a children’s hospital in Japan in 2015. Pediatr Int. 2019;61:768–776.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster JE, Selvarangan R, Hassan F, et al. Clinical course of enterovirus D68 in hospitalized children. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2017;36:290–295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster JE, Miller JO, Selvarangan R, et al. Severe enterovirus 68 respiratory illness in children requiring intensive care management. J Clin Virol. 2015;70:77–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savage TJ, Kuypers J, Chu HY, et al. Enterovirus D-68 in children presenting for acute care in the hospital setting. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2018;12:522–528.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uprety P, Curtis D, Elkan M, et al. Association of enterovirus D68 with acute flaccid myelitis, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, 2009-2018. Emerg Infect Dis. 2019;25:1676–1682.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messacar K, Asturias EJ, Hixon AM, et al. Enterovirus D68 and acute flaccid myelitis-evaluating the evidence for causality. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18:e239–e247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bigi S, Ramette A, Barbani MT, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis in Switzerland – association with enterovirus D68. Swiss Med Wkly. 2023;153:40045.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zumstein J, Heininger U. Decline of pertussis in hospitalised children following the introduction of immunisation in pregnancy - results from a nationwide, prospective surveillance study, 2013-2020. Swiss Med Wkly. 2021;151:w30064.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>