<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39251138</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1995-820X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virologica Sinica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virol Sin</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Bis-benzylisoquinoline alkaloids inhibit flavivirus entry and replication by compromising endolysosomal trafficking and autophagy.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1995-820X(24)00140-8</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.virs.2024.09.001</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Flaviviruses, such as dengue virus (DENV), Zika virus (ZIKV), and Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), represent a substantial public health challenge as there are currently no approved treatments available. Here, we investigated the antiviral effects of bis-benzylisoquinoline alkaloids (BBAs) on flavivirus infections. We evaluated five specific BBAs-berbamine, tetrandrine, iso-tetrandrine, fangchinoline, and cepharanthine-and found that they effectively inhibited infections by ZIKV, DENV, or JEV by blocking virus entry and genome replication stages in the flavivirus life cycle. Furthermore, we synthesized a fluorophore-conjugated BBA and showed that BBAs targeted endolysosomes, causing lysosomal pH alkalization. Mechanistic studies on inhibiting ZIKV infection by BBAs revealed that these compounds blocked TRPML channels, leading to lysosomal dysfunction and reducing the expression of NCAM1, a key receptor for the entry of ZIKV into cells, thereby decreasing cells susceptibility to ZIKV infection. Additionally, BBAs inhibited the fusion of autophagosomes and lysosomes, significantly reducing viral RNA replication. Collectively, our results suggest that BBAs inhibit flavivirus entry and replication by compromising endolysosomal trafficking and autophagy, respectively, underscoring the potential of BBAs as therapeutic agents against flavivirus infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Publishing services by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Lihong</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Lele</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Junhai</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Nanjun</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, 999077, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan</LastName><ForeName>Chuen-Fuk</ForeName><Initials>CF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Sciences, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, 999077, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Fei</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yin</LastName><ForeName>Youqin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Jiufeng</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Workstation for Emerging Infectious Disease Control and Prevention, Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Pathogen Detection for Emerging Infectious Disease Response, Guangdong Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Guangzhou, 511430, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Rongxin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Immunology and Inflammation, Institute of Basic Medical Sciences and Department of Biotechnology, School of Life Sciences and Biopharmaceutics, Guangdong Pharmaceutical University, Guangzhou, 510006, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Kehui</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Bioactive Substance and Function of Natural Medicines, Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, 100730, China; Beijing Key Laboratory of Active Substances Discovery and Druggability Evaluation, Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, 100730, China. Electronic address: kehuizhang@imm.ac.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qi</LastName><ForeName>Wenbao</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Prevention, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642, China; National and Regional Joint Engineering Laboratory for Medicament of Zoonoses Prevention and Control, Guangzhou, 510642, China; Key Laboratory of Zoonoses Prevention and Control of Guangdong Province, Guangzhou, China. Electronic address: qiwenbao@scau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yue</LastName><ForeName>Jianbo</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>City University of Hong Kong Shenzhen Research Institute, Shenzhen, 518057, China; Division of Natural and Applied Sciences, Synear Molecular Biology Lab, Global Health Research Center, Duke Kunshan University, Kunshan, 215316, China; College of Life Sciences, Wuhan University, Wuhan, 430072, China. Electronic address: jianbo.yue@duke.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Virol Sin</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101514185</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1995-820X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Autophagy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bis-benzylisoquinoline alkaloids (BBAs)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Endolysosomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Flavivirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TRPML channels</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zika virus (ZIKV)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest This work has applied patent (Methods of preventing or treating flavivirus infections and methods of inhibiting the entry of flavivirus, enterovirus or lentivirus into host cells. US patent No: 11,357.771 B2). L. Huang and J. Yue are the inventors of the patent. The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39251138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virs.2024.09.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1995-820X(24)00140-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>