<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39227731</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1651-2227</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta paediatrica (Oslo, Norway : 1992)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Paediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of viral testing on duration of antibiotic treatment and hospitalisation of febrile infants.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/apa.17413</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To assess the duration of antimicrobial treatment; hospital length of stay; and invasive bacterial infections rates in hospitalised infants following the adoption of a management guideline.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Faculty agreed to a standard of 24 h of antibiotic treatment for well-appearing febrile infants with proven viral infection and no growth on bacterial cultures. The outcomes were the duration of hospitalisation and antibiotic treatment of febrile infants less than 8 weeks of age who have enterovirus, parechovirus, respiratory viruses detected. We monitored re-admissions and missed invasive infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Of the total 1696 infants studied, the median antibiotic treatment duration decreased from 31.5 to 24.8 h in virus-infected infants ≤21 days of age (p = 0.02) and from 26 to 19.7 h in infants 22-56 days of age (p &lt; 0.001). The decrease was less in infants not infected with a virus. No patient had an invasive infection identified after discharge.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The implementation of our care standard resulted in reduction in antibiotic treatment duration without known delayed diagnosis of bacterial infections. Infants without a proven viral aetiology may need further study to inform management decisions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Foundation Acta Paediatrica. Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erdem</LastName><ForeName>G</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7368-359X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Nationwide Children's Hospital and The Ohio State University School of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Watson</LastName><ForeName>J R</ForeName><Initials>JR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Nationwide Children's Hospital and The Ohio State University School of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tomatis</LastName><ForeName>C</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Nationwide Children's Hospital and The Ohio State University School of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ceyhan</LastName><ForeName>K</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, The Ohio State University School of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barson</LastName><ForeName>W</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Nationwide Children's Hospital and The Ohio State University School of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Norway</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Paediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9205968</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0803-5253</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibiotic treatment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">febrile infant</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">length of stay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severe bacterial infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral testing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39227731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apa.17413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Pantell RH, Roberts KB, Adams WG, et al. Evaluation and management of well‐appearing febrile infants 8 to 60 days old. Pediatrics. 2021;148(2):e2021052228. doi:10.1542/peds.2021-052228</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woll C, Neuman MI, Aronson PL. Management of the febrile young infant. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2017;33:748‐753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuppermann N, Dayan PS, Levine DA, et al. A clinical prediction rule to identify febrile infants 60 days and younger at low risk for serious bacterial infections. JAMA Pediatr. 2019;173:342‐351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krief WI, Levine DA, Platt SL, et al. Influenza virus infection and the risk of serious bacterial infections in young febrile infants. Pediatrics. 2009;124(1):30‐39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadambari S, Braccio S, Ribeiro S, et al. Enterovirus and parechovirus meningitis in infants younger than 90 days old in the UK and Republic of Ireland: a British Paediatric Surveillance Unit study. Arch Dis Child. 2019;104:552‐557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen DK, Friedlander S, Fleischman RJ, Zangwill KM. Length of stay and complications associated with febrile infants &lt;90 days of age hospitalized in the United States, 2000‐2012. Hosp Pediatr. 2018;8:746‐752.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byington CL, Reynolds CC, Korgenski K, et al. Costs and infant outcomes after implementation of a care process model for febrile infants. Pediatrics. 2012;130(1):e16‐e24. doi:10.1542/peds.2012-0127</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biondi EA, Byington CL. Evaluation and management of febrile, well‐appearing young infants. Infect Dis Clin N Am. 2015;29:575‐585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mintegi S, Garcia‐Garcia JJ, Benito J, et al. Rapid influenza test in young febrile infants for the identification of low‐risk patients. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009;28:1026‐1028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bender JM, Taylor CS, Cumpio J, et al. Infants 1‐90 days old hospitalized with human rhinovirus infection. J Clin Lab Anal. 2014;28:349‐352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levine DA, Platt SL, Dayan PS, et al. Risk of serious bacterial infection in young febrile infants with respiratory syncytial virus infections. Pediatrics. 2004;113:1728‐1734.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahajan P, Browne LR, Levine DA, et al. Risk of bacterial coinfections in febrile infants 60 days old and younger with documented viral infections. J Pediatr. 2018;203:86‐91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholson EG, Avadhanula V, Ferlic‐Stark L, Patel K, Gincoo KE, Piedra PA. The risk of serious bacterial infection in febrile infants 0‐90 days of life with a respiratory viral infection. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2019;38:355‐361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaschke AJ, Korgenski EK, Wilkes J, et al. Rhinovirus in febrile infants and risk of bacterial infection. Pediatrics. 2018;141(2):e20172384. doi:10.1542/peds.2017-2384</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doan Q, Enarson P, Kissoon N, Klassen TP, Johnson DW. Rapid viral diagnosis for acute febrile respiratory illness in children in the emergency department. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;2014(9):CD006452. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD001431.pub4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenfield BW, Lowery BM, Starke HE, et al. Frequency of serious bacterial infections in young infants with and without respiratory tract infections. Am J Emerg Med. 2021;50:744‐747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crook J, Xu M, Slaughter JC, et al. Impact of clinical guidance and rapid molecular pathogen detection on evaluation and outcomes of febrile or hypothermic infants. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2020;41:1285‐1291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai S, Calhoun T, Sosa T, et al. Decreasing hospital observation time for febrile infants. J Hosp Med. 2021;16:267‐273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foster LZ, Beiner J, Duh‐Leong C, et al. Implementation of febrile infant management guidelines reduces hospitalization. Pediatric Qual Saf. 2020;5(1):e252. doi:10.1097/pq9.0000000000000252</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCulloh RJ, Commers T, Williams DD, Michael J, Mann K, Newland JG. Effect of combined clinical practice guideline and electronic order set implementation on febrile infant evaluation and management. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2021;37(1):e25‐e31. doi:10.1097/PEC.0000000000002012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guernsey D 3rd, Kostin S, Silver M, Vazquez H, Zerzan J. The evolving relationship between COVID‐19 and serious bacterial infection evaluation in febrile neonates. Acta Paediatr. 2023;112:1398‐1403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paret M, Lalani K, Hedari C, et al. SARS‐CoV‐2 among infants &lt;90 days of age admitted for serious bacterial infection evaluation. Pediatrics. 2021;148:e2020044685.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>