<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39280569</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Viral Etiology Associated With Acute Respiratory Tract Infection Patients in Bangkok, Thailand.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e66897</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e66897</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e66897</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.66897</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Acute respiratory infections (ARIs) are a significant public health concern globally. After the relaxation of COVID-19 containment measures, there has been an increase in respiratory tract infections. However, the epidemiological data on circulating respiratory pathogens after the COVID-19 pandemic in Bangkok, Thailand are interesting. We conducted a study on the respiratory pathogens detected in patients with ARIs in 2023. Methodology This retrospective study utilizes archived nasopharyngeal swab samples from patients with ARIs of all ages at Bangpakok 9 Hospital between January and December 2023. These samples were collected when physicians ordered multiplex polymerase chain reaction testing as part of the diagnostic investigation. All samples were tested for 23 types of respiratory viruses and bacteria using multiplex reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (QIAstat-Dx, Qiagen) testing. Results Of 321 patients, viral pathogens were found in 78.5% of cases, with 21.5% remaining unidentified. Most patients (47%) were aged between two months to five years. The most common pathogen identified was rhino/enterovirus (28.0%), followed by human parainfluenza virus (15.1%), influenza virus (12.0%), respiratory syncytial virus (9.9%), human metapneumovirus (9.5%), adenovirus (9.2%), bocavirus (8.0%), and coronavirus (5.5%). Interestingly, the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 infection was relatively low at 2.8%. Moreover, viral co-infection was observed in 25% of cases. Monthly distribution revealed the fluctuating prevalence of detected respiratory pathogens co-circulation throughout the year. In addition, the proportion of identified pathogens varied among patients across all age groups. Conclusions Our study reported the high prevalence of respiratory pathogens in ARI patients of all ages after the COVID-19 pandemic. The most prevalent respiratory pathogens among ARI cases were viruses, particularly rhino/enterovirus. The data hold significance for physician awareness regarding diagnosis, treatment, and the implementation of infection control strategies in cases of ARIs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Inma et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Inma</LastName><ForeName>Phattharaporn</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, THA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suntronwong</LastName><ForeName>Nungruthai</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, THA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sinsulpsiri</LastName><ForeName>Silpsiri</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence In Clinical Virology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, THA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srimaneewiroon</LastName><ForeName>Suriya</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bangpakok 9 International Laboratory, Bangpakok 9 International Hospital, Bangkok, THA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poovorawan</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, THA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory tract infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thailand</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Institutional Review Board of the Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University issued approval 0376/67. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11399110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.66897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Burden of disease scenarios for 204 countries and territories, 2022-2050: a forecasting analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet. 2024;403:2204–2256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11121021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38762325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The SARS-CoV-2 outbreak: what we know. Wu D, Wu T, Liu Q, Yang Z. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;94:44–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viral and atypical bacterial aetiologies of infection in hospitalised patients admitted with clinical suspicion of influenza in Thailand, Vietnam and Indonesia. Wertheim HF, Nadjm B, Thomas S, et al. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2015;9:315–322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4605413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25980749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas M, Bomar PA. Treasure Island, FL: StatPearls Publishing; 2023. Upper Respiratory Tract Infection.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30422556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novel SARS-CoV-2 variants: the pandemics within the pandemic. Boehm E, Kronig I, Neher RA, Eckerle I, Vetter P, Kaiser L. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2021;27:1109–1117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34015535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 public health interventions on influenza incidence in Thailand. Suntronwong N, Thongpan I, Chuchaona W, et al. Pathog Glob Health. 2020;114:225–227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7480427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotic prescribing in remote versus face-to-face consultations for acute respiratory infections in primary care in England: an observational study using target maximum likelihood estimation. Vestesson E, De Corte K, Chappell P, Crellin E, Clarke GM. EClinicalMedicine. 2023;64:102245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10568332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37842171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology and clinical characteristics of severe acute respiratory infections among hospitalized children under 5 years of age in a tertiary care center in Bangkok, Thailand, 2019-2020. Wanlapakorn N, Thongpan I, Sarawanangkoor N, et al. Heliyon. 2023;9:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10692904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38045212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Queensland Government. Acute Respiratory Infection - Infection Prevention and Control.  [
Aug;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.health.qld.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0025/1246228/acute-respiratory-infection.pdf https://www.health.qld.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0025/1246228/acute-respiratory-infection.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>QIAGEN. QIAstat-Dx ® Respiratory SARSCoV-2 Panel Instructions for Use (Handbook)  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.qiagen.com/us/resources/download.aspx?id=861ea5d1-4f8f-448f-a020-aad523cccb41&amp;lang=en https://www.qiagen.com/us/resources/download.aspx?id=861ea5d1-4f8f-448f-a020-aad523cccb41&amp;lang=en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>QIAGEN. QIAstat-Dx Analyzer 1.0 User Manual (Handbook)  [
Aug;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.qiagen.com https://www.qiagen.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sample size calculation for prevalence studies using Scalex and ScalaR calculators. Naing L, Nordin RB, Abdul Rahman H, Naing YT. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2022;22:209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9338613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35907796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changing epidemiology of influenza and other respiratory viruses in the first year of COVID-19 pandemic. Agca H, Akalin H, Saglik I, Hacimustafaoglu M, Celebi S, Ener B. J Infect Public Health. 2021;14:1186–1190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34399190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology of respiratory infections during the COVID-19 pandemic. Principi N, Autore G, Ramundo G, Esposito S. Viruses. 2023;15:1160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10224029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37243246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiological trends of respiratory tract pathogens detected via mPCR in Australian adult patients before COVID-19. Grech AK, Foo CT, Paul E, Aung AK, Yu C. BMC Infect Dis. 2024;24:38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10763466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38166699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changes in the prevalence of respiratory pathogens in children due to the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Tang Y, Dang X, Lv M, Norris SL, Chen Y, Ren L, Liu E. J Infect. 2023;86:154–225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9708107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36460171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dynamic patterns and predominance of respiratory pathogens post-COVID-19: insights from a two-year analysis. AlBahrani S, AlZahrani SJ, Al-Maqati TN, et al. J Epidemiol Glob Health. 2024;14:311–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11176149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38589755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Climate factors influence seasonal influenza activity in Bangkok, Thailand. Suntronwong N, Vichaiwattana P, Klinfueng S, Korkong S, Thongmee T, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y. PLoS One. 2020;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7523966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32991630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Respiratory syncytial virus, human metapneumovirus, and influenza virus infection in Bangkok, 2016-2017. Thongpan I, Suntronwong N, Vichaiwattana P, Wanlapakorn N, Vongpunsawad S, Poovorawan Y. PeerJ. 2019;7:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6462397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30997293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Respiratory viruses and influenza-like illness: epidemiology and outcomes in children aged 6 months to 10 years in a multi-country population sample. Taylor S, Lopez P, Weckx L, et al. J Infect. 2017;74:29–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27667752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology and clinical manifestations of different enterovirus and rhinovirus types show that EV-D68 may still have an impact on severity of respiratory infections. Larsson SB, Vracar D, Karlsson M, Ringlander J, Norder H. J Med Virol. 2022;94:3829–3839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9321759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35403229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seasonal prevalence of respiratory pathogens among children in the United Arab Emirates: a multicenter cross-sectional study in the pre-COVID-19 era. Salim S, Celiloglu H, Tayyab F, Malik ZA. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10576196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37842349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>