<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39224868</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1687-918X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2024</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Genetic Diversity of Human Enterovirus in Kazakhstan, during 2022.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>7796913</StartPage><MedlinePgn>7796913</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">7796913</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2024/7796913</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Enteroviral infection is a common cause of aseptic meningitis, herpangina, and hand, foot, and mouth disease in children. Limited data are available on the enteroviral subtypes associated with hospitalization for these conditions in Kazakhstan. We collected cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and nasopharyngeal swabs (NSW) from children (<i>N</i> = 152, median age = 8 years) hospitalized with symptoms of aseptic meningitis (AM, <i>N</i> = 139) or herpangina (HA, <i>N</i> = 13) disease. We then genotyped enteroviral subtypes associated with AM (<i>n</i> = 50) and HA (<i>n</i> = 9) using next-generation sequencing (NGS) on the viral protein 1 (VP1), followed up by whole-genome sequencing of the isolated viral species. All identified EVs were species B EV, consisting of five echoviruses (E6, E9, E11, E21, and E25) and three coxsackieviruses (CVA9, CVB3, and CVB5) serotypes within the cohort. The most abundant EVs were CVA9 (38.5%), CVB5 (21.5%), and E6 (13.8%). Most HA samples (6/9) were genotyped with coxsackievirus CVA9, while AM was associated with a variety of both echovirus and coxsackievirus serotypes. The results suggest that coxsackievirus CVA9 may be the dominant serotype circulating in the HA population, while AM is more diverse in terms of circulating echovirus and coxsackievirus serotypes. Further studies are needed to determine the clinical implications of these findings and to investigate potential differences in disease severity or outcomes associated with different EV serotypes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Dinara Kamalova et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kamalova</LastName><ForeName>Dinara</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>L. N. Gumilyov Eurasian National University, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akhmetova</LastName><ForeName>Assel</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amirgazin</LastName><ForeName>Asylulan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sytnik</LastName><ForeName>Igor</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rudenko</LastName><ForeName>Viktoriya</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Astana Medical University, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yessimkhanova</LastName><ForeName>Gulzhan</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Astana Medical University, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bayesheva</LastName><ForeName>Dinagul</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Astana Medical University, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yegorov</LastName><ForeName>Sergey</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology School of Sciences and Humanities Nazarbayev University, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shevtsov</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0307-1053</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology, Astana, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Egypt</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101516125</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39224868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11368554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2024/7796913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Park K., Lee B., Baek K., et al. Enteroviruses isolated from herpangina and hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Korean children. Virology Journal . 2012;9:p. 205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3490919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22985487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawyer M. H. Enterovirus infections: diagnosis and treatment. Seminars in Pediatric Infectious Diseases . 2002;13(1):40–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12118843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsino C. B., Ali R., Linklater D. R. StatPearls . Treasure Island, FL, USA: StatPearls Publishing; 2023. Herpangina.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29939569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero J. R. Hand, foot, and mouth disease and Herpangina. 2022.  
 https://www.uptodate.com/contents/hand-foot-and-mouth-disease-and-herpangina
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyypia T., Hovi T., Knowles N. J., Stanway G. Classification of enteroviruses based on molecular and biological properties. Journal of General Virology . 1997;78(Pt 1):1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9010279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Crom S. C., Rossen J. W., van Furth A. M., Obihara C. C. Enterovirus and parechovirus infection in children: a brief overview. European Journal of Pediatrics . 2016;175(8):1023–1029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4930465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27156106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pöyry T., Kinnunen L., Hyypiä T., et al. Genetic and phylogenetic clustering of enteroviruses. Journal of General Virology . 1996;77(Pt 8):1699–1717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8760417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasri D., Bouslama L., Omar S., et al. Typing of human enterovirus by partial sequencing of VP2. Journal of Clinical Microbiology . 2007;45(8):2370–2379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1951248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17537940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laitinen O. H., Svedin E., Kapell S., Nurminen A., Hytönen V. P., Flodström-Tullberg M. Enteroviral proteases: structure, host interactions and pathogenicity. Reviews in Medical Virology . 2016;26(4):251–267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7169145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27145174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joffret M. L., Polston P. M., Razafindratsimandresy R., Bessaud M., Heraud J. M., Delpeyroux F. Whole genome sequencing of enteroviruses species A to D by high-throughput sequencing: application for viral mixtures. Frontiers in Microbiology . 2018;9:p. 2339.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6172331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30323802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caro V., Guillot S., Delpeyroux F., Crainic R. Molecular strategy for “serotyping” of human enteroviruses. Journal of General Virology . 2001;82(Pt 1):79–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11125161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste M. S., Maher K., Kilpatrick D. R., Flemister M. R., Brown B. A., Pallansch M. A. Typing of human enteroviruses by partial sequencing of VP1. Journal of Clinical Microbiology . 1999;37(5):1288–1293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC84754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10203472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste M. S., Maher K., Kilpatrick D. R., Pallansch M. A. Molecular evolution of the human enteroviruses: correlation of serotype with VP1 sequence and application to picornavirus classification. Journal of Virology . 1999;73(3):1941–1948.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC104435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9971773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King A. M. Q. Family picornaviridae. Virus Taxonomy, Seventh Report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of viruses . 2000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bubba L., Martinelli M., Pellegrinelli L., et al. A 4-year study on epidemiologic and molecular characteristics of human parechoviruses and enteroviruses circulating in children younger than 5 Years in northern Italy. The Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal . 2017;36(1):13–19. doi: 10.1097/inf.0000000000001344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/inf.0000000000001344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27749661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stellrecht K. A., Harding I., Woron A. M., Lepow M. L., Venezia R. A. The impact of an enteroviral RT-PCR assay on the diagnosis of aseptic meningitis and patient management. Journal of Clinical Virology . 2002;25(Suppl 1):S19–S26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12091078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majer A., McGreevy A., Booth T. F. Molecular pathogenicity of enteroviruses causing neurological disease. Frontiers in Microbiology . 2020;11:p. 540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7161091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32328043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isaacs S. R., Kim K. W., Cheng J. X., et al. Amplification and next generation sequencing of near full-length human enteroviruses for identification and characterisation from clinical samples. Scientific Reports . 2018;8(1)11889</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6082906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30089864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews S. FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. 2010.  
 http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste M. S., Maher K., Pallansch M. A. Evidence for frequent recombination within species human enterovirus B based on complete genomic sequences of all thirty-seven serotypes. Journal of Virology . 2004;78(2):855–867.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC368751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14694117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darriba D., Posada D., Kozlov A. M., Stamatakis A., Morel B., Flouri T. ModelTest-NG: a new and scalable tool for the selection of DNA and protein evolutionary models. Molecular Biology and Evolution . 2020;37(1):291–294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6984357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31432070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Letunic I., Bork P. Interactive Tree of Life (iTOL): an online tool for phylogenetic tree display and annotation. Bioinformatics . 2007;23(1):127–128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17050570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H., Wang J., Chen J., et al. Molecular epidemiology and evolution of coxsackievirus A9. Viruses . 2022;14(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9024771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35458552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Y., Wei H., Wei L., et al. Molecular epidemiology reveals the Co-circulation of two genotypes of coxsackievirus B5 in China. Viruses . 2022;14(12)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9785520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Q., Yan D., Song Y., et al. Whole-genome analysis of coxsackievirus B3 reflects its genetic diversity in China and worldwide. Virology Journal . 2022;19(1):p. 69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9014606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35436962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng W., Ji T., Zhou S., et al. Molecular epidemiological characteristics of echovirus 6 in mainland China: extensive circulation of genotype F from 2007 to 2018. Archives of Virology . 2021;166(5):1305–1312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8036204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33638089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M., Guo W., Xu D., et al. Molecular characterization of echovirus 9 strains isolated from hand-foot-and-mouth disease in Kunming, Yunnan Province, China. Scientific Reports . 2022;12(1):p. 2293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8831506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35145190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J., Yan D., Chen L., et al. Multiple genotypes of Echovirus 11 circulated in mainland China between 1994 and 2017. Scientific Reports . 2019;9(1)10583</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6646367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31332200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grapin M., Mirand A., Pinquier D., et al. Severe and fatal neonatal infections linked to a new variant of echovirus 11, France, July 2022 to April 2023. Euro Surveillance . 2023;28(22)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10236930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37261730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S., Stecher G., Li M., Knyaz C., Tamura K. Mega X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. Molecular Biology and Evolution . 2018;35(6):1547–1549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5967553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29722887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K., Standley D. M. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability. Molecular Biology and Evolution . 2013;30(4):772–780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3603318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23329690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rambaut A., Lam T. T., Max Carvalho L., Pybus O. G. Exploring the temporal structure of heterochronous sequences using TempEst (formerly Path-O-Gen) Virus Evolution . 2016;2(1):p. vew007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4989882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27774300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. 
R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing
. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2022.  
 https://www.R-project.org
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oberste M. S., Maher K., Kennett M. L., et al. Molecular epidemiology and genetic diversity of echovirus type 30 (E30): genotypes correlate with temporal dynamics of E30 isolation. Journal of Clinical Microbiology . 1999;37(12):3928–3933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC85848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10565909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A., Borghesi A., Di Comite A., et al. Fulminant echovirus 11 hepatitis in male non-identical twins in northern Italy, April 2023. Euro Surveillance . 2023;28(24)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10318938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37318763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 
Enterovirus Infection-France
. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2023.  
 https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2023-DON469
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begaidarova R. K., Devdariani K. G., Baygutanova G. Z., Starikov Y. G., Dzhshibekova Z. Z., Zolotareva O. A. Clinical and laboratory features of enteroviral meningitis caused by echo-30 in children of different age groups. Medicine and Ecology . 2015;2(75):47–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bumburidi Y., Utepbergenova G., Yerezhepov B., et al. Etiology of acute meningitis and encephalitis from hospital-based surveillance in South Kazakhstan oblast, February 2017-January 2018. PLoS One . 2021;16(5)e0251494</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8121361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33989305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer L., Moreni G., Wolthers K. C., Pajkrt D. World-wide prevalence and genotype distribution of enteroviruses. Viruses . 2021;13(3) doi: 10.3390/v13030434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v13030434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7999254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33800518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W., Xu D., Cong S., et al. Co-infection and enterovirus B: post EV-A71 mass vaccination scenario in China. BMC Infectious Diseases . 2022;22(1):p. 671.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9354358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35927711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi M. H., Wong S. C., Podin Y., et al. Human enterovirus 71 disease in Sarawak, Malaysia: a prospective clinical, virological, and molecular epidemiological study. Clinical Infectious Diseases . 2007;44(5):646–656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17278054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F., Du J., Hu Y., et al. Enterovirus coinfection during an outbreak of hand, foot, and mouth disease in Shandong, China. Clinical Infectious Diseases . 2011;53(4):400–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21785005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batcup G., Holt P., Hambling M. H., Gerlis L. M., Glass M. R. Placental and fetal pathology in Coxsackie virus A9 infection: a case report. Histopathology . 1985;9(11):1227–1235. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2559.1985.tb02802.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2559.1985.tb02802.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4085986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y. C., Chu Y. H., Yen T. Y., et al. Clinical features and phylogenetic analysis of coxsackievirus A9 in northern Taiwan in 2011. BMC Infectious Diseases . 2013;13:p. 33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3565879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23347781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson J. E., Vogt P. K. Cell entry by non-enveloped viruses. Current Topics in Microbiology and Immunology . 2010;343</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21166102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shabani A., Makvandi M., Samarbafzadeh A., et al. Echovirus 30 and coxsackievirus A9 infection among young neonates with sepsis in Iran. Iranian Journal of Microbiology . 2018;10(4):258–265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6243150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30483379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui A., Yu D., Zhu Z., et al. An outbreak of aseptic meningitis caused by coxsackievirus A9 in Gansu, the People’s Republic of China. Virology Journal . 2010;7(1):p. 72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2907575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20367886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pabbaraju K., Wong S., Chan E. N., Tellier R. Genetic characterization of a Coxsackie A9 virus associated with aseptic meningitis in Alberta, Canada in 2010. Virology Journal . 2013;10:p. 93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3620579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23521862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smuts H., Cronje S., Thomas J., Brink D., Korsman S., Hardie D. Molecular characterization of an outbreak of enterovirus-associated meningitis in mossel Bay, South Africa, December 2015–January 2016. BMC Infectious Diseases . 2018;18(1):p. 709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6311073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30594238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itani T. M., Chalapa V. I., Slautin V. N., et al. Non-polio enterovirus surveillance in the ural federal district and western Siberia, 2022: is there a need for a vaccine? Vaccines . 2023;11(10):p. 1588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10610881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37896990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novikova N. A., Golitsina L. N., Fomina S. G., Efimov E. I. Molecular monitoring of non-polio enteroviruses in European territory of Russia in 2008–2011. Zhurnal Mikrobiologii, Epidemiologii i Immunobiologii . 2013;(1):75–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23805657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh S., Rawlinson W. D., Andrews P. I., Stelzer-Braid S. Global epidemiology of nonpolio enteroviruses causing severe neurological complications: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Reviews in Medical Virology . 2020;30(1)e2082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31588651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toczylowski K., Wieczorek M., Bojkiewicz E., Wietlicka-Piszcz M., Gad B., Sulik A. Pediatric enteroviral central nervous system infections in Bialystok, Poland: epidemiology, viral types, and drivers of seasonal variation. Viruses . 2020;12(8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7472221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32824117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu H., Zhang H., Zhang M., et al. Epidemiological and etiological characteristics of viral meningitis for hospitalized pediatric patients in Yunnan, China. Medicine (Baltimore) . 2022;101(26)e29772</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9239644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35777023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H. Y., Li Y., Xu A. Q., et al. Identification and phylogenic analysis of Coxsackie-virus B5 during an outbreak of aseptic meningitis in Shandong. Zhonghua Liuxingbingxue Zazhi . 2010;31(1):64–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20302702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farshadpour F., Taherkhani R. Molecular epidemiology of enteroviruses and predominance of echovirus 30 in an Iranian population with aseptic meningitis. Journal of NeuroVirology . 2021;27(3):444–451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33788142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Nonpolio enterovirus and human parechovirus surveillance—United States, 2006–2008. Morbidity &amp; Mortality Weekly Report . 2010;59(48):1577–1580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21150865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khetsuriani N., Kutateladze T., Zangaladze E., et al. High degree of genetic diversity of non-polio enteroviruses identified in Georgia by environmental and clinical surveillance, 2002–2005. Journal of Medical Microbiology . 2010;59(Pt 11):1340–1347.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20671086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrerizo M., Trallero G., Simmonds P. Recombination and evolutionary dynamics of human echovirus 6. Journal of Medical Virology . 2014;86(5):857–864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24114692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieczorek M., Figas A., Krzysztoszek A. Enteroviruses associated with aseptic meningitis in Poland, 2011–2014. Polish Journal of Microbiology . 2016;65(2):231–235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30015449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Z., Wang H., Li Y., Liu G., Xu A., Lin X. Molecular epidemiology of human enterovirus associated with aseptic meningitis in Shandong Province, China, 2006–2012. PLoS One . 2014;9(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3931826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24587020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J., Meng M., Xu H., et al. Analysis of enterovirus genotypes in the cerebrospinal fluid of children associated with aseptic meningitis in Liaocheng, China, from 2018 to 2019. BMC Infectious Diseases . 2021;21(1):p. 405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8088645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33933008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y., Zhou X., Liu J., et al. Molecular identification of human enteroviruses associated with aseptic meningitis in Yunnan province, Southwest China. SpringerPlus . 2016;5(1):p. 1515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5016492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27652088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramalho E., Sousa I., Jr., Burlandy F., et al. Identification and phylogenetic characterization of human enteroviruses isolated from cases of aseptic meningitis in Brazil, 2013–2017. Viruses . 2019;11(8):p. 690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6723535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31362357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamalova D., Akhmetova A., Amirgazin A., Sytnik I., Shevtsov A. Genetic diversity of enteroviral meningitis, herpangina and hand, foot, and mouth disease in Kazakhstan. Preprint (Version 1) Available at Research Square . 2023</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>