<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39216128</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>31</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-2448</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>266</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Water research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Water Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring waterborne viruses in groundwater: Quantification and Virome characterization via passive sampling and targeted enrichment sequencing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>122305</StartPage><MedlinePgn>122305</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.watres.2024.122305</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0043-1354(24)01204-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Aquifers, which provide drinking water for nearly half the world's population, face significant challenges from microbial contamination, particularly from waterborne viruses such as human adenovirus (HAdV), norovirus (NoV) and enterovirus (EV). This study, conducted as part of the UPWATER project, investigates the sources of urban groundwater contamination using viral passive sampling (VPS) and target enrichment sequencing (TES). We assessed the abundance of eight viral pathogens (HAdV, EV, NoV genogroup I and II, rotavirus, influenza A virus, hepatitis E virus and SARS-CoV-2) and investigated the virome diversity of groundwater in the aquifer of the Besòs River Delta in Catalonia. Over a period of 7 months, we collected 114 samples from the aquifer using nylon and nitrocellulose membranes to adsorb viruses over a 10-day period. Human faecal contamination was detected in nearly 50 % of the groundwater samples, with mean HAdV total counts ranging from 1.23E+02 to 3.66E+03 GC, and occasional detections of EV and NoV GI and GII. In addition, deep sequencing revealed a diverse virome in the aquifer, with detection of human pathogens, including adenovirus, astrovirus, calicivirus, enterovirus, herpesvirus, papillomavirus and rotavirus. Time-integrated sampling using VPS increases the likelihood of virus detection and, when combined with TES, can provide a deeper understanding of virus prevalence in this important water compartment. This approach is expected to streamline long-term monitoring efforts and enable small communities or water managers with limited resources to effectively manage their groundwater reservoirs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mejías-Molina</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viruses Contaminants of Water and Food, Secció de Microbiologia, Departament de Genètica, Microbiologia i Estadística, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08028 Barcelona, Spain; Institut de Recerca de l'Aigua (IdRA), Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08001 Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Estarlich-Landajo</LastName><ForeName>Ignasi</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viruses Contaminants of Water and Food, Secció de Microbiologia, Departament de Genètica, Microbiologia i Estadística, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08028 Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martínez-Puchol</LastName><ForeName>Sandra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viruses Contaminants of Water and Food, Secció de Microbiologia, Departament de Genètica, Microbiologia i Estadística, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08028 Barcelona, Spain; Vicerectorat de Recerca, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08007 Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bofill-Mas</LastName><ForeName>Sílvia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viruses Contaminants of Water and Food, Secció de Microbiologia, Departament de Genètica, Microbiologia i Estadística, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08028 Barcelona, Spain; Institut de Recerca de l'Aigua (IdRA), Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08001 Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rusiñol</LastName><ForeName>Marta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Viruses Contaminants of Water and Food, Secció de Microbiologia, Departament de Genètica, Microbiologia i Estadística, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08028 Barcelona, Spain; Institut de Recerca de l'Aigua (IdRA), Universitat de Barcelona (UB), 08001 Barcelona, Spain. Electronic address: mrusinol@ub.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Water Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0105072</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0043-1354</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adenovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Groundwater monitoring</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Norovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Passive sampling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Target enrichment sequencing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Marta Rusinol reports financial support was provided by European Commission. Marta Rusinol reports administrative support was provided by Government of Catalonia Agency for Administration of University and Research Grants. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39216128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2024.122305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0043-1354(24)01204-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>