<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39345463</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2692-8205</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>bioRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>TDRD3 functions as a selective autophagy receptor with dual roles in autophagy and modulation of stress granule stability.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.22.614367</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.22.614367</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Tudor Domain Containing 3 (TDRD3) is a methylarginine-reader protein that functions as a scaffold in the nucleus facilitating transcription, however TDRD3 is also recruited to stress granules (SGs) during the Integrated Stress Response (ISR) although its function therein remains largely unknown. We previously showed that TDRD3 is a novel antiviral restriction factor that is cleaved by virus 2A protease, and plays complex modulatory roles in both interferon and inflammatory signaling during stress and enterovirus infections. Here we have found that TDRD3 contains structural motifs similar to known selective autophagy receptors such as p62/SQSTM1, sharing ubiquitin associated domains (UBA) and LC3 interacting regions (LIR) that anchor cargo destined for autophagosomes to activated LC3 protein coating autophagosome membranes. This is of interest since enteroviruses hijack autophagy machinery to facilitate formation of viral replication factories, virus assembly and egress from the infected cell. Here we explored possible roles of TDRD3 in autophagy, hypothesizing that TDRD3 may function as a specialized selective autophagy receptor. We found that KO of TDRD3 in HeLa cells significantly reduces starvation induced autophagy, while its reintroduction restores it in a dose-dependent manner. Autophagy receptors are degraded during autophagy and expression levels decrease during this time. We found that TDRD3 levels decrease to the same extent as the autophagy receptor p62/SQSTM1 during autophagy, indicating autophagy-targeted turnover in that role. Knockout of TDRD3 or G3BP1 did not make significant changes in overall cell localization of LC3B or p62/SQSTM1, but did result in greater concentration of Lamp2 phagosome marker for phagosomes and phagolysosomes. To test the potential roles of TDRD3 in autophagic processes, we created a series of deletion mutants of TDRD3 lacking either UBA domain or the various LIR motifs that are predicted to interact with LC3B. Microscopic examination of starved cells expressing these variants of TDRD3 showed ΔLIR-TDRD3 had defects in colocalization with LC3B or Lamp2. Further, super resolution microscopy revealed ring structures with TDRD3 interfacing with p62/SQSTM1. In examination of arsenite induced stress granules we found recruitment of TDRD3 variants disrupted normally tight SG condensation, altered the decay rate of SGs upon release from stress and the kinetics of SG formation. We found evidence that the LIR3 motif on TDRD3 is involved in TDRD3 interaction with LC3B in coIP experiments, colocalization studies, and that this motif plays a key role in TDRD3 recruitment to SGs and SG resolution. Overall, these data support a functional role of TDRD3 in selective autophagy in a mode similar to p62/SQSTM1, with specific roles in SG stability and turnover. Enterovirus cleavage of TDRD3 likely affects both antiviral and autophagic responses that the virus controls for replication.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deater</LastName><ForeName>Matthew</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Immunology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lloyd</LastName><ForeName>Richard E</ForeName><Initials>RE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6550-3237</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Immunology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R44 AI150237</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>S10 OD028480</GrantID><Acronym>OD</Acronym><Agency>NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>bioRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101680187</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2692-8205</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Disclosures: The authors declare no competing interests exist</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>39</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11430058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.22.614367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.22.614367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Goulet I., Boisvenue S., Mokas S., Mazroui R. &amp; Côté J. TDRD3, a novel Tudor domain-containing protein, localizes to cytoplasmic stress granules. Human Molecular Genetics 17, 3055–3074 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2536506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18632687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y. et al. TDRD3 is an effector molecule for arginine-methylated histone marks. Mol Cell 40, 1016–1023 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3090733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21172665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linder B. et al. Tdrd3 is a novel stress granule-associated protein interacting with the Fragile-X syndrome protein FMRP. Human Molecular Genetics 17, 3236–3246 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18664458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morettin A. et al. Tudor Domain Containing Protein 3 Promotes Tumorigenesis and Invasive Capacity of Breast Cancer Cells. Sci Rep 7, 5153 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5506013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28698590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S. et al. The TDRD3-USP9X complex and MIB1 regulate TOP3B homeostasis and prevent deleterious TOP3B cleavage complexes. Nat. Commun. 14, 7524 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10657456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37980342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y. et al. Arginine methylation facilitates the recruitment of TOP3B to chromatin to prevent R loop accumulation. Mol Cell 53, 484–497 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3959860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24507716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pommier Y., Nussenzweig A., Takeda S. &amp; Austin C. Human topoisomerases and their roles in genome stability and organization. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 23, 407–427 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8883456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35228717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin M. et al. PRMT1 and TDRD3 promote stress granule assembly by rebuilding the protein-RNA interaction network. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 277, 134411 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39097054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deater M., Tamhankar M. &amp; Lloyd R. E. TDRD3 is an antiviral restriction factor that promotes IFN signaling with G3BP1. Plos Pathog 18, e1010249 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8824378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35085371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White J. P., Cardenas A. M., Marissen W. E. &amp; Lloyd R. E. Inhibition of cytoplasmic mRNA stress granule formation by a viral proteinase. Cell Host Microbe 2, 295–305 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18005751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visser L. J. et al. Essential Role of Enterovirus 2A Protease in Counteracting Stress Granule Formation and the Induction of Type I Interferon. J Virol 93, (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6498061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30867299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L. &amp; Yue J. The interplay of autophagy and enterovirus. Semin. Cell Dev. Biol. 101, 12–19 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31563390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C., Li Y. &amp; Li J. Dysregulated autophagy contributes to the pathogenesis of enterovirus A71 infection. Cell Biosci. 10, 142 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7724827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33298183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi J., Fung G., Piesik P., Zhang J. &amp; Luo H. Dominant-negative function of the C-terminal fragments of NBR1 and SQSTM1 generated during enteroviral infection. Cell Death Differ. 21, 1432–1441 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4131175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24769734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi J. et al. Cleavage of sequestosome 1/p62 by an enteroviral protease results in disrupted selective autophagy and impaired NFKB signaling. Autophagy 9, 1591–1603 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23989536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchan J. R., Kolaitis R.-M., Taylor J. P. &amp; Parker R. Eukaryotic Stress Granules Are Cleared by Autophagy and Cdc48/VCP Function. Cell 153, 1461–1474 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3760148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23791177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seguin S. J. et al. Inhibition of autophagy, lysosome and VCP function impairs stress granule assembly. Cell Death Differ 21, 1838–1851 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4227144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25034784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Z. &amp; Klionsky D. J. An overview of the molecular mechanism of autophagy. Curr. Top. Microbiol. Immunol. 335, 1–32 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2832191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19802558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan L. &amp; Rubinsztein D. C. The autophagy of stress granules. FEBS Lett. 598, 59–72 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38101818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monahan Z., Shewmaker F. &amp; Pandey U. B. Stress granules at the intersection of autophagy and ALS. Brain Res 1649, 189–200 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5055418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27181519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M. et al. The Eukaryotic Linear Motif resource: 2022 release. Nucleic Acids Res 50, D497–D508 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8728146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34718738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmussen N. L., Kournoutis A., Lamark T. &amp; Johansen T. NBR1: The archetypal selective autophagy receptor. J. Cell Biol. 221, e202208092 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9582228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36255390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mizushima N. &amp; Yoshimori T. How to Interpret LC3 Immunoblotting. Autophagy 3, 542–545 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17611390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahani M. H., Itakura E. &amp; Mizushima N. Expression of the autophagy substrate SQSTM1/p62 is restored during prolonged starvation depending on transcriptional upregulation and autophagy-derived amino acids. Autophagy 10, 431–441 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4077882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24394643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gayatri S. &amp; Bedford M. T. Readers of histone methylarginine marks. Biochim Biophys Acta 1839, 702–710 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4099268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24583552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirchner P. et al. Proteome-wide analysis of chaperone-mediated autophagy targeting motifs. PLoS Biol. 17, e3000301 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6561683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31150375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen J. A. &amp; Yates R. M. Better Together: Current Insights Into Phagosome-Lysosome Fusion. Front. Immunol. 12, 636078 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7946854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33717183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oughtred R. et al. The BioGRID database: A comprehensive biomedical resource of curated protein, genetic, and chemical interactions. Protein Sci. 30, 187–200 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7737760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33070389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y. G. &amp; Zhang H. The Incredible ULKs: Autophagy and Beyond. Mol. Cell 62, 475–476 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27203174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calderilla-Barbosa L. et al. Interaction of SQSTM1 with the motor protein dynein – SQSTM1 is required for normal dynein function and trafficking. J. Cell Sci. 127, 4052–4063 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4163647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25015291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chitiprolu M. et al. A complex of C9ORF72 and p62 uses arginine methylation to eliminate stress granules by autophagy. Nat. Commun. 9, 2794 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6052026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30022074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qamar S. et al. FUS Phase Separation Is Modulated by a Molecular Chaperone and Methylation of Arginine Cation-π Interactions. Cell 173, 720–734.e15 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5927716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29677515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai W.-C., Reineke L. C., Jain A., Jung S. Y. &amp; Lloyd R. E. Histone arginine demethylase JMJD6 is linked to stress granule assembly through demethylation of the stress granule-nucleating protein G3BP1. J Biol Chem 292, 18886–18896 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5704473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28972166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang H. J. et al. LC3B is an RNA-binding protein to trigger rapid mRNA degradation during autophagy. Nat. Commun. 13, 1436 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8931120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35302060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gwon Y. et al. Ubiquitination of G3BP1 mediates stress granule disassembly in a context-specific manner. Science 372, eabf6548 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8574224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34739333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wirth M. et al. Phosphorylation of the LIR Domain of SCOC Modulates ATG8 Binding Affinity and Specificity. J. Mol. Biol. 433, 166987 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8202330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33845085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reggiori F. &amp; Klionsky D. J. Autophagy in the eukaryotic cell. Eukaryot. cell 1, 11–21 (2002).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC118053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12455967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L., Klionsky D. J. &amp; Shen H.-M. The emerging mechanisms and functions of microautophagy. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 24, 186–203 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36097284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arias E. &amp; Cuervo A. M. Chaperone-mediated autophagy in protein quality control. Curr. Opin. Cell Biol. 23, 184–189 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3078170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21094035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollenstein D. M. &amp; Kraft C. Autophagosomes are formed at a distinct cellular structure. Curr. Opin. Cell Biol. 65, 50–57 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7588827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32203894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y. &amp; Reggiori F. Molecular regulation of autophagosome formation. Biochem. Soc. Trans. 50, 55–69 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9022990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35076688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakatogawa H. Mechanisms governing autophagosome biogenesis. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 21, 439–458 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32372019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Axe E. L. et al. Autophagosome formation from membrane compartments enriched in phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate and dynamically connected to the endoplasmic reticulum. J. Cell Biol. 182, 685–701 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2518708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18725538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosokawa N. et al. Nutrient-dependent mTORC1 Association with the ULK1–Atg13–FIP200 Complex Required for Autophagy. Mol. Biol. Cell 20, 1981–1991 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2663915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19211835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brier L. W. et al. Regulation of LC3 lipidation by the autophagy-specific class III phosphatidylinositol-3 kinase complex. Mol. Biol. Cell 30, 1098–1107 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6724508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30811270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazio F. et al. mTOR inhibits autophagy by controlling ULK1 ubiquitylation, self-association and function through AMBRA1 and TRAF6. Nat. Cell Biol. 15, 406–416 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23524951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olivas T. J. et al. ATG9 vesicles comprise the seed membrane of mammalian autophagosomes. J. Cell Biol. 222, e202208088 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10148236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37115958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeda S. et al. Structure, lipid scrambling activity and role in autophagosome formation of ATG9A. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 27, 1194–1201 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7718406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33106659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matoba K. et al. Atg9 is a lipid scramblase that mediates autophagosomal membrane expansion. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 27, 1185–1193 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33106658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birgisdottir Å. B., Lamark T. &amp; Johansen T. The LIR motif – crucial for selective autophagy. J. Cell Sci. 126, 3237–3247 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23908376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercer T. J., Gubas A. &amp; Tooze S. A. A molecular perspective of mammalian autophagosome biogenesis. J. Biol. Chem. 293, 5386–5395 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5900756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29371398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen L. E. et al. Membrane curvature sensing and stabilization by the autophagic LC3 lipidation machinery. Sci. Adv. 8, eadd1436 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9750143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36516251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dancourt J. &amp; Melia T. J. Lipidation of the autophagy proteins LC3 and GABARAP is a membrane-curvature dependent process. Autophagy 10, 1470–1471 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4203524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24991828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogov V. V. et al. Atg8 family proteins, LIR/AIM motifs and other interaction modes. Autophagy Rep. 2, 27694127.2023.2188523 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7615515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38214012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>