<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39315747</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-0496</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pediatric pulmonology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Pulmonol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical characteristics of Chinese children with EV-D68-associated pneumonia: A single-center retrospective analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ppul.27285</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Human enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) has been associated with an increase in mild-to-severe pediatric respiratory diseases in western countries. However, the prevalence and clinical characteristics of EV-D68-associated pneumonia in China remain understudied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Between January 2022 and January 2024, 28 patients with EV-D68-associated pneumonia were enrolled. We described the prevalence, demographic, and clinical characteristics of patients with EV-D68-associated pneumonia.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among the 28 enrolled patients, the male-to-female ratio was 1.5:1, and the average age at onset was 4.6 ± 2.7 years. Four (14.3%) required intensive care support. Monoinfection occurred in 11 cases (39.3%), while coinfections were seen in 17 cases (60.7%). 82.1% of patients had a history of one or more atopic diseases. The primary symptoms of EV-D68-associated pneumonia included cough (100%), wheezing (53.6%), and fever (53.6%). Radiologically, patchy opacity was the predominant feature, observed in 72.7% of cases. No statistically significant differences were found in symptoms, laboratory tests, or imaging findings between the monoinfection and coinfection groups. Except for one case who developed quadriplegia sequelae, all patients had a favorable prognosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">EV-D68 is not a common pathogen for community-acquired pneumonia in China. It mainly affects young children, particularly those with atopic constitution. The overall prognosis is favorable, although neurological complications are rare and may lead to severe sequelae. This study is the first investigation into the prevalence and clinical characteristics of EV-D68-associated pneumonia in China.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Shasha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tang</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Min</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Lei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Su</LastName><ForeName>Yanyan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yanqiong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yuemei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department, Children's Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University, Henan Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou Children's Hospital, Zhengzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Yuelin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-3206-610X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory Department II, National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases, National Center for Children's Health, Beijing Children's Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NRMC0107</GrantID><Agency>National Regional Medical Center Opening Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2024YLZDJH358</GrantID><Agency>Zhengzhou Science and Technology Innovation Guidance Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Pulmonol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8510590</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1099-0496</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chinese children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">atopic constitution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community‐acquired pneumonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enterovirus D68</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39315747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ppul.27285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abedi GR, Watson JT, Nix WA, Oberste MS, Gerber SI. Enterovirus and parechovirus surveillance—United States, 2014–2016. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2018;67(18):515‐518. doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm6718a2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greninger AL, Naccache SN, Messacar K, et al. A novel outbreak enterovirus D68 strain associated with acute flaccid myelitis cases in the USA (2012–14): a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2015;15(6):671‐682. doi:10.1016/S1473-3099(15)70093-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyrdak R, Grabbe M, Hammas B, et al. Outbreak of enterovirus D68 of the new B3 lineage in Stockholm, Sweden, August to September 2016. Euro Surveill. 2016;21(46):30403. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2016.21.46.30403</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun KW. Community‐acquired pneumonia in children: updated perspectives on its etiology, diagnosis, and treatment. Clin Exp Pediatr. 2024;67(2):80‐89. doi:10.3345/cep.2022.01452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan HH, Tsai CR, Ting PJ, et al. Respiratory presentation of patients infected with enterovirus D68 in Taiwan. Pediatr Neonatol. 2020;61(2):168‐173. doi:10.1016/j.pedneo.2019.09.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fall A, Han L, Abdullah O, et al. An increase in enterovirus D68 circulation and viral evolution during a period of increased influenza like illness, the Johns Hopkins Health System, USA, 2022. J Clin Virol. 2023;160:105379. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2023.105379</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duval M, Mirand A, Lesens O, et al. Retrospective study of the upsurge of enterovirus D68 clade D1 among adults (2014–2018). Viruses. 2021;13(8):1607. doi:10.3390/v13081607</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cottrell S, Moore C, Perry M, Hilvers E, Williams C, Shankar AG. Prospective enterovirus D68 (EV‐D68) surveillance from September 2015 to November 2018 indicates a current wave of activity in Wales. Euro Surveill. 2018;23(46):1800578. doi:10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2018.23.46.1800578</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwin J, Reyes Domingo F, Booth T, et al. Surveillance summary of hospitalized pediatric enterovirus D68 cases in Canada, September 2014. Can Commun Dis Rep. 2015;41(suppl 1):2‐8. doi:10.14745/ccdr.v41is1a01</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggs HM, Nix WA, Zhang J, et al. Enterovirus D68 infection among hospitalized children with severe acute respiratory illness in El Salvador and Panama, 2012–2013. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15(2):181‐187. doi:10.1111/irv.12815</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltola V, Österback R, Waris M, et al. Enterovirus D68 outbreak in children, Finland, August–September 2022. Emerging Infect Dis. 2023;29(6):1258‐1261. doi:10.3201/eid2906.221795</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridhar A, Depla JA, Mulder LA, et al. Enterovirus D68 infection in human primary airway and brain organoids: no additional role for heparan sulfate binding for neurotropism. Microbiol Spectr. 2022;10(5):e0169422. doi:10.1128/spectrum.01694-22</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piralla A, Principi N, Ruggiero L, et al. Enterovirus‐D68 (EV‐D68) in pediatric patients with respiratory infection: the circulation of a new B3 clade in Italy. J Clin Virol. 2018;99‐100:91‐96. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2018.01.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imamura T, Oshitani H. Global reemergence of enterovirus D68 as an important pathogen for acute respiratory infections. Rev Med Virol. 2015;25(2):102‐114. doi:10.1002/rmv.1820</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y, Musharrafieh R, Zheng M, Wang J. Enterovirus D68 antivirals: past, present, and future. ACS Infect Dis. 2020;6(7):1572‐1586. doi:10.1021/acsinfecdis.0c00120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sooksawasdi Na Ayudhya S, Laksono BM, van Riel D. The pathogenesis and virulence of enterovirus‐D68 infection. Virulence. 2021;12(1):2060‐2072. doi:10.1080/21505594.2021.1960106</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yogo N, Imamura T, Muto Y, Hirai K. Cardiopulmonary failure as a result of brainstem encephalitis caused by enterovirus D68. BMJ Case Rep. 2019;12(11):e231990. doi:10.1136/bcr-2019-231990</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun S, Bian L, Gao F, et al. A neonatal mouse model of enterovirus D68 infection induces both interstitial pneumonia and acute flaccid myelitis. Antiviral Res. 2019;161:108‐115. doi:10.1016/j.antiviral.2018.11.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsumoto M, Awano H, Ogi M, et al. A pediatric patient with interstitial pneumonia due to enterovirus D68. J Infect Chemother. 2016;22(10):712‐715. doi:10.1016/j.jiac.2016.03.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vazquez‐Perez JA, Ramirez‐Gonzalez JE, Moreno‐Valencia Y, et al. EV‐D68 infection in children with asthma exacerbation and pneumonia in Mexico City during 2014 autumn. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2016;10(3):154‐160. doi:10.1111/irv.12384</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poelman R, Schuffenecker I, Van Leer‐Buter C, Josset L, Niesters HGM, Lina B. European surveillance for enterovirus D68 during the emerging North‐American outbreak in 2014. J Clin Virol. 2015;71:1‐9. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2015.07.296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filipe IC, Guedes MS, Zdobnov EM, Tapparel C. Enterovirus D: a small but versatile species. Microorganisms. 2021;9(8):1758. doi:10.3390/microorganisms9081758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen‐Tran H, Thompson C, Butler M, et al. Duration of enterovirus D68 RNA shedding in the upper respiratory tract and transmission among household contacts, Colorado, USA. Emerging Infect Dis. 2023;29(11):2315‐2324. doi:10.3201/eid2911.230947</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong L, Wang Y, Zhang W, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis in children in Zhejiang province, China. Front Neurol. 2020;11:360. doi:10.3389/fneur.2020.00360</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Zampiero A, Ruggiero L, Madini B, Niesters H, Principi N. Enterovirus D68‐associated community‐acquired pneumonia in children living in Milan, Italy. J Clin Virol. 2015;68:94‐96. doi:10.1016/j.jcv.2015.05.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito S, Chidini G, Cinnante C, et al. Acute flaccid myelitis associated with enterovirus‐D68 infection in an otherwise healthy child. Virol J. 2017;14(1):4. doi:10.1186/s12985-016-0678-0</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>