<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314969</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Detection of enterovirus RNA in pancreas and lymphoid tissues of organ donors with type 1 diabetes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.11.24313112</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.11.24313112</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIMS/HYPOTHESIS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The nPOD-Virus group collaboratively applied innovative technologies to detect and sequence viral RNA in pancreas and other tissues from organ donors with type 1 diabetes. These analyses involved the largest number of pancreas samples collected to date.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We analysed pancreas, spleen, pancreatic lymph nodes, and duodenum samples from the following donor groups: a) donors with type 1 diabetes (n=71), with (n=35) or without (n=36) insulin-containing islets, (b) donors with single or double islet autoantibody positivity without diabetes (n=22) and c) autoantibody-negative donors without diabetes (control donors) (n=74). Five research laboratories participated in this collaborative effort using approaches for unbiased discovery of RNA viruses (two RNA-Seq platforms), targeted detection of <i>Enterovirus A-D</i> species using RT-PCR, and tests for virus growth in cell-culture.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Direct RNA-Seq did not detect virus signal in pancreas samples, whereas RT-PCR detected enterovirus RNA confirmed by sequencing in low amounts in pancreas samples in three of the five donor groups, namely donors with type 1 diabetes with insulin-containing islets, 16% (5/32) donors being positive, donors with single islet autoantibody positivity with 53% (8/15) donors being positive, and non-diabetic donors with 8% (4/49) being enterovirus RNA positive. Detection of enterovirus RNA was significantly more frequent in single islet autoantibody-positive donors compared to donors with type 1 diabetes with insulin-deficient islets (p-value &lt;0.001) and control donors (p-value 0.004). In some donors, pancreatic lymph nodes were also positive. RT-PCR detected enterovirus RNA also in spleen of a small number of donors and virus enrichment in susceptible cell lines before RT-PCR resulted in much higher rate in spleen positivity, particularly in donors with type 1 diabetes. Interestingly, the enterovirus strains detected did not cause a typical lytic infection, possibly reflecting their persistence-prone nature.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS/INTERPRETATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This was the largest coordinated effort to examine the presence of enterovirus RNA in pancreas of organ donors with type 1 diabetes, using a multitude of assays. These findings are consistent with the notion that both the subjects with type 1 diabetes and those with islet autoantibodies may carry a low-grade enterovirus infection in the pancreas and lymphoid tissues.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laiho</LastName><ForeName>Jutta E</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oikarinen</LastName><ForeName>Sami</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morfopoulou</LastName><ForeName>Sofia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation, UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health, University College London, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oikarinen</LastName><ForeName>Maarit</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Renner</LastName><ForeName>Ashlie</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Microbiology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Depledge</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NYU, Grossman School of Medicine, New York, New York, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ross</LastName><ForeName>Matthew C</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Microbiology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alkek Center for Metagenomics and Microbiome Research, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gerling</LastName><ForeName>Ivan C</ForeName><Initials>IC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Endocrinology, Diabetes, and Metabolism, Department of Medicine, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Breuer</LastName><ForeName>Judith</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation, UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health, University College London, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Petrosino</LastName><ForeName>Joseph F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Microbiology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alkek Center for Metagenomics and Microbiome Research, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Plagnol</LastName><ForeName>Vincent</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Genomics PLC, Oxford, Oxfordshire, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pugliese</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Diabetes Immunology, Arthur Riggs Diabetes &amp; Metabolism Research Institute, Beckmann Research Institute, City of Hope, Duarte, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toniolo</LastName><ForeName>Antonio</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Virus Network, University of Insubria, Varese, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lloyd</LastName><ForeName>Richard E</ForeName><Initials>RE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Microbiology, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hyöty</LastName><ForeName>Heikki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology, Tampere University, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fimlab Laboratories, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Tampere University Hospital, Tampere, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>JDRF nPOD-Virus Group</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI050237</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enterovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Islet autoimmunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lymph nodes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Organ donors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pancreas</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Persistent infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spleen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Type 1 diabetes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interest H.H. is a board member and stock owner of Vactech Oy, a Finnish biotech company which has contributed to the development of a coxsackie B virus vaccine. No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this work were reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.11.24313112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.11.24313112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Richardson SJ, Willcox A, Bone AJ, Foulis AK, Morgan NG. The prevalence of enteroviral capsid protein vp1 immunostaining in pancreatic islets in human type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2009;52(6):1143–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19266182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotta F, Censini S, van Halteren AGS, Marselli L, Masini M, Dionisi S, et al. Coxsackie B4 virus infection of beta cells and natural killer cell insulitis in recent-onset type 1 diabetic patients. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007. Mar 20;104(12):5115–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1829272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17360338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krogvold L, Edwin B, Buanes T, Frisk G, Skog O, Anagandula M, et al. Detection of a low-grade enteroviral infection in the islets of langerhans of living patients newly diagnosed with type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2015;64(5):1682–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ylipaasto P, Klingel K, Lindberg AM, Otonkoski T, Kandolf R, Hovi T, et al. Enterovirus infection in human pancreatic islet cells, islet tropism in vivo and receptor involvement in cultured islet beta cells. Diabetologia. 2004;47(2):225–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14727023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shibasaki S, Imagawa A, Tauriainen S, Iino M, Oikarinen M, Abiru H, et al. Expression of toll-like receptors in the pancreas of recent-onset fulminant type 1 diabetes. Endocr J. 2010;57(3):211–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20009359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen S, Krogvold L, Edwin B, Buanes T, Korsgren O, Laiho JE, et al. Characterisation of enterovirus RNA detected in the pancreas and other specimens of live patients with newly diagnosed type 1 diabetes in the DiViD study. Diabetologia. 2021. Nov;64(11):2491–501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8494699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34390364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenson AB, Rosenberg HS, Notkins AL. Pancreatic islet-cell damage in children with fatal viral infections. Lancet Lond Engl. 1980;2(8190):354–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6105486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bissel SJ, Winkler CC, DelTondo J, Wang G, Williams K, Wiley CA. Coxsackievirus B4 myocarditis and meningoencephalitis in newborn twins. Neuropathol Off J Jpn Soc Neuropathol. 2014. Oct;34(5):429–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4188796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24702280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krogvold L, Genoni A, Puggioni A, Campani D, Richardson SJ, Flaxman CS, et al. Live enteroviruses, but not other viruses, detected in human pancreas at the onset of type 1 diabetes in the DiViD study. Diabetologia. 2022. Aug 12;</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9630231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35953727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elshebani A, Olsson A, Westman J, Tuvemo T, Korsgren O, Frisk G. Effects on isolated human pancreatic islet cells after infection with strains of enterovirus isolated at clinical presentation of type 1 diabetes. Virus Res. 2007;124(1–2):193–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17169456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ifie E, Russell MA, Dhayal S, Leete P, Sebastiani G, Nigi L, et al. Unexpected subcellular distribution of a specific isoform of the Coxsackie and adenovirus receptor, CAR-SIV, in human pancreatic beta cells. Diabetologia. 2018;(Journal Article).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6182664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30074059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vehik K, Lynch KF, Wong MC, Tian X, Ross MC, Gibbs RA, et al. Prospective virome analyses in young children at increased genetic risk for type 1 diabetes. Nat Med. 2019;25(12):1865–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6898786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31792456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Op de Beeck A, Eizirik DL. Viral infections in type 1 diabetes mellitus--why the β cells? Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2016;12(5):263–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5348720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27020257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tracy S, Smithee S, Alhazmi A, Chapman N. Coxsackievirus can Persist in Murine Pancreas by Deletion of 5 ‘ Terminal Genomic Sequences. J Med Virol. 2015;87(2):240–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25111164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Kim KS. Persistent coxsackievirus infection: enterovirus persistence in chronic myocarditis and dilated cardiomyopathy. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 2008;323(Journal Article):275–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18357775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen M, Tauriainen S, Oikarinen S, Honkanen T, Collin P, Rantala I, et al. Type 1 diabetes is associated with enterovirus infection in gut mucosa. Diabetes. 2012. Mar;61(3):687–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3282798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22315304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen M, Tauriainen S, Honkanen T, Oikarinen S, Vuori K, Kaukinen K, et al. Detection of enteroviruses in the intestine of type 1 diabetic patients. Clin Exp Immunol. 2008;151(1):71–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2276929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17991291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercalli A, Lampasona V, Klingel K, Albarello L, Lombardoni C, Ekström J, et al. No evidence of enteroviruses in the intestine of patients with type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2012. Sep;55(9):2479–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22684312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell-Thompson ML, Montgomery EL, Foss RM, Kolheffer KM, Phipps G, Schneider L, et al. Collection protocol for human pancreas. J Vis Exp JoVE. 2012. May 23;(63):e4039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3466941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22665046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depledge DP, Palser AL, Watson SJ, Lai IYC, Gray ER, Grant P, et al. Specific capture and whole-genome sequencing of viruses from clinical samples. PloS One. 2011;6(11):e27805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3220689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22125625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson SJ, Leete P, Bone AJ, Foulis AK, Morgan NG. Expression of the enteroviral capsid protein VP1 in the islet cells of patients with type 1 diabetes is associated with induction of protein kinase R and downregulation of Mcl-1. Diabetologia. 2013;56(1):185–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23064357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson SJ, Rodriguez-Calvo T, Gerling IC, Mathews CE, Kaddis JS, Russell MA, et al. Islet cell hyperexpression of HLA class I antigens: a defining feature in type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2016;59(11):2448–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5042874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27506584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown JR, Roy S, Ruis C, Yara Romero E, Shah D, Williams R, et al. Norovirus Whole-Genome Sequencing by SureSelect Target Enrichment: a Robust and Sensitive Method. J Clin Microbiol. 2016. Oct;54(10):2530–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5035417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27487952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmieder R, Edwards R. Quality control and preprocessing of metagenomic datasets. Bioinforma Oxf Engl. 2011. Mar 15;27(6):863–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3051327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21278185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ. Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol. 1990. Oct 5;215(3):403–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2231712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zerbino DR, Birney E. Velvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs. Genome Res. 2008. May;18(5):821–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2336801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18349386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langmead B, Salzberg SL. Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2. Nat Methods. 2012. Mar 4;9(4):357–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3322381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22388286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morfopoulou S, Plagnol V. Bayesian mixture analysis for metagenomic community profiling. Bioinforma Oxf Engl. 2015. Sep 15;31(18):2930–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4565032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26002885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Vries JJC, Brown JR, Fischer N, Sidorov IA, Morfopoulou S, Huang J, et al. Benchmark of thirteen bioinformatic pipelines for metagenomic virus diagnostics using datasets from clinical samples. J Clin Virol Off Publ Pan Am Soc Clin Virol. 2021. Aug;141:104908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7615111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34273858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duncan CJA, Mohamad SMB, Young DF, Skelton AJ, Leahy TR, Munday DC, et al. Human IFNAR2 deficiency: Lessons for antiviral immunity. Sci Transl Med. 2015. Sep 30;7(307):307ra154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4926955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26424569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morfopoulou S, Brown JR, Davies EG, Anderson G, Virasami A, Qasim W, et al. Human Coronavirus OC43 Associated with Fatal Encephalitis. N Engl J Med. 2016. Aug 4;375(5):497–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27518687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morfopoulou S, Mee ET, Connaughton SM, Brown JR, Gilmour K, Chong WK, Kling,” et al. Deep sequencing reveals persistence of cell-associated mumps vaccine virus in chronic encephalitis. Acta Neuropathol (Berl). 2017. Jan;133(1):139–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5209397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27770235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lum SH, Turner A, Guiver M, Bonney D, Martland T, Davies E, et al. An emerging opportunistic infection: fatal astrovirus (VA1/HMO-C) encephalitis in a pediatric stem cell transplant recipient. Transpl Infect Dis Off J Transplant Soc. 2016. Dec;18(6):960–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27632248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown JR, Morfopoulou S, Hubb J, Emmett WA, Ip W, Shah D, et al. Astrovirus VA1/HMO-C: an increasingly recognized neurotropic pathogen in immunocompromised patients. Clin Infect Dis Off Publ Infect Dis Soc Am. 2015. Mar 15;60(6):881–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4345817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25572899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honkanen H, Oikarinen S, Pakkanen O, Ruokoranta T, Pulkki MM, Laitinen OH, et al. Human enterovirus 71 strains in the background population and in hospital patients in Finland. J Clin Virol Off Publ Pan Am Soc Clin Virol. 2013;56(4):348–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23261080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genoni A, Canducci F, Rossi A, Broccolo F, Chumakov K, Bono G, et al. Revealing enterovirus infection in chronic human disorders: An integrated diagnostic approach. Sci Rep. 2017;7(1):5013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5504018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28694527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maccari G, Genoni A, Sansonno S, Toniolo A. Properties of Two Enterovirus Antibodies that are Utilized in Diabetes Research. Sci Rep. 2016. Apr 19;6:24757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4835795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27091243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson SJ, Leete P, Dhayal S, Russell MA, Oikarinen M, Laiho JE, et al. Evaluation of the fidelity of immunolabelling obtained with clone 5D8/1, a monoclonal antibody directed against the enteroviral capsid protein, VP1, in human pancreas. Diabetologia. 2014;57(2):392–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24190581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM, Kim KS, Drescher KM, Oka K, Tracy S. 5’ terminal deletions in the genome of a coxsackievirus B2 strain occurred naturally in human heart. Virology. 2008;375(2):480–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2440640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18378272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KS, Tracy S, Tapprich W, Bailey J, Lee CK, Kim K, et al. 5’-Terminal deletions occur in coxsackievirus B3 during replication in murine hearts and cardiac myocyte cultures and correlate with encapsidation of negative-strand viral RNA. J Virol. 2005. Jun;79(11):7024–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1112132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15890942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen M, Bertolet L, Toniolo A, Oikarinen S, Laiho JE, Pugliese A, et al. Differential Detection of Encapsidated versus Unencapsidated Enterovirus RNA in Samples Containing Pancreatic Enzymes—Relevance for Diabetes Studies. Viruses. 2020. Jul;12(7):747.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7411921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32664501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapman NM. Persistent Enterovirus Infection: Little Deletions, Long Infections. Vaccines. 2022. May;10(5):770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9143164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35632526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim PY, Hickey AC, Jamiluddin MF, Hamid S, Kramer J, Santos R, et al. Immunogenicity and performance of an enterovirus 71 virus-like-particle vaccine in nonhuman primates. Vaccine. 2015. Nov 4;33(44):6017–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26271825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingel K, McManus BM, Kandolf R. Enterovirus-infected immune cells of spleen and lymph nodes in the murine model of chronic myocarditis: a role in pathogenesis? Eur Heart J. 1995. Dec;16 Suppl O:42–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8682099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho-Yen DO, Hardie R, McClure J, Cunningham NE, Bell EJ. Fatal outcome of echovirus 7 infection. Scand J Infect Dis. 1989;21(4):459–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2587948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingel K, Kandolf R. Molecular in situ localization techniques in diagnosis and pathogenicity studies of enteroviral heart disease. Clin Diagn Virol. 1996. May;5(2–3):157–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15566874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geravandi S, Richardson S, Pugliese A, Maedler K. Localization of enteroviral RNA within the pancreas in donors with T1D and T1D-associated autoantibodies. Cell Rep Med. 2021. Aug 17;2(8):100371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8385321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34467248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honkimaa A, Sioofy-Khojine AB, Oikarinen S, Bertin A, Hober D, Hyöty H. Eradication of persistent coxsackievirus B infection from a pancreatic cell line with clinically used antiviral drugs. J Clin Virol Off Publ Pan Am Soc Clin Virol. 2020;128(Journal Article):104334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32450550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Vainionpää R, Kettinen H, Hyypiä T. Coxsackievirus B3 infection in human leukocytes and lymphoid cell lines. Blood. 1994. Aug 1;84(3):823–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8043865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mena I, Perry CM, Harkins S, Rodriguez F, Gebhard J, Whitton JL. The Role of B Lymphocytes in Coxsackievirus B3 Infection. Am J Pathol. 1999;155(4):1205–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1867001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10514403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuorinen T, Vainionpää R, Vanharanta R, Hyypiä T. Susceptibility of human bone marrow cells and hematopoietic cell lines to coxsackievirus B3 infection. J Virol. 1996. Dec;70(12):9018–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC191003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8971035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sioofy-Khojine AB, Richardson SJ, Locke JM, Oikarinen S, Nurminen N, Laine AP, et al. Detection of enterovirus RNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cells correlates with the presence of the predisposing allele of the type 1 diabetes risk gene IFIH1 and with disease stage. Diabetologia. 2022. Jul 22;</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9477938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35867130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker RE, Yang W, Vecchi GA, Takahashi S. Increasing intensity of enterovirus outbreaks projected with climate change. Nat Commun. 2024. Jul 31;15(1):6466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11291881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39085256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>