<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39342950</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2666-5247</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Microbe</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Microbe</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence and clinical relevance of viraemia in viral respiratory tract infections: a systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100967</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100967</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.lanmic.2024.100967</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2666-5247(24)00220-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this Review, we analysed the prevalence of viraemia during infection with SARS-CoV-2 and other relevant respiratory viruses, including other human coronaviruses such as MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV, adenovirus, human metapneumovirus, human rhinovirus/enterovirus, influenza A and B virus, parainfluenza virus, and respiratory syncytial virus. First, a preliminary systematic search was conducted to identify articles published before May 23, 2024 that reported on viraemia during infection with respiratory viruses. The articles were then analysed for relevant terms to identify the prevalence of viraemia, its association with the disease severity and long-term consequences, and host responses. A total of 202 articles were included in the final study. The pooled prevalence of viraemia was 34% for SARS-CoV-2 and between 6% and 65% for other viruses. Association of viraemia with disease severity was extensively reported for SARS-CoV-2 and also for SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, adenoviruses, rhinoviruses, respiratory syncytial virus, and influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 (albeit with low evidence). SARS-CoV-2 viraemia was linked to memory problems and worsened quality of life. Viraemia was associated with signatures denoting dysregulated host responses. In conclusion, the high prevalence of viraemia and its association with disease severity suggests that viraemia could be a relevant pathophysiological event with important translational implications in respiratory viral infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hagman</LastName><ForeName>Karl</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg, Sweden; Department of Infectious Diseases, Institute of Biomedicine, Sahlgrenska Academy at University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Postigo</LastName><ForeName>Tamara</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Group for Biomedical Research in Respiratory Infection &amp; Sepsis (BioSepsis), Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Salamanca (IBSAL), Gerencia Regional de Salud de Castilla y León, Salamanca, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diez-Castro</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomy and Histology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Salamanca, Salamanca, Spain; Group for Biomedical Research in Neuroendocrinology and Obesity, IBSAL, University of Salamanca, Salamanca, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ursing</LastName><ForeName>Johan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Danderyd Hospital, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden; Department of Clinical Sciences, Danderyd Hospital, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bermejo-Martin</LastName><ForeName>Jesús F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Group for Biomedical Research in Respiratory Infection &amp; Sepsis (BioSepsis), Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Salamanca (IBSAL), Gerencia Regional de Salud de Castilla y León, Salamanca, Spain; Department of Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Salamanca, Salamanca, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red en Enfermedades Respiratorias (CIBERES, CB22/06/00035), Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: jfbermejo@usal.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de la Fuente</LastName><ForeName>Amanda</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Group for Biomedical Research in Respiratory Infection &amp; Sepsis (BioSepsis), Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Salamanca (IBSAL), Gerencia Regional de Salud de Castilla y León, Salamanca, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red en Enfermedades Respiratorias (CIBERES, CB22/06/00035), Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tedim</LastName><ForeName>Ana P</ForeName><Initials>AP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Group for Biomedical Research in Respiratory Infection &amp; Sepsis (BioSepsis), Instituto de Investigación Biomédica de Salamanca (IBSAL), Gerencia Regional de Salud de Castilla y León, Salamanca, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red en Enfermedades Respiratorias (CIBERES, CB22/06/00035), Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Microbe</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101769019</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2666-5247</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests JFB-M has a patent application on SARS-CoV-2 antigenaemia as a predictor of mortality in COVID-19. The remaining authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39342950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lanmic.2024.100967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2666-5247(24)00220-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>