<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39420189</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2052-4463</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific data</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Data</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Human pathogen nucleic acids in wastewater solids from 191 wastewater treatment plants in the United States.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1141</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1141</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1141</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41597-024-03969-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We measured concentrations of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and its variants, influenza A and B viruses, respiratory syncytial virus, human metapneumovirus, enterovirus D68, human parainfluenza types 1, 2, 3, 4a, and 4b in aggregate, norovirus genotype II, rotavirus, Candida auris, hepatitis A virus, human adenovirus, mpox virus, H5 influenza A virus, and pepper mild mottle virus nucleic acids in wastewater solids prospectively at 191 wastewater treatment plants in 40 states across the United States plus Washington DC. Measurements were made two to seven times per week from 1 January 2022 to 30 June 2024, depending on wastewater treatment plant staff availability. Measurements were made using droplet digital (reverse-transcription-) polymerase chain reaction (ddRT-PCR) following best practices for making environmental molecular biology measurements. These data can be used to better understand disease occurrence in communities contributing to the wastewater.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boehm</LastName><ForeName>Alexandria B</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8162-5090</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering, School of Engineering and Doerr School of Sustainability, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA. aboehm@stanford.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wolfe</LastName><ForeName>Marlene K</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gangarosa Department of Environmental Health, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bidwell</LastName><ForeName>Amanda L</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering, School of Engineering and Doerr School of Sustainability, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zulli</LastName><ForeName>Alessandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering, School of Engineering and Doerr School of Sustainability, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan-Herur</LastName><ForeName>Vikram</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences, South San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>White</LastName><ForeName>Bradley J</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences, South San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shelden</LastName><ForeName>Bridgette</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences, South San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duong</LastName><ForeName>Dorothea</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Verily Life Sciences, South San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D064886">Dataset</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Data</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101640192</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2052-4463</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D009696">Nucleic Acids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="Y">Wastewater</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002175" MajorTopicYN="N">Candida</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009696" MajorTopicYN="N">Nucleic Acids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Bradley White, Dorothea Duong, Bridgette Shelden, and Vikram Chan-Herur are employees of Verily Life Sciences. The other authors have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39420189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41597-024-03969-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41597-024-03969-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bivins, A. et al. Wastewater-Based Epidemiology: Global Collaborative to Maximize Contributions in the Fight Against COVID-19. Environ. Sci. Technol.54, 7754–7757 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32530639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B., Wolfe, M. K., White, B. J., Hughes, B. &amp; Duong, D. Divergence of wastewater SARS-CoV-2 and reported laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 incident case data coincident with wide-spread availability of at-home COVID-19 antigen tests. PeerJ11, e15631 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10312197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37397016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. Wastewater concentrations of human influenza, metapneumovirus, parainfluenza, respiratory syncytial virus, rhinovirus, and seasonal coronavirus nucleic-acids during the COVID-19 pandemic: a surveillance study. The Lancet Microbe4, e340–e348 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10032662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36965504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. Human norovirus (HuNoV) GII RNA in wastewater solids at 145 United States wastewater treatment plants: Comparison to positivity rates of clinical specimens and modeled estimates of HuNoV GII shedders. Journal of Exposure Science &amp; Environmental Epidemiology10.1038/s41370-023-00592-4 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11222142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37550566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber, C. et al. Community-Scale Wastewater Surveillance of Candida auris during an Ongoing Outbreak in Southern Nevada. Environ. Sci. Technol.57, 1755–1763 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9893721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36656763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCall, C., Wu, H., Miyani, B. &amp; Xagoraraki, I. Identification of multiple potential viral diseases in a large urban center using wastewater surveillance. Water Research184, 116160 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7342010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32738707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe, M. K. et al. Detection of Hemagglutinin H5 Influenza A Virus Sequence in Municipal Wastewater Solids at Wastewater Treatment Plants with Increases in Influenza A in Spring, 2024. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.11, 526–532 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe, M. K. et al. Use of Wastewater for Mpox Outbreak Surveillance in California. N Engl J Med10.1056/NEJMc2213882 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36652340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowry, S. A., Wolfe, M. K. &amp; Boehm, A. B. Respiratory virus concentrations in human excretions that contribute to wastewater: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Journal of Water and Health jwh2023057 10.2166/wh.2023.057 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37387346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin, Z., Voice, T., Tarabara, V. &amp; Xagoraraki, I. Sorption of Human Adenovirus to Wastewater Solids. Journal of Environmental Engineering144, 06018008 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roldan-Hernandez, L., Van Oost, C. &amp; Boehm, A. Solid-liquid partitioning of Dengue, West Nile, Zika, Hepatitis A, Influenza A, and SARS-CoV-2 viruses in wastewater from across the United States. Environ. Sci.: Water Res. Technol. 10.1039/D4EW00225C (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye, Y., Ellenberg, R. M., Graham, K. E. &amp; Wigginton, K. R. Survivability, Partitioning, and Recovery of Enveloped Viruses in Untreated Municipal Wastewater. Environ. Sci. Technol.50, 5077–5085 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27111122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symonds, E. M., Nguyen, K. H., Harwood, V. J. &amp; Breitbart, M. Pepper mild mottle virus: A plant pathogen with a greater purpose in (waste)water treatment development and public health management. Water Research144, 1–12 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6162155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30005176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McClary-Gutierrez, J. S. et al. Standardizing data reporting in the research community to enhance the utility of open data for SARS-CoV-2 wastewater surveillance. Environ. Sci.: Water Res. Technol.7, 1545–1551 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8459677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34567579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson, A. et al. Effect of storage conditions on SARS-CoV-2 RNA quantification in wastewater solids. PeerJ9, e11933 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8364322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34447628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. Human viral nucleic acids concentrations in wastewater solids from Central and Coastal California USA. Scientific Data10, 396 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10287720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37349355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huisman, J. S. et al. Wastewater-based estimation of the effective reproductive number of SARS-CoV-2. Environmental Health Perspectives130, 057011–1 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9135136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35617001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoen, M. E. et al. SARS-CoV-2 RNA Wastewater Settled Solids Surveillance Frequency and Impact on Predicted COVID-19 Incidence Using a Distributed Lag Model. ACS EST Water10.1021/acsestwater.2c00074 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9092194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36380770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galani, A. et al. SARS-CoV-2 wastewater surveillance data can predict hospitalizations and ICU admissions. Science of The Total Environment804, 150151 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8421077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34623953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, M., Roldan-Hernandez, L. &amp; Boehm, A. Persistence of human respiratory viral RNA in wastewater-settled solids. Applied and Environmental Microbiology90, e02272–23 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11022535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38501669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roldan-Hernandez, L. &amp; Boehm, A. B. Adsorption of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), rhinovirus, SARS-CoV-2, and F + bacteriophage MS2 RNA onto wastewater solids from raw wastewater. Environmental Science &amp; Technology (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10501194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37647137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AWWA. Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater. (American Public Health Association, American Water Works Association, Water Environment Federation, Baltimore, 2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topol, A., Wolfe, M., White, B., Wigginton, K. &amp; Boehm, A. High Throughput pre-analytical processing of wastewater settled solids for SARS-CoV-2 RNA analyses. protocols.io10.17504/protocols.io.btyqnpvw (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topol, A., Wolfe, M., Wigginton, K., White, B. &amp; Boehm, A. High Throughput RNA Extraction and PCR Inhibitor Removal of Settled Solids for Wastewater Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 RNA. protocols.io10.17504/protocols.io.btyrnpv6 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kantor, R. S., Nelson, K. L., Greenwald, H. D. &amp; Kennedy, L. C. Challenges in Measuring the Recovery of SARS-CoV-2 from Wastewater. Environ. Sci. Technol.55, 3514–3519 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33656856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borchardt, M. A. et al. The Environmental Microbiology Minimum Information (EMMI) Guidelines: qPCR and dPCR Quality and Reporting for Environmental Microbiology. Environ. Sci. Technol.55, 10210–10223 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34286966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The dMIQE Group &amp; Huggett, J. F. The Digital MIQE Guidelines Update: Minimum Information for Publication of Quantitative Digital PCR Experiments for 2020. Clinical Chemistry66, 1012–1029 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32746458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe, M. K. et al. High-Frequency, High-Throughput Quantification of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in Wastewater Settled Solids at Eight Publicly Owned Treatment Works in Northern California Shows Strong Association with COVID-19 Incidence. mSystems6, e00829–21 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8547422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34519528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topol, A., Wolfe, M., White, B., Wigginton, K. &amp; Boehm, A. High Throughput SARS-COV-2, PMMOV, and BCoV quantification in settled solids using digital RT-PCR. protocols.io10.17504/protocols.io.btywnpxe (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. Data for Human pathogen nucleic acids in wastewater solids from 191 wastewater treatment plants in the United States. Stanford Digital Repository 10.25740/hj801ns5929 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39420189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins, L. et al. Citywide wastewater SARS-CoV-2 levels strongly correlated with multiple disease surveillance indicators and outcomes over three COVID-19 waves. Science of The Total Environment855, 158967 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36162580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe, M. K. et al. Wastewater-Based Detection of Two Influenza Outbreaks. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.9, 687–692 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes, B. et al. Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV) RNA in Wastewater Settled Solids Reflects RSV Clinical Positivity Rates. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.9, 173–178 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfe, M. K. et al. Detection of SARS-CoV-2 Variants Mu, Beta, Gamma, Lambda, Delta, Alpha, and Omicron in Wastewater Settled Solids Using Mutation-Specific Assays Is Associated with Regional Detection of Variants in Clinical Samples. Applied and Environmental Microbiology0, e00045-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9040616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35380449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, A. et al. Estimating relative abundance of two SARS-CoV-2 variants through wastewater surveillance at two large metropolitan sites. Emerging Infect. Dis.28, 940–947 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9045426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35349402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. Regional Replacement of SARS-CoV-2 Variant Omicron BA.1 with BA.2 as Observed through Wastewater Surveillance. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.9, 575–580 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9159514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35711323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulli, A., Varkila, M. R. J., Parsonnet, J., Wolfe, M. K. &amp; Boehm, A. B. Observations of Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV) Nucleic Acids in Wastewater Solids Across the United States in the 2022–2023 Season: Relationships with RSV Infection Positivity and Hospitalization Rates. ACS EST Water10.1021/acsestwater.3c00725 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11019535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38633368</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zulli, A. et al. Prospective study of Candida auris nucleic-acids in wastewater solids in 190 wastewater treatment plants in the United States suggests widespread occurrence. mBio15, e00908–24 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11323724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39041799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoen, M. E., Bidwell, A. L., Wolfe, M. K. &amp; Boehm, A. B. United States Influenza 2022–2023 Season Characteristics as Inferred from Wastewater Solids, Influenza Hospitalization, and Syndromic Data. Environ. Sci. Technol.57, 20542–20550 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10720384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38014848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. More than a Tripledemic: Influenza A Virus, Respiratory Syncytial Virus, SARS-CoV-2, and Human Metapneumovirus in Wastewater during Winter 2022–2023. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.10, 622–627 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10413932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37577361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. et al. Trends of Enterovirus D68 Concentrations in Wastewater, California, USA, February 2021–April 2023. Emerging Infectious Disease journal29, 2362 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10617337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37877593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehm, A. B. et al. A retrospective longitudinal study of adenovirus group F, norovirus GI and GII, rotavirus, and enterovirus nucleic-acids in wastewater solids at two wastewater treatment plants: Solid-liquid partitioning and relation to clinical testing data. mSphere9, e00736–23 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10964402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38411118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhao, H., Wilkins, K., Hughes, C. &amp; Damon, I. K. Real-time PCR assays for the specific detection of monkeypox virus West African and Congo Basin strain DNA. Journal of Virological Methods169, 223–227 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9628942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20643162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jothikumar, N. et al. Quantitative real-time PCR assays for detection of human adenoviruses and identification of serotypes 40 and 41. Applied and Environmental Microbiology71, 3131–3136 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1151802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15933012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham, K. E. et al. SARS-CoV-2 RNA in Wastewater Settled Solids Is Associated with COVID-19 Cases in a Large Urban Sewershed. Environ. Sci. Technol.55, 488–498 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33283515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>