<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39422382</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Macrophages can transmit coxsackievirus B4 to pancreatic cells and can impair these cells.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70009</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70009</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.70009</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Macrophages are suspected to be involved in the pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. The role of macrophages in the transmission of coxsackievirus B4 (CVB4) to pancreatic cells and in the alteration of these cells was investigated. Human monocytes isolated from peripheral blood were differentiated into macrophages with M-CSF (M-CSF macrophages) or GM-CSF (GM-CSF macrophages). M-CSF macrophages were inoculated with CVB4. M-CSF and GM-CSF macrophages were activated with lipopolysaccharide and interferon (IFN)-γ. Human pancreatic beta cells 1.1B4 were inoculated with CVB4 derived from M-CSF macrophages or were cocultured with CVB4-infected M-CSF macrophages. The antiviral activity of synthetic molecules in macrophage cultures was evaluated. Activated macrophages were cocultured with CVB4-persistently infected 1.1B4 cells, and the specific lysis of these cells was determined. Our study shows that CVB4 can infect M-CSF macrophages, leading to the release of interleukin-6 and tumor necrosis factor-α and later IFN-α. M-CSF macrophage-derived CVB4 can infect 1.1B4 cells, which were then altered; however, when these cells were cultured in medium containing agarose, cell layers were not altered. Fluoxetine and CUR-N373 can inhibit CVB4 replication in macrophage cultures. Supernatants of activated M-CSF and GM-CSF macrophage cultures induced lysis of CVB4-persistently infected 1.1B4 cells. The cytolytic activity of activated GM-CSF macrophages was higher towards CVB4-persistently infected 1.1B4 cells than mock-infected 1.1B4 cells. In conclusion, macrophages may play a role in CVB4 infection of pancreatic cells, and are capable of inducing lysis of infected pancreatic cells.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Medical Virology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vergez</LastName><ForeName>Inès</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nekoua</LastName><ForeName>Magloire Pandoua</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2981-0803</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arbrandt</LastName><ForeName>Gustav</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curovir, Tengelinsgatan 12, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Westman</LastName><ForeName>Jacob</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curovir, Tengelinsgatan 12, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alidjinou</LastName><ForeName>Enagnon Kazali</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1106-9826</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hober</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4301-2074</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratoire de Virologie URL3610, Univ. Lille et CHU Lille, Lille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016207">Cytokines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>81627-83-0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016173">Macrophage Colony-Stimulating Factor</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008264" MajorTopicYN="Y">Macrophages</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029822" MajorTopicYN="Y">Enterovirus B, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D050417" MajorTopicYN="N">Insulin-Secreting Cells</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003384" MajorTopicYN="N">Coxsackievirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002460" MajorTopicYN="N">Cell Line</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018920" MajorTopicYN="N">Coculture Techniques</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002478" MajorTopicYN="N">Cells, Cultured</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016207" MajorTopicYN="N">Cytokines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016173" MajorTopicYN="N">Macrophage Colony-Stimulating Factor</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CUR‐N373</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coxsackievirus B4</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cytolytic activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fluoxetine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">macrophages</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pancreatic cells</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39422382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.70009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Simmonds P, Gorbalenya AE, Harvala H, et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of enteroviruses and rhinoviruses. Arch Virol. 2020;165(3):793‐797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hober D, Sauter P. Pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus: interplay between enterovirus and host. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2010;6(5):279‐289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeung WCG, Rawlinson WD, Craig ME. Enterovirus infection and type 1 diabetes mellitus: systematic review and meta‐analysis of observational molecular studies. BMJ. 2011;342:d35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaïdane H, Hober D. Role of coxsackievirus B4 in the pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Metab. 2008;34(6):537‐548.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Ye F, Chen Y, et al. Association between enterovirus infection and type 1 diabetes risk: a meta‐analysis of 38 case‐control studies. Front Endocrinol. 2021;12:706964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Alidjinou EK, Hober D. Persistent coxsackievirus B infection and pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2022;18(8):503‐516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Debuysschere C, Vergez I, et al. Viruses and endocrine diseases. Microorganisms. 2023;11(2):361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Chehadeh W, Weill J, et al. Monocytes of patients with type 1 diabetes harbour enterovirus RNA. Eur J Clin Invest. 2015;45(9):918‐924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen M, Tauriainen S, Oikarinen S, et al. Type 1 diabetes is associated with enterovirus infection in gut mucosa. Diabetes. 2012;61(3):687‐691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikarinen S, Martiskainen M, Tauriainen S, et al. Enterovirus RNA in blood is linked to the development of type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2011;60(1):276‐279.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin H, Berg AK, Westman J, Hellerström C, Frisk G. Complete nucleotide sequence of a coxsackievirus B‐4 strain capable of establishing persistent infection in human pancreatic islet cells: effects on insulin release, proinsulin synthesis, and cell morphology. J Med Virol. 2002;68(4):544‐557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willcox A, Richardson SJ, Bone AJ, Foulis AK, Morgan NG. Analysis of islet inflammation in human type 1 diabetes. Clin Exp Immunol. 2009;155(2):173‐181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calderon B, Suri A, Unanue ER. In CD4+ T‐cell‐induced diabetes, macrophages are the final effector cells that mediate islet β‐cell killing. Am J Pathol. 2006;169(6):2137‐2147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jun HS, Yoon CS, Zbytnuik L, van Rooijen N, Yoon JW. The role of macrophages in T cell–mediated autoimmune diabetes in nonobese diabetic mice. J Exp Med. 1999;189(2):347‐358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Gassen N, Staels W, Van Overmeire E, et al. Concise review: macrophages: versatile gatekeepers during pancreatic β‐cell development, injury, and regeneration. Stem Cells Transl Med. 2015;4(6):555‐563.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Mercier A, Vergez I, et al. Coxsackievirus B infection and pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. Virologie. 2022;26(6):415‐430.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou E, Sané F, Trauet J, Copin MC, Hober D. Coxsackievirus B4 can infect human peripheral blood‐derived macrophages. Viruses. 2015;7(11):6067‐6079.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Bertin A, Sane F, et al. Pancreatic beta cells persistently infected with coxsackievirus B4 are targets of NK cell‐mediated cytolytic activity. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2020;77(1):179‐194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nekoua MP, Bertin A, Sane F, et al. Persistence of coxsackievirus B4 in pancreatic β cells disturbs insulin maturation, pattern of cellular proteins, and DNA methylation. Microorganisms. 2021;9(6):1125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chehadeh W, Kerr‐Conte J, Pattou F, et al. Persistent infection of human pancreatic islets by coxsackievirus B is associated with alpha interferon synthesis in β cells. J Virol. 2000;74(21):10153‐10164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCluskey JT, Hamid M, Guo‐Parke H, McClenaghan NH, Gomis R, Flatt PR. Development and functional characterization of insulin‐releasing human pancreatic beta cell lines produced by electrofusion. J Biol Chem. 2011;286(25):21982‐21992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sane F, Caloone D, Gmyr V, et al. Coxsackievirus B4 can infect human pancreas ductal cells and persist in ductal‐like cell cultures which results in inhibition of Pdx1 expression and disturbed formation of islet‐like cell aggregates. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2013;70(21):4169‐4180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel DYS, Glim JE, Stavenuiter AWD, et al. Human macrophage polarization in vitro: maturation and activation methods compared. Immunobiology. 2014;219(9):695‐703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzmán C, Bagga M, Kaur A, Westermarck J, Abankwa D. ColonyArea: an ImageJ plugin to automatically quantify colony formation in clonogenic assays. PLoS One. 2014;9(3):e92444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Sané F, Bertin A, Caloone D, Hober D. Persistent infection of human pancreatic cells with coxsackievirus B4 is cured by fluoxetine. Antiviral Res. 2015;116:51‐54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benkahla MA, Alidjinou EK, Sane F, Desailloud R, Hober D. Fluoxetine can inhibit coxsackievirus‐B4 E2 in vitro and in vivo. Antiviral Res. 2018;159:130‐133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sioofy‐Khojine AB, Honkimaa A, Hyöty H. A preclinical assessment to repurpose drugs to target type 1 diabetes‐associated type B coxsackieviruses. Diabetic Med. 2020;37(11):1849‐1853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benkahla MA, Elmastour F, Sane F, et al. Coxsackievirus‐B4E2 can infect monocytes and macrophages in vitro and in vivo. Virology. 2018;522:271‐280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei X, Xiao X, Wang J. Innate immunity evasion by enteroviruses: insights into Virus‐Host interaction. Viruses. 2016;8(1):22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong X, Zhou J, Zhu W, et al. Excessive proinflammatory cytokine and chemokine responses of human monocyte‐derived macrophages to enterovirus 71 infection. BMC Infect Dis. 2012;12(1):224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Paget M, Wang C, Zhu Z, Zheng H. Innate immune evasion by picornaviruses. Eur J Immunol. 2020;50(9):1268‐1282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cifuentes‐Munoz N, El Najjar F, Dutch RE. Viral cell‐to‐cell spread: conventional and non‐conventional ways. Adv Virus Res. 2020;108:85‐125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netanyah E, Calafatti M, Arvastsson J, Cabrera‐Rode E, Cilio CM, Sarmiento L. Extracellular vesicles released by enterovirus‐infected endoC‐βH1 cells mediate non‐lytic viral spread. Microorganisms. 2020;8(11):1753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sin J, McIntyre L, Stotland A, Feuer R, Gottlieb RA. Coxsackievirus B escapes the infected cell in ejected mitophagosomes. J Virol. 2017;91(24):e01347‐17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owusu IA, Quaye O, Passalacqua KD, Wobus CE. Egress of non‐enveloped enteric RNA viruses. J Gen Virol. 2021;102(3):001557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson SJ, Leete P, Bone AJ, Foulis AK, Morgan NG. Expression of the enteroviral capsid protein VP1 in the islet cells of patients with type 1 diabetes is associated with induction of protein kinase R and downregulation of Mcl‐1. Diabetologia. 2013;56(1):185‐193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krogvold L, Edwin B, Buanes T, et al. Detection of a low‐grade enteroviral infection in the islets of langerhans of living patients newly diagnosed with type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 2014;64(5):1682‐1687.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertin A, Sane F, Gmyr V, et al. Coxsackievirus‐B4 infection of human primary pancreatic ductal cell cultures results in impairment of differentiation into insulin‐producing cells. Viruses. 2019;11(7):597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alidjinou EK, Engelmann I, Bossu J, et al. Persistence of Coxsackievirus B4 in pancreatic ductal-like cells results in cellular and viral changes. Virulence. 2017;8:1229‐1244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yap IS, Giddings G, Pocock E, Chantler JK. Lack of islet neogenesis plays a key role in beta‐cell depletion in mice infected with a diabetogenic variant of coxsackievirus B4. J Gen Virol. 2003;84(Pt 11):3051‐3068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganor Y, Real F, Sennepin A, et al. HIV‐1 reservoirs in urethral macrophages of patients under suppressive antiretroviral therapy. Nat Microbiol. 2019;4(4):633‐644.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sattentau QJ, Stevenson M. Macrophages and HIV‐1 – an unhealthy constellation. Cell Host Microbe. 2016;19(3):304‐310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavegnano C, Schinazi RF. Antiretroviral therapy in macrophages: implication for HIV eradication. Antiviral Chem Chemother. 2009;20(2):63‐78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulferts R, de Boer SM, van der Linden L, et al. Screening of a library of FDA‐approved drugs identifies several enterovirus replication inhibitors that target viral protein 2C. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016;60(5):2627‐2638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Wang M, Cheng A, et al. Enterovirus replication organelles and inhibitors of their formation. Front Microbiol. 2020;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan YW, Yam WK, Kooi RJW, Westman J, Arbrandt G, Chu JJH. Novel capsid binder and PI4KIIIbeta inhibitors for EV‐A71 replication inhibition. Sci Rep. 2021;11:9719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>First‐in‐human Clinical Trial Evaluating CUR‐N399 in Healthy Volunteers. Curovir. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasu S, McClenaghan NH, McCluskey JT, Flatt PR. Mechanisms of toxicity by proinflammatory cytokines in a novel human pancreatic beta cell line, 1.1B4. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2014;1840(1):136‐145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brozzi F, Nardelli TR, Lopes M, et al. Cytokines induce endoplasmic reticulum stress in human, rat and mouse beta cells via different mechanisms. Diabetologia. 2015;58(10):2307‐2316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Zakharov PN, Peterson OJ, Unanue ER. Cytocidal macrophages in symbiosis with CD4 and CD8 T cells cause acute diabetes following checkpoint blockade of PD‐1 in NOD mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2020;117(49):31319‐31330.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaguin M, Houlbert N, Fardel O, Lecureur V. Polarization profiles of human M‐CSF‐generated macrophages and comparison of M1‐markers in classically activated macrophages from GM‐CSF and M‐CSF origin. Cell Immunol. 2013;281(1):51‐61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rey‐Giraud F, Hafner M, Ries CH. In vitro generation of monocyte‐derived macrophages under serum‐free conditions improves their tumor promoting functions. PLoS One. 2012;7(8):e42656.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bazzi S, El‐Darzi E, McDowell T, et al. Cytokine/chemokine release patterns and transcriptomic profiles of LPS/IFNγ‐activated human macrophages differentiated with heat‐killed mycobacterium obuense, M‐CSF, or GM‐CSF. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(13):7214.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>