<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39411664</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2732-494X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Antimicrobial stewardship &amp; healthcare epidemiology : ASHE</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Respiratory virus infections in symptomatic and asymptomatic children upon hospital admission: new insights.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e162</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e162</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e162</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1017/ash.2024.407</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Describe and compare the prevalence of symptomatic and asymptomatic or recently resolved respiratory infections in hospitalized children.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Cross-sectional study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Three hospital primary-to-quaternary care pediatric healthcare system.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">People less than 22 years old who underwent admission screening for respiratory viruses using a multitarget polymerase chain reaction (PCR) panel from August 2020 through April 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The symptom status of each patient was recorded by the ordering provider. The prevalence of each virus was described comparing symptomatic and asymptomatic patients. Results for each virus were stratified by age group and trends were examined over time.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Of the 32,812 eligible PCR panels collected, 12,965 (39.5%), 18,651 (56.8%), and 1,196 (3.6%) were obtained from patients who were symptomatic, asymptomatic, or had missing or unknown symptom status, respectively. Symptomatic patients were much more likely to test positive for a respiratory virus (67.3% vs 27.0%). The most common viruses detected in asymptomatic patients were rhinovirus/enterovirus (18.0%), SARS-CoV-2 (3.6%), and parainfluenza viruses (2.3%). The odds ratio of testing positive when symptomatic was significantly greater than unity for all viruses but varied by virus and age group. The proportion of positive tests for each virus was dynamic and changed with intermittent epidemics, or viral "waves."</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">More than one-quarter of children without respiratory symptoms admitted to a pediatric healthcare system had PCR-detectable respiratory viruses. Children with symptoms of a respiratory infection are nevertheless much more likely to have a respiratory virus detected by PCR.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Most</LastName><ForeName>Zachary M</ForeName><Initials>ZM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7021-8951</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease, Department of Pediatrics, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's Health System of Texas, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Peter O'Donnell, Jr. School of Public Health, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perl</LastName><ForeName>Trish M</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9539-2358</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and Geographic Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Peter O'Donnell, Jr. School of Public Health, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sebert</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4136-150X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease, Department of Pediatrics, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's Health System of Texas, Dallas, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918266096106676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2732-494X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>None.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39411664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11474761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/ash.2024.407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2732494X24004078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Armstrong GL, Pinner RW. Outpatient visits for infectious diseases in the United States, 1980 through 1996. Arch Intern Med 1999;159:2531–2536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10573043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byington CL, Ampofo K, Stockmann C, et al. community surveillance of respiratory viruses among families in the Utah better identification of germs-longitudinal viral epidemiology (BIG-LoVE) study. Clin Infect Dis 2015;61:1217–1224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4583580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26245665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairchok MP, Martin ET, Chambers S, et al. Epidemiology of viral respiratory tract infections in a prospective cohort of infants and toddlers attending daycare. J Clin Virol 2010;49:16–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20650679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pappas DE, Hendley JO. The common cold and decongestant therapy. Pediatr Rev 2011;32:47–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21285300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi T, Vennard S, Jasiewicz F, et al. Disease burden estimates of respiratory syncytial virus related acute respiratory infections in adults with comorbidity: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect Dis 2022;226:S17–S21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34522961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowser DM, Rowlands KR, Hariharan D, et al. Cost of respiratory syncytial virus infections in US infants: systematic literature review and analysis. J Infect Dis 2022;226:S225–S235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9377037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35968875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fendrick AM, Monto AS, Nightengale B, Sarnes M. The economic burden of non-influenza-related viral respiratory tract infection in the United States. Arch Intern Med 2003;163:487–494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12588210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molinari NA, Ortega-Sanchez IR, Messonnier ML, et al. The annual impact of seasonal influenza in the US: measuring disease burden and costs. Vaccine 2007;25:5086–5096.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17544181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Branche A, Branche AR, Saiman L, et al. Incidence of respiratory syncytial virus infection among hospitalized adults, 2017–2020. Clin Infect Dis 2022;74:1004–1011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34244735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cillóniz C, Pericàs JM, Rojas JR, Torres A. Severe Infections Due to Respiratory Viruses. Semin Respirat Crit Care Med 2022;43:60–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35172359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltola V, Jartti T, Putto-Laurila A, et al. Rhinovirus infections in children: a retrospective and prospective hospital-based study. J Med Virol 2009;81:1831–1838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7166645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19697407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suh M, Movva N, Jiang X, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus is the leading cause of United States infant hospitalizations, 2009–2019: a study of the national (nationwide) inpatient sample. J Infect Dis 2022;226:S154–S163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9377046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35968878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Li Y, Vazquez Fernandez L, et al. respiratory syncytial virus–associated hospital admissions and bed days in children &lt;5 years of age in 7 European countries. J Infect Dis 2022;226:S22–S28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35023567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fast Stats HCUP. Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP), National Inpatient Sample (NIS) 2015. Rockville, MD: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klompas M, Milton DK, Rhee C, Baker MA, Leekha S. Current insights into respiratory virus transmission and potential implications for infection control programs: a narrative review. Ann Intern Med 2021;174:1710–1718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34748374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegel JD, Rhinehart E, Jackson M, Chiarello L, the Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee. 2007 Guideline for isolation precautions: preventing transmission of infectious agents in healthcare settings. Am J Infect Control 2007;35:s65–s164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7119119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18068815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow EJ, Mermel LA. Hospital-acquired respiratory viral infections: incidence, morbidity, and mortality in pediatric and adult patients. Open Forum Infect Dis 2017;4:ofx006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5414085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28480279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hei H, Bezpalko O, Smathers SA, Coffin SE, Sammons JS. Development of a novel prevention bundle for pediatric healthcare-associated viral infections. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2018;39:1086–1092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30027857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitt E, Brennan L, Harrison C, et al. Dodging the bundle-Persistent healthcare-associated rhinovirus infection throughout the pandemic. Am J Infect Control 2022;50:1140–1144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35588914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Most ZM, Jackson P, Sebert M, Perl TM. Contrasting definitions and incidence of healthcare-associated respiratory viral infections in a pediatric hospital. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2022;44:55–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35317879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quach C, Shah R, Rubin LG. Burden of healthcare-associated viral respiratory infections in children’s hospitals. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc 2018;7:18–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7204516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28040689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin LG, Kohn N, Nullet S, Hill M. Reduction in rate of nosocomial respiratory virus infections in a children’s hospital associated with enhanced isolation precautions. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2018;39:152–156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29331160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manchal N, Mohamed MRS, Ting M, et al. Hospital acquired viral respiratory tract infections: an underrecognized nosocomial infection. Infect Dis Health 2020;25:175–180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinna S, Lakshmanan A, Tan S, et al. Outcomes of nosocomial viral respiratory infections in high-risk neonates. Pediatrics 2016;138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27940783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin CY, Hwang D, Chiu NC, et al. increased detection of viruses in children with respiratory tract infection using PCR. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2020;17:564–564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7013517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31952364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birger R, Morita H, Comito D, et al. Asymptomatic shedding of respiratory virus among an ambulatory population across seasons. mSphere 2018;3:e00249–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6041500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29997120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanti M, Birger R, Ud-Dean M, et al. Rates of asymptomatic respiratory virus infection across age groups. Epidemiol Infect 2019;147:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6518513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31063096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jartti T, Lehtinen P, Vuorinen T, Koskenvuo M, Ruuskanen O. Persistence of rhinovirus and enterovirus RNA after acute respiratory illness in children. J Med Virol 2004;72:695–699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14981776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrenzeller S, Zaffini R, Pecora ND, Kanjilal S, Rhee C, Klompas M. Cycle threshold dynamics of non–severe acute respiratory coronavirus virus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) respiratory viruses. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2024;45:1–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38234188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teoh Z, Conrey S, McNeal M, et al. Factors associated with prolonged respiratory virus detection from PCR of nasal specimens collected longitudinally in healthy children in a U.S. birth cohort. J Pediatr Infect Dis Soc 2024;13:189–195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38366142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Advani S, Sengupta A, Forman M, Valsamakis A, Milstone AM. Detecting Respiratory Viruses in Asymptomatic Children. Pediatr Infect Dis J 2012;31:1221–1221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3505556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22739572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huijskens EG, Biesmans RC, Buiting AG, Obihara CC, Rossen JW. Diagnostic value of respiratory virus detection in symptomatic children using real-time PCR. Virol J 2012;9:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3511061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23164039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olofsson S, Brittain-Long R, Andersson LM, Westin J, Lindh M. PCR for detection of respiratory viruses: seasonal variations of virus infections. Exp Rev Anti Infect Therapy 2011;9:615–615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7103711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21819328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buitrago-Garcia D, Ipekci AM, Heron L, et al. Occurrence and transmission potential of asymptomatic and presymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections: Update of a living systematic review and meta-analysis. PLOS Med 2022;19:e1003987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9135333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35617363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ip DK, Lau LL, Leung NH, et al. Viral shedding and transmission potential of asymptomatic and paucisymptomatic influenza virus infections in the community. Clin Infect Dis 2017;64:736–742.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5967351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28011603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson MA, Quandelacy TM, Kada S, et al. SARS-CoV-2 transmission from people without COVID-19 symptoms. JAMA Netw Open 2021;4:e2035057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7791354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33410879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McEvoy D, McAloon C, Collins A, et al. Relative infectiousness of asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infected persons compared with symptomatic individuals: a rapid scoping review. BMJ Open 2021;11:e042354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8098293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33947725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamò R, Turk T, Böni J, et al. Secondary attack rates from asymptomatic and symptomatic influenza virus shedders in hospitals: Results from the TransFLUas influenza transmission study. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2022;43:312–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8961411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33952361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>